<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Legislative Foreword</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the Cost-Benefit State Legislative Foreword</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>"</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>48</volume>
      <fpage>1995</fpage>
      <lpage>1996</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the
Cost-Benefit State</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein*</p>
      <p>In this article,Cass Sunstein exploresthe 104th Congress' attempts at
regulatory reform. ProfessorSunstein believes that the election of this Congress,
with its distinctive approachto government,signals the dawning of a
"constitutional moment" in which the role ofgovernment at all levels will be
reexamined. Without full public supportfor sweeping changes in government, this
moment has not yet materialized. When and ifit does, regulatory reform will
be one of its aspects. Indeed the nation has alreadybegun to examine
regulation to determineifthe benefitsjustify the costs. Unfortunately, the 104th
Congress has, thusfar,failed adequately to address this burgeoning cost-benefit
state. Sunstein claims that Congress'failurereflects its inability to redesign
the massive federalregulatoryscheme. He suggests that the executive branch
should oversee regulatoryreform, with Congressrelegatedto providingbroad
policy direction. Sunstein also suggests that Congressadopt an Administrative
Substance Act, building upon the recent learning about the performance of
regulation and modeled after the AdministrativeProcedureAct.
Sunsteinfurther callsfor the enactment of a "substantivesupermandate"requiringa
general background rule of cost-benefit balancingfor allfederal regulation; but
he contends that any description of costs and benefits should reflect the full
range of diverse values expressed by the public at large.
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Law, The University of Chicago Law
School and Department of Political Science. I am grateful to Bruce Ackerman and Susan
Rose-Ackerman for helpful discussions; to Ackerman, Elizabeth Garrett, Richard Pierre, Richard Posner, Richard
Stewart, Peter Strauss, and Jonathan Wiener for valuable comments; to Keith Sharfman for outstanding
and indispensable research assistance; and to many participants in the legislative debates for helpful
background.
3. Government should recognize and counteractharmful</p>
      <p>unintended consequences of regulations................ 261
4. Government needs more information and should create
better incentives to compile andprovide accurate
information........................................... 264</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>5. Government should respond to both expert and citizen</title>
      <p>judgments in regulatingrisks.......................... 264</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>6. Government should concentrate on basic ends rather</title>
      <p>than means and should use performancestandards
ratherthan design standards.......................... 267
III. REGULATORY REFORM AND THE 104TH CONGRESS: A FAILED
EFFORT AT FUNDAMENTAL CHANGE ............................. 269</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>A. The Contractand Two Kinds of Supermandates............ 270</title>
      <p>B. Particulars.............................................. 272
1. Unfunded mandates................................... 272
2. Moratorium and legislative review..................... 273</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>3. Generic reform, supermandates,and APA amendments:</title>
      <p>the House. ........................................... 274
4. Generic reform: the Senate ........................... 277</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>5. Statute-by-statute reform and appropriation............. 282</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>6. A note on the politics of regulatory reform............. 284</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>7. An evaluation: contract without (enough) deliberation... 284</title>
      <p>IV. TOWARD NEW INITIATivEs ..................................... 286</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>A. Procedureand Paperwork:Less is More .................. 286</title>
      <p>1. Existing rules andjudicialreview ..................... 286
2. "Peerreview .. ...................................... 288
3. Joint resolution of disapproval........................ 288
B. Modest Changes ......................................... 289
1. Valuation of benefits.................................. 289</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>2. Cost-benefit analysis as a quasi-constitutionalmoment.. 290</title>
      <p>3. Theory and practice.................................. 292
4. Substitute risks....................................... 296
C. Ambitious Goals ......................................... 296</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>1. Rank risks and reallocateresources to the most severe</title>
      <p>problems and increase the executive's role in priority
setting. .............................................. 297</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>2. Allow plansfrom the private sector that show greater</title>
      <p>and more cost-effective reductions..................... 297
3. Regulate with incentives............................... 298
V. POSSIBLE FUTURES ............................................. 298
A. Cost-Benefit Balancing................................... 300
B. Pollution Prevention ..................................... 301
C. Free Market Environmentalism ........................... 303
D. DemocraticEnvironmentalism ............................ 305
VI. CONCLUSION .................................................. 307</p>
      <p>INTRODUCTION</p>
      <sec id="sec-12-1">
        <title>A Stalled ConstitutionalMoment</title>
        <p>The 104th Congress promised to change the national government in
fundamental ways. Spurred by widespread popular dissatisfaction with government,
the House of Representatives attempted to rethink national institutions more
deeply than at any time since the New Deal; in fact the New Deal itself was a
central target of the process of rethinking. America may be on the verge of a
constitutional moment in which Americans answer foundational questions in
novel ways.'</p>
        <p>The election of the 104th Congress signalled the transformation of America
into a genuinely post-New Deal regulatory state. This emerging nation remains
in a process of development; but it may be described as a cost-benefit state, one
whose performance will be assessed, both in particular and in general, by
comparing the costs of government action with its benefits. This idea requires a
good deal of specification, but it unites developments not only in the national
legislature, but in the executive branch, the judiciary, and state government as
2
well.</p>
        <p>My purpose here is to evaluate the efforts of the 104th Congress to give
legal form to this constitutional moment. My particular interest is Congress'
effort to reform the modem regulatory state. Charged by a popular mandate for
reform and a high level of ambition, Congress debated both substantive and
procedural "supermandates" cutting across all federal regulation. 3 Thus the
104th Congress devoted a large part of its agenda to "rethinking the regulatory
state." The Contract With America also promised to address basic regulatory
issues. 4 In large-scale hearings, Congress examined problems of
overregula1. I borrow the idea of a constitutional moment from Bruce Ackerman, who proposes a "dualist"
approach to constitutional interpretation-an approach that claims that America has witnessed two types
of decisions: foundational ones made by the American people and more ordinary ones made by their
representatives. 1 BRUCE AcKEImsAN, WE Ta PEOPLE: FoUNDATIONS 6 (1991). A constitutional
moment is a period of popular development of principles that results in revolutionary reform. Id. at 21.
Ackerman identifies three such moments in American history: the Founding, Reconstruction, and the
New Deal. Id. at 58; see also text accompanying notes 16-34 infra.</p>
        <p>
          2. Thus Executive Orders by Presidents Reagan and Clinton endorse cost-benefit analysis in some
form. See Exec. Order No. 12,866, 3 C.F.R. 638 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ), reprintedin 5 U.S.C. ยง 601 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ) (mandating
that agencies assess the costs and benefits of a regulation before adopting it); Exec. Order No. 12,498, 3
C.F.R. 323 (1986), repintedin 5 U.S.C. ยง 601 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ) (requiring agencies to submit a plan ofproposed
regulations annually) (revoked 1993); Exec. Order No. 12,291, 3 C.F.R. 127 (1982), reprinted in 5
U.S.C. ยง 601 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ) (prohibiting regulatory action unless the potential benefits of the regulation
outweigh its costs) (revoked 1993). On the role of cost-benefit balancing in the courts, see Motor Vehicles
Mfrs. Ass'n v. State Farm Mutual Auto. Ins., 463 U.S. 29, 54-55 (1983) (endorsing cost-benefit analysis
for automobile safety standards regarding automatic seatbelt systems); Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA,
947 F.2d 1201, 1215-17 (5th Cir. 1991) (rejecting EPA's ban on asbestos because EPA failed to adhere
to its statutory mandate to impose the least burdensome solution). On state and local government, see
TED GAEBLER &amp; DAVID OSBORNE, REINVENTING GoVERNMENT: How Tm ENrmPRNmUIAL SPIRIT Is
TRANSFORnmiNo a PUBLIc SECTOR (1991) (advocating that government at all levels should be reformed
to behave more like the private sector).
        </p>
        <p>3. See text accompanying notes 106-178 infra.</p>
        <p>4. CONTRACT WITH AMEIucA: THE BOLD PLAN BY REP. NEWr GINGRICH, REP. DICK ARmEY, AND
THE HOUSE REPUBLICANS TO CHANGE THE NATION 131-35 (Ed Gillespie &amp; Bob Schellhas eds., 1994)
(proposing to require federal agencies to prepare a risk assessment for each new regulation, an annual
tion and the prospects for cost-benefit balancing.5 Finally, the House passed
and the Senate debated measures that, if enacted, would have represented the
largest changes to the Administrative Procedure Act6 since its enactment in
1946.</p>
        <p>By the close of the first session, however, relatively little had happened.
There was no constitutional transformation for a simple reason: The public has
not (yet) called for one in the way that American institutions require. To be
sure, the House passed eleven major pieces of legislation in two
monthsincluding the Congressional Accountability Act,7 the Line Item Veto Act s and
the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act.9 But only six of those measures were
enacted into law. The Balanced Budget Amendment 10 passed the House but
faced defeat in the Senate, as did tax legislation, welfare reform, a new crime
bill, and term limits legislation. The Line Item Veto Act and litigation reform
passed the House and Senate in different forms, but await the work of
conference committees, stalled in the case of the line item veto by the Republicans'
reluctance to give this power to President Clinton."</p>
        <p>All in all, there was a great deal of noise and bluster-a great deal of
signalling-but surprisingly little in the way of concrete results. In the end, the
enacted measures proved modest and mostly procedural. The apparently more
ambitious proposals contained some good features. But many of their
provisions were crude, unimaginative, and far more procedural than advertised.
Rather than reflecting new and better thinking about substantive regulation,
these provisions represented an effort to clog the administrative process with
paperwork. In fact, members of Congress sometimes appeared to
misunderstand the content of the very legislation they were debating. Congress revealed
only a partial awareness of the recent outpouring of research on
regulationresearch that could have produced the basis not only for fundamental change,
but also for a consensus cutting (more or less) across partisan lines. Congress'
emphasis on cost-benefit analysis showed a healthy appreciation for balancing
rather than absolutism; but it was only a start. Congress may well have laid the
groundwork for future developments. But because of its own institutional
weaknesses and the system of checks and balances-including above all
bicameralism and the possibility of presidential veto-actual changes will take
more time. As a practical matter, these institutional weaknesses significantly
hamper Congress' ability to produce a constitutional moment in the context of
the modem regulatory state.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-12-2">
        <title>B. Lessons</title>
        <p>Both institutional and substantive lessons will emerge from this article. On
the institutional side, I claim that Congress is quite ill-equipped to produce
sensible, constitution-like reform, at least if it tries to offer details. With
respect to regulation, a group of generalist representatives-all with numerous
issues to address, few with particular expertise in regulatory law, and many
beholden to special interests-is not in a position to produce desirable,
largescale reforms, unless it restricts itself to generalities. Such a group is prone to
sharp internal divisions that are not subject to reasonable mediation without a
good deal of specialization in regulation. Indeed, the task of producing
constitution-like change in the modem state is far more difficult than it was in the
New Deal era. It is easier to create a regulatory state than it is to dismantle one,
especially in an era in which every industrialized nation is committed to
controlling the operation of the marketplace.</p>
        <p>
          These skeptical claims about Congress' institutional capacities are
reinforced by recent experience. As we will see, the 104th Congress was split
between two different sets of interests: technocratic forces seeking to discipline
agency decisions with better policy analysis and forces of reaction seeking to
stop agency action even when it would improve social well-being. There is
thus an interesting contrast between the performances of Congress and the
executive branch. Even those who reject President Clinton's approach to
regulation should recognize that his administration has shown far more sophistication
and creativity in this area than Congress. 12 (The same is true for the
adminis12. For example, Vice President Gore's task force, which is currently conducting the National
Performance Review, has produced a series of reports on "reinventing government.' See, e.g., BILL
CLINTON &amp; AL GORE., REINvENTNr, WORKER SAFETY AND HEALTH (May 1995) (detailing reforms of
OSHA); BILt CLINTON &amp; AL GoRE, REvENTINrG RGULATION OF DRuGs AND MEDICAL DEVICES
(April 1995) (detailing reforms of FDA); BILL CLINTON &amp; At GORE, REINvENTING ENVIRONMENTAL
REGULATION (March 1995) (detailing reforms of EPA). See alsoExec. Order No. 12,898, 3 C.F.R. 859
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ), reprintedas amended in 42 U.S.C. ยง4321 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (requiring agencies to make achieving
environmental justice part of their missions); Exec. Order No. 12,866, supra note 2 (defining principles of
regulation including examining the effectiveness of existing regulation, encouraging flexibility in
method of compliance, and assigning costs and benefits of new regulations); Memorandum on
Regulatory Reform, 31 WEEKt.Y Coam. PREs. Doc. 695, 695-96 (Apr. 21, 1995) (directing agencies to waive
penalties in certain cases and to reduce the frequency of required reports); Memorandum on Customer
Service, 31 WEEKLY CoM. PREs. Doc. 456, 456 (March 22, 1995) (directing agencies to implement
steps to ensure better customer service); Memorandum on Regulatory Reform, 31 WEmKLY Comp'. PREs.
Doc. 363, 364 (Mar. 4, 1995) (calling on agencies to cut obsolete regulations).
        </p>
        <p>On March 16, 1995, President Clinton announced govermnentwide regulatory reform. White</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-12-3">
        <title>House Office of Communications, PresidentAnnounces GovernmentwideRegulatoryReforms, Mar. 16,</title>
        <p>trations of Presidents Reagan and Bush. 13) The executive branch has been
highly attuned to the need to compare costs and benefits, to attend to results
rather than processes, and to enlist the private sector in engineering least-cost
solutions. Improvements in regulatory performance are more likely to come
from the executive than from a Congress saddled with its institutional
deficiencies. Perhaps Congress should give substantial discretion to administrators,
allowing them to design appropriate regulatory tools and perhaps to set priorities
as well.14 Indeed many current problems result from statutes that either
produce poor incentives or forbid more imaginative, cheaper, and more effective
solutions-or that ban cost-benefit balancing altogether.' 5</p>
        <p>
          On the substantive side, a cost-benefit state may well be better than what
we now have: a system containing both economic and democratic failures,
where priorities are not set carefully and where interest groups wield excessive
power over government. Certainly it is important to provide methods for
assessing regulatory performance. At least in principle, some form of
cost-benefit analysis could simultaneously promote political accountability and
regulatory efficiency. In this way, it could be part of a system of deliberative
democracy. But any movement toward a cost-benefit state should be
accompanied by an understanding of the importance of public judgments in regulatory
law, the limits of the criterion of private willingness to pay, and the need to
1995 (press release), available in WESTLAW, Pres-Daily Database. The initiative to reform EPA will:
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          ) simplify reporting burdens; (2) allow grace periods for small business violations; (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          ) provide
incentives for self-disclosure and correction; (4) increase the use of emissions trading; (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">5</xref>
          ) consolidate air
pollution rules; (6) give greater flexibility to recipients of grants; and (7) create a faster self-certification
program for minor changes to pesticides. Id. The initiative to reform OSHA will: (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          ) switch from
command-and-control to partnerships with business (which means negotiated, rather than dictated,
regulations); (2) update obsolete and confusing standards; and (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          ) identify priorities sensibly (i.e., a ranking a
hazards in order of danger). White House Office of Communications, Presidentand Vice President
Announce OSHA Reform. May 16, 1995 (press release), availablein WESTLAW, Pres-Daily Database.
See also Regulation:EPA, DOE,DOI Reform andEliminate Rules, GRE Nwm, Aug. 3, 1995, available
in LEXIS, News Library, Gmwre File (reporting Clinton administration announcement of reforms of
twenty-eight federal agencies).
        </p>
        <p>
          In an important recent initiative, involving toxic pollution by refineries, the EPA concluded that the
benefits (at $150 million annually) would exceed the costs (at S95 million annually). Bruce Alpert, EPA
Issues New Rules on Refinery Pollution,N. ORLEANS TIMEs-PIcAYUNE, July 29, 1995, at A8. On
another front, the National Performance Review report on the FDA, REINVanNG REGULATION OF DRUGS
AND MEDICAL DEvicEs, supra, called for exemptions of low-risk medical devices from premarket
review; reducing or eliminating many approval requirements for drugs; excluding drug and biologic
manufacturers from most environmental assessments; and spreading the marketing of medical devices by
charging use fees for reviews and also by committing FDA to meet performance standards. Id.at 4-5.
13. See Exec. Order No. 12,498, supra note 2; Exec. Order No. 12,291, supra note 2.
14. It follows that I reject the idea that Congress should closely limit agency discretion. See
BRUCE A. ACKERMAN &amp; WILIAM T. HASSLER, CLEAN COAL/DIRTY AIR: OR How THE CLEAN Am ACT
BECAME A MULTIBILLION-DOLLAR BAr.-OUT FOR HIGH SULFUR COAL PRODUCERS AND WHAT SHOULD
BE DONE ABotrr IT 4-12 (1983) (defending the New Deal model); STEPHEN BREYER, BREArmNG TaE
Vicious CIRCLE: TowARD EFFECTivE RISK REGULATION 59-61, 64-68 (calling for the creation of a new
administrative group to oversee "risk regulation") (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47 ref48">1992</xref>
          ); Jerry L. Mashaw,
Prodelegation:WhyAdministratorsShouldMake PoliticalDecisions, IJ. L. ECON. &amp; ORG. 81, 95 (1985) ("[I]t may make sense to
imagine the delegation of political authority to administrators as a device for improving the
responsiveness of government to the desires of the electorate.').
        </p>
        <p>15. See text accompanying notes 49-58 infra.
create market mechanisms that do not place excessive informational demands
on government.</p>
        <p>More specifically, I suggest that a general requirement of cost-benefit
analysis would indeed be a constitution-like amendment, and a highly undesirable
one, if it is understood in the most ambitious possible way: as an effort to
ensure that all regulatory statutes are implemented by reference to the principle
of economic efficiency based on the criterion of private willingness to pay.
Regulatory measures have diverse foundations, and many legitimate statutes
are not rooted in the efficiency criterion at all.</p>
        <p>If cost-benefit analysis is understood more modestly as an effort to require
balancing rather than absolutism, it is a good idea and should generally be
required. But so understood, cost-benefit analysis can be specified in many
different ways. Congress should give appropriate guidance so that agencies can
make reasonable rather than unreasonable specifications. I offer some
suggestions about how these tasks might be accomplished; to this end I emphasize
qualitative as well as quantitative factors, public judgments about risk, and the
highly diverse foundations of regulatory enactments.</p>
        <p>This article comes in four parts. Part I examines the popular shift in the
perceived role of the national government-a shift that may yet culminate in a
constitutional moment. Part I also outlines what has been learned thus far
about regulation. Part II describes what the 104th Congress proposed and
summarizes this failed constitutional moment. Part III explores how the principal
proposals might be improved. Part IV addresses the future of the cost-benefit
state.</p>
        <p>II.</p>
        <sec id="sec-12-3-1">
          <title>THE ATrACK ON THE NEw DEAL</title>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-12-4">
        <title>A. A New ConstitutionalMoment?</title>
        <p>The New Deal was of course a substantial reformation of the original
constitutional structure. 16 It qualifies as a substantial reformation above all because
it refashioned the three basic cornerstones of that structure: federalism, checks
and balances, and individual rights. 17</p>
        <p>In the 1930s the powers of the national government were expanded in an
extraordinary way, in favor of a system that exercised something close to
general police powers.' 8 The original understanding of a sharply constrained
cen16. See AcKERmAN, supra note 1,at 47-50, 105-130 (discussing the New Deal as the third
American constitutional regime); Cass R. Sunstein, ConstitutionalismAfter the New Deal, 101 HARv. L. REV.
421, 423-25, 430-46 (1987) (discussing the substantial effects of the New Deal on previous
constitutional understandings).</p>
        <p>
          17. See TnaoDooE J. Lowi, THE END OF THE REPUBLICAN ERA 23 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) [hereinafter REPUBLICAN
ERA] (describing President Roosevelt's emphasis on populism and nationalism, rather than
individualism); THEODORE J. Lowi, Tan PERSONAL PRESIDENT: POWER INVESTED, PRONSE UNFULFILLED 52-58
(1985) hereinafter PERSONAL PREsmENT] (describing the New Deal shift in power from Congress to the
President by delegating significant discretion to federal agencies).
        </p>
        <p>18. See Wickard v. Filbum, 317 U.S. 111, 118-25 (1942) (interpreting Congress' power to
regulate interstate commerce broadly to include the regulation of private activity that may indirectly affect
commerce); see alsoPERSONAL PRESIDENT supranote 17, at 49-50 (discussing the judicial ratification of
the government's expansive powers).
tral government was therefore repudiated by the nation. There were simple
grounds for this repudiation. First, state autonomy seemed an obstacle to
democratic self-government, not a crucial part of it-especially in the midst of the
Depression, when states were generally perceived as ineffectual entities
buffeted by private factions. As a result of the New Deal, state autonomy was very
different in 1940 from what it had been in 1920.</p>
        <p>Second, the system of checks and balances came under sharp criticism. To
many observers, especially during the Depression, that system seemed
dysfunctional and anachronistic in modem society. 19 Effective businesses do not
operate through checks and balances; why should government paralyze itself in this
way?20 In response, Congress delegated enormous policymaking power to the
President and created a large number of powerful executive and independent
agencies.2 ' Crucially, Congress designed these agencies to limit the
consequences of the system of checks and balances by allowing a high degree of
administrative autonomy. Thus the new agencies had a large degree of
discretionary authority under open-ended statutory standards. They also combined
traditionally separated powers of adjudication, execution, and legislation.</p>
        <p>These institutional shifts resulted from a critical national judgment made
during the Depression: that individual rights, properly conceived, included not
merely the common law catalogue of private interests, but also governmental
protection against many of the harms and risks of a market economy. These
harms and risks included unemployment, poverty, malnutrition, homelessness,
lack of education, and hopelessness as a result of disability.22 Indeed the
common law catalogue seemed overprotective as well as underprotective, for it was
unduly solicitous of private property. The common law was a regulatory
system enjoying no special status; it should be evaluated pragmatically and in
terms of its consequences for the human beings subject to it. Here it often
seemed to fail. Hence the national government was authorized to engage in a
wide range of redistributive policies.</p>
        <p>If the New Deal qualifies as a constitutional moment, it is because of its
revolutionary redefinition of constitutional commitments. 23 Indeed, an
astonishing feature of the New Deal was its relative rapidity. Many changes came in
the brief period from 1932 through 1936, and were clearly supported and
ratified by the public. Such rapid change was possible partly because it is a
relatively simple step for a legislature to create a range of new bureaucratic
institutions, at least if the legislature does not specify each agency's duties in
advance. In fact, the New Deal entities operated with little statutory guidance;
Congress usually contented itself with open-ended delegations of authority.24
As we shall see, the relative simplicity of the New Dealers' task contrasts
dramatically with the complexity of the task faced by the 104th Congress. 25
Moreover, in the early 1930s the public's support for the New Deal was broader and
deeper than public support for fundamental change in the 1990s-though the
public may unite behind such change before long.</p>
        <p>The New Deal reformation served as the foundation for the basic
orientation of the national government until the election of President Ronald Reagan.
One development during that period has been of special importance: the
"rights revolution" of the 1960s and 1970s, which reinforced many New Deal
tendencies through the creation of a remarkable array of new agencies. These
agencies were designed to protect against threats to life, health, and safety from
consumer products, workplaces, and, above all, to protect the environment.26
Economic arguments about external harms reinforced claims for new statutory
"rights." Hence this period saw the creation of the Environmental Protection
Agency, the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, the Consumer
Protect Safety Commission, the Council on Environmental Quality, and several
other administrative agencies.</p>
        <p>It is notable that during both the New Deal and the rights revolution, no
mechanism was created to evaluate regulatory performance. No system
assessed whether agencies were making things better or worse. In the New Deal,
any such system might have seemed peculiar in light of the widespread national
enthusiasm for the President and for the possibilities of benign administration.
In addition, cost-benefit thinking was largely foreign to political actors, and
hence cost-benefit analysis played little or no role in public debate. No
mechanism existed to protect against the possibility that "government failure" would
replicate "market failure."</p>
        <p>One of the most striking features of the period since 1980 has been
sustained national criticism of the New Deal reformation. In light of the election
of the 104th Congress, this criticism may well be signalling the first genuinely
foundational challenge to American government since the New Deal itself. The
Contractwith America clearly suggested that large-scale change was at issue.
It is worthwhile to pause over the constitution-like character of recent
challenges to the current governmental structure. Critics often suggest that the
naienced a constitutional moment. If the term is seen as a metaphor, rather than a legal term of art, it is
sufficient to work from more abstract and intuitive ideas of the sort described in the text.</p>
        <p>24. See THEODORE J. Lowr, THE END OF LERALISM: IDEOLOGY, POLICY, AND THE CRISIS OF
PuBLic Autorrry 132-33 (Ist ed. 1969) (describing the perceived need for broad authorizing statutes
as government expanded its powers).</p>
        <p>25. See text accompanying notes 99-100 infra.
26. See SuNsTEnN, supra note 21, at 24-30.
tional government has far exceeded the appropriate limits of its authority and
argue for a return to the original structure.2 7 Many assert that a devolution of
power to the states would promote both democratic and economic goals;2 s the
Unfunded Mandate Reform Act and Congress' recent interest in "block grants"
for states to use basically as they wish reflect this criticism.2 9</p>
        <p>In this way there is a wholesale attack on the existing allocation of authority
between the national government and the states. But "horizontal" issues of
government structure are receiving similar attention. Concerned about the
extent of policymaking discretion given to regulatory agencies, many suggest that
Congress should reassert its constitutional prerogatives by narrowing
administrative discretion. 30 It is urged that the New Deal's enthusiasm for independent
bureaucracy, and for a large lawmaking role for executive agencies, should be
revisited, and that Congress should make the fundamental choices of policy.</p>
        <p>Finally, and perhaps most fundamentally, pre-New Deal principles of
private right have enjoyed a rebirth with the suggestion that modem regulatory
programs violate liberty, rightly conceived. 31 These principles play a
significant part in current debates, as reflected in arguments in favor of removing
constraints from the marketplace and imposing new compensation obligations
on government. 32 Thus the movement for deregulation has become far more
sweeping than it was in the Reagan period. The Takings Clause has become a
rallying cry for a new enthusiasm for the protection of private
property-challenging such well-established federal programs as the Endangered Species Act
and the Federal Water Pollution Control Act's protection of wetlands.</p>
        <p>Some criticisms of regulatory performance have been far narrower and
more pragmatic in character, focusing less on basic theory and more on the
economic consequences of regulation. It is here that cost-benefit balancing,
accompanied by risk analysis, has played a special role. As I have noted, the
New Deal period was accompanied by no mechanism for monitoring regulatory
performance. But it is now suggested that national government has failed to
perform the tasks assigned to it and has often made things worse.33 In this
view, there is no suggestion that markets are ideal; but often markets work
better than the regulatory programs designed as solutions. Increasingly,
assessment of regulatory performance has taken the form of cost-benefit analysis. 34</p>
        <p>If we are indeed in the midst of a constitutional moment, it began with the
election of President Ronald Reagan and was spurred by the dramatic and
largely unanticipated shift in the direction and composition of the Congress in
the 1994 elections. The Contract With America presented the electorate with a
set of promises for fundamental reform. The importance of the Contract
should not be understated, for it helped to organize a formerly unruly House of
Representatives and provided public benchmarks against which the House
would be measured. It is clear that in the 104th Congress, the House of
Representatives acted in a remarkably rapid and sweeping fashion, offering the
Senate a chance to make the most significant changes in the national government
since the New Deal. The Senate declined the opportunity, largely because the
public showed its uncertainty about such far-reaching change. If the nation
follows the Senate's course, the effort at constitutional revision will have failed.
But any predictions on this count are premature. Let us turn, then, away from
theory and toward more pragmatic issues involving the performance of the
regulatory state.</p>
        <p>B.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-12-5">
        <title>Post-New Deal LearningAbout Regulation</title>
        <p>In the last decade, something very close to a consensus has emerged on
some of the most important problems in existing government regulation. If
government were to act on this consensus, it would introduce important
changes. Those changes need not amount to anything like a constitutional
moment; here we are not speaking of the most basic constitutional commitments.
But the changes would be far from a mere matter of tinkering. The consensus
has the following features.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-12-6">
        <title>Government should engage in betterpriority-setting.</title>
        <p>As we will see, measurement of costs and benefits can be highly
controversial. But under any measure, there can be no doubt that resources for risk
reduction are badly allocated.3 5 As much as $500 billion may be spent each
year on regulation,3 6 and of this amount, more than $130 billion is spent on
(claiming that the mattress flammability standard resulted in a substantial increase in costs, but no
statistically significant increases in consumer safety); Sam Peltzman, Toward a More General Theory of
Regualtion, in CHICAGO Srtmms N PoLmcAL EcoNoMY, supra, at 234 (explaining the problem of
diffuse interests that allows small groups to exert control over regulatory agencies); George J. Stigler,
The Theory ofEconomic Regulation, in CHICAGO STUins iN POLITICAL EcONoMY, supra,at 209
(arguing that regulatory agencies created to protect the public often succumb to interest group pressures).</p>
        <p>34. E.g., Exec Order No. 12,866, supranote 2; Exec. Order No. 12,498, supranote 2; Exec. Order
No. 12,291, supra note 2.</p>
        <p>
          35. See BRaYER, supra note 14, at 10-19 (arguing that frequently too many resources are spent to
eliminate small public health risks); Richard H. Pildes &amp; Cass R. Sunstein, Reinventing the Regulatory
State 62 U. Cm. L. RE. 1, 4 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (claiming that regulatory costs often exceed the benefits).
        </p>
        <p>
          36. See Thomas D. Hopkins, The Costs ofFederalRegulation,2 J. REG. &amp; Soc. CoSTS 5,25 tbl. 2
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47 ref48">1992</xref>
          ) (estimate of $400 million).
environmental protection alone.37 A recent study suggests that better allocation
of health expenditures could save 60,000 additional lives at no increased cost,
and that, alternatively, we could maintain the current number of lives saved
with $31 billion in annual savings.3 8
        </p>
        <p>This overall spending pattern includes serious and apparently unjustified 39
asymmetries in life-saving expenditures among the areas of regulation. For
example, compare transportation safety regulation, which costs a median of
$56,000 per life-year saved, to occupational safety regulation, costing a median
of $350,000 per life-year saved, and environmental regulation, costing a
median of $4,200,000 per life-year saved. 40 These variations are compounded by
variations in the effectiveness of safety standards within each area. 41 Annual
lives saved are highly variable. In transportation, the Federal Aviation
Administration's seat cushion flammability regulation saves thirty-seven lives each
year, while the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration's passive
restraints/belts regulation saves no fewer than 1,850 lives annually; in
occupational safety, OSHA's hazard communication regulation saves 200 lives per
year, OSHA's oil and gas well service regulation saves fifty lives per year,
OSHA's grain dust regulation saves four lives per year, and OSHA's
formaldehyde regulation saves 0.010 lives per year; and in environmental safety, EPA's
asbestos regulation saves ten lives each year, while EPA's land disposal
regulation saves 2.5 lives per year.42</p>
        <p>Of course calculations of costs and benefits are somewhat speculative, and
these numbers are only estimates. But with better allocation of resources and
more deliberative judgments, much could be improved. Consider Table 1,
which certainly does not capture all relevant factors-it does not even describe
total benefits-but which is at least highly suggestive of poor resource
allocations. 43</p>
        <p>In addition to this apparently inconsistent structure, the goal of achieving
sensible priority-setting is undermined by the fact that agencies have
substantially different standards for deciding when risks are large enough to require
any regulation at all.44 For example, the International Commission on
Radiological Protection recommends that environmental factors be regulated when
calculated to cause an incremental cancer risk of about 3 in 1000, for those
exposed over a lifetime. American agencies do not follow this
recommendation, and national practices are highly variable. The Nuclear Regulatory
Commission mandates regulation where incremental cancer risks exceed 1 in 1000;
the EPA does so when the risk exceeds an acceptable range that varies from 1
in 10,000 to 1 in 1,000,000.4 5</p>
        <p>The FDA set its standard at 1 in 1,000,000, but
courts have interpreted the Delaney Clause to require a standard of essentially
zero.46</p>
        <p>OSHA interprets the "significant risk" requirement in its governing
statute to mean that an incremental cancer risk of 1 in 1000 will initiate
regulation;4 7 labor groups have sought to require regulation when the risk is 1 in
1,000,000. As we will see, a single number may not make sense in light of
different contextual judgments. 48 But in the face of these variations, good
priority-setting is unlikely.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-13">
      <title>Government shouldfavorflexible, market-based incentives rather</title>
      <p>than rigid commands.</p>
      <p>Too often government regulates through rigid commands, precluding
industries from using more flexible and cost-effective
measures that achieve the
same goals.49 For example, in air and water pollution control, the rigid "best
available technology" approach,50 which mandates control technologies for
hundreds or even thousands of firms, gives industries little incentive to improve
existing pollution control technologies. Incentive-based systems could save
billions of dollars. 51 Yet in spite of the potential advantages, efforts to seek
better regulatory tools are hobbled by the statutory status quo, which either
forbids such tools or engrafts them onto a bureaucratically complex system.52
cost.</p>
      <p>A study based on data from 1984 suggests that the EPA's "netting" emissions
trading program saves between $525 million and $12 billion each year.5 3 The
Clinton Administration calculates that its market-oriented proposals for
amending the Clean Water Act could save between $1 and $12 billion over alternative
approaches.5 4 Thus studies show that incentive-based mechanisms for
controlling air pollution could have accomplished the same result at one-quarter the
55</p>
      <p>Encouraging companies to disclose information is an especially valuable
incentive-based approach to risk regulation. If companies offer information
about risk, consumer and worker behavior will probably be affected.5 6 The
national government has offered many initiatives in this direction. Consider in
particular the Toxic Release Inventory of the Superfund Amendments, which
requires companies to publish annual reports detailing the amount of toxics
they release into the environment. This program has been highly successful,
spurring voluntary reductions at relatively low costs. Reacting to public
concern about the information in these mandatory disclosures, many companies
have voluntarily pledged to reduce toxic releases. 57 A great deal of work
remains to be done in conceiving and designing appropriate informational
approaches to risk.5 8</p>
      <sec id="sec-13-1">
        <title>Government should recognize and counteract harmful unintended</title>
        <p>consequences of regulations.</p>
        <p>Many regulatory initiatives result in harmful unintended consequences.
Under the existing regulatory system, there is no systematic way to ensure that
those consequences receive attention.5 9 Hence regulation tends to be based on
partial perspectives that emerge from close attention to mere pieces of complex
problems. This myopic approach ignores the importance of ensuring that
regulation does not have unexplored side-effects or increase harms or risks on
balance. 60 A particular problem arises from "health-health" tradeoffs, which arise
when regulation of one health risk increases another health risk.61 Suppose, for
example, that elimination of asbestos, a carcinogenic substance, makes cars less
safe because asbestos is the best substance to use in making brake linings. 62 Or
suppose that the ban on asbestos encourages companies to use even more
dangerous substitutes. 63 It is pervasively true that controls on one risk may
increase another risk. Unfortunately, risk regulation is not designed with this
problem in mind.</p>
        <p>An incipient literature deals with a related issue. It suggests that regulatory
expenditures can profoundly affect social well-being and actually cost health
and even lives. Regulatory expenditures may produce greater unemployment
by increasing production costs and decreasing profits. Unemployment breeds
poverty, which, in turn, breeds poor health and increased mortality rates. A
1990 study developed a model to quantify the common sense view that "richer
is safer."' 4 The study suggests that a regulatory expenditure of $3 million to
$7.5 million may cause a statistical fatality.65</p>
        <p>In a concurring opinion in a 1991 D.C. Circuit case involving an
occupational safety and health regulation, Judge Williams invoked this evidence to
suggest that OSHA's refusal to engage in cost-benefit analysis might not be
beneficial for workers. 66 Judge Williams reasoned that if a fatality results from
an expenditure of $12 million, some regulations might produce more fatalities
than they prevent. 67 As Table I illustrates, many regulations do cost more than
$12 million per life saved. In Judge Williams' view, an agency that fails to
measure the overall social costs against benefits falls accurately to measure
mortality gains against losses.</p>
        <p>The claimed relationship between wealth reductions and mortality is
controversial.68 But a number of studies find such a relationship and indicate that
regulations may, in fact, cause more fatalities than they prevent. Consider the
following summary of studies showing a causal relation between wealth and
69
mortality:
68. See Portney &amp; Stavins, supra note 37, at 118 (arguing that slight real income losses are
unlikely to translate into significant, aggregate health impacts).</p>
        <p>
          69. Randall Lutter &amp; John F. Morrall III, Health-HealthAnalysis: A New Way to EvaluateHealth
and Safety Regulation, 8 J. RIsK &amp; UNCERTAITY 43, 49, tbl. 1 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ) (reprinted by permission).
        </p>
        <p>This work is in its initial stages, and any findings should be taken with
many grains of salt.70 But certainly it would be good for government to know
about unintended adverse consequences and to try to counteract them to the
extent feasible. Unfortunately, there is now no systematic mechanism by
which government regulators are made attentive to harmful unintended
consequences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-2">
        <title>Government needs more information and should create better incentives to compile andprovide accurateinformation.</title>
        <p>Often government lacks information about the harms that regulation is
designed to counteract. Often it must act, or fail to act, in a context of
considerable scientific uncertainty. 7 1 Without accurate data, any exercise in
quantification can be illusory,72 giving the impression of far more knowledge than
people actually have.</p>
        <p>In these circumstances government should place a high premium on
acquiring as much accurate information as possible. Much of the relevant
information can be found in the private sector, which is best equipped to determine
actual emissions levels and the costs of risk control. But the current regulatory
structure does not create incentives to compile accurate information about risks.
Indeed, it creates incentives to distort the facts. Hence industry faces incentives
to report costs that are far higher than reality73 and is not encouraged to
compile more information than is already available.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-3">
        <title>Government should respond to both expert and citizen judgments in</title>
        <p>regulatingrisks.</p>
        <p>It seems clear that government should respond to reasonable judgments
about risk; but whose judgments should be counted as reasonable? Countless
studies show systematic differences between expert and citizen judgments
about risk.7 4 This is one of the most robust findings in an extensive
litera70. See Portney &amp; Stavins, supra note 37, at 118-19 (advocating use of cost-benefit analysis
because the theoretical limitations of health-health analysis make it less useful in practice).</p>
        <p>
          71. See Robert A. Pollak, RegulatingRisks, 33 J. EcoN. LrrERATtu. 179, 183-89 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          )
(examining formaldehyde regulation to emphasize the difficulty of determining what poses a health risk and the
degree to which regulation is necessary).
        </p>
        <p>72. See Sheila Jasanoff, Acceptable Evidence in a PluralisticSociety, in ACCErABLE EvmENcE:
ScIENcE AND VAs.Es IN RiSK MANAGEmENT 29, 42-43 (Deborah G. Mayo &amp; Rachelle D. Hollander
eds., 1991) (attributing the push toward quantification to the adversariness of law and politics in the
United States).</p>
        <p>73. See Sunstein, supra note 58, at 656 (explaining that industry has little incentive to provide
information about hazardous products because the information may reduce sales).</p>
        <p>74. See Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supra note 35, at 33-40 (discussing risk assessment differences
between experts and laypersons).
ture.75 The following table summarizes the results of a national opinion poll in
which experts and citizens ranked environmental health risks.7 6</p>
        <p>A recent study in Canada shows similar results. 77 It reveals that the
Canadian public sees cigarette smoking and motor vehicle accidents as far less
dangerous than do Canadian toxicologists. It also shows that the public ranks
many risks higher than do toxicologists; the most dramatic disparities along this
dimension involve chemical pollution, ozone depletion, nuclear waste, food
additives, pesticides in goods, and PCBs.</p>
        <p>What accounts for these differences? Some are simply attributable to
citizens' ignorance of scientific facts. This ignorance has many sources, including
sensationalist media reports and heuristics that produce systematic biases. 78
process of congressional review might also deter agencies from submitting
illconsidered or faction-driven regulations to Congress. Moreover, agencies
might more frequently signal to Congress that some statutorily mandated
regulations make little sense, and the process of review might lead Congress to
change the relevant statute.20 7 It is in part for these reasons that President
Clinton expressed enthusiasm for congressional review. 20 8</p>
        <p>It is unclear, however, how much this provision would add, since Congress
can already enact legislation to prevent any and all regulations from becoming
law. There are risks as well. A serious problem with congressional review is
that it might, in practice, give well-organized interest groups a chance to bring
pressure to bear on hundreds or even thousands of regulations. In this way it
might increase rather than decrease the problem of factional influence. 20 9
Section 801 would also require Congress to expend limited resources reviewing a
wide range of agency rules, many of which should be uncontroversial.</p>
        <p>The competing considerations do not lead to any obvious conclusion. But a
new statutory provision for congressional review adds nothing to Congress'
existing authority. Setting up a formal mechanism for review of regulations is
probably too costly and time-consuming to be worthwhile; narrower
"reporting" strategies could accomplish the same goals. Hence section 801 might well
impose costs that are not justified by benefits.</p>
        <p>Modest Changes2 10</p>
        <p>How might Congress improve the proposals mentioned above? I begin
with some modest changes designed to accomplish Congress' apparent goals in
a more effective manner.</p>
        <p>Some theoretical issues. If a substantive supermandate is to operate as a
kind of constitutional amendment to the regulatory state, it seems crucial to
understand what cost-benefit balancing actually entails. Much of the national
debate in the last year involved the value of cost-benefit analysis. Proponents
characterized cost-benefit analysis as a method of disciplining administrative
power through salutary balancing; opponents feared that cost-benefit analysis
cold-heartedly sacrifices human health and life for the sake of mere dollars.
But this is at best a caricature. By itself, the notion of cost-benefit analysis
appears very close to empty; everything depends on how costs and benefits are
characterized and on how underlying issues of valuation are resolved. 2 11</p>
        <p>Two criticisms can be made of a proposed framework (or supermandate)
for evaluating governmental performance. The first is that the framework is
wrong because it ignores certain important variables, or is founded on an
indefensible theory of value. The second criticism is that the framework is
incompletely specified, in the sense that its meaning depends on further
subsidiary judgments that have yet to be offered. Cost-benefit analysis is
properly subject to the first kind of criticism to the extent that it purports to align
values along the single metric of aggregated private willingness to pay-and
evaluates regulation by reference to that criterion alone. Indeed, regulation
might be founded on citizen judgments that have no clear parallel in aggregated
willingness to pay.2 12 Or it may be rooted in distributive rather than allocative
goals; consider the antidiscrimination laws as possible examples. To the extent
that cost-benefit analysis is rooted in the technical economists' understanding,
it has a great deal to offer, but it cannot capture many appropriate goals of
regulation.</p>
        <p>As a political creed, however, the principal problem with cost-benefit
analysis is that it is incompletely specified. Its meaning depends on how costs and
benefits are characterized and on how issues of valuation are resolved. Do
equitable concerns enter the cost-benefit calculus? Suppose, for example, that
a certain environmental risk is concentrated among African-Americans. 21 3 Can
a good cost-benefit analysis take this into account? Or suppose that some of
the benefits of regulation are aesthetic. How will these benefits be valued? An
extensive literature explores the valuation of human life.2 14 Though, by itself,
cost-benefit analysis takes no position on the associated controversies,
regulators asked to operate under cost-benefit analysis must take some such position.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-4">
        <title>Cost-benefit analysis as a quasi-constitutionalamendment.</title>
        <p>With these points in mind we can ask the general question: Would a
general requirement of cost-benefit analysis be a sensible supermandate for the
regulatory state?</p>
        <p>Would such a requirement be like a constitutional
amendment, or would it be a modest way of disciplining agency discretion?</p>
        <p>The most basic point here is that the modem state includes a diverse array
of regulatory statutes, with diverse legitimate purposes, including but not at all
limited to economic efficiency.</p>
        <p>Consider the following:
" Many important regulatory states are plausibly understood in terms of
economic efficiency; 2 15 they can be seen as efforts to counteract market failures.
The Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act 2 16 and the Toxic
Substances Control Act2 17 are examples. Such statutes may be designed to
overcome an absence of sufficient information; harms to third parties; or
collective action problems of various sorts.218
" Some statutes are designed to eliminate illegitimate discrimination or what
might be understood as caste-like features in modem society.2 19 Though
some people think that such statutes
can be defended
on efficiency
grounds, 22 0 their animating impulse has little to do with economic efficiency.
" Some statutes are designed to protect cultural aspirations. 2 21 Examples
include measures safeguarding the national parks, encouraging high-quality
programming, and protecting endangered species.
" Some statutes are designed to redistribute to the poor or to others understood
as having a good claim to public help. This is so even though regulation is a
poor tool for this purpose,22- and though redistribution may really benefit
well-organized interest groups with little claim to public assistance. The
Social Security Act is an obvious example of redistributive law; the Agricultural
Adjustment Act can also be understood in this way, with appropriate
qualifications for its interest-group dimensions.</p>
        <p>Doubtless other possibilities could be mentioned. 223 The point is that the
highly diverse grounds for federal regulation raise many questions about
costbenefit analysis as the only ground for regulation.</p>
        <p>If it is intended as a quasi-constitutional amendment to the regulatory state,
a cost-benefit supermandate could be understood in at least three different
ways. In its most ambitious form, the mandate would amount to an
endorsement of the principle of economic efficiency as the exclusive basis-the
"decision criterion"--for interpretation and application of all statutes.2 2 4 This
would be a fundamental change both because it would understand cost-benefit
analysis in a particular way-as a term for the criterion of economic
efficiency-and because it would amend statutes that, when enacted, seemed
motivated by something other than the efficiency criterion.</p>
        <p>If this were the understanding of the supermandate, all of the statutes to
which the supermandate applies would henceforth be understood in efficiency
terms. To say the least, this would be a dramatic shift in national
understandings. It would indeed represent a kind of constitutional amendment of the
administrative state, rebuilding regulatory efforts on a new foundation. While the
most ambitious reformers in the Senate and the House came close to this view,
none endorsed it explicitly.</p>
        <p>Another, less ambitious possibility is to understand the cost-benefit criteria
in efficiency terms, but only for those statutes that were designed to promote
economic efficiency. Under this approach, the supermandate would not alter
the basic understandings of existing statutes. It would instead have a more
modest but nonetheless important goal: imposing a particular understanding of
technocratic rationality on statutes formerly understood and implemented in a
less precise, more ad hoc, and more intuitive way. As we will see, there is
much to be said in favor of this basic approach.</p>
        <p>A third and least ambitious possibility is to understand cost-benefit criteria
in a less technical and more common-sensical way, as an invitation to balance a
range of variables under statutes that had formerly been thought to be absolutist
and hence to forbid balancing. On this view, a supermandate would not be so
ambitious as to call for the use of purely economic criteria. It would more
modestly ask administrators to look at costs, or adverse effects, as well as at
benefits. This was probably the goal of the majority of those members of
Congress who were in favor of a substantive supermandate. And if the
supermandate is understood in these terms, it makes a great deal of sense. As we
will see, the principal objection to such a supermandate is that it is too
openended. Congress can and should take steps to clarify it, though-I
emphasize-without mandating the efficiency criterion outside of the context of
"market failure" statutes.225</p>
        <p>The House and Senate bills offered almost no guidance for characterizing
costs and benefits, and no guidance at all on the crucial issue of how to value
224. EPsTrEN, supra note 31, at 30 (asserting that the efficiency approach to justice "offer[s] the
best justificatory apparatus for demarcating the scope of state power from the area of individual
choice"). Even when economic efficiency is not the basis for the statute, or when benefits cannot be
quantified, it makes sense to require agencies to quantify costs to the extent that this is possible.
225. See text accompanying notes 237-239 infra (discussing the problem of valuing life).
costs and benefits. For this reason, the provisions look highly substantive but
are in fact largely procedural. Without guidance to constrain valuation, a
requirement of cost-benefit analysis is quite open-ended, though certainly not
meaningless. It alerts agencies to the need to balance a range of considerations
and as a procedural requirement, it will affect outcomes. Moreover, courts may
invalidate outcomes that, by general understandings, seem either out of line
with existing practice or too absolutist. 226 Certainly there is a difference
between agency behavior under balancing statutes and agency behavior under
statutes that forbid balancing. 227</p>
        <p>It is possible to conclude that Congress should restrict itself to a call for
cost-benefit analysis and leave the details to agencies.228 Perhaps Congress
lacks the detailed understanding that would enable it to answer the more
specific questions. But if we are at all concemed about administrative discretion,
we should urge greater guidance from the national legislature.2 29 In any case
the generic bills introduced in the House and Senate would be much improved
if they offered more direction to agencies. I offer two suggestions here.</p>
        <p>
          Qualitativefactors. As I noted in Part I, people care not simply about the
aggregate amount of lives saved, but also about a range of factors involving the
nature of the particular risk. For most people, the most salient contextual
features are: (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          ) whether the risk is catastrophic in nature; (2) whether the risk is
uncontrollable; (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          ) whether the risk involves irretrievable or permanent losses;
(4) whether the risk is voluntarily incurred; (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">5</xref>
          ) whether the risk is equitably
distributed or concentrated on identifiable, innocent, or traditionally
disadvantaged victims; (6) whether the risk is well understood; (7) whether the risk
would be faced by future generations; and (8) whether the risk is familiar.2 30
        </p>
        <p>Any cost-benefit analysis that Congress requires regulatory agencies to
perform should reflect these factors. In developing a cost-benefit formula,
Congress should recognize that a purely quantitative or monetary understanding of
costs and benefits is inadequate. The various consequences of regulation ought
not to be thought commensurable along a single metric. 23 1 Any cost-benefit
analysis should be accompanied by a disaggregated, qualitative description of
the consequences of government action, so that Congress and the public can
226. See Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201, 1215-17, 1229 (5th Cir. 1991)
(rejecting an EPA asbestos regulation issued under the Toxic Substance Control Act because the agency
failed to consider less burdensome alternatives).</p>
        <p>
          227. CompareToxic Substances Control Act, 15 U.S.C. ยงยง 2601-2692 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ), and Federal
Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act, 7 U.S.C. ยงยง 136-136y (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ), with Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C.
ยงยง 7401-7671q (1988 &amp; Supp. V 1993), Delaney Clause, 21 U.S.C. ยง 348(c)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          )(A) (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ), and
Endangered Species Act, 16 U.S.C. ยงยง 1531-1544 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>228. See AcKEumAN &amp; HAssLER, supra note 14, at 5 (describing flexible agencies that can adapt
to changes in science and newly discovered evidence and arguing that "Congress should content itself
with the most general kinds of policy guidance").</p>
        <p>229. See SCHOamROD, supra note 30, at 3-15 (encouraging courts to ban delegation of authority
to administrative agencies and advocating that Congress enact detailed legislation to limit agencies'
power). But see Mashaw, supra note 14, at 97 (arguing against greater guidance and instead advocating
broad delegations of authority to administrative agencies).</p>
        <p>230. See, e.g., BREYER, supranote 14, at 16 (noting that "people value different risks differently").
231. See Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supra note 35, at 65 (calling for "disaggregating costs and benefits,
identifying qualitatively different effects, and taking account of effects on diverse groups").
obtain a fuller picture than the crude and misleadingly precise "bottom line" of
the cost-benefit analysis. 232 This is not at all to deny that it is important to be
precise and quantitative when possible. It is only to say that any "bottom line"
characterization and assessment of costs and benefits will involve judgments
about values, not about science; Congress and the public should see what those
judgments are. 233</p>
        <p>I have suggested that regulatory statutes have legitimate and diverse
functions and that some of those functions do not involve economic efficiency. For
this reason, the efficiency criterion is inadequate as a complete guide to the
regulatory state. It is therefore best for Congress to understand costs and
benefits in the economic fashion only for statutes that are designed to overcome
market failures. And even here, there is room for qualifying the economic
analysis-when, for example, the risk at issue is inequitably distributed, and
when political actors believe that it deserves special attention for that reason.2 4
When the statute does not involve market failure, Congress would still require
cost-benefit balancing as the general background rule; but it should understand
the definition of costs and benefits to be sufficiently broad as to allow
administrators to depart from purely economic criteria. Judicial review should be
available to police administrative decisions for reasonableness and
consistency.2 35 In the long run, it might be hoped, a common law of regulatory
practice might emerge to create rationality and reasonableness where there is now a
high degree of arbitrariness.</p>
        <p>
          The issues I have discussed-the diverse grounds for regulatory statutes,
problems of incommensurability, qualitative distinctions-are probably too
subtle and complex to justify anything like legislative codification. Instead
they suggest that Congress should: (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          ) enact a general background requirement
232. See ANDERSON, supranote 222, at 191-216 (arguing that consequentialist cost-benefit
analysis fails to account for "the diversity of people's values").
        </p>
        <p>
          233. To account for citizens' value judgments, Senate Bill 343 should be amended as follows:
1. Definition of "benefit." Change section 621(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">5</xref>
          ) to read "the term 'benefit' means the reasonably
identifiable significant benefits, including social, economic, ecological, distributional,and aesthetic
benefits, that are reasonablyexpected to result directly or indirectly from implementation of a rule or an
alternative to a rule." My italicized additions allow agencies to define "benefit" to account for citizen
judgments.
        </p>
        <p>
          2. Description of benefits and costs. Add the following sentence to section 622(e)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          )(A): "An
agency shall offer a disaggregated description of the relevant costs and benefits, containing an account
of the qualitative differences, if any, among the costs and benefits at stake." This provision permits a
more comprehensive examination of the full cost-benefit landscape.
        </p>
        <p>
          3. Diverse cost andbenefit factors. Add the following section, 622(e)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          )(C): "Where practicable,
the agency shall, in evaluating and comparing costs and benefits, consider public judgments about how
best to assess relevant risks, including whether the risks under consideration are involuntarily incurred,
likely to affect future generations, potentially catastrophic, especially dreaded, irreversible, or
inequitably distributed." The list is not exhaustive, but does provide agencies an opportunity to account for
diverse public judgments.
        </p>
        <p>234. This qualification should not be used to allow private groups to skew economic analyses in
their preferred directions. It should instead provide room for a formal channel to qualify the economic
analysis when, for example, poor people are peculiarly at risk.</p>
        <p>
          235. See, e.g., Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201, 1220-22 (5th Cir. 1991)
(discussing whether the EPA regulatory decision had a "reasonable basis").
of cost-benefit balancing, 236 with a relatively open-ended understanding of
both costs and benefits; (2) permit agencies to understand cost-benefit analysis
in a way that best fits with the particular statutory scheme; (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          ) impose a
costeffectiveness or "least cost" requirement as part of the supermandate; and (4)
require more technical cost-benefit balancing on a statute-by-statute basis,
when there is a considered legislative judgment that the statute is a response to
a market failure, economically defined. Congress should, however, attempt to
impose some constraints on agency valuations and tools, as I will now discuss.
        </p>
        <p>Floors and ceilings. It is of course troublesome to assign dollar values to
life, partly for the reasons I have sketched. But since tradeoffs of multiple
kinds are inevitable, it may be best for Congress to set out some guidelines,
including floors and ceilings governing expenditures, without pretending to say
how much a life is "really worth." In light of the diversity of regulated risks,
no single number would make sense for valuing life. 237 But it may make sense
to set benchmark standardsof, for example, $10 million per life saved as the
presumptive maximum amount and $3 million as the presumptive minimum.
These benchmarks might be accompanied by explicit permission for agencies
to select a lower or higher amount if the agency can explain that special
circumstances call for it.</p>
        <p>There is a crudeness, however, in the very notion of "dollars per life saved."
A well-functioning regulatory state should not be interested in how many lives
are saved, but in how many statistical years, or how many decently liveable
statistical years, are added by regulation.23 8 An agency would do better to save
forty statistical years than it would to save three, even though, through both
steps, it might be taken to have "saved a life." Where resources are limited, it
makes sense to devote resources to saving people who have the most good
years ahead. This judgment may appear controversial, but it seems supported
by common sense and economic criteria.239 Hence Congress should probably
set floors and ceilings not for lives saved but for life-years saved, with
permission to depart on the basis of justifications that are articulated publicly and are
reasonable on the merits. For life-years, a presumptive ceiling of $500,000
might be a reasonable place to start. Of course any floors and ceilings should
be accompanied with adjustments for inflation.</p>
        <p>Without a figure per life or life-year saved, agencies effectively have
discretion to weigh costs and benefits however they wish. Congress should offer
some guidelines to achieve consistency across agency lines. At a minimum
Congress should require agencies to be explicit about their valuations, so that
these valuations will be subject to legislative and public oversight and review.</p>
        <p>236. Such balancing can be handled with some fairly straightforward language. See note 233
supra.</p>
        <p>237. See VALuING HEA.TH FOR POLICY (George Tolley, Donald Kenkel, &amp; Robert Fabian eds.,
1994) (discussing the diversity of valuations suggested in contingent valuation studies).</p>
        <p>238. For a discussion of quality-adjusted life years, see Richard Zeckhauser and Donald Shepard,
Were Now for Saving Lives?, 40 LAW &amp; CorrEw. PRoBs. 5 (Autumn 1976); Pildes and Sunstein,
supranote 35, at 83-86 (asserting that quality-adjusted life years is a promising method for
incorporating lay perspectives into regulation).</p>
        <p>239. Pildes and Sunstein, supranote 35, at 83-86.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-5">
        <title>Substitute risks.</title>
        <p>We have seen that there is a pervasive problem in risk regulation, one that
is only now receiving public attention, and one that was not adequately
addressed in the proposals before the 104th Congress.2 40 The problem occurs
when the diminution of one risk simultaneouslyincreasesanotherrisk.24 1 For
example, fuel economy standards, designed partly to reduce environmental
risks to life and health, may make automobiles less safe, thus increasing risks to
life and health. Regulations designed to control the spread of AIDS and
hepatitis among health care providers may actually cost lives by increasing the costs
of health care, and thus making health care less widely available.2 42
Regulation of nuclear power may make nuclear power safer; but by increasing costs,
such regulation promotes reliance on other energy sources, such as coal-fired
power plants, which carry risks of their own.2 43 The general problem is
ubiquitous.</p>
        <p>
          As I have noted, no provision in the current proposals deals directly with
this problem. Congress should consider a new provision to this effect:
"(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref19 ref94">1</xref>
          ) Agencies shall ensure, to the extent feasible, that regulations do not
create countervailing risks that are greater than those of regulated risks.
(2) This section shall not apply if it is inconsistent with the provisions of the
enabling statute pursuant to which the agency is acting."
        </p>
        <p>Such a provision would require agencies to ensure that overall risks are not
increased. It would not fundamentally change current law. But it would be a
modest step toward a more coordinated treatment of risk.244</p>
        <p>Thus far I have offered modest suggestions that build on existing proposals.
Three more ambitious strategies would accomplish a great deal more.</p>
        <p>240. H.R. 1022 does contain a reference to substitute risks in section 105, but agencies are
required only to 'consider' such risks. H.R. 1022, 104th Cong., 1st Sess. ยง 105(4).</p>
        <p>241. See Breyer, supra note 14, at 17 (explaining that the ban on EDB, a grain fumigant, could
lead farmers to switch to other, more dangerous fumigants); Graham &amp; Wiener, supra note 61, at 5-25;
Sunstein, supranote 61; text accompanying notes 59-70 supra(discussing harmful, unintended
consequences of regulations).</p>
        <p>242. In American Dental Ass'n v. Martin, 984 F.2d 823 (7th Cir. 1993), the court upheld an
OSHA regulation, but commented on OSHA's failure to follow the "universal precautions" requirement.
Id. at 825. Judge Posner explains:</p>
        <p>OSHA also exaggerated the number of lives likely to be saved by the rule by ignoring lives
likely to be sacrificed by it, since the increased cost ofmedical care, to the extent passed on to
consumers, will reduce the demand for medical care, and some people may lose their lives as a
result.</p>
        <p>Id. at 826.</p>
        <p>
          243. See Kathleen C. Reilly, GlobalBenefits Versus Local Concerns: The Needfor a Bird'sEye
View of NuclearEnergy, 70 IND. L.J. 679, 705-06 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (noting that emissions from coal-fired power
plants contribute significantly to greenhouse gases and to the air pollution which causes acid rain).
        </p>
        <p>244. For a more detailed discussion, see Jonathon Baert Wiener &amp; John D. Graham, Resolving
Risk Tradeoffs, in RisK VERsus RisK, supra note 61, at 220-40.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-6">
        <title>1. Rank risks and reallocate resources to the most severe problems and</title>
        <p>increase the executive's role in priority setting.</p>
        <p>As Justice Breyer suggests, a statute could give the executive some degree
of authority to divert public and private resources from small environmental
problems to large ones, ensuring greater cost-effectiveness in government and
better priority-setting. 245 There are some dangers with this proposal-a small
group of bureaucrats should not have the authority to decide on basic social
priorities. Nonetheless, a greater degree of executive priority-setting would
make sense.</p>
        <p>Justice Breyer's approach should be qualified by remembering that people
are legitimately concerned with the various contextual factors discussed
above-the voluntariness of the risk, its potentially catastrophic character,
whether it is especially dreaded, whether it is equitably distributed, and so
forth.24 6 Efforts at better priority-setting received some modest attention in the
104th Congress; but the proposals were not very ambitious. 24 7</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-7">
        <title>Allow plans from the private sector that show greaterand more cost-effective reductions.</title>
        <p>Often the problem with federal regulation is that the government lacks
knowledge of the least expensive means of producing the preferred regulatory
end. If the private sector were permitted to select the means, it could do so far
more cheaply. This point has been recognized in Europe and Japan, under the
general rubric of "environmental contracting." 248 In the Netherlands, for
example, the government has experimented with comprehensive, multimedia
environmental targets for pollution reduction and has developed strategies to
work with industry groups to achieve overall goals. 249 As part of the
agreement with industry groups, the government agrees to waive otherwise
applicable pollutant-by-pollutant regulations, and to limit changes in requirements
during the length of the contract period.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the EPA has taken modest steps in the same direction.
For example, the EPA and Amoco concluded that a plantwide approach would
better decrease chemical releases than the existing command-and-control
system. 5 0 Similarly, under the Clean Air Act, companies can, in essence,
"contract out" of technology-based regulations for six years if they achieve a 90
245. BREYER, supranote 14, at 18-19; see AcKE mAN &amp; HASsI.ER, supra note 14, at 8 (noting that
environmental law "proved to be especially fertile ground" for agency experimentation).
246. See text accompanying note 230 supra.</p>
        <p>247. See, eg., 141 CONG. REc. S9836-38 (daily ed. July 13, 1995) (Roth-Biden modified
amendment No. 1507).</p>
        <p>248. See MEMNEL &amp; STmwART, supra note 82, at 420-22; see generally ENviRONmENTAL
CONTRACTs AND CovENANTs: NEav INSTRUMENTS FOR A REALISTIC ENvIRmOmmrNAL PoLICY? (Jan M. van
Dunn6 ed., 1993).</p>
        <p>
          249. See Francis H. Irwin, An IntegratedFrameworkfor PreventingPollution andProtectingthe
Environment, 22 ENvrL. L. 1, 29 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47 ref48">1992</xref>
          ) (discussing Netherlands' plan); MENELL &amp; ST WART,supra
note 82, at 421-22.
        </p>
        <p>250. MENELL &amp; STwART,supra note 82, at 421.
percent reduction in toxic pollutants before the EPA promulgates relevant
regulations. 2 5'</p>
        <p>Under most federal statutes, however, the EPA cannot approve private
plans as substitutes for public mandates, even if the plans promise better results
for less money. Congress should move in the direction of allowing private
substitutes, so long as government monitoring is maintained.2 52 A provision of
the June discussion draft of the Dole bill endorsed this strategy, but because its
relationship to other statutes was quite ambiguous, it was unclear whether the
provision would enable agencies to waive existing statutory requirements. 2 53</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-8">
        <title>Regulate with incentives.</title>
        <p>We have seen that command-and-control regulation can be highly
dysfunctional. Sometimes relevant statutes forbid agencies from choosing
incentivebased strategies even where such strategies would be more effective. Congress
might move away from command-and-control regulation by enacting a statute
stating: "Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an agency shall be
permitted to use economic incentives to induce industries to eliminate or reduce
risks, if it can show that these methods will produce at least equivalent benefits
in a more cost-effective manner."2 54 Of course, such a provision could increase
the risk of litigation initiated by self-interested private groups seeking to stall
desirable regulation.2 55 It could also allow agencies unenthusiastic about
regulatory mandates to proceed with less effective means of achieving compliance.
But despite the potential for abuse, the problems with existing
command-andcontrol processes-excessive costs and insufficient regulatory benefits25 6-are
probably sufficient to make it worthwhile to move in this direction.</p>
        <sec id="sec-13-8-1">
          <title>V. POSSIBLE FuTuR~s</title>
          <p>In the area of regulatory reform, and particularly in the context of health,
safety, and the environment, a number of creative ideas are percolating
throughout the nation. These ideas have already had effects on legislation; they
will have increasingly significant consequences inthe coming years. Using
Perceived
Problems
Approved
Measures
1970s
Environmentalism
excessive
pollution; power of
industry</p>
          <p>Cost-Benefit
Analysis
refusal to
balance; absolutism</p>
          <p>Pollution Preven- Free Market
tion Environmentalism
technological
fixes; end of the
pipe controls;
power of industry
national ambient Toxic Substances elimination of
air quality stan- Control Act; lead (CAA);
dards; technologi- FIFRA asbestos rule
cal requirements (TSCA)
Disapproved
Measures</p>
          <p>common law
Preferred
Soluions
Attitude Toward
CBA
command-andcontrol; best
available
technology; technology
forcing
hostility</p>
          <p>Delaney Clause;
national ambient
air quality
standards;
technology-based
regulation
of course
favorable
tinkering with Clean Air Act best available
current cars; tech- especially unholy technology in
nological fixes coalitions CAA and CWVA;
for water pollu- Superfund;
comtion mon law
balancing require- solar energy; create property
ments electric cars; rights; watch the
clean fuels; elimi- market work
nating "root
cause"
economic
incenives in the form
of "polluters pay"
and emissions
trading</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-9">
        <title>LEGISLATIVE FOREWORD</title>
        <p>environmental regulation as an example, I organize those ideas into four
general frameworks: cost-benefit analysis, pollution prevention, free
market
environmentalism,
and
democratic
environmentalism.</p>
        <p>The following table is
designed to provide capsule descriptions:
Five Approaches to Regulatory Reform
absence of
welldefined property
rights;
environmentalism as a
form of
socialism; factionalism
command-andcontrol; poor
priority-setting;
absence of public
deliberation;
interest group
power
common law; the Emergency
Plantakings approach ning and
Conto environmental sumer Right to
regulation; ef. Know Act;
wetlands protec- National
Environion and endan- mental Policy
gered species act Act; acid
deposireform tion provisions of</p>
        <p>CBA
favorable, but favorable insofar
tany questions, as they limit
facsince there is a tional power,
large government focus democracy
role in setting on right
quesprices and/or tions, and put a
quantities; under- premium on
stands "eco- acquiring
infornomic" incentives mation
as creation of real
markets
consumer
sovereignity, based on
maximizing
welfare through
well-informed
public judgments
based on people's
ideals and
convictions
suspicion, since
CBA need not
produce pollution
prevention
Attitude Toward
Economic
Inentives
hostility
favorable insofar
as they minimize
costs
suspicion
Normative Ideal
strict enforcement good balancing of clean
pollutionof statutory man- relevant variables; free technologies,
dates maximizing social with "deep"
ecolwelfare ogy and spiritual
values as possible aggregating
prianimating ideals; vate preferences
nature as a source for environmental
of value and other goods</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-10">
        <title>Cost-Benefit Balancing</title>
        <p>One possibility, captured in many of the current proposals, is to shift in the
direction of cost-benefit balancing for all statutes. Many current statutes forbid
balancing and call for absolutism. Such an approach is not easy to justify.257
Thus the various statutes that are defined in terms of health or technology
might be amended to call for cost-benefit analysis.2 58 As we have seen, this
shift-in the direction of a cost-benefit state-responds to several current
problems with regulation. Moreover, it is important to offer some criteria by
which to monitor regulatory performance, and cost-benefit analysis is probably
the best available technique for embarking on a form of "national performance
review."</p>
        <p>By itself, however, a shift towards cost-benefit analysis would be only a
modest improvement over the status quo. We have seen that, as an abstraction,
cost-benefit analysis lacks a theory of value. If this defect is remedied in the
economist's fashion, by rooting cost-benefit analysis in the economic criterion
of private willingness to pay, it becomes quite controversial and indeed hard to
defend as a global approach. Environmental amenities are not best valued by
aggregating private willingness to pay.259</p>
        <p>Apart from the question of valuation, engrafting a cost-benefit requirement
onto current law is only a modest shift; it does not represent a sufficiently
fundamental change from the system of command-and-control regulation.
Because the calculation of both costs and benefits can be enormously difficult,
requiring agencies to make the necessary inquiries will impose large
informational burdens on government. A general requirement of cost-benefit analysis
allows legislators to take credit for "getting the regulators under control"
without making the hard choices. Such a credit-claiming device hardly substitutes
for reinvented government.</p>
        <p>
          Imagine-to take a rough analogy-that the Soviet Union had decided in,
say, 1986 to replace an "absolutist" five-year plan for producing wheat with
another five-year plan, one that better recognized the need for balancing
competing variables. This step might have been an improvement; but a five-year
257. One such provision is the Delaney Clause, 21 U.S.C. ยง 348(C)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">3</xref>
          )(A) (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ), which forbids
the use of carcinogens in food additives. Congress has enacted several bans on cost-benefit balancing.
See, e.g., 42 U.S.C. ยง 7409(c) (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ) (mandating standard for nitrogen dioxide concentrations); see also
Federal Water Pollution Control Act, 33 U.S.C. ยง 1311(b) (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ); Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C.
ยงยง 7475(a)(4), 7503(a)(2) (1988 &amp; Supp. V 1993). See generallyNational Ambient Air Quality
Standard Regulations, 40 C.F.R. ยงยง 50.1-.12 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">1994</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>258. Critics charge cost-benefit analysis with assuming a misleading wealth of knowledge. See
Howard Latin, Ideal Versus Real Regulatory Efficiency: Implementation of Uniform Standards and
"Fine-Tuning" RegulatoryReforms, 37 STAN. L. REv. 1267, 1273-75, 1279 (1985) (criticizing
proponents of cost-benefit analysis for their unrealistic assumption that all environmental conditions and
control strategies can be known). It is of course possible that cost-benefit analysis would itself fail
costbenefit analysis; thus technology-based approaches could be justified as a response to government's lack
of information and proper incentives. Similarly, it is possible that health-based standards can be
justified by their aspirational and political values-providing a benchmark to which even dirty places may
aspire. These ideas do not, however, argue against the background rule I defend above. See text
accompanying notes 226-244 supra.</p>
        <p>259. See ANZERsoN, supranote 222, at 195-96 (noting difficulty in using private willingness to
pay); text accompanying notes 272-276 infra.
plan based on governmental balancing is no less a five-year plan than one
based on governmental absolutism. 260 Governmental dictation of outcomes
based on cost-benefit analysis is better than governmental dictation based on
absolutism, but neither is ideal. A system in which agencies decide what is to
be done only after considering all costs and benefits is likely to be
time-consuming and will inevitably produce large-scale errors. Such a system imposes
enormous data collection requirements on agencies and also forces them to
make difficult, and hardly scientific, judgments about basic values. This
approach may well be attractive to members of Congress seeking reelection, but it
is not a great deal better than the status quo.</p>
        <p>In fact it would be easy to imagine a generation of dreary cycles with
respect to regulatory reform. In those cycles, conservatives might call for more
balancing of costs and benefits, more procedures, and fewer deadlines for
administrators; liberals would then argue against cost-benefit analysis and for
health-based or technology-based standards, fewer procedures, citizen suits for
regulatory beneficiaries, and stricter deadlines; conservatives, a few years later,
would seek greater procedural requirements and more attention to costs;
liberals would respond with the familiar litany; and so on until, say 2050.</p>
        <p>Although this cyclical model is not a bad description of the regulatory
debates since 1980, its continuation would represent an enormous failure of
imagination and creativity. It would fix American policy in the outmoded debates of
the early 1970s, before the outpouring of learning that makes the "more" or
"less" debate seem so unhelpful. A cost-benefit state ought not to content itself
with governmental specification of outcomes after governmental cost-benefit
judgments have been made. It ought instead to create incentives for
nongovernmental actors to generate information and to produce outcomes based on
incentives generated by democratic judgments.</p>
        <p>In the last decade many people have enthusiastically embraced "pollution
prevention" as the regulatory strategy of choice.261 On this view, government
should eliminate pollutants from the market rather than require pretreatment or
impose technological requirements to reduce the harmful effects of pollutants.
Prominent examples of pollution prevention include the elimination of lead
from gasoline; the phaseout of chlorofluorocarbons; government bans on DDT,
260. This is a Hayekian point based on the government's informational limitations. Thus markets
can be justified partly on the ground that individuals have far better relevant information than does
government. See F.A. HAYEK, Tim CoNsTuToN oF LmERTY 106-120 (1960).</p>
        <p>
          261. See BARRY Co.NoN-R, MAKING PEACE VrrH m PLAT 189-90 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58 ref75">1990</xref>
          ) (asserting that
pollution prevention is the only effective environmental strategy); Barry Commoner, Failureofthe
Environmental Effort, 18 ENvTL. L. REP. 10,195, 10,195 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1988</xref>
          ) (noting that the lesson of the
environmental effort is that pollution can be prevented). See alsoSymposium, PollutionPrevention,29 GA. L. REv.
313 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (surveying issues in pollution prevention); Remarks of Presidentat Rego Event, Mar. 16,
1995, available in WESTLAW, Pres-Daily Database (President Clinton's statement announcing the
launch of EPA project to reduce pollution).
PCBs, and asbestos 262; the shift from high-polluting fossil fuels to clean,
renewable energy sources; and restrictions on mercury pollution in the Great
Lakes and phosphate pollution in local rivers.
        </p>
        <p>Why is pollution prevention so attractive to so many people? Enthusiasts
contend that by preventing the production or use of certain pollutants,
government can make much more progress in reducing pollution than it can by
imposing technological controls or fixes. 263 The proper analogy, it is said, is to the
contrast between prevention and cure. We know that cures tend to be both
more expensive and less effective than preventive measures. American
government has focused on cures; it should shift to prevention. From this perspective,
the basic cause of environmental degradation is current technology, above all
fossil fuels and modem cars. At the same time, the capacity of technology to
diminish its own environmental damage is rapidly becoming exhausted.
Instead of imposing decreasingly effective technological fixes, would it not be
better to take steps to ensure that environmentally harmful substances are not
produced at all?</p>
        <p>Often the answer to this question is affirmative; often pollution prevention
is both feasible and appropriate. 264 But as a global approach, pollution
prevention is inadequate. 265 In some cases pollution prevention would impose
extremely high costs-including environmental costs-for little environmental or
other gain. Recall here that a federal court of appeals invalidated one of the
most ambitious of the recent pollution prevention strategies-the ban on the
manufacture and use of asbestos--on the ground that: (a) the benefits of the
ban could not, in many sectors, be shown to justify the costs and (b) the ban on
asbestos could itself produce a variety of environmental and health-related
problems stemming from the use of environmentally inferior substitutes.266</p>
        <p>This example can be duplicated in many other contexts. Indeed the goal of
pollution prevention, if taken literally, would be a social disaster. For example,
an immediate and wholesale shift to electric cars might seem the best way to
prevent air pollution from motor vehicles. But electric cars are now extremely
expensive, and the costs, for workers and consumers, of a ban on contemporary
automobiles would plainly be excessive. In fact, electric cars produce
environ262. But see Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201, 1215-17 (5th Cir. 1991)
(invalidating EPA ban on "for all practical purposes, all present and future uses of asbestos").</p>
        <p>263. See CommoNER, supranote 261, at 41-44 (concluding that the best environmental results are
achieved by pollution prevention rather than control technologies).</p>
        <p>
          264. Hence the idea is playing a large role within EPA. See 60 Fed. Reg. 23,928 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (to be
codified at 40 C.F.R. ยง 1) (detailing EPA's agenda for a comprehensive reevaluation of its rfles);
SciaNcE ADvisoRy BOARD, EPA, No. SAB-EC-90-021, RFDUcINo RISK: SErr7No PRIORmEs AND
SmaTA'GIES FOR Evrmo~mEaNrAL PROTECnON 22 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58 ref75">1990</xref>
          ) (recommending pollution prevention). Some Clean
Water Act proposals have also focused on pollution prevention strategies. See, e.g., 141 CONG. Rac.
ES10 (daily ed. Mar. 3, 1995) (statement of Rep. Oberstar).
        </p>
        <p>265. See ViLDAVSKy, supra note 214, at 77-103 (arguing for a version of cure rather than
prevention).</p>
        <p>266. Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201, 1220-22 (5th Cir. 1991) (finding that EPA
presented insufficient evidence to justify asbestos ban).
mental harms of their own267 -a potential problem for many pollution
prevention strategies.</p>
        <p>In these circumstances, pollution prevention is sometimes worse than
costbenefit analysis or economic incentives. By imposing a direct cost on polluting
activity, economic incentives can identify the circumstances in which
prevention or cure makes the most sense. For example, fees imposed on the
production of sulfur dioxide may lead some companies to eliminate sulfur dioxide; in
any case the judgment would be left to (appropriately constrained) market
forces. Alternatively, cost-benefit analysis might show that pollution
prevention is not worthwhile.</p>
        <p>The appropriate conclusion is that pollution prevention is often a good
regulatory strategy, but that it cannot be adopted in all or even most contexts.
Whether it is the best solution depends on the pollutant in question, the
available substitutes, and the effects of the preventative approach.</p>
        <p>Much creative thought has been dedicated to using "free markets" as a
mechanism for promoting environmental and other goals. 268 To free market
advocates, the problem of environmental degradation stems from a simple fact:
the absence of secure property rights in environmental amenities.2 69 The
creation of secure property rights tends to reduce environmental problems.</p>
        <p>There is much truth to this suggestion, and there is considerable promise to
the resulting proposals. If environmental assets were owned, so that owners
faced the full costs of excessive development, it is likely that excessive
pollution would be prevented. In many settings, free market environmentalism
points in promising directions. Consider, for example, possible amendments to
the Endangered Species Act, related to proposals introduced in the 104th
Congress. In its current form, the Act creates difficult problems for any landowner
who discovers that his land contains a critical habitat for an endangered or
threatened species. Discovery of such a habitat subjects the property to a range
of limitations.270 Hence a landowner has an incentive either to lie about the
facts or to proceed with development as rapidly as possible to avoid the
constraints of the Endangered Species Act. It would be far better to use market
approaches so that landowners are rewarded rather than punished by a
discovery that threatened or endangered species need their land.27 1</p>
        <p>267. See Lori A. Burkhart, Benefits of Low-Emission Vehicles Uncertain,FORT., Dec. 1, 1994, at
34 (doubting the ability of low emission vehicles to improve air quality and energy security).</p>
        <p>
          268. See generally Symposium, FreeMarket Environmentalism:The Role of theMarket in
EnvironmentalProtection,15 HARv. J.L. &amp; PUB. POL'Y 297 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47 ref48">1992</xref>
          ) (surveying approaches to environmental
protection, including market-based solutions).
        </p>
        <p>269. See TERRY L. ANDERSON &amp; DON.ALD R. LEAL, FREE MAuc=r ENVRoNM NTA.SM 20-23
(1991) (proposing an approach to environmental protection based on property rights).
270. See EpsrarN,supra note 31, at 291-93.</p>
        <p>
          271. See EndangeredSpecies Act: HearingsBefore theSenate Comm. on EnvironmentandPublic
Works, 104th Cong., Ist Sess. (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) available in LEXIS, Legis Library, Cngtst File (statement of
Gregg Easterbrook, author) (advocating the creation ofprivate preservation firms that would operate on
a free market basis); see also Incentivesfor PrivateLandowners Underthe EndangeredSpecies Act:
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-11">
        <title>STANFORD LAW REVIEWV</title>
        <p>For two reasons, however, free market environmentalism is an incomplete
solution. First, it is not always possible to assign ownership rights. Consider,
for example, the problems posed by acid deposition, the greenhouse effect, and
the destruction of the ozone layer. Economic incentives, based on market
thinking, may be preferable to command-and-control measures; but it is
difficult to imagine a system in which private ownership rights are fully allocated.</p>
        <p>The second reason is more theoretical. Free market environmentalism
depends on the view that the market paradigm should be deemed normative for
purposes of environmental protection. Thus the key question becomes how
much people, as consumers, would pay for environmental amenities. 272 The
answer to that question defines people's "choices" and "values." Indeed, for
free market environmentalists it is hard to imagine how choices and values
might otherwise be understood.</p>
        <p>But it is wrong to take private choices, expressed in the market domain, as
definitional of preferences. 273 Private willingness to pay in the market domain
reflects a particular setting; it does not reflect global choices or valuations.2 74
The choices people make are a function of the particular role in which they find
themselves. As consumers, people make choices that diverge from those they
make as citizens. The appropriate kind and degree of environmental protection
raise issues that should be discussed by citizens offering reasons for one or
another view. This democratic conception of environmental protection
competes with the market-oriented view. Of course, a democratic approach to
environmental law will use market incentives in many contexts, partly because of
the advantages of market incentives on simple democratic grounds.</p>
        <p>
          Moreover, private willingness to pay is undergirded by social norms and
existing habits, and these should probably be changed; indeed, in the
environmental context they had better be.2 75 Consider, for example, the issues posed
by littering and recycling. Social norms with respect to these issues have
shifted dramatically in the last generation. Thus the act of recycling is now, in
many communities, taken for granted, where a decade ago that same act was
perceived as odd or fanatical. Or consider smoking. A principal issue here is
whether smoking is promoted or undermined by social norms. Large
reductions in smoking among African-American teenagers appear to have been
Hearings Before the Subcomm. On Environment and Natural Resources of the House Comm. on
MerchantMarineandFisheries,103d Cong., 1st Sess. (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref112 ref120">1993</xref>
          ) availablein LEXIS, Legis Library, Cngtst
File [hereinafter Hearings](statement ofRobert Thornton, attorney, Nossaman, Guthner, Knox &amp; Elliot)
(advocating a "Habitat Transaction Method" that awards conservation credits to landowners who
preserve or enhance habitats).
        </p>
        <p>272. ANDEDsoN &amp; LEAL, supranote 269, at 3, 147-51; see also Viscusi, supra note 41, at 19-23
(exploring private willingness to pay as a method of valuation).</p>
        <p>273. See Sen, supranote 212, at 23-24 (questioning the view that the individual in a free market
best addresses environmental evaluation).</p>
        <p>274. See generallyCAss R. SusTan , FP.aa MARars AND SociAL JusTicE (forthcoming 1996);
Cass R. Sunstein, Social Norms and Social Rules, 96 CoLum. L. Rav. (forthcorning 1996); Cass R.
Sunstein, On the ExpressiveFunction ofLaw, 144 U. PA. L. REv. (forthcoming 1996).</p>
        <p>
          275. See generallyLawrence Lessig, The Regulation of SocialMeaning, 62 U. Cm. L. REv. 943
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (exploring how law helps to construct social reality and the techniques used by government to
construct social meaning); Sunstein, supra note 274.
brought about by changes in social norms.276 A prime purpose of
environmental law is to shape norms and habits. The central weakness of free market
environmentalism is that it removes this issue from the agenda.
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-12">
        <title>DemocraticEnvironmentalism</title>
        <p>A final approach would base regulatory law on people's reflective
judgments, as citizens, about their basic goals. On this view, the most significant
problems in the current system consist of interest-group power, myopic
responses to sensationalist anecdotes, and inadequate information. A
market-oriented understanding of the regulation is inadequate because it fails to provide a
forum for public deliberation. Similarly, a purely technocratic conception is
inadequate because it devalues the need to rely on people's reflective
judgments.2 77 More specifically, the technocratic approach fails to reflect the
various qualitative factors that influence public judgments about risk-whether a
risk is voluntarily incurred, equitably distributed, potentially catastrophic,
especially dreaded, and so forth.2 78 And as we have seen, there is a difference
between the judgments people make as citizens and those they make as
consnmers; in principle, the former are the relevant judgments with respect to
public policy.</p>
        <p>A good model for democratic environmentalism is the Emergency Planning
and Community Involvement Right-to-Know Act,2 79 which requires the
creation and publication of a list of release levels for each of more than three
hundred toxic chemicals that exceed threshold quantities. 280 The result is a Toxic
Release Inventory, an annual EPA report of toxic chemical releases that
summarizes the relevant information. The publicity has two desirable
consequences. First, the Toxic Release Inventory gives states and localities the
information needed to decide whether to act at the governmental level. The
Toxic Release Inventory thereby spurs decentralized political action. Second,
public reaction to the publication leads many companies to pledge to make
voluntary reductions. Thus the Monsanto Corporation pledged a ninety percent
cut within four years, and AT&amp;T established a goal of eliminating all toxic air
emissions by the turn of the century; many other companies have produced new
waste reduction initiatives as well.2 8'</p>
        <p>276. See Abigail Trafford, Winners &amp; Losers:A Look at the PastTen Years, WASH. PosT, Jan. 3,
1995, availablein WESTLAW, Alinews Database (noting a 51% drop in smoking among black teens,
but a 14% increase among white teens); see alsoRichard J. Bonnie &amp; Barbara S. Lynch, Time to Up the
Ante in the War on Smoking, Issuas Sci. &amp; TEcH., Sept. 22, 1994, at 33 (noting a decline in daily
smoking among African Americans from 16% in 1980 to 4A% in 1993).</p>
        <p>277. This is the drawback of Breyer's proposal, which offers a "better-government or bureaucratic
solution" to the problem of risk regulation. BREYEPR, supra note 14, at 59
278. See Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supranote 35, at 88.</p>
        <p>279. Emergency Planning and Community Right-To-Know Act of 1986, 42 U.S.C. ยงยง
11,00111,050 (1988 &amp; Supp. V 1993).</p>
        <p>280. Id. at ยง 11,023.
281. PERcrvAL Er A., supra note 57, at 624-26.</p>
        <p>For democratic environmentalists, 28 2 much of the promise of economic
incentives lies in the fact that they promise to reduce interest-group power by
removing attention from the question of means, which is so clearly a recipe for
interest-group struggle. Economic incentives also have the advantage of
focusing the public's attention on the right questions. 28 3 Hence the acid deposition
provisions of the 1990 Clean Air Act are a model for the future because they
reflect a democratic judgment about outcomes. 28 4 The much-criticized (and
internationally much-imitated) National Environmental Policy Act285 is also a
model from the democratic point of view, insofar as it requires the disclosure of
environmental consequences before the government can act,2 86 and in that
sense spurs political (but not judicial 28 7) safeguards. It is especially important
to ensure that public judgments are adequately informed. A system in which
the public responds to misleading and sensationalistic anecdotes only parodies
democratic aspirations.28 8</p>
        <p>Of course these are stylized discussions of abstractions that must be applied
to complex policy initiatives. It is best to approach particular problems in a
pragmatic and experimental manner. All four approaches have something to
offer, and they can be combined in different ways to arrive at the best solution.
In cases involving dangerous substances with good substitutes, the argument
for pollution prevention is overwhelming. Where private ownership is
possible, free market environmentalism may well be preferable to the alternatives,
notwithstanding the theoretical objections offered above. In some situations,
cost-benefit balancing at the government level is unavoidable. We may believe
that for reasons associated with democratic environmentalism, a strong
commitment to the protection of endangered species makes sense. But even if this
is so, it may be best to use market-like instruments to accomplish democratic
goals-through, for example, "habitat credits" that reward rather than punish
landowners who discover that their land supports the continued existence of an
endangered species. 2 89</p>
        <p>Some of the most promising modem initiatives are rooted in democratic
judgments, but at the same attempt time to harness private initiative and market
forces in the interest of those veryjudgments. In this way it may be possible to
282. See Bruce A. Ackerman &amp; Richard B. Stewart, Reforming EnvironmentalLaw, 37 STAN. L.
REv. L. 1333, 1341-55 (1985) (arguing for use of marketable pollution rights to enhance democratic
quality of environmental policy making).</p>
        <p>283. See id. at 1353.</p>
        <p>
          284. But see Lisa Heinzerling, Selling Pollution,ForcingDemocracy, 14 STAN. ENVrL. L.J. 300,
318 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">1995</xref>
          ) (challenging the view that the incentive-based regulatory strategy of the Clean Air Act
Amendments of 1990 promotes democratic deliberation about environmental protection).
        </p>
        <p>285. National Environmental Policy Act of 1969, 42 U.S.C. ยงยง 4321-4370d (1988 &amp; Supp. V
1993).</p>
        <p>286. Id. ยง 4332(C).</p>
        <p>
          287. See Strycker's Bay Neighborhood Council, Inc. v. Karlen, 444 U.S. 223, 227 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">1980</xref>
          ) (per
curiam) (holding that so long as an agency follows NEPA's procedural requirements, the only role for a
court is to make sure that the agency considered environmental consequences).
        </p>
        <p>288. See WXLDAvsKY, supranote 85, at 151, 375-94. For example, Superfund is a product of the
less than fully informed public outcry surrounding the Love Canal scandal. Subsequent studies suggest
that the risks to humans from hazardous waste dumps are actually very low. See id. at 160.
289. See HAm~iNos, supranote 271.
accommodate both free market and democratic environmentalism, nominally
opposed foundations that could make a creative rapprochement. This is the
direction in which the most productive reforms might lead. They would
produce a kind of cost-benefit state, but one that is neither purely technocratic nor
entirely founded on the willingness-to-pay criterion. In such a state, regulatory
outcomes would be founded on value judgments that are reflective, reasoned,
and democratically developed. An approach of this kind would synthesize
emerging enthusiasm for technocratic tools and for decreased cost with the
basic American commitment to deliberative democracy.</p>
        <p>VI.</p>
        <p>CONCLUSION</p>
        <p>The election of the 104th Congress, together with the Contract with
America, signals that the nation may be in the midst of a constitutional
moment. At the very least the 104th Congress raised more fundamental questions
about the national government than at any time since the New Deal. Most of
the key initiatives were passed by the House but floundered in the Senate. The
public never authoritatively committed itself to such fundamental change, and
hence the constitutional moment, though signalled, failed to occur. Whether it
will happen in the future depends on the judgments of the American
peopleon whether those judgments will be made with the firmness that American
institutions require.</p>
        <p>Even if regulatory reform does not become part of a constitutional moment,
the nation is embarking increasingly on the project of assessing government
performance by asking whether the benefits justify the costs. The regulatory
state is becoming something like a cost-benefit state; this is an unmistakable
feature of public life in many institutions of American government. In light of
the chaotic and uncoordinated character of modem regulation, this is in many
ways a salutary development. But it is only a start, above all because the
abstract ideas of "cost" and "benefit" need to be specified by some theory of
value. In the 104th Congress, legislative debates over regulatory reform were
mostly procedural and unimaginative, trapped in an increasingly pointless
discussion of whether "more" or "less" regulation is desirable. In the end, almost
nothing happened.</p>
        <p>To be sure, some proposals would have improved the modem regulatory
state by reducing regulatory excesses and encouraging better priority-setting.
In addition, the deliberative process of the Senate reflected a learning process
in which poorly conceived provisions were deleted 290 and better alternatives
were proposed. 291 But for the most part, these proposals were far less
sophisti290. See for example, the Glenn bill, which preserved the EPA's Toxic Release Inventory
program in its entirety; this bill was defeated by Senate Republicans. Ronald Begley, FrustrationsMount
in Effort to Scale BackRegulations, CHEMIcAL WL-, July 26, 1995, at 9. See also Proposalto Revive
Regulatory Bill Gets Cool Reception from Dole, Industry, Daily Lab. Rep. (BNA) No. 152, at D-16
(Aug. 8, 1995).</p>
        <p>291. One example is the Roth-Biden Amendment. 141 CONG. REc. S9836-37 (daily ed. July 13,
1995).
cated and creative than those that emerged from the executive branch, including
the "reinventing government" working groups.</p>
        <p>A general lesson emerges from this phenomenon. In the last fifteen years,
the executive branch has embraced a form of cost-benefit analysis for specific
purposes-to promote better priority-setting, to move towards market-oriented
tools, to exempt de minimis risks, to attend to informed public judgments, to
foster voluntary and least-cost compliance, and to focus on ultimate results
rather than methods and processes. To be sure, there is much to criticize in the
efforts of the executive branch.292 But all in all, they are quite
promisingcertainly more so than the various bills that attracted so much attention in the
104th Congress.</p>
        <p>As we have seen, balancing is preferable to absolutism. The point is
especially important in light of the fact that with respect to the protection of human
health, absolutism may actually be counterproductive and hence far from what
it seems.293 But cost-benefit balancing is an abstract idea that needs
specification, and it is insufficient to graft a supermandate of "balancing" on top of a
structure of command-and-control regulation. Future congressional debate
over the regulatory state should not remain frozen in a discussion of whether
regulation imposes excessively high costs (it surely does) or whether more
should be done to protect people from a range of harms, including risks to life
and health (it surely should). Too many proposals in the 104th Congress
reflected too little of the learning of the last twenty years of experience.
Embodying instead the unhelpful (though accurate) judgment that there is "excessive"
regulation, they attempted to clog the administrative process with paperwork.</p>
        <p>There is an institutional lesson from all this: Congress is not well-equipped
effectively to redesign the regulatory state. The executive branch, with its
cadre of experts in numerous substantive areas, is in a better position. For this
reason it may be best for Congress to limit its efforts to providing broad signals
about what is wrong and to allow the executive branch, within limits, to
provide solutions. Statutes that permit or require economic incentives, and that
call for suitably constrained balancing, may be the best that Congress can do.</p>
        <p>But there is a substantive lesson as well. If there is to be an Administrative
Substance Act, it should build on the foundation laid by recent learning about
regulatory performance. In the process it would be possible not only to save
billions of dollars unnecessarily wasted on current programs, but also to save
many thousands of lives.</p>
        <p>A constitutional moment of the sort signaled by the 104th House of
Representatives deserves far more reflection and scrutiny than the House itself was
willing to give it. And a cost-benefit state will have many questions to answer,
292. A good discussion appears in THOMAS 0. McGAiTY, REInVENTNG RATIONALrrY: Tim ROLE
OF REGULATORY ANALYsIs INTE FEDERAL BUREAUCRACY 165-75 (1991) (evaluating the regulatory
analysis conducted by various executive branch agencies). See also OFFCE OF POUCY ANALYsis, EPA,
REP. No. EPA/23012-871025a, UNFINSHED Busnwss: A CoMPARATIVE ASSESSMENT OF
ENviRoNmENTAL PROBLEMS 94-100 (1987) (challenging the focus of EPA's regulatory priorities through a
comparison of the risks associated with thirty-one major environmental problems).</p>
        <p>293. See notes 59-70 supra and accompanying text.
especially on underlying questions of valuation. I have suggested that a general
background requirement of cost-benefit balancing-a substantive
supermandate-should be enacted. I have also suggested that this background rule
can and should be rejected through clearly expressed legislative judgments in
particular statutes. In describing costs and benefits, Congress should allow
room for a diverse array of values, and not limit agencies to the criterion of
private willingness to pay. Many statutes require or permit agencies to promote
goals independent of economic efficiency, and such statutes are entirely
legitimate. Legislation that would amend all such statutes in favor of the efficiency
criterion would indeed be quasi-constitutional in nature. But in a
well-functioning deliberative democracy, such legislation would be hard to defend on the
merits.</p>
        <p>More modestly, an Administrative Substance Act, amending the regulatory
state, should include the background requirement I have described and also
require agencies to act in a cost-effective fashion. Congress should move as
well in the direction of requiring economic criteria where the underlying statute
is best understood as remedying a market failure, economically defined. A
cost-benefit state, understood in these terms, could make large improvements,
without embarking on foundational reform and without answering the hardest
questions, by offering initiatives that make sense under any reasonable theory
of value.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          1.
          <string-name>
            <surname>INTRODUCTION .................................................. 249</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. A Stalled ConstitutionalMoment .......................... 249</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>B. Lessons ................................................. 251</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>II.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>THE ATTACK ON THE NEW DEAL ..</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>.............................. 253</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. A New</surname>
            <given-names>ConstitutionalMoment? ........................... 253</given-names>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
            <surname>Post-New Deal</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>LearningAbout Regulation ................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>257 1. Government should engage in betterpriority-setting</article-title>
          ....
          <volume>257</volume>
          2.
          <article-title>Government shouldfavor flexible, market-based</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>incentives ratherthan rigid commands................. 260</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>paperwork</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and
          <article-title>protect against regulatory abuses by agencies). 5</article-title>
          . See, e.g.,
          <article-title>Reform of the OccupationalSafety and Health Administration'sEnforcement Pro-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>gram: Hearings Before the Senate Comm. on Labor and Human Resources, 104th Cong., 1st Sess.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(statement of William Steinmetz Jr</article-title>
          ., National Roofing Contractors Association)
          <article-title>(advocating less</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>regulation on small business); Hearingson H</article-title>
          .R.
          <volume>994</volume>
          ,
          <article-title>"The RegulatorySunset andReview Act of</article-title>
          .
          <year>1995</year>
          ,"
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>House Comm. on Government Reform and Oversight, 104th Cong., 1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(statement of Paul</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mashburn</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Viking Builders)
          <article-title>(calling for support of H</article-title>
          .R.
          <volume>994</volume>
          , which, among
          <article-title>its provisions, provides for</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>cost-benefit analysis and review of all federal regulation). 6</article-title>
          . Administrative Procedure Act, ch.
          <volume>324</volume>
          ,
          <issue>60</issue>
          <year>Stat</year>
          .
          <volume>237</volume>
          (
          <article-title>codified as amended in scattered sections</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          of 5 U.S.C.). 7.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pub</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. No.
          <issue>104-1</issue>
          ,
          <issue>109</issue>
          <year>Stat</year>
          .
          <volume>3</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(making certain laws regarding, inter alia</article-title>
          , employment
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>discrimination and fair labor standards applicable to Congress itself). 8</article-title>
          . H.R.
          <volume>2</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>104th</given-names>
            <surname>Cong</surname>
          </string-name>
          .,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(authorizing the President to veto appropriations acts and</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>targeted tax benefits contained in revenue acts). 9</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pub</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. No.
          <issue>104-4</issue>
          ,
          <issue>109</issue>
          <year>Stat</year>
          .
          <volume>48</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(requiring special consideration of federal mandates that</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>impose a burden on the private sector or on state or local governments of more than $100 million)</article-title>
          . 10.
          <string-name>
            <surname>H.R.J. Res</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>104th</given-names>
            <surname>Cong</surname>
          </string-name>
          .,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Steve</surname>
            <given-names>Daley</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , GOPAgenda Moves U.S.
          <article-title>Toward a Turning Point, Cm</article-title>
          . TRM.,
          <source>Aug</source>
          .
          <volume>13</volume>
          ,
          <year>1995</year>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          ยง 1, at 1. 19.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See JAMES M. LANDIS</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>THE ADmISmmATrv PROCESS 1</source>
          ,
          <issue>46</issue>
          (
          <year>1935</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing the inadequacy</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>of the tripartite system)</source>
          .
          <source>20. See id. at 11</source>
          . 21.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>PERSONAL</given-names>
          </string-name>
          PRmSDENr, supra note 17,
          <article-title>at 1-6 (documenting the expansion of executive</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>RECONCEIVING =a REGULATORY STATE 18-24</source>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Franklin D. Roosevelt</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Message to the
          <source>Congress on the State ofthe Union (Jan. 11</source>
          ,
          <year>1944</year>
          ),
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>in 13 THE PUBLIC PAPERS</article-title>
          AND
          <string-name>
            <surname>ADDRESSES OF FRANKLn D. ROOSEVELT</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>VICrORY</article-title>
          AND THRESHOLD
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>OF PEACE</source>
          ,
          <year>1944</year>
          -
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          , at
          <volume>32</volume>
          , 41 (
          <string-name>
            <surname>Samuel</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Rosenman ed.,
          <year>1950</year>
          ).
          <article-title>23. I do not intend here to engage the debate over whether the New Deal actually qualifies as a</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>constitutional amendment</article-title>
          .
          <source>CompareAcsnEMA, supra note 1</source>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>with Laurence</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tribe</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Taking Text
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>and StructureSeriously: Reflections on Free-FormMethod in ConstitutionalInterpretation,108 HARv.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>L.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>REv</year>
          .
          <volume>1221</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1299</issue>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(rejecting Ackerman's theory of higher lawmaking)</article-title>
          .
          <source>In my view, the New</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Deal should not be so understood</article-title>
          . See
          <string-name>
            <surname>CAss R. SunsmIN</surname>
          </string-name>
          , New Deals, NEw REPUBLIC, Jan.
          <volume>20</volume>
          ,
          <year>1992</year>
          , at
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <volume>32</volume>
          (
          <string-name>
            <surname>reviewing</surname>
            <given-names>ACKERMAN</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>supra note 1)</source>
          .
          <article-title>The idea of a constitutional moment should, I think, be seen</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>tutional amendment. Nor do I intend to specify the criteria for deciding whether the nation has exper27</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>See CoNTRAcr WIrH AMERICA, supra note 4, at 125 (criticizing government efforts to legis-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>late solutions to social problems); Richard A. Epstein, The ProperScope of the Commerce Power,73</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>VA. L.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>REv</year>
          .
          <volume>1387</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>1388</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>(arguing that the Commerce Clause should not be used as a vehicle for expan-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>sive government powers)</source>
          .
          <volume>28</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See CoNrrcr WrrH</surname>
            <given-names>AMERICA</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>supra note 4</source>
          , at 73 (
          <article-title>arguing for state-based welfare</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>programs)</source>
          .
          <source>29. See Welfare Reform Consolidation Act of</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          , H.R.
          <volume>999</volume>
          , 104th Cong.,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          );
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Local</given-names>
            <surname>Government Law Enforcement Block Grants</surname>
          </string-name>
          of
          <year>1995</year>
          , H.R.
          <volume>728</volume>
          , 104th Cong.,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          );
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Welfare and Teenage Pregnancy Reduction Act</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>H.R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>513</year>
          , 104th Cong.,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          . See JoHN HART ELY,
          <string-name>
            <surname>DEMOCRACY AD DistRusr: A THEORY OF JuDICIAL RvEw</surname>
          </string-name>
          131-
          <fpage>34</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing the lack of accountability of administrative agencies); DAVID SCHOENROD</article-title>
          , POwER
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>WITHoT REsPoNsIat</article-title>
          .rY: How CoNGR.
          <source>ss ABusEs rH PEOPLE THROUGH DELEGATION 163-64</source>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>(recommending a constitutional amendment prohibiting delegation of power to agencies</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>31</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See RICHARD</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A. EPsTEIN, SIMPLE RurLs FOR A</article-title>
          COMPLEX WORLD
          <volume>21</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(asserting that</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>foster')</source>
          .
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>See text accompanying notes 127-128 infra (discussing the emphasis on property rights and</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>compensation requirements in current bills)</source>
          .
          <volume>33</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generally Peter Linneman</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Effects of ConsumerSafety Standard: The 1973 Mattress</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>FlammabilityStandard</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,in CHICAGO STUDrms IN POLITICAL ECONOMY
          <volume>441</volume>
          (
          <string-name>
            <surname>George</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Stigler ed.,
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Paul</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Portney</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Robert N. Stavins</surname>
          </string-name>
          , RegulatoryReview ofEnvironmentalPolicy: The Poten-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>tial Role of Health-HealthAnalysis, 8 J. RISK &amp; UNCERTAINTY 111, 119 n.1</source>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ). 38.
          <article-title>HARvARD GROUP ON RISK MANAGEMENT REFORM, REFORM OF RISK REGULATION: ACIEVING</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>MORE PROTECTION AT Lass CosT</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(citing Tammy 0</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tengs</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Optimizing Societal Investments
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>in Preventing Premature Death</source>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(doctoral dissertation</article-title>
          ,
          <source>Harvard School of Public Health))</source>
          .
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>I use the word "apparently" because legitimate public judgments will support some disparities</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>See text accompanying notes 74-88 infra. 40. Tammy 0</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tengs</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Miriam E. Adams, Joseph S. Pliskin, Dana Gelb Safran, Joanna E. Siegel,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>tiveness, 15 RISK ANALYSIs 369, 371 tbl. 1</source>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ). 41. W. Kip Viscusi,
          <article-title>FATAL TRADEoFFs: PUBLIC AND PRIVATE RESPONSmILITIES FOR RISK 264</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
          <fpage>42</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          . 43.
          <article-title>OFFICE OF MANAGEMENT AND BtDGET, BUDGEr OF THE UNITED STATES GovERNMmrr</article-title>
          , Fis-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>CAL YEAR</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          , pt. 2, at 370, tbl. C-
          <article-title>2</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>This table does not prove that current allocations are inefficient</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref49">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>gains for plants and animals, and improvements in aesthetics. Table 1 does not include this information</article-title>
          . 44.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generallyMarch Sadowitz &amp; John D. Graham</surname>
          </string-name>
          , A Survey of ResidualCancerRisks Permit-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>ted by Health,Safety andEnvironmentalPolicy,6 RISK: HEMTH, SAFEvY</article-title>
          &amp; EtNviRoNmENT
          <volume>17</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>(documenting differences in agencies' standards for acceptable risk levels from hazardous substances</article-title>
          ).
          <source>45. Id. at 19-20</source>
          .
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          . Public Citizen v.
          <source>Young</source>
          ,
          <volume>831</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1108</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1111</fpage>
          -22
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1987</year>
          )
          <article-title>(holding that the Delaney</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Clause considers even de minimus risks of cancer unacceptable), cert</article-title>
          . denied, 485 U.S.
          <volume>1006</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          . See Industrial Union Dep't v. American Petroleum Inst.,
          <volume>448</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>607</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>614</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          ,
          <fpage>649</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          (iden-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>tifying and describing the significant risk requirement)</source>
          .
          <source>48. See text accompanying notes 74-88 infra. 49</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cf Whitman AdministrationReport Urges Revamped</surname>
            <given-names>RegulatoryProcedures</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,St. Env't Daily
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>(3NA)</source>
          ,
          <source>Aug. 4</source>
          ,
          <year>1995</year>
          , available in LEXIS,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Environ</surname>
            <given-names>Library</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>BNASED</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>File (summarizing New Jersey's</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>control regulation)</source>
          .
          <source>50. See Federal Water Pollution Control Act</source>
          ,
          <volume>33</volume>
          U.S.C. ยง
          <volume>1311</volume>
          (
          <article-title>b)(1)(A) (</article-title>
          <year>1988</year>
          ); Clean Air Act,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>42 U.S.C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>ยงยง 741 l(a)(1), 7412(d)(2), 7475(a)(4), 7502(c)(1) (1988 &amp;</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Supp. V</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See T.H. T mTENBEiRMGss</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>iONs TRADINo 38-59</source>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          )
          <article-title>(estimating the potential savings</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>The EPA at "Thirtysomething,"21 ENrL</source>
          . L.
          <volume>1461</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1463</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(noting savings ofup to $3 million</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref58">
        <mixed-citation>
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>For example, the "offset" provisions of the nonattainment program of the Clean Air Act im-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref59">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>pose a "lowest achievable emissions rate" requirement in addition to the offsets</article-title>
          .
          <source>Clean Air Act</source>
          ,
          <volume>42</volume>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref60">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>U.S.C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>ยงยง 7410(a)(2)(I), 7501(3) (1988 &amp;</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Supp. V</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Robert</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hahn</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Gordon L. Hester, MarketablePermits:Lessonsfor Theory andPractice,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref61">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>16 ECOLOGY L.Q</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>361</volume>
          , 374 tbl.
          <volume>2</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>"Bubble" programs, combined state and federal, save an</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref62">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>additional S435 million per year</article-title>
          .
          <source>Id. 54. See 141 CONG. REc. H4690-4691</source>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(debating Clinton's Clean Water Act proposals</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>55</volume>
          . TiErENnBuR, supra note 51, at
          <volume>44</volume>
          . 56.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Wesley A. Magat</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>W. Kip</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Viscusi</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Joel
          <string-name>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Consumer ProcessingofHazard</surname>
          </string-name>
          Warn-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref63">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ing Information</source>
          , 1
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. RISK</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; UNCERTAeNTY
          <volume>201</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>(concluding that cognitive factors must</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref64">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>be considered when analyzing the rationality ofrisk-taking behavior); Pildes</article-title>
          &amp; Sunstein, supranote
          <volume>35</volume>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref65">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>at 76-80 (explaining that perceived risks will affect individual behavior); V. Kerry Smith</article-title>
          , William H.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref66">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Desvousges &amp; John W. Payne</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Do Risk Information ProgramsPromoteMitigatingBehavior</source>
          ,
          <volume>10</volume>
          J. RiSK
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref67">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>&amp; UNcERTAwNTY 203</source>
          ,
          <fpage>210</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          ROBERT V.
          <article-title>PERCIVAL, ALAN S. MILLER</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>CHRISTOPHER H. SCHROEDER</surname>
          </string-name>
          , &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>JAMEs D. LEAPE</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref68">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ENVIONMmENTAL REGrLATOn</source>
          ,4: LAW,
          <string-name>
            <surname>SCIENCE</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>AND POLICY 624-27</source>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>(describing effectiveness of</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref69">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>information disclosure in attaining voluntary pollution reductions)</source>
          .
          <volume>58</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See WEst.E A. MAGAT</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>W. Kip</surname>
            <given-names>Viscust</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , INFORMAnONAL ApPROACHES TO REGULATION,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref70">
        <mixed-citation>
          87-
          <fpage>105</fpage>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>(examining consumer reaction to product risk information); Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supra</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref71">
        <mixed-citation>
          note 35, at 19-22 (
          <article-title>explaining that risk disclosure is important for the development of sound regulatory</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref72">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>policy); Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>InformingAmerica: Risk Disclosure,and the FirstAmendment, 20 FLA</article-title>
          . ST.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref73">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>U. L. REv</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>653</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>655</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that a participatory democracy is meaningful only if the public</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref74">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>possesses accurate information about risks)</source>
          .
          <volume>59</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generallyCass R. Sunstein</surname>
            , Paradoxesof the Regulatory State, 57
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cm</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L.
          <source>REv. 407</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref75">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          )
          <article-title>(exploring some unintended consequences of several regulations). 60. What constitutes an "increase" depends not merely on quantitative considerations but also on</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref76">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>normative judgments</article-title>
          .
          <source>See text accompanying notes 74-88 infra. 61</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See John D. Graham</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Jonathan Baert Wiener, ConfrontingRisk Tradeoffs, in RIsK Vansus
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref77">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>RISK: TRADEOFFS IN PROTECriNG HEALTH AND Tan ENvmoNm'rr 1, 1</article-title>
          (
          <string-name>
            <surname>John D. Graham</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Jonathan
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref78">
        <mixed-citation>
          Baert Wiener eds.,
          <year>1995</year>
          ),
          <article-title>for an excellent overview</article-title>
          .
          <source>See also AARON WILDAVSKY</source>
          , SEARCING FOR
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref79">
        <mixed-citation>
          <fpage>SAFETY48</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing the potentially harmful consequences of measures intended to increase</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref80">
        <mixed-citation>
          safety); Portney &amp; Stavins, supranote
          <volume>37</volume>
          , at 115-16
          <article-title>(discussing the tradeoffbetween safety regulations</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref81">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>and the adverse effects of compliance); Cass R</article-title>
          . Sunstein,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Health-Health</surname>
            <given-names>Tradeoffs</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , 63
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
            <surname>CHI. L. REv</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref82">
        <mixed-citation>
          (forthcoming
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <fpage>62</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>See Corrosion Proof Fittings v</article-title>
          .
          <source>EPA</source>
          ,
          <volume>947</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1201</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1221</issue>
          (
          <issue>5th</issue>
          <year>Cir</year>
          .
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          . See id.
          <volume>64</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ralph L. Kenney</surname>
          </string-name>
          , MortalityRisks Induced by Economic Expenditure, 10 RiSK ANALsis 147,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref83">
        <mixed-citation>
          148-
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          )
          <article-title>; see also WiLDAVSKY</article-title>
          , supranote
          <volume>61</volume>
          , at 61-68
          <article-title>(explaining the correlation between health</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref84">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>and wealth)</source>
          .
          <volume>65</volume>
          . See Kenney, supranote
          <volume>64</volume>
          , at 154, tbl. VI. 66.
          <string-name>
            <surname>International</surname>
            <given-names>Union</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , UAW v.
          <source>OSHA</source>
          ,
          <volume>938</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1310</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1326</fpage>
          -27
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Williams</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref85">
        <mixed-citation>
          concurring);
          <source>see alsoNew York State Ophthalmological Soc'</source>
          y v.
          <source>Bowen</source>
          ,
          <volume>854</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1379</volume>
          , 1395 n.1
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C.</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref86">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cir.</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Williams, J., concurring) (explaining that "extravagant expenditures on health may in some</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref87">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>thereon"); Building &amp; Constr. Trades Dep't v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Brock</source>
          ,
          <volume>838</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1258</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>1267 (D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>(suggesting</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref88">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ing risk")</source>
          .
          <source>67. InternationalUnion, UAW, 938 F.2d at 1326-27</source>
          .
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g., id.; BHEy-w,
          <source>supra note 14</source>
          , at 33-39 (
          <article-title>discussing differences in perceived risks be-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref89">
        <mixed-citation>
          digm,
          <source>in SOCIAL THEoRIEs OF RISK 117</source>
          ,
          <issue>150</issue>
          (
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Sheldon</given-names>
            <surname>Krimsky</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Dominic Golding eds.,
          <year>1992</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref90">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>are based on qualitative values)</source>
          .
          <volume>76</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pildes</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Sunstein, supra note 35, at 36, tbl.
          <volume>3</volume>
          . 77.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Paul</surname>
          </string-name>
          Slovic et al.,
          <article-title>Intuitive Toxicology ff: Expert and Lay Judgments of Chemical Risks in</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref91">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Canada</surname>
            ,16
            <given-names>RIsK</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>ANALYSis</article-title>
          (forthcoming
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          . See Colin Camerer,
          <article-title>IndividualDecision Making, in THE HANDBOOK OF ExPEzMENrAL Eco-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref92">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>NOMICS 587</source>
          ,
          <fpage>595</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          (
          <string-name>
            <surname>John H. Kagel</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Alvin E. Roth eds.,
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>The EPA has on several occasions signalled that it would prefer not to issue statutorily re-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref93">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>form Proposalson</surname>
            <given-names>EPA</given-names>
          </string-name>
          :
          <article-title>HearingsBefore the Senate Comm</article-title>
          .
          <source>on Environment andPublic Works</source>
          , 104th
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref94">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cong.</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(statement of Carol Browner, Administrator</article-title>
          , EPA).
          <source>208. See note 121 supra and accompanying text. 209. See Stephen Breyer, The Thomas F. Ryan Lecture: The Legislative Veto After Chadha</source>
          ,
          <volume>72</volume>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref95">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>GEo. L</surname>
          </string-name>
          .J.
          <volume>785</volume>
          ,
          <issue>797</issue>
          (
          <year>1984</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that congressional review of regulations favors special interests); cf</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref96">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Legislative</given-names>
            <surname>Vetoes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>90</volume>
          HAgv. L. REv.
          <volume>1369</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1413</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          (
          <year>1977</year>
          )
          <article-title>(showing that the legislative veto increased</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref97">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>the power exerted on committees by wealthy and well-organized interest groups). 210. I testified on issues involving regulatory reform before the Senate Judiciary Committee and</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref98">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>some of this section. 211</source>
          .
          <article-title>The use of a single metric does, however, raise some difficulties</article-title>
          .
          <source>See Pildes &amp; Sunstein,</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref99">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>supranote 35, at 46 (recognizing problem posed by valuation requirement of cost-benefit analysis where</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref100">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>benefit is not easily quantified</article-title>
          );
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Incommensurabilityand Valuation in Lmv,
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>MicH</fpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref101">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>L.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>REv</year>
          .
          <volume>779</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>782</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(noting difficulty of reducing varying notions of value to a single descrip-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref102">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>FfrANALYsis: AN INFoRMAL INTRODUCTION</surname>
          </string-name>
          (2d ed.
          <year>1975</year>
          )
          <article-title>; STEVmKEELMAN</article-title>
          , WHAT PtucE INcETIVEs?:
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref103">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>ECONOMIsTS AND = ENVIRoNMENT</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1981</year>
          ).
          <fpage>212</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Amartya</surname>
            <given-names>Sen</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , EnvironmentalEvaluation andSocial Choice:
          <article-title>Contingent Valuation and the</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref104">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Market</given-names>
            <surname>Analogy</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>46 JAIANEs ECON</article-title>
          . Rzv.
          <volume>23</volume>
          ,
          <issue>24</issue>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ). See generallyCass
          <string-name>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Preferences
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref105">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>and Politics</source>
          ,
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>PHiL</fpage>
          . &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>PUB. As</surname>
          </string-name>
          'F.
          <volume>3</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that in some cases a democracy should be free to</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref106">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>override private preferences)</source>
          .
          <volume>213</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Exec</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Order No.
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <issue>898</issue>
          , 59 Fed. Reg.
          <volume>7629</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(requiring agencies to make achieving</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref107">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ately high adverse effects on minority populations)</source>
          .
          <volume>214</volume>
          . See generally Viscusi,
          <source>supra note 41</source>
          . 215.
          <article-title>I understand this notion in terms of wealth maximization</article-title>
          .
          <volume>216</volume>
          . 7 U.S.C. ยงยง
          <fpage>136</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>136y</lpage>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <volume>217</volume>
          . 15 U.S.C. ยงยง
          <fpage>2601</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>2692</lpage>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <fpage>218</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>For analysis of such objectives of regulation, see STEPmN BRaEYR, REGULATION</article-title>
          AND ITS
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref108">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>RProm- 15-35</source>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          )
          <article-title>; ANTHONY OGus, REGLATION: LErA</article-title>
          . Fox.
          <source>M AND ECONOMIC THEORY 15-28</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref109">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ); SUNsTmN, supra note 21, at 41-
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          .
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          . See Civil Rights Act of
          <year>1964</year>
          ,42 U.S.C. ยง
          <article-title>ยง 1981 to 2000h-6 (1988</article-title>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Supp</surname>
          </string-name>
          . V 1993)
          <article-title>; Voting</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref110">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>Rights Act of</source>
          <year>1965</year>
          , 42 U.S.C. ยงยง
          <fpage>1971</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1974e</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Supp</surname>
          </string-name>
          . V 1993)
          <article-title>; Pregnancy Discrimination Act,</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref111">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>42 U.S.C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>ยง 2000e(k) (</article-title>
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Americans With Disabilities Act of</article-title>
          <year>1990</year>
          , 42 U.S.C. ยงยง
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          ,
          <fpage>213</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref112">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>(Supp. V</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Shelly</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Lundberg and Richard Startz, Private Discriminationand Social Intervention in
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref113">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Competitive</given-names>
            <surname>Labor Markets</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>73</volume>
          AM. Ec. Rsv.
          <volume>340</volume>
          ,
          <issue>340</issue>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that in some instances the</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref114">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>"competitive equilibrium" may be improved through nondiscriminatory policies</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>221</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>SuNsramN</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , supra note 21, at 57-
          <fpage>60</fpage>
          .
          <fpage>222</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Steven Shavell</surname>
          </string-name>
          , A Note on
          <article-title>Efficiency vs</article-title>
          . DistributionalEquity in Legal Rulemaking:
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref115">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Should DistributionalEquity Matter Given Optimal Income Taxation</surname>
          </string-name>
          ?,
          <volume>71</volume>
          AM. EcoN. REv.,
          <source>May</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref116">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>at 414</source>
          ,
          <article-title>414 (papers and proceedings) (arguing that redistribution is best served by taxation)</article-title>
          .
          <source>Sometimes</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref117">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>ANDERSON</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>VALUE INETmcs</article-title>
          AND EcoNoMIcs 17-
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing expressive theory</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>223</volume>
          . See Richard B. Stewart,
          <article-title>Regulation in a LiberalState: The Role ofNon-</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Commodity</surname>
            <given-names>Values</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref118">
        <mixed-citation>
          92 YALE L.J.
          <volume>1537</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1537</issue>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that regulation reflects governmental ends such as "the protec-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref119">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>tion of entitlements, the promotion of production, and the nurture of non-commodity values"</article-title>
          ).
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          . Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C.
          <article-title>ยง 7412(i)(5)(A) (Supp</article-title>
          . V
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>252</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>The</surname>
          </string-name>
          much-criticized
          <source>Federal Water Pollution Control Act</source>
          ,
          <volume>33</volume>
          U.S.C. ยงยง
          <fpage>1251</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1387</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          &amp;
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref120">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Supp. V</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1993</year>
          ),
          <article-title>included such a feature</article-title>
          . Id. ยง
          <volume>1281</volume>
          (h); see also H.R.
          <volume>879</volume>
          , 104th Cong.,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref121">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>technologies)</source>
          .
          <volume>253</volume>
          . 141 CONG. Rac.
          <fpage>S9542</fpage>
          -
          <volume>43</volume>
          (daily ed.
          <source>June 30</source>
          ,
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(containing performance-based stan-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref122">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>specific requirements)</source>
          .
          <volume>254</volume>
          . PreparedStatement ofJonathanB. Wiener,Associate Professor,School ofLaw &amp; School of
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref123">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>ate</surname>
          </string-name>
          , FED. NEws SEnv.,
          <source>Mar. 8</source>
          ,
          <year>1995</year>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>availablein</surname>
            <given-names>LEXIS</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>News</surname>
            <given-names>Library</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Curaws File (discussing the</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref124">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>tory policy)</source>
          .
          <volume>255</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sidney</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>Thomas 0</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>McGarity</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Not So Paradoxical:The Rationalefor
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref125">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Technology-Based</surname>
            <given-names>Regulation</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , 1981 DuK L.J.
          <volume>729</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          , available in WESTLAW, JLR Database
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref126">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>(discussing a situation in which eleven asbestos manufacturers found it more cost-effective to pay $640</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref127">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>per hour in legal fees to challenge OSHA's air quality standards than to comply with the standards</article-title>
          ).
          <source>256. See text accompanying notes 49-58 supra.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

