<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta />
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Assessing Punitive Damages...</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Economics</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, Daniel Kahneman &amp; David Schkade, "Assessing Punitive Damages...", Coase-Sandor Institute for Law &amp; Economics Working Paper No.</institution>
          <addr-line>50, 1997</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <fpage>86</fpage>
      <lpage>127</lpage>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Follow this and additional works at</kwd>
        <kwd>https</kwd>
        <kwd>//chicagounbound</kwd>
        <kwd>uchicago</kwd>
        <kwd>edu/law_and_economics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>(WITH NOTES ON COGNITION AND VALUATION IN LAW)</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>I. INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>This Article has two goals. The first is to investigate the
sources of arbitrariness in punitive damage awards.4 This
investigation, which we believe to be the first of its kind, helps
to answer an important question: What are the sources of
unpredictability in punitive damage awards?5 On the basis of
1 Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor, Law School and
Department of Political Science, University of Chicago.</p>
      <p>2 Eugene Higgins Professor of Psychology and Professor of Public
Affairs, Princeton University.</p>
      <p>3 Professor of Management and William W. Spriegel Fellow, Graduate
School of Business, University of Texas, Austin. The authors are grateful
to Exxon Corporation for financial support of the empirical study contained
in this Article; Exxon Corporation bears no responsibility for our analysis or
our conclusions. We are grateful to Richard Craswell, Richard Epstein,
Dan Kahan, William Landes, Tracey Meares, Martha Nussbaum, Eric
Posner, and Richard Posner for valuable comments. We are also grateful
to participants in the rationality workshop at the University of California,
Berkeley and the law and economics and legal theory workshops at the
University of Chicago. J.B. Heaton provided research assistance and
excellent comments.</p>
      <p>4 A technical version of the survey and study, accompanied with more
detailed statistical analysis, is reported in Daniel Kahneman, David
Schkade, and Cass R. Sunstein, Shared Outrage and Erratic Awards: The
Psychology of Punitive Damages, J. of Risk and Uncertainty (forthcoming
1998). This paper provides a nontechnical summary of our findings and
develops, as that paper does not, its implications for law and legal reform.</p>
      <p>5 We do not contend that we have identified the only source. See TAN
infra. There are also questions about the difference between experimental
and real-world conditions. See TAN infra.
responses from 899 jury-eligible citizens, we estimate the
results of deliberations consisting of all-white juries,
allAfrican-American juries, all-female juries, all-male juries,
allwealthy juries, all-poor juries, and juries of widely diverse
degrees of age and education.</p>
      <p>Our principal conclusions, stated briefly, are that people’s
moral judgments are remarkably widely shared, but that
people have a great deal of difficulty in mapping their moral
judgments onto an unbounded scale of dollars. Erratic,
unpredictable, and arbitrary awards, possibly even
meaningless awards, are a potential product of this difficulty.
Since participants in law are frequently asked to map their
judgments onto an unbounded dollar scale, this answer
relates not only to punitive damage reform but also to a
number of other positive and normative questions now faced
by the legal system, including the law governing libel, awards
for pain and suffering, sexual harassment and other civil
rights violations, intentional infliction of emotional distress,
administrative penalties, and contingent valuation. In addition
to identifying serious problems in current practices, our study
points in the direction of a large and potentially fruitful
research agenda.</p>
      <p>Our second goal involves what might be called the
behavioral analysis of law. In the last three decades, a great
deal of progress has come from the application, to legal
problems, of a certain understanding of economics.6 Within
economics and psychology, but outside law, that
understanding has been under sustained attack.7 Within
social science generally, the attack has produced insights that
supplement, and sometimes undermine, those versions of
economics that have undergirded economic analysis of law.8
6 See Richard Posner, Economic Analysis of Law (5th ed. 1997) for a
wide range of relevant discussions.</p>
      <p>7 A good recent collection is William Goldstein and Robin Hogarth,
Research on Judgment and Decisionmaking (1997).</p>
      <p>8 There are some important exceptions. See, e.g., Edward McCaffery,
Matthew Spitzer, and Daniel Kahneman, Framing the Jury, 81 Va. L Rev
These insights very much bear on law. Our study helps show
what might be missing, impractical, or wrong in standard
economic approaches to punitive damage awards, and in a
way that bears on a range of additional issues as well.9</p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>B. Shared Outrage and Erratic Awards</title>
        <p>The award of punitive damages has become one of the
most controversial and important uses of the tort law,
extending well beyond the common law to such statutory
areas as environmental protection and employment
discrimination.10 Punitive damages are allowed in forty-seven
of the fifty states,11 and over sixty federal statutes now permit
the award of punitive damages, making judicial review of
punitive awards a significant part of federal law.12</p>
        <p>The purposes of such awards are not obscure. Sometimes
compensatory awards provide insufficient deterrence of
1341 (1995); Mark Kelman, Yuval Rottenstreich, and Amos Tversky,
Context-Dependence in Legal Decisionmaking, 25 J. Legal Stud. 287
(1996); George Loewenstein and Linda Babcock, Explaining Bargaining
Impasse, 11 J. Econ. Persp. 109 (1997).</p>
        <p>9 See A. Michell Polinsky and Steven Shavell, Punitive Damages: An
Economic Analysis, Harv L Rev (1997) (forthcoming). In brief, the
difficulty with the Polinsky/Shavell suggestion— that juries should decide
punitive damage problems by reference to the likelihood that the
defendant’s acts will go undetected— is that it does not deal with
psychological and institutional problems that sharply limit jurors’capacity
and willingness to analyze the punitive damage problem in the way they
suggest. Thus a reader might conclude from the Polinsky/Shavell analysis
that punitive damages should be assessed by an administrative agency, or
some other expert body, and not by juries or even judges. See TAN infra.
10 See the Civil Rights Act of 1991, 42 U.S.C. 1977A.</p>
        <p>11 See Richard Blatt et al., Punitive Damages: A State by State Guide
to Law and Practice (1991).</p>
        <p>
          12 See, e.g., 7 U.S.C. (a)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">11</xref>
          )(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">3</xref>
          ); 7 U.S.C. 18(a)B); 7 U.S.C. 21 (b)
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">10</xref>
          ); 7 U.S.C. 25(a)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">3</xref>
          )(B); 10 USC 2207 (a)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ); 10 USC 2409(c)(C)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ); 15
USC 1681n(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ); 15 USC 1681u(i) 15 USC 2622((b)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          )(B); 18 USC
248(cc)(1)(B)); 18 USC 25209(b)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ); 18 USC 2724 (b)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ); 42 USC 300j-9;
42 USC 300a-23; 42 USC 1981a; 42 USC 3613; 42 USC 7622; 42 USC
9607; 42 USC 13981.
private behavior, simply because injured parties do not detect
and seek compensation for all injuries. Punitive damages can,
in theory, take account of the infrequency of private suits by
penalizing the defendant to the point where it will undertake
optimal precautions.13 Moreover, punitive damages may have
a retributive or expressive function, designed to embody
social outrage at the actions of serious wrongdoers.14 They
may reflect the “sense of the community”about the egregious
character of the defendant’s action.
        </p>
        <p>Understood in these terms, however, punitive awards raise
several puzzles. Such awards interact in complex ways with
public law— with the elaborate network of regulatory
requirements and criminal prohibitions that overlap with the
tort law. These requirements and prohibitions also have
deterrent, retributive, and expressive functions. It is not clear
how they can best be brought together with tort law to
produce a coherent whole.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the most important concern is that
whatever their purposes, punitive damages are unpredictable,
even “out of control.”15 One study of 47 counties in eleven
states over a several-year period showed a high degree of
variability:16 Punitive damages were awarded in about 25% of
the successful verdict cases in some counties and not
awarded at all in others.17 Median verdicts ranged from less
than $10,000 in some areas to as much as $204,000 in San
Diego.18 Another study showed increasingly large awards
against businesses, from a total of $1.1 million in five large
states from 1968 to 1971 to $343 million from 1988 to 1991,
an 89-fold increase.19 A recent study finds that in San
Francisco, California and Cook County, Illinois, punitive
damage awards increased from about $1 million during
196064, to $147 million during 1985-1989, and $215 million during
1990-94.20</p>
        <p>On the basis of evidence of this kind, many people have
complained that punitive awards have a “lottery-like”
character21 and require legislative or judicial remedy.22 Thus it
is said, in well-publicized documents, that the arbitrary
character of punitive damage awards is “news to no one,”that
they produce an affront to the rule of law by “distributing
awards in a random and capricious manner,”23 and that they
should be subject to a cap of three times the actual harm.24
Congress continues to debate bills that would limit the
availability and amount of punitive damages.25</p>
        <p>It is not difficult to understand the widespread concern with
erratic punitive damage awards. If similarly situated people—
plaintiffs and defendants alike— are not treated similarly,
erratic awards are unfair. As a matter of fairness, the
evidence suggests that some awards are too low, while others
are too high. From the standpoint of economic efficiency,
unpredictable awards need not be troublesome; perhaps
individual awards cannot be calculated in advance, but if
people can calculate the expected value of the relevant risks,
there should be no efficiency loss. If awards are
unpredictable, however, resources are likely to be wasted on
that calculation, and as a practical matter a risk of extremely
high awards is likely to produce excessive caution in
riskaverse managers and companies.26 Hence unpredictable
awards create both unfairness and (on reasonable
assumptions) inefficiency, 27 in a way that may create
overdeterrence of desirable activity.28</p>
        <p>25 See, e.g., H.R. 956, 104th Cong, section 2(a) (1995); H.R. 955,
104th Cong, section 8(a), (C) (1995).</p>
        <p>26 See Kenneth MacCrimmon and Donald Wehrung, Taking Risks:
The Management of Uncertaity (1986).</p>
        <p>27 These concerns about punitive damage awards have not produced
a consensus that punitive damages are unpredictable. Some empirical
work suggests that the aggregate data show a reasonably orderly pattern,
though the relevant data can be interpreted in different ways. See
Theodore Eisenberg et al., The Predictability of Punitive Damages, 26 J.
Legal Stud. 623 (1997). A response, coming to a different conclusion on
the basis of the same data, is A. Mitchell Polinsky, Are Punitive Damages
Really Insignificant, Predictable, and Rational?, 26 J. Legal Stud. 663
(1997).</p>
        <p>In their careful analysis, Eisenberg et al. show that the logarithmic
transformation yields a distribution that is almost normal. They also show
that the log of awards is predicted rather well from a set of objective
characteristics of cases in which such awards were made. Eisenberg et al.
conclude that the unpredictability of punitive awards has been overstated.
We find no inconsistency between their analyses of real jury awards and
our experimental data. Indeed, we agree with their conclusion that log</p>
        <p>Our principal interest here is in identifying some of the
sources of unpredictability in jury judgments. On the basis of a
study of 899 jury-eligible citizens, we offer the following major
findings.</p>
        <p>1. People have a remarkably high degree of moral
consensus on the degree of outrage and punishment that are
appropriate for punitive damage cases.29 At least in the
products liability cases we offer, this moral consensus, on
what might be called outrage and punitive intent, cuts across
differences in gender, race, income, age, and education. For
example, our study shows that all-white, all-female,
allHispanic, all-male, all-poor, all-wealthy, all-black juries, all-old
juries, and all-young juries are likely to come to similar
conclusions about how to rank a range of cases.</p>
        <p>2. This consensus fractures when the legal system uses
dollars as the vehicle to measure moral outrage. Even when
there is a consensus on punitive intent, there is no consensus
about how much in the way of dollars is necessary to produce
appropriate suffering in a defendant. Under existing law,
widely shared and reasonably predictable judgments about
awards are fairly predictable. But defendants and plaintiffs live in a world
of dollars, not of log dollars. In terms of dollars the judgments of our
respondents and of the juries examined by Eisenberg et al. are correctly
described as erratic and unpredictable, because the severe skewness
creates the possibility of either modest or disastrous losses in identical
cases. This produces unfairness, because the similarly situated are treated
differently, and also might induce risk aversion even in very large firms.</p>
        <p>28 For relevant evidence see Paul H. Rubin et al., BMW v. Gore:
Mitigating the Punitive Economics of Punitive Damages, 5 Supreme Court
Economic Review 179, 192-96 (1997); Richard L. Manning, Products
Liability and Prescription Drug Prices in Canada and the United States, 40
J. L. &amp; Economics 203, 210-34 (1997).</p>
        <p>29 Two qualifications are necessary. First, this conclusion is restricted
to the area we investigate, involving products liability suits. It is an open
question whether the moral consensus would operate in areas involving,
for example, sexual harassment and discrimination on the basis of race.
Second, there is a greater consensus on how to rank the scenarios than on
the “absolute”numbers for outrage and punishment. See below.
punitive intent are turned into highly erratic judgments about
appropriate dollar punishment. A basic source of arbitrariness
with the existing system of punitive damages (and a problem
not limited to the area of punitive damages) is the use of an
unbounded dollar scale.</p>
        <p>
          3. A modest degree of additional arbitrariness is created
by the fact that juries have a hard time making appropriate
distinctions among cases in what we call “a no-comparison
condition.” When one case is seen apart from other cases,
people show a general tendency to place it toward the
midpoint of any bounded scale. It is therefore less likely that
sensible discriminations will be made among diverse cases.
This effect is, however, far less important than the effect
identified in (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ) in producing arbitrary awards.
        </p>
        <p>The principal purpose of this Article is to set out and to
elaborate these findings and to use them to develop some
policy reforms in the area of punitive damages. Our basic
suggestion is that the legal system should enable juries to
engage in tasks that they are capable of performing, and
should not require juries to carry out tasks that they cannot
perform well. Juries are likely to produce erratic judgments
about dollar amounts; their judgments are likely to be much
less erratic when they are asked to rank cases or to assess
the degree to which a defendant should be punished on a
bounded rating scale.30 Thus there is reason to ask whether
the civil justice system ought not to be brought more closely in
line with the criminal justice system, where juries of course
decide questions of liability, and judges decide questions
30 Of course there is a large question about the importance of
predictability in an assessment of punitive damage awards. Such awards
may be predictable but nonetheless problematic, because (for example)
they are too high or too low to produce optimal deterrence, or they do not
reflect the right theory of retribution. Our focus here is on the problem of
unpredictability, which is an affront to the rule of law and a particular
problem under the due process clause and associated principles. See TAN
infra. But we discuss below the relationship between unpredictability and
other possible problems with damage awards.
about punishment, subject to guidelines and constraints. If
juries cannot consistently or sensibly “map” their judgments
onto an unbounded dollar scale, might it follow that judges,
rather than juries, should be making decisions about punitive
awards? Should the legal system shift to a system of civil
sentencing? Might the same conclusion make sense for
compensatory awards in cases in which dollar awards are
also likely to be arbitrary? Might the current system of civil
liability, both punitive and compensatory, sometimes be
displaced by an administrative process, one that can aspire to
more in the way of coherence and rationality?</p>
        <p>The choice of reform of course depends on an assessment
of precisely what defects ought to be corrected, and thus on a
set of normative judgments about the problems with punitive
awards in their current form. We attempt to disaggregate
three possible judgments here, partly as thought experiments,
and partly to raise some questions about the appropriate
domain of populist elements in the legal system.</p>
        <p>If the basic problem is simple unpredictability, the legal
system might reduce that problem by asking juries not to
come up with dollar amounts, but to rank the case at hand
among a preselected set of exemplar cases, or by using a
bounded scale of numbers rather than an unbounded scale of
dollars. A conversion formula, based on previously compiled
population-wide data, might be used to generate
populationwide judgments about dollar amounts. Through this route, it
would be possible to reduce variability and to ensure that jury
judgments about appropriate dollar punishments do not reflect
the likely unrepresentative views of twelve randomly selected
people, but those of the population as a whole. The result
would be a form of predictable populism.</p>
        <p>If the basic problem is that people cannot sensibly map
their moral judgments onto dollar awards, the legal system
should provide a mechanism by which judges or
administrators, rather than jurors, can translate the relevant
moral judgments into dollar amounts. It is reasonable to
question whether ordinary people can know what a given
dollar amount would mean for, or do to, the defendant or
those in the position of the defendant. On this view, the jury
should also rank the case at hand in comparison to
preselected cases or come up with a number on a bounded
scale. A conversion formula, based not on population-wide
data but on expert judgments about what various awards
would actually mean or do, would be used to produce rational
judgments about dollar amounts. The result would be a form
of technocratic populism— populist in the sense that normative
judgments of the jury would be the foundation of decision,
technocratic in the sense that experts would translate those
judgments into legal awards.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-2">
        <title>If the basic problem is that people’s moral judgments are</title>
        <p>not the proper basis for punitive awards, judges might, in
some or all contexts, use those moral judgments as one factor
to be considered among others, or the legal system might
dispense with jury judgments entirely in some or all contexts.
If, for example, it is believed that existing social norms are not
the appropriate basis for punishment, or if deterrence rather
than retribution is the appropriate goal of punitive damages,
an expert body might decide on appropriate awards, or it
could offer general guidance to trial court judges. The result
would be a form of bureaucratic rationality.</p>
        <p>We discuss these points in some detail. We also compare
these reform proposals with other alternatives, including
punitive damage “caps,” simple multipliers, greater judicial
control of awards, and monetary schedules building on the
workers’ compensation model. We suggest that caps and
multipliers have serious problems, but that firmer judicial
control would likely be a desirable and easily administrable
step, at least if judges can produce or work from monetary
schedules or otherwise attempt to work from comparison
cases. A more radical reform, with much promise but also
some risk, would involve a shift from juries to administrators,
operating from a set of guidelines produced by specialists in
the areas at hand, subject of course to democratic
safeguards.</p>
        <p>Both the empirical findings and the policy
recommendations have implications well beyond the problem
of punitive damages. The problem of “mapping” onto a dollar
scale arises not only in the setting of punitive damages, but
also in damages for “pain and suffering,” libel actions, sexual
harassment cases, intentional infliction of emotional distress,
administrative penalties, and judgments about the appropriate
focus of the regulatory state. About one-half of tort law
involves monetary awards for injuries that are hard to
monetize.31 From our findings, it is reasonable to infer that the
phenomenon of shared judgments and erratic or arbitrary32
dollar amounts create a serious and unaddressed problem in
many areas. Very typically, juries and judge are mapping
judgments onto an unbounded dollar scale; the phenomenon
of widespread and predictable judgments, combined with the
demonstrable cognitive difficulty of translating preferences
and values into dollar amounts, has wide-ranging implications
for the operation of both private and public law.</p>
        <p>Most generally, our findings raise a simple question: How
can the normative goals of the legal system be made to mesh
with what is, or might be, known about human psychology?
This is a large and unanswered question. We attempt to make
some progress on it here.</p>
        <p>This Article comes in six parts. Part II outlines existing
understandings about punitive damages, showing how the
sources of variable judgments are relevant to constitutional
issues and also to existing theories of deterrence and
retribution. Part III outlines our study and the basic
conclusions. Part IV presents policy recommendations
designed to provide a role for community judgments without
the “noise” and arbitrariness that accompany the current
system. What is important is not the details of the proposals
31 See W. Kip Viscusi, Reforming Products Liability 102-104 (1993).
32 They may be arbitrary either in the sense of erratic or in the sense
of a product of a normatively questionable “anchor” on which the jury has
seized. See TAN infra.
but their basic goal and direction: to provide juries with an
opportunity to do what they are capable of doing relatively
well, without requiring juries to do what they are bound to do
badly.</p>
        <p>Part V briefly discusses some analogies and implications,
dealing above all with the general problem of jury
determination of dollar amounts in contexts in which
monetization is unfamiliar and difficult. We show how an
evaluation of appropriate reforms with respect to
compensatory awards call for an ambitious decision about
role of populist and technocratic ingredients of
“compensation” judgments— or, in other words, a decision
about what the vexing idea of “compensation”should be taken
to mean. We also outline a possible research agenda to see
how actual or potential descriptive findings in psychology
might bear on the normative goals of the legal system. Part VI
is a conclusion.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>II. DETERRENCE, RETRIBUTION, AND THE CONSTITUTION</title>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>A. Policy Notes</title>
        <p>It is not our purpose to resolve the debate about whether
and why a court should award punitive damages.33 Our
modest goal is to outline some of the relevant arguments by
way of introduction. It is important to provide those arguments
here, since they provide the foundation for the constitutional
law governing punitive damage awards, and because the
arguments play a large role in our empirical study.</p>
        <p>33 Relevant discussions include Polinsky and Shavell, supra note;
Dorsey Ellis, Fairness and Efficiency in the Law of Punitive Damages, 56
Southern Cal. L. Rev. 1 (1982); Robert Cooter, Economic Analysis of
Punitive Damages, 56 S. Cal. L. Rev. 79 (1982); Robert Cooter, Punitive
Damages for Deterrence, 40 Alabama L. Rev. 1143 (1989); David Owen,
The Moral Foundations of Punitive Damages, 40 Ala. L. Rev. 705 (1989);
Marc Galanter and David Luban, Poetic Justice, 42 Am. L. Rev. 1393
(1993).</p>
        <p>The traditional view is that punitive awards serve deterrent
and retributive goals. Thus a standard jury instruction says,
“In determining whether or not you should award punitive
damages, you should bear in mind that the purpose of such
an award is to punish the wrongdoer and to deter that
wrongdoer from repeating such wrongful acts. In addition,
such damages are also designed to serve as a warning to
others, and to prevent others from committing such wrongful
acts.”34</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>1. Deterrence</title>
        <p>(a) Conventional arguments. With respect to the goal of
deterrence, there is a simple and standard economic
argument for punitive damages: Compensatory damages work
well for deterrence if and only if it is easy to identify and to
bring suit against the injurer, and to collect full damages.
Under these conditions, the wrongdoer faces liability for the
full social costs of the wrong. Thus there is no need for
additional damages if the probability of detection and
successful suit for compensation is 100%. But sometimes it is
difficult to identify the injurer, perhaps because the tort has
occurred surreptitiously. In such cases, adequate deterrence
will not be provided, since wrongdoers will be able to continue
to engage in conduct whose social costs exceed social
benefits. Punitive damages are necessary to pick up the slack
for undetected wrongdoers.35</p>
        <p>Under this view, the goal of punitive damages is to
ensure that the award of compensatory damages is
supplemented by an amount reflecting the fact that the
probability of that award is less than 100%. The simplest
conclusion is that total damages should be the harm
multiplied by the reciprocal of the probability than the
defendant will be found liable when he should be found
liable; punitive damages would then consist of the excess of
total damages over compensatory damages.36 We will
suggest some institutional and psychological reasons to
doubt that jurors can or will make judgments of this kind; let
us continue the simple account for now.</p>
        <p>With some torts— medical malpractice is an obvious
example— it is very plausibly the case that many defendants
will be able to avoid compensatory damages. When the
defendant has been able to conceal his identity, or otherwise
to escape being sued, there is therefore good reason to
award punitive damages. Interestingly, this analysis supports
a relatively high punitive damages award in the BMW case
(discussed below), because it is not easy to detect fraudulent
repaintings of cars. But in cases in which the probability of
detection and suit is extremely high, punitive damages make
far less sense. This may be true, for example, of certain
homicides and assaults.</p>
        <p>From the standpoint of optimal deterrence, there is a
second possible reason to award punitive damages. There
may be cases in which a social judgment has been, and
should be, made that certain subjective gains ought not to be
allowed to count at all.37 If someone has gained utility from
murder, rape, assault, or sexual harassment, it might be
thought— reasonably enough— that that gain should not be
permitted to count. Of course the argument that such gains
should not count is not itself an economic judgment, but it is
not hard to imagine defenses of that argument.38 Punitive
damages are necessary to offset the utility gain that is judged
illicit. Compensatory damages are inadequate, in such cases,
36 See Polinsky &amp; Shavell, Punitive Damages: An Economic Analysis,
Harv. L. Rev., forthcoming.</p>
        <p>37 Some utilitarians make just this argument. See the discussion of the
exclusion of sadistic or malicious preferences in John Harsanyi, Morality
and the Theory of Rational Behavior, in Utilitarianism and Beyond 39
(Amartya Sen and Bernard Williams eds. 1982)</p>
        <p>38 See id.
because they do not have this effect; they require the
defendant to internalize the victim’s costs without also
eliminating the hedonic effects of the defendant’s benefits.</p>
        <p>A third possible reason for punitive damages stems from
the fact that sometimes compensatory damages may be lower
than they should be, and sometimes it is especially costly for
courts to calculate compensatory damages. If compensatory
awards are systematically low, and if calculation costs are
high, the amount awarded for punitive damages may move
the legal system closer to optimal deterrence.39 Of course this
argument has a degree of speculativeness and also
crudeness, because it is unlikely that punitive damages can
be calibrated with sufficient precision to make up for the
shortfall in compensatory damages. But perhaps it is
reasonable to think that punitive damages bring the incentives
of wrongdoers closer to where they should be.</p>
        <p>On this view, intentional torts, involving deliberate infliction
of an injury, may well provide good cases for punitive
damages. Of course it is in such cases that socially illicit
gains are most likely to be involved. In such cases, the
probability of obtaining damages from the injurer may well be
less than 100%; intentional torts frequently (though not
always) involve a form of concealment. But an important
implication is that punitive damages generally do not make
sense for highly visible torts where the probability of detection
and compensation is extremely high; there, compensatory
damages are all that is required.40</p>
        <p>(b) Puzzles and problems. Even from the economic point
of view, these arguments for punitive damages raise some
serious puzzles. An important question, not yet taken up in
the economic literature, is the relation between this rationale
for punitive damages and the existence of other regulatory
controls, for example those created by administrative and
criminal law. Both administrative and criminal law are often
39 See Landes and Posner, supra note, at 160.</p>
        <p>40 See id.; Polinsky and Shavell, supra note.
defended as an effort to compensate for private
underenforcement of law;41 if the tort system also attempts to
pick up the slack via punitive damages, overdeterrence may
well result. A system containing compensatory and punitive
damages may be both necessary and sufficient taken by
itself, but if it is complemented by administrative and criminal
law, it is likely to become incoherent.</p>
        <p>There is an independent point, closely related to our
findings here. Even without administrative and criminal law,
efforts to impose punitive damages may well misfire because
of the inevitable confusion or cognitive and motivational errors
of jurors and judges. There is thus a question whether
realworld institutions should or can reliably engage in the
enterprise of seeking to obtain optimal deterrence even if they
seek to do so. That enterprise is very costly, and the costs of
decision may argue in favor of some other system for
calculating punitive damages. Perhaps juries will not
understand the inquiry into optimal deterrence; perhaps it will
be too costly to give them the relevant understanding;
perhaps they will refuse to undertake that inquiry even if they
are asked to do so. We return to these issues below.</p>
        <p>A general problem is that if juries are not thinking in
economic terms, they may award large punitive damages in a
way that deters desirable activity (or award small punitive
damages in a way that produces insufficient deterrence). With
large awards, activity that produces benefits as well as costs
may be stopped or significantly reduced, with possible
adverse effects on safety and health itself.42 It is for this
41 See, e.g., Richard A. Posner, Economic Analysis of Law 220 (4th
ed. 1994). A general discussion is Edward Rubin, Punitive Damages:
Reconceptualizing the Runcible Remedies of Common Law, Wisconsin
Law Review (forthcoming 1997).</p>
        <p>42 Thus there is a possibility here of health-health tradeoffs, which
occur when a strategy designed to reduce health risks actually increases
health risks. Some punitive damage awards may actually have adverse
health effects, if they serve to increase prices. For a recent discussion,
see Richard L. Manning, Products Liability and Prescription Drug Prices in
reason that the strongest cases involve intentional torts, and
the weakest case involves negligence. In cases involving
negligence, punitive damages would be likely to reduce
desirable activity. This is much less likely for intentional
wrongdoing, where desirable activity by hypothesis is not at
issue. Reckless behavior is of course an intermediate case.</p>
        <p>For those interested in optimal deterrence, a particularly
important dispute is whether, on economic grounds, the
wealth or income of the defendant should matter.43 As we will
explain, our findings suggest that the defendant’s wealth is
likely to be an important variable in actual damage awards,
though it plays little or no role in people’s judgments about
outrageousness or appropriate punishment on a bounded
numerical scale.44 The Supreme Court has said that wealth
and income can be taken into account.45 On a conventional
view about optimal deterrence, however, wealth and income is
irrelevant. Properly calculated by reference to the probability
of punishment and the need to counteract illicit gains, a
punitive damages award should encourage a defendant to
Canada and the United States, 40 J. L. &amp; Economics 203, 210-34 (1997).
For general discussion, see John Graham and Jonathan Weiner, Risk vs.
Risk (1996); Cass R. Sunstein, Health-Health Tradeoffs, 63 U. Chi. L.
Rev. 1533 (1996). Evidence of such effects, in the particular context of
punitive damages, can be found in Paul Rubin, John Calfee, and Mark
Grady, BMW v. Gore: Mitigating the Punitive Economics of Punitive
Damages, 1997 Supreme Court Review 179, 192-96.</p>
        <p>43 For the view that wealth should be irrelevant, see Kemezy v.
Peters, 79 F.3d 22 (7th Cir. 1996); Kenneth Abraham and John Jeffries,
Punitive Damages and the Rule of Law, 18 J. Legal Stud. 415 (1989);
Ellis, supra note, at 61-63; Polinsky and Shavell, supra note. For an
argment the other way, see Jennifer Arlen, Should Defendants’ Wealth
Matter?, 21 J. Legal Stud. 413, 414 (1992) (discussing deterrence of
riskaverse people).</p>
        <p>44 See TAN supra. Compare Robert MacCoun, infra note 45.
45 See infra. Cf. Robert MacCoun, Differential Treatment of Corporate
Defendants by Juries, 30 Law &amp; Society Review 121, 133-39 (1996)
(finding effects from corporate identity and commercial activity, but not
from wealth per se).
engage in optimal behavior, whatever its wealth (assuming
risk neutrality).46 But there is a question whether this is
realistic; we take up this issue below.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>2. Retribution</title>
        <p>Thus far we have spoken in terms of deterrence; but under
conventional noneconomic analysis, punitive damages also
have an expressive or retributive purpose. They are designed
to punish as well as to deter. Juries believe that such awards
express the community’s outrage at certain forms of behavior,
and judges’instructions encourage juries to think in precisely
these terms. In fact empirical evidence, including that
provided here,47 suggests that juries are not attempting to
promote optimal deterrence but instead to punish wrongdoing
with, at most, a signal designed to ensure that certain
misconduct “will not happen again.”</p>
        <p>Regrettably, the legal culture lacks a careful normative
account of the relationship between retributive goals and
punitive damages. Those who emphasize retribution are
seeking to ensure that the community’s outrage about certain
acts is reflected in punishment. Probably the retributive idea
would focus on two principal factors: the defendant’s state of
mind and the degree of harm actually caused or likely to be
caused by defendant’s behavior. The first point is especially
important. Retributists who are moral egalitarians48 attempt,
through civil or criminal punishment, to capture the intuition
that certain intentional states are especially bad because they
reflect abhorrent and false views about the moral worth of
persons.49 In cases where one person murders another, or
46 See Landes and Posner, supra note, at 163-64; Polinsky and
Shavell, supra note.</p>
        <p>47 See TAN infra.</p>
        <p>48 Of course retributivists need not be egalitarians; we could imagine
retributists who thought that harms against some persons deserve less
punishment than harms against other persons.</p>
        <p>49 See Jean Hampton, The Retributive Idea, in Jean Hampton and
Jeffrie Murphy, Forgiveness and Mercy 111 (1988).
acts with gross negligence that produces another’s death, the
wrongdoer reveals a belief that some people do not matter
very much.50 Public outrage is the appropriate response.</p>
        <p>In this sense retribution, properly understood, embodies a
principle of moral equality. The award of punitive damages
can also be taken to have an expressive function; it expresses
the community’s outrage at certain kinds of conduct, in a way
that is intended both to reflect and to entrench the relevant
social norms. This idea connects the award of punitive
damages with their historical origins in affronts to the honor of
the victims.51 With this understanding it is not surprising that
punitive damages have come to be awarded for sexual
harassment and for other violations of civil rights statutes;52
the relevant community now believes that these kinds of
illegality reflect an especially bad state of mind, and hence
that punitive damages are a necessary supplement to other
sanctions. The defendant must be punished accordingly. In
any event the retributive idea suggests that the most serious
cases for punitive damage awards thus involve harms that are
both grave in degree and affirmatively desired by the
defendant, as, for example, in examples of homicide or
assault.</p>
        <p>We connect these factors to the psychology of punitive
damage awards in the discussion below. The central point is
that if retribution is the goal of punitive damage awards, it is
important to ensure that juries are asked questions that allow
them to express, in a rational and coherent manner, their
comparison cases219— especially because, as we have
shown, the dollar awards of any particular jury are not likely to
reflect the population’s judgment about appropriate dollar
awards. A more dramatic approach— probably the best for the
long term, though not without risks of its own— would involve
the development of a system of administrative penalties for
serious misconduct, based on judgments made in advance
and subject to democratic control.</p>
        <p>Our findings have implications well beyond the area of
punitive damages. Three implications are of special
importance. First, there is, in the personal injury cases studied
here, a high degree of agreement within diverse demographic
groups with respect to both outrage and punishment. It is
possible that there is a similar consensus across other
domains; thus ample room remains for further related work. It
would be valuable to see, for example, whether such a
consensus exists across gender with respect to compensatory
damage awards, or punitive damage awards, for pain and
suffering or sexual harassment; it would be valuable too to
see whether there are substantive areas in which race,
education, age, and wealth have measurable effects.
Relatively simple studies could produce evidence on some
much-disputed questions.</p>
        <p>Second, our study raises serious doubts about whether
jurors are able to make sensible judgments about dollar
219 See Klein v. Grynberg, 44 F. 3d 1497 (10th Cir. 1995); Stafford v.
Puro, 63 F.3d 1436 (7th Cir. 1995): Allahar v. Zahora, 59 F.3d 693 (7th
Cir. 1995): Ross v. Black and Decker, Inc., 977 F.2d 1178 (7th Cir. 1992):
Vasbinder v. Scott, 976 F.2d 118 (2nd Cir. 1992); Kimzey v. Wal-Mart
Stores, Inc., 107 F.3d 568 (8th Cir. 1997): Lee v. Edwards, 101 F.3d 805
(2nd Cir. 1996): King v. Macri, 993 F.2d 294 (2nd Cir. 1993): Michelson v.
Hamada, 36 Cal.Rptr.2d 343 (Cal. Ct. App. 1994): Wollersheim v. Church
of Scientology, 6 Cal.Rptr.2d 532 (Cal. Ct. App. 1992): Baume v. 212 E.
10 N.Y. Bar Ltd., 634 N.Y.S. 2d 478 (N.Y. App. Div. 1995); Parkin v.
Cornell University Inc., 581 N.Y.S.2d 914 (N.Y. App. Div. 1992). As noted,
our evidence suggests that if community-wide judgments are the goal, it is
important to have a mechanism for additur as well as remittitur.
awards in cases in which market measures are unavailable,
and it throws into sharp relief the question whether this task
should not be given to judges or to some other institution. The
legal system is not occasionally but pervasively in the
business of requiring people to map their judgments onto
dollar amounts, and outside of the context of punitive
damages, the translation is likely to suffer from the same
problems found here. In particular, difficulties with mapping
probably affect jury awards of damages for libel, pain and
suffering, sexual harassment and other civil rights violations,
and intentional infliction of emotional distress— all of which
notoriously suffer from unpredictability, in part, we believe, as
a result of unbounded dollar scales. The consequence is that
rule of law values are badly compromised. Reform proposals
might ensure against unfairness (in the form of dissimilar
treatment of the similarly situated) and unpredictability for
both individuals and firms, plaintiffs and defendants alike.
More particularly, reforms involving “compensatory”awards in
these controversial areas must be evaluated by an
assessment of the appropriate place of purely factual
judgments, for which juries are not especially well-suited.
Thus the three kinds of punitive damage reforms may well
have parallels in each of these areas.</p>
        <p>Third, our findings support the general proposition, on
which there is growing consensus, that both values and
preferences are often constructed, rather than elicited, by
social situations.220 In their various social roles, people lack a
preexisting “master list”of values and preferences from which
to make selections in situations of choice. This is true for
consumer choices, which depend on context and alternative
options, as well as for medical decisions,221 politics, and
law.222 It is true as well for judgments made by jurors, judges,
representatives, and citizens generally. Rather than emerging
from some menu in the mind, these judgments are a function
of procedure, description, and context. In the legal context in
particular, participants are pervasively in the business of
constructing procedures, descriptions, and contexts.
Frequently they have not been self-conscious about that
point.</p>
        <p>To be sure, there is no uncontroversial way to develop the
context and frames for eliciting, or constructing, social
preferences and values. But some ways are worse than
others, because they make people perform tasks for which
they are ill-equipped— or, more specifically, produce poor
translation of some plausible “bedrock” set of normative
judgments, generate arbitrariness, aggravate the problem of
selective attention, exploit heuristic devices that produce
error, or provide people with too little understanding to yield
sensible or consistent decisions. We have suggested some
ways to handle these problems with the award of punitive
damages, where bedrock judgments do seem discoverable
through the right methods, and where the legal system allows
those judgments to be transformed into dollar amounts in
erratic ways. Both the problem and the potential solutions
bear on many issues now facing the legal system.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>APPENDIX 1. EXCERPTS FROM INSTRUCTIONS</title>
      <p>In this study we would like you to imagine that you are a
juror for a legal case in a civil court. Civil law suits can involve
disputes between private individuals, companies, or
individuals and companies, in which the plaintiff alleges that
the defendant harmed them or their property in some way. A
civil suit is brought by a plaintiff for the purpose of gaining
compensation from the defendant for the alleged harm.</p>
      <p>
        Civil suits involve two different types of penalties that
could be imposed upon a defendant that is found liable for
damages. Compensatory damages are intended to fully
compensate a plaintiff for the harm suffered as a result of the
defendant’s actions. Punitive damages are intended to
achieve two purposes: (1) to punish the defendant for unusual
misconduct, and (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
        ) to deter the defendant and others from
committing the same actions in the future.
      </p>
      <p>In the cases you will consider, the defendant has already
been ordered to pay compensatory damages to the plaintiff.
This does not necessarily mean that punitive damages must
also be awarded. Whether or not punitive damages should be
awarded and, if so, how large they should be, is completely
separate from compensatory damages.</p>
      <p>Punitive damages should be awarded if a preponderance
of the evidence shows that the defendants either acted
maliciously or with reckless disregard for the welfare of
others. Defendants are considered to have acted maliciously
if they intended to injure or harm someone. Defendants are
considered to have acted with reckless disregard for the
welfare of others if they were aware of the probable harm to
others but disregarded it, and their actions were a gross
deviation from the standard of care that a normal person
would use.</p>
      <p>Civil suits differ from criminal cases, in which the
government prosecutes an individual or a company for
alleged violations of the law. Plaintiffs in a civil trial must
prove their claim by “a preponderance of the evidence,”which
means that it is more likely than not that the plaintiff’s claim is
justified. This differs from criminal trials, where the
prosecution must prove the defendant’s guilt “beyond a
reasonable doubt.”</p>
      <p>In each of the cases you will consider, the jury (of which
you are a member) has already decided to accept the
plaintiff's claim. As a consequence the jury has ordered the
defendant to pay $200,000 in compensatory damages to the
plaintiff as full compensation. The defendants are large
[medium-sized] companies with profits of $100-200 [$10-20]
million per year.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>APPENDIX 2. PERSONAL INJURY SCENARIOS</title>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>Mary Lawson</title>
        <p>Mary Lawson, a manufacturing worker, developed chronic
anemia. Although after a hospital stay she is now better, the
condition has not been fully cured. She believes that
exposure to benzene in her work place caused the condition
and sued her employer, TGI International. The jury (of which
you are a member) ordered TGI International to pay her
$200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>TGI International is a large company (with profits of
$100200 million per year) that manufactures high-tech machine
parts. Some years ago the scientists at TGI International
discovered that manufacturing workers at Mary Lawson’s
plant were often exposed to benzene, a substance that can
cause anemia, leukemia and cancer. Internal documents
show that the top management at TGI International decided
not to do anything about the problem, because benzene
levels in the plant were slightly below the maximum level
allowed by OSHA regulations. They thought that the risk was
worth taking and that “with any luck no one will get sick”. They
also decided against warning the workers, because “warnings
would just create panic”.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-2">
        <title>Frank Williams</title>
        <p>Frank Williams suffered serious internal injuries when the
braking system on his motorcycle failed to work at a traffic
light. He felt that that the brakes were defective, and sued
National Motors, the company that manufactures and sells his
motorcycle. The jury (of which you are a member) ordered
National Motors to pay him $200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>National Motors is a large company (with profits of
$100200 million per year) that makes motorcycles, scooters, and
other motorized single person vehicles. The evidence showed
that the braking system used by National Motors has a basic
design defect. National Motors was aware that “there might be
a problem with our brakes,” because in pre-market tests, the
defect appeared on several occasions. But the pre-market
tests were not extensive, despite the fact that auto industry
regulations require elaborate testing. Internal company
documents show National Motors’belief that “it would be quite
expensive for us to do much more now, we can't be certain we
have a serious problem here, and anyway we can fix the
problem afterwards if it really does turn out to be serious.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-3">
        <title>Thomas Smith</title>
        <p>While he was visiting the circus, Thomas Smith was shot
in the arm by a security guard who mistakenly thought that
Smith had threatened another customer with bodily harm. The
security guard was drunk at the time. Smith sued Public
Entertainment, the company that operates the circus. The jury
(of which you are a member) ordered Public Entertainment to
pay him $200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>Public Entertainment is a large company (with profits of
$100-200 million per year) which operates circuses and public
fairs. Fred Williams, the security guard who was involved in
the incident, is an alcoholic with a history of incidents of
drunkenness on the job. During one of these incidents
Williams took out his gun and started waving it around wildly,
but he did not shoot anyone. Public Entertainment had
repeatedly warned Williams to “clean up his act” but took no
other action. In his company personnel file Williams was
described as “basically a good guy with a bit of a drinking
problem, but not enough of a risk to fire him.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-4">
        <title>Susan Douglas</title>
        <p>Susan Douglas suffered significant injuries to her legs and
neck when an airbag in her car opened unexpectedly while
she was driving the vehicle. She believes that the airbag was
defective and sued the manufacturer, Coastal Industries. The
jury (of which you are a member) ordered Coastal Industries
to pay her $200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>Coastal Industries is a large company (with profits of
$100-200 million per year) that specializes in parts and
accessories that can be added to existing vehicles, such as
adding the latest safety equipment to older cars. While its
airbag conforms to the requirements stated in government
regulations, it does not include certain additional “fail-safe”
systems that are used in other airbags to ensure against
accidental opening. Internal documents show that most but
not all of the Coastal Industries designers believed that their
system “is certainly safe enough, even if it does not include all
possible safeguards”and that their marketing department said
that “there will be no market for our airbag if we raise its price
by adding more safety bells and whistles.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-5">
        <title>Carl Sanders</title>
        <p>Carl Sanders used Nalene, an over-the-counter baldness
treatment available at drugstores. While a small amount of
hair did grow back, he also developed severe side-effects,
including open sores on the scalp and permanent brown spots
over his forehead. He sued the manufacturer, A&amp;G
Cosmetics. The jury (of which you are a member) ordered
A&amp;G Cosmetics to pay him $200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>A&amp;G Cosmetics is a large company (with profits of
$100200 million per year) that sells many different cosmetic
products, including wigs, “weaves” and chemical solutions
designed to combat baldness. Nalene has proven effective in
promoting hair growth in 30% of people in clinical trials.
However, Nalene caused unpleasant side effects in some
cases, although none were as severe as those Carl Sanders
experienced. When marketing Nalene, A&amp;G Cosmetics did
not fully disclose these findings. It only said “minor side
effects have been observed in a very small number of people
tested.” While this amount of disclosure was within legal
limits, other companies that make hair products voluntarily
disclosed more about their products.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-6">
        <title>Sarah Stanley</title>
        <p>Sarah Stanley, a seventy-five year old woman, suffered
serious back injuries as a result of following an exercise
video, “Good Health For All,”that she purchased through her
local community health center. When Stanley attempted to
perform the exercises, she found herself unable to do so, but
she pressed on beyond her physical capacities. She claimed
that she was not adequately warned of these dangers and
sued the producer of the video, Gersten Productions. The jury
(of which you are a member) ordered Gersten Productions to
pay her $200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>Gersten Productions is a large company (with profits of
$100-200 million per year) that produces informational
materials in health-related fields, including videos on many
topics concerning healthy lifestyles. The “Good Health for All”
video contains a series of exercises suitable mostly for people
in good shape and good health. The exercise coaches and
models in the video are all relatively young, and no federal or
state law requires exercise videos to come with any special
warning for elderly people. The witnesses in the case testified
that Gersten Productions believed that most people would be
able to tell when the exercises were beyond their capacities,
that Good Health for All has produced good results for almost
all people who have seen it, and that very few people had
reported injuries of any type from doing so.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-7">
        <title>Jack Newton</title>
        <p>Jack Newton, a five year old child, was playing with
matches when his cotton flannel pajamas caught fire. He was
severely burned over a significant portion of his body and
required several weeks in the hospital and months of physical
therapy. His parents sued the manufacturer of the pajamas,
Novel Clothing. The jury (of which you are a member) ordered
Novel Clothing to pay the Newtons $200,000 in
compensation.</p>
        <p>Novel Clothing is a large company (profits of $100-200
million per year) that specializes in making clothes for
children. Before marketing the pajamas, Novel conducted the
tests normally used in the industry for problems like
flammability, and observed no incidents like the Newtons
experienced. Companies in the industry as well as federal
regulators have known for a while that it is possible to add
extra fire-retardant chemicals to their fabrics (in addition to
those specified in current regulations), but these extra
measures are not required. The process is very expensive,
and no other manufacturers currently use it. Internal
documents show that the management of Novel Clothing had
decided that “when it comes to costly safety innovations we
will follow our competitors. We don't want to be less safe than
anyone else but we don't have to lead the way either.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-8">
        <title>Low Harm version:</title>
        <p>Jack Newton, a five year old child, was playing with
matches when his cotton flannel pajamas caught fire. His
hands and arms were badly burned, and required regular
professional medical treatment for several weeks.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-9">
        <title>Joan Glover</title>
        <p>Joan Glover, a six year old child, ingested a large number
of pills of Allerfree, a non-prescription allergy medicine, and
required an extensive hospital stay. The overdose weakened
her respiratory system, which will make her more susceptible
to breathing-related diseases such as asthma and
emphysema for the rest of her life. The Allerfree bottle used
an inadequately designed child-proof safety cap. The Glovers
sued the manufacturer of Allerfree, the General Assistance
company. The jury (of which you are a member) ordered
General Assistance to pay the Glovers $200,000 in
compensation.</p>
        <p>General Assistance is a large company (with profits of
$100-200 million per year) that manufactures a variety of
nonprescription medicines. A federal regulation requires
“childproof”safety caps on all medicine bottles. General Assistance
has systematically ignored the intent of this regulation by
selling tens of thousands of bottles of medicines with a
childproof safety cap that was generally effective, but had a failure
rate much higher than any others in the industry. An internal
company document says that “this stupid, unnecessary
federal regulation is a waste of our money”; it acknowledges
the risk that Allerfree may be punished for violating the
regulation but says, “the federal government has many other
things to worry about and probably won't bother us on this”
and in any case “the punishments for violating the regulation
are extremely mild; basically we'd be asked to improve the
safety caps in the future.” An official at the Food and Drug
Administration had previously warned a vice president of
General Assistance that they were “on shaky ground” but the
company decided not to take any corrective action.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-10">
        <title>Low Harm version:</title>
        <p>Joan Glover, a six year old child, ingested a large number
of pills of Allerfree, a non-prescription allergy medicine. She
had to spend several days in a hospital, and is now deeply
traumatized by pills of any kind. When her parents try to get
her to take even beneficial medications such as vitamins,
aspirin, or cold remedies, she cries uncontrollably and says
that she is afraid.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-11">
        <title>Martin West</title>
        <p>Martin West, a right-handed disabled veteran who lived in
a two story house, was seriously injured in a fall when the
chain broke on his electric lift-chair (a device that allows
someone to be carried up stairs in a chair that moves up and
down an angled track). He fell from near the top of the stairs
and tumbled awkwardly all the way to the bottom landing,
damaging his spinal cord in the process. As a result he now
has only partial control of his right arm, a condition which
doctors believe is permanent. He sued the manufacturer of
the lift-chair, MedTech Products. The jury (of which you are a
member) ordered MedTech to pay him $200,000 in
compensation.</p>
        <p>MedTech Products is a large company (profits of $100-200
million per year) that manufactures many types of medical
equipment, including wheelchairs, car-lifts, and other devices
used by the disabled. The lift-chair is a new product for
MedTech, and instead of producing a new design, company
engineers decided to adapt the design of the hydraulic lifts for
cars already on the market. Unfortunately, there are several
unique problems in designing a safe and effective lift-chair
that are beyond the experience of the company’s engineers.
Product managers said that hiring new engineers with the
proper expertise was “too expensive, and would take too long”
and ordered current engineers to “just do the best you can,
but be sure you meet our deadline for announcing the
product.” The inexperience of the engineers and the rush to
meet the product announcement date led to testing
procedures that were less rigorous than those required by
federal medical product regulations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-12">
        <title>Low Harm version:</title>
        <p>Martin West, a left-handed disabled veteran who lived in a
two story house, was injured in a fall when the chain broke on
his electric lift-chair (a device that allows someone to be
carried up stairs in a chair that moves up and down an angled
track). He fell from near the bottom of the stairs and tumbled
to the bottom landing, injuring his spinal cord in the process.
His right arm was paralyzed for several weeks, after which
doctors were able to repair most of the injury, and he was
able to regain most of the previous range of motion in the
arm.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-13">
        <title>Janet</title>
        <p>Janet Windsor, a secretary who works on computer
equipment, developed a rare form of skin cancer. After a long
course of painful chemotherapy, doctors were able to cure the
cancer, although they cannot be sure that it will not return.
She believed that it had been caused by the computer
monitors that she worked on and sued the manufacturer,
International Computers. The jury (of which you are a
member) ordered International Computers to pay her
$200,000 in compensation.</p>
        <p>International Computers is a large company (profits of
$100-200 million per year) that manufactures components of
computer systems. The type of International Computers
monitor that Ms. Windsor used emits an unusually high level
of radiation compared to other similar monitors, a level that
pushes the limit in government safety guidelines. Internal
company documents cite experts who concluded that “the
evidence that this level of radiation could create any serious
risk to health and life is weak and tentative”. The company
was not legally required to disclose the unusual level of
radiation, and it did not do so.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-14">
        <title>Low Harm version:</title>
        <p>Janet Windsor, a secretary who works on computer
equipment, suffered from frequent and severe migraine
headaches. As a result, for several years she often
experienced nausea, insomnia and depression, and missed
many workdays and family events.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>APPENDIX 3. RESPONSE MODE MANIPULATION</title>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>Outrage</title>
        <p>Which of the following best expresses your opinion of the
defendant’s actions? (please circle your answer)</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>Objectionable</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>Shocking</title>
      <sec id="sec-8-1">
        <title>Punishment</title>
        <p>In addition to paying compensatory damages, how much
should the defendant be punished? Please circle the number
that best expresses your opinion of the appropriate level of
punishment.</p>
        <p>No
Punishmen
t</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>Mild Punishmen t</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>Severe Punishmen t</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>Extremely Severe</title>
      <p>Punishment
0
1
2
3
4
$ Damages</p>
      <p>In addition to paying compensatory damages, what
amount of punitive damages (if any) should the defendant be
required to pay as punishment and to deter the defendant and
others from similar actions in the future? (please write your
answer in the blank below)</p>
      <p>$ _____________________</p>
      <sec id="sec-11-1">
        <title>Samples and Procedures</title>
        <p>The sample had good representation from various
demographic and socio-economic groups. For example,
respondents were 44% male; 64% Caucasian, 16%
AfricanAmerican, 15% Hispanic; median income = $30K-$50K;
median education = some college; median age = 30-39.
Thirty-two respondents were dropped from the sample
because they gave incomplete responses or failed to
understand the task.</p>
        <p>The survey was conducted at a downtown hotel.
Participants were run in large groups at pre-arranged times
over a four day period. Most respondents completed their task
in 30 to 45 minutes.</p>
        <p>
          Each respondent received three pages of general
instructions and four numbered envelopes. The first three
envelopes contained the materials for Parts 1, 2 and 3 of the
study, as described below. The fourth envelop contained
demographic question and debriefing information. The
instructions (which are excerpted in Appendix 1)included (1)
an overview of the survey procedure, (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">2</xref>
          ) an explanation of the
task of jurors in civil (as opposed to criminal) trials, (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">3</xref>
          )
definitions of and distinctions between compensatory and
punitive damages, including the fact that compensatory
damages had already been awarded in the cases they would
consider, (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">4</xref>
          ) a summary of standard legal conditions for
punitive damages (maliciousness or reckless disregard for the
welfare of others), and (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">5</xref>
          ) a reminder about the standard of
evidence required in this situation (preponderance of the
evidence).
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-11-2">
        <title>Design and Stimuli</title>
        <p>Ten scenarios describing personal injury cases were
constructed. The first six were used in Parts 1 and 2 of the
procedure and the other four in Part 3. Each respondent rated
some version of all ten scenarios. Envelope #1 contained
material about one of the scenarios. Envelope #2 contained
five other scenarios. Envelope #3 contained the four
scenarios used in Part 3 of the experiment.</p>
        <p>In Parts 1 and 2, between-subjects manipulations were
response mode (Outrage, Punishment or $ Damages) and
firm size (annual profits of $10-$20 million (Medium) or
$100$200 million (Large)), and scenario sequence, including which
scenario was evaluated first, in isolation from the others (in
Part 1 of the procedure). Scenario order was counterbalanced
using a Latin square so that each scenario appeared in each
ordinal position with equal frequency. Table 2 shows the
wording of the evaluation questions in the three response
modes. Instructions in all scenarios stated that compensatory
damages of $200,000 had already been awarded.</p>
        <p>Part 3 had the same structure as Parts 1 and 2, except
that the isolation manipulation was replaced by a
manipulation in which the degree of harm suffered by the
plaintiff was varied. For each of the four scenarios used in
Part 3, we formulated a high-harm and a low-harm version.
For example, in the case in which a child playing with
matches was burned when his pajamas caught fire, the
injuries were described as “He was severely burned over a
significant portion of his body and required several weeks in
the hospital and months of physical therapy” (high harm) or
“His hands and arms were badly burned, and required regular
professional medical treatment for several weeks”(low harm).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>Chicago Working Papers in Law and Economics</title>
      <p>(Second Series)
15. Richard A. Posner, What Do Judges and Justices
Maximize? (The Same Thing Everyone Else Does) (April
1993).
16. Lucian Arye Bebchuk and Randal C. Picker, Bankruptcy
Rules, Managerial Entrenchment, and Firm-Specific
Human Capital (August 1993).
17. J. Mark Ramseyer, Explicit Reasons for Implicit Contracts:
The Legal Logic to the Japanese Main Bank System
(August 1993).
18. William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, The
Economics of Anticipatory Adjudication (September
1993).
19. Kenneth W. Dam, The Economic Underpinnings of Patent</p>
      <p>Law (September 1993).
20. Alan O. Sykes, An Introduction to Regression Analysis
(October 1993).
21. Richard A. Epstein, The Ubiquity of the Benefit Principle
(March 1994).
22. Randal C. Picker, An Introduction to Game Theory and
the Law (June 1994).
23. William M. Landes, Counterclaims: An Economic Analysis
(June 1994).
24. J. Mark Ramseyer, The Market for Children: Evidence
from Early Modern Japan (August 1994).
25. Robert H. Gertner and Geoffrey P. Miller, Settlement</p>
      <p>Escrows (August 1994).
26. Kenneth W. Dam, Some Economic Considerations in the
Intellectual Property Protection of Software (August
1994).
27. Cass R. Sunstein, Rules and Rulelessness, (October
1994).
28. David Friedman, More Justice for Less Money: A Step</p>
      <p>Beyond Cimino (December 1994).
29. Daniel Shaviro, Budget Deficits and the Intergenerational</p>
      <p>Distribution of Lifetime Consumption (January 1995).
30. Douglas G. Baird, The Law and Economics of Contract</p>
      <p>Damages (February 1995).</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          13
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>William</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Richard Posner,
          <source>The Economic Structure of Tort Law 160-65</source>
          ,
          <fpage>184</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          ,
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ); Polinsky &amp; Shavell, supra note.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          14
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>David Owen</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Moral Foundations of Punitive Damages, 40 Ala L Rev</source>
          <volume>705</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Marc Galanter</article-title>
          and David Luban, Poetic Justice,
          <volume>42</volume>
          Am. U. L. Rev.
          <volume>1393</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Jean Hampton, The Retributive Idea</article-title>
          , in Jean Hampton and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Jeffrie</given-names>
            <surname>Murphy</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Forgiveness and Mercy</source>
          <volume>111</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          15
          <string-name>
            <given-names>John</given-names>
            <surname>Jeffries</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Comment on the Constitutionality of Punitive Damages, 72 Va L Rev</source>
          <volume>139</volume>
          ,
          <issue>139</issue>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          16
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
            <surname>Daniels</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Joane Martin,
          <source>Myth and Reality in Punitive Damages, 75 Minn L Rev</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>17 Id. at 32.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>18 Id. at 42.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          19
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>Punitive Damages Explosion</source>
          , Washington Legal Foundation, Working Paper Series No.
          <volume>50</volume>
          (
          <issue>Nov</issue>
          .
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          20
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Deborah</given-names>
            <surname>Hensler</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Erik</given-names>
            <surname>Moller</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Trends in Punitive Damages:
          <article-title>Preliminary Data from Cook County, Illinois</article-title>
          and San Francisco, California (
          <article-title>RAND Institute for Civil Justice unrestricted draft series</article-title>
          ,
          <year>March 1995</year>
          ).
          <article-title>See also Rand Institute for Civil Justice, Punitive Damages in Financial Injury Verdicts (</article-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>(showing substantial variability and growth in punitive awards).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          21
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>No-Fault</surname>
            <given-names>Punishment</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , 40 Ala L Rev
          <volume>1037</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1037</issue>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          22
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Paul</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rubin</surname>
          </string-name>
          , John Calfee, and Mark Grady, BMW v.
          <source>Gore: Mitigating the Punitive Economics of Punitive Damages</source>
          ,
          <source>1997 Supreme Court Economic Review</source>
          <volume>179</volume>
          , 184; E. Donald Elliott,
          <source>Why Punitive Damages Don't Deter Corporate Misconduct Effectively</source>
          ,
          <volume>40</volume>
          Ala. L. Rev.
          <volume>1053</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1057</issue>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>See the attempted response in the Product Liability Reform Act of 1997, S. 5</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>105th</given-names>
            <surname>Cong</surname>
          </string-name>
          .,
          <source>1st Sess</source>
          .
          <article-title>(</article-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>(proposing to require a clear and convincing evidence standard and also to cap punitive damage awards).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>23 Contract with America: The Bold Plan by Rep</article-title>
          .
          <source>Newt Gingrich, Rep. Dick Armey, and The House Republicans to Change the Nation</source>
          <volume>154</volume>
          (Ed Gillespie and Bob Schellhas eds.,
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>24 Id. at 147.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          34
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
            <surname>Eades</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Jury Instructions of Damages in Tort Actions</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          (3d ed.
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          35
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>William</surname>
          </string-name>
          Landes and Richard A. Posner,
          <source>The Economic Structure of Tort Law 160-65</source>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Polinsky &amp; Shavell, Punitive Damages: An Economic Analysis</article-title>
          , Harv L. Rev, forthcoming.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          50 See id.; Jean Hampton,
          <source>Correcting Harms Versus Righting Wrongs: The Goal of Retribution</source>
          , 39 UCLA
          <string-name>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
            <surname>Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>1659 (</article-title>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Hampton discusses punitive damage awards in particular in id</article-title>
          . at 1687-89;
          <article-title>see also the illuminating discussion in Marc Galanter</article-title>
          and David Luban,
          <source>Poetic Justice: Punitive Damages and Legal Pluralism, 42 Am Univ L Rev</source>
          <volume>1393</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
          <article-title>(connecting punitive awards with retributive goals and community outrage).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          51
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Dorsey</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ellis</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Fairness and Efficiency in the Law of Punitive Damages, 56 S Cal L Rev</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          52 See, e.g., 42 U.S.C.
          <year>1977A</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          220
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Amos</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tversky</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Rational Theory and Constructive Choice, in The Rational Foundations of Economic Behavior</source>
          <volume>185</volume>
          (
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
            <surname>Arrow</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al. eds.
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>221 See A. Bastardi and Eldar Shafir, On the search for and misuse of useless information</article-title>
          (forthcoming
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          222
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Mark</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kelman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Yuval Rottenstreich, and Amos Tversky, Context-Dependence in Legal Decisionmaking, 25
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J Legal</given-names>
            <surname>Stud</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>287</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <article-title>APPENDIX 4: EXPERIMENT DESIGN 1</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Copyright Protection of Letters, Diaries and Other Unpublished Works: An Economic Approach (July</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          2.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Epstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Path to The T. J.
          <article-title>Hooper: The Theory and History of Custom in the Law of Tort (August</article-title>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          3.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>On Property and Constitutionalism (September</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          4.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Blackmail, Privacy, and Freedom of Contract (
          <year>February 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          5.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Randal</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picker</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Security Interests, Misbehavior, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Common Pools</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>February 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          6.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tomas</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Philipson</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Richard A. Posner, Optimal Regulation of AIDS (April
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          7.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Baird,
          <source>Revisiting Auctions in Chapter 11 (April</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          8.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Sequential versus Unitary Trials: An Economic Analysis (July</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          9.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>Richard A. Posner, The Influence of Economics on Law: A Quantitative Study</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          10.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Alan O. Sykes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Welfare Economics of Immigration Law: A Theoretical Survey With An Analysis of U.S. Policy</article-title>
          (
          <year>September 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          11.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Baird</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>1992 Katz Lecture: Reconstructing Contracts (November</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          12.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gary</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Economic Way of Looking at Life (
          <year>January 1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          13.
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. Mark</surname>
            <given-names>Ramseyer</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Credibly Committing to Efficiency
          <source>Wages: Cotton Spinning Cartels in Imperial Japan (March</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          14.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Endogenous Preferences, Environmental
          <string-name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>April 1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

