<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cass R. Sunstein, "Is the Clean Air Act Unconstitutional?,"</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1990</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>303</volume>
      <issue>1999</issue>
      <fpage>1999</fpage>
      <lpage>2000</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, University of
Chicago Law School and Department of Political Science. A.B. 1975, J.D. 1978, Harvard.
Ed. I am grateful to Bruce Ackerman, E. Donald Elliot, Joseph Feller, Elizabeth Garrett,
John Graham, Robert Hahn, Lisa Heinzerling, Jeffrey Knight, William Pederson, Eric
Posner, Richard Posner, David Strauss, Jonathan Wiener, and participants in a work in
progress lunch at the University of Chicago Law School for valuable comments on a previous
draft. I am also grateful to Robert Hahn for organizing two panel discussions at the
Brookings-American Enterprise Institute - Brookings Joint Center for Regulatory Studies,
where I learned a great deal from the comments of my co-panelists - at the first session,
Boyden Gray, Carol Browner, and Edward Warren, and at the second, Christopher
DeMuth, Lisa Heinzerling, and Jonathan Wiener. Brooke May provided superb research
assistance. Thanks also to Robert Gasaway and attorneys at the Environmental Protection
Agency for providing valuable information.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>A. Kenneth Culp Davis'sInterestingInnovation..................... 340</title>
      <p>B. The (Early)Life ofan Idea .................................................. 342</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>C. The Rise of the New NondelegationDoctrine..................... 344</title>
      <p>D. Particulatesand Ozone in Court.......................................... 347
V. EVALUATING THE NEW NONDELEGATION DOCTRINE ........... 349
A. Is This a NondelegationDoctrineatAll? ............................ 349</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>1. The Appeal of the New Doctrine: Surrogate</title>
      <p>Safeguards........................................................................ 349
2. Problems........................................................................... 350</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>B. The Placeof the NondelegationDoctrinein</title>
      <p>AdministrativeLaw ............................................................... 356
1. Invalidationsin Extreme Cases ...................................... 356
2. Statutory Construction.................................................... 357</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>3. Democracy-PromotingMinimalism: Clear</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>StatementPrinciplesas NondelegationCanons............ 357</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>C. Why the CleanAir Act Is Constitutional(and WhatIt</title>
      <p>Means) .................................................................................... 359
VI. OPTIONS, FUTURES, AND CLEAN AIR ....................................... 361
A. A Twenty-first Century EPA: Ceilings,Floors,
and "BenefitsAnalysis"........................................................ 362
1. The Problem..................................................................... 362
2. TowardBenefits Analysis ............................................... 363</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>3. Difficulties, Uncertainty,ContentiousAssumptions..... 365</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>4. An Analogy: From Health to the Environment........... 366</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>5. Toward a (New) Common Law ofRegulatory</title>
      <p>Protection......................................................................... 367</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>B. Ordinary(NotExtraordinary)JudicialReview:</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-13">
      <title>Democracy-PromotingMinimalism in Practice................. 369</title>
      <p>1. Failingthe HardLook .................................................... 369
2. Surviving a Softer Look .................................................. 370</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-14">
      <title>3. The Problemof Ossificationand the Tyranny of the</title>
      <p>Status Quo Revisited........................................................ 370</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-15">
      <title>4. ProceduralInnovations: AdministrativeLaw</title>
      <p>Minimalism ...................................................................... 372
5. A Health-HealthWrinkle................................................ 374
6. A FinalContrast.............................................................. 375
C. Congress: Safety andIts Cost............................................... 376
1. How Safe Is Safe Enough? ............................................. 376
2. More Flexible Tools ........................................................ 377
3. Costs andBenefits............................................................ 377
CONCLUSION............................................................................................. 379
The American people are suffering from what can be called "a syndrome
of paranoia and neglect" about potential dangers to their health, safety,
and the environment. This leads to a paradox that is becoming
increasingly recognized. Large amounts of resources are devoted to slight or
speculative dangers while substantial and well-documented dangers
remain unaddressed.
-John Graham'
The last third of the twentieth century is not too late a time for turning
the rule of law and the non-delegation doctrine into effective and useful
legal tools for minimizing injustice from improper discretionary power.
-Kenneth Culp Davis2</p>
      <sec id="sec-15-1">
        <title>ADMINISTRATIVE LAW</title>
        <p>This Article deals with two linked questions. The first involves the
future of the Clean Air Act.' The particular concern is how the
Environmental Protection Agency ("EPA") might be .encouraged, with
help from reviewing courts, to issue better ambient air quality
standards, and in the process to shift from some of the anachronisms of
1970s environmentalism to a more fruitful approach to environmental
protection. The second question involves the role of the
nondelegation doctrine in American public law, a doctrine that shows
unmistakable signs of revival. I will suggest that improved performance by
EPA and agencies in general, operating in tandem with a new
approach to judicial review, would make it altogether unnecessary to
revive the nondelegation doctrine. Indeed, the nondelegation doctrine
would emerge as a crude and unhelpful response to existing problems
in modern regulation, even a form of judicial usurpation. Far better
responses are available.</p>
        <p>In issuing and revising a national ambient air quality regulation
under the Clean Air Act, EPA should provide a detailed "benefits
analysis." To this end, it should undertake two tasks. First,it should
1. John D. Graham, Making Sense of Risk- An Agenda for Congress,in RISKS, COSTS,
AND LIVES SAVED: GETrING BETrER RESULTS FROM REGULATION 183,183 (Robert W.
Hahn ed., 1996).</p>
        <p>2. KENNETH CULP DAVIS, DISCRETIONARY JUSTICE: A PRELIMINARY INQUIRY 51
(1969).</p>
        <p>3. Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C. §§ 7401-7671q (1994).
specify the range of benefits that it believes are likely to result from
the regulation, along with a specification of the range of benefits that
it believes would result from at least two reasonable alternative
approaches, one stricter and one more lenient. In the process EPA
should identify the residualrisk left under the competing regulatory
regimes; it should also acknowledge scientific uncertainty, to the
extent that uncertainty exists and requires guesswork. This proposal is
an effort to strengthen the role of sound science in environmental
protection.</p>
        <p>Second, EPA should explain why it believes that the chosen rule is
preferable to the less and more stringent alternatives - why the set of
benefits to be received from the selected rule justify that rule, whereas
the set of benefits to be received from the less and more stringent
rules do not. In the process it should explain why the residual risk left
by the selected rule is acceptable, while the residual risk left by the
less stringent rule is not. This proposal is an effort to strengthen the
role of democratic forces in environmental protection.4</p>
        <p>If necessary, reviewing courts should require EPA to perform
these tasks. Taken together, the two proposals should increase the
level of consistency across regulations, reduce the power of
wellorganized private groups, and diminish the risks associated with both
insufficient and excessive environmental regulation. If EPA has
undertaken the two tasks, and carried them out in a reasonable way,
judicial review is at an end; courts should uphold EPA's decision.</p>
        <p>Ideas of this kind have potentially broad implications, extending
well beyond the Clean Air Act and even EPA, to the work of the
Occupational Safety and Health Administration ("OSHA"), the
Consumer Product Safety Commission, and the National Highway Traffic
and Safety Administration as well. They would mark a key moment in
the movement toward a system of environmental protection that is at
once more democratic and better informed. At the same time, they
would accelerate the continuing shift from 1970s environmentalism
and indeed 1970s regulation in general, away from recognizing the
existence of problems of safety and health and toward assessing their
magnitude, in such a way as to reduce both regulatory paranoia and
regulatory neglect, and to put a premium on the acquisition of
information</p>
        <p>4. Of course costs are important too; the two proposals are based on the current
understanding that benefits, but not costs, may be taken into account in issuing primary standards.
The question of costs is taken up later. See infra Section VI.C.</p>
        <p>5. For general discussion in this vein, see STEPHEN BREYER, BREAKING THE VICIOUS
CIRCLE: ToWARD EFFECTIVE RISK REGULATION (1993), and NEIL GUNNINGHAM &amp;
PETER GRABOSKY, SMART REGULATION: DESIGNING ENVIRONMENTAL POLICY (1998).</p>
        <p>If agencies undertook tasks of this kind, there would be little point
to the recent resurgence of interest in the nondelegation doctrine.
The sensible impulses that underlie that interest - impulses that
involve accountability, deliberation, and sound policymaking - can be
handled through other means, a point that casts a more general light
on the proper role of the nondelegation doctrine in American public
law. I suggest that the proper role of that doctrine consists in statutory
construction that imposes floors and ceilings on agency action, and in
a set of "nondelegation canons" that prevent agencies from acting
without clear congressional authorization. Taken together, judicial
requirements of this kind would constitute a form of
"democracypromoting minimalism"' in the distinctive context of administrative
law - and a partial step toward a better and more sophisticated
approach to environmental protection. These are the basic claims that I
will attempt to defend in this Article.</p>
        <p>B.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-16">
      <title>The CleanAir Act</title>
      <p>The Clean Air Act may well be the most important of all
environmental statutes. Its effects include a wide range of beneficial
consequences for human health and well-being and high costs on the private
sector. The Environmental Protection Agency estimates overall
compliance costs at $0.5 trillion.7 The Act's claim to success rests on
enormous improvements in ambient air quality and corresponding
health benefits. EPA estimates that the Act prevents at least 45,000
deaths annually and that it also prevents a minimum of 13,000 heart
attacks and 7,000 annual strokes! On a standard (though not
undisputed) view, the benefits of the Act, ranging between $5.6 trillion and
$49.4 trillion, far exceed its costs.9</p>
      <p>6. See CASS R. SUNSTEIN, ONE CASE AT A TIME: JUDICIAL MINIMALISM ON THE
SUPREmE COURT (1999), on the general topic ofjudicial minimalism.</p>
      <p>7. See J. CLARENCE DAVIES &amp; JAN MAZUREK, POLLUTION CONTROL IN THE UNITED
STATES: EVALUATING THE SYSTEM 130 (1998).</p>
      <p>8. See id.Judgments about benefits, nonmonetized but especially monetized, are highly
sensitive to contentions assumptions, and hence the "bottom line" numbers should be taken
with many grains of salt. See RANDALL LUrrER, AN ANALYSIS OF THE USE OF THE EPA'S
BENEFIT ESTIMATES IN OMB's DRAFT REPORT ON THE COSTS AND BENEFITS OF
REGULATION (1998) (urging the use of plausible alternative assumptions and asserting that
EPA's benefit calculations are inflated); see also Lisa Heinzerling, Regulatory Costs of
Mythic Proportions,107 YALE LJ.1981 (1998) (urging that costs per lives saved are inflated,
also because of contentious assumptions). Though coming from different directions, Lutter
and Heinzerling both argue, convincingly, that characterization of both benefits and costs
can shift dramatically with small changes in assumptions, an argument that much bears on
the central claims of this Article. See Randall Lutter &amp; Christopher DeMuth, Ozone and the
Constitutionatthe EPA, ON THE ISSUES, July 1999, at 3.</p>
      <p>9. See DAVIES &amp; MAZUREK, supranote 7, at 130,147.</p>
      <p>The Act has nonetheless been subject to telling criticism. The
foundation of clear air regulation consists of EPA's issuance of
nationally uniform ambient air quality standards;" but in light of the
extraordinary diversity of the fifty states, it is not clear that the idea of
national standards can be rationally defended." In addition, both
lower courts and EPA seem to think that the standard-setting process
does not and cannot involve consideration of costs.12 But does it make
sense, or is it even feasible, to say that national standards will be
founded on an assessment of benefits alone, conducted in a cost
vacuum? 3 If an improvement in ambient air quality would produce
health benefits that are small but not trivial, isn't it clear that the
improvement is justified if compliance costs are trivial, but not if the
costs are extremely high? There is reason to think that at least in
some cases, an understanding of costs has affected EPA's decision
about appropriate standards - but that the cost-benefit balancing has
been left implicit and free from public scrutiny and review. 4</p>
      <p>Perhaps the largest question involves the criteria by which EPA
decides whether one or another level of regulation is (in the statutory
phrase) "requisite to protect the public health."15 For most pollutants,
air quality at various levels is not either "safe" or "not safe"; there are
diminishing degrees of risk associated with diminishing degrees of
exposure. On what basis is a particular level of residual risk said to be
the appropriate one? What judgments do, or should, enter into that
conclusion? EPA has been criticized for sometimes suggesting, in an
unhelpful and conclusory fashion, that it chooses the "safe" level, as if
this were solely a technocratic judgment and as if "safety" were an
onoff switch, 6 when its decision about permissible levels rests instead on
a series of political, scientific, and economic judgments and
compromises.</p>
      <p>There are two problems with this state of affairs. The first involves
democratic deliberation. 7 If EPA does not give a clear sense of the
range of adverse effects, and if it does not say why one set of such
effects calls for regulation and another does not, the public and its
representatives are not informed of the nature of the underlying
questions, and they are unable to evaluate the choices actually made.
Under EPA's articulated position, a purely technical issue (would a
certain level be safe?) is sometimes substituted, at least publicly, for
the real and more complicated ones (what level of safety is
appropriate in light of all the relevant factors? why should one level of
regulation be preferred to another?).</p>
      <p>The second problem involves sound regulatory policy. Any
proposed national standard could be loosened or tightened, and the
question is whether the agency has chosen the optimal, or at least a
reasonable, regulatory "point." Without a clear and (to the extent
possible) quantified presentation of the expected environmental
benefits of the various alternatives," there can be no assurance that the
agency has chosen that point, rather than one that is too strict or too
lenient.</p>
      <p>C.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-17">
      <title>A Remarkable Decisionand a New Doctrine</title>
      <p>In its extraordinary decision in American Trucking Ass'ns v.
EPA,9 the United States Court of Appeals for the District of
Columbia Circuit responded to this last concern in the strongest possible
terms. It held that as interpreted by EPA, the key provisions of the
Clean Air Act - those that give EPA authority to issue national air
quality standards - represent an unconstitutional delegation of
legislative power.10 The decision announces the birth of a new
nondelegation doctrine, one with potentially large implications for regulatory
policy. Under the new doctrine, open-ended statutory terms will be
invalidated unless agencies are able to specify the governing legal
criteria - to discipline their own authority through narrowing
interpretations.</p>
      <p>17. See id.</p>
      <p>18. Costs are of course important too. As discussed below, the prevailing view forbids
EPA from considering costs, and my basic proposal does not challenge that prevailing view.
I do, however, raise some doubts about it below. See infra Section VI.C.</p>
      <p>19. 175 F.3d 1027 (D.C. Cir. 1999) (per curiam), rehearingen banc denied, Nos. 97-1440,
97-1441,1999 WL 979463 (D.C. Cir. Oct. 29,1999).</p>
      <p>20. See American Trucking,175 F.3d at 1033.</p>
      <p>The new nondelegation doctrine is remarkable for many reasons.
First, the Supreme Court has not used the doctrine to invalidate a
federal statute since (or for that matter before) 1935,1 and hence any
such decision by a court of appeals is reasonably taken to mark a fresh
departure. Second, the new doctrine does not require Congress to
legislate with clarity. It says instead that if Congress has not been
clear, agencies must act on their own, to set out limits on their own
legal authority. Third, there now appears to be a genuine doctrine in
place; American Trucking represents no isolated decision, but the
culmination of a line of lower court cases, one of which was a similar
decision about the Occupational Safety and Health Act.' The
decision therefore signals a distinctive approach to judicial review of
agency action. Fourth, the doctrine is conspicuously responsive to
what the court of appeals saw (and often sees) as a general problem in
federal regulation: the difficulty of knowing why an agency chooses
one level of regulation rather than another that is somewhat higher or
somewhat lower.</p>
      <p>The new doctrine raises a number of questions. The narrowest
(though far from unimportant) issue has to do with the fate of EPA
rulemaking with respect to national ambient air quality standards
("NAAQS"). What, if anything, can EPA do in the future? The
question is significant both because of its consequences for implementation
of the Clean Air Act and because of its implications for regulatory
policy in general. On its face, the American Trucking decision would
seem to draw into serious constitutional question not only EPA's
ozone and particulates regulations, but also a wide range of other
regulations by EPA, and indeed a wide range of decisions by many
other agencies involved in the protection of health and welfare (and
other areas as well; consider the Federal Communications
Commission). And what, exactly, is the relationship between the new doctrine
and ordinary judicial review to test whether agency action has been
"arbitrary" or "capricious"? An especially large question, and the
central focus here, has to do with how American Trucking exposes
continuing problems with the design and implementation of
environmental regulation as a whole and the Clean Air Act in particular, a
statute whose key provisions seem to depend on implausible
assumptions, and under which EPA has sometimes hidden crucial questions
of value with uninformative platitudes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-18">
      <title>D. Goals and Plans</title>
      <p>In this Article, my most general goal is to understand current
difficulties with environmental policy, the Clean Air Act, and EPA
promulgation of ambient air quality standards, and to see how EPA and
courts might perform a constructive role in making things better
rather than worse. My simplest claim is that EPA should undertake
the two tasks identified above; it should specify the range of benefits
that it believes will follow from the regulation it seeks to impose,
including a discussion of the benefits from more lenient and more
stringent alternatives and a treatment of the residual risks under the
various regulatory regimes. It should also explain why it believes that the
chosen regulation is preferable to the alternatives.</p>
      <p>Steps in these directions would satisfy the legitimate concerns of
most critics of EPA's performance under the Clean Air Act and also
of the court of appeals in American Trucking. Such steps also have
broad applicability and would represent a new departure of their own
in administrative law, covering the activities of EPA under a wide
range of statutes and also the activities of (for example) the
Occupational Safety and Health Administration, the Consumer Product
Safety Commission, and the National Highway Traffic Safety
Administration. Steps of this sort would not amount to a nondelegation
doctrine, new or old. But they are designed to promote both rule-of-law
values and sound regulatory policy, in a way that should respond to
growing understandings about current problems in environmental
policy and the administrative state.</p>
      <p>I have three more particular goals. The first is to reject the
nondelegation doctrine, both old and new, as a way of ensuring better and
more transparent policy analysis by EPA and other agencies. That
issue raises large questions about democratic accountability and about
the appropriate role of courts in reviewing agency action. I suggest
that although the new doctrine has considerable appeal, this is not
really a nondelegation doctrine at all, and the relevant goals would be
better accomplished through a form of more conventional (but better
informed) judicial review of agency action. The Clean Air Act is
hardly unconstitutional, for it is possible to generate an interpretation
of the Act that imposes both "floors" and "ceilings" on agency action.</p>
      <p>My second goal is to propose a contemporary role for the
nondelegation doctrine in American public law. I claim that the doctrine is
properly held in reserve for extreme cases - that it serves as a
genuine, but judicially underenforced, constitutional norm - and that it
operates as a legitimate tool of statutory construction. More
importantly, I contend that the doctrine is not so much dead as relocated.
Its current home can be found not in cases invalidating open-ended
grants of authority, but in the many decisions using various "clear
statement" principles to discipline legislative and administrative
action.z3 When courts require Congress to speak clearly in order to
authorize an agency to raise a serious constitutional problem, or to
apply a statute extraterritorially or retroactively, they are applying a
narrower and more targeted version of the nondelegation doctrine
a version that requires Congress to focus, with particularity, on certain
especially sensitive questions. By requiring congressional rather than
merely executive deliberation on those questions, the various "clear
statement" principles operate as a nondelegation doctrine in another
guise. As such, the principles are easily defended, for they promote
the key functions of the nondelegation doctrine without carrying the
risks of the old and new versions.</p>
      <p>My third goal is to discuss possible improvements in the operation
of the Clean Air Act, at the legislative, administrative, and judicial
levels, improvements that might respond to various concerns about
EPA performance, including the concerns expressed in American
Trucking. I attempt to explain how the Act seems based on the (false)
assumption that pollutants generally have "safe thresholds," and how
this assumption has seriously impaired both regulatory policymaking
and democratic deliberation. I also suggest that the Act should be
interpreted, or if necessary amended, to allow and require EPA to
engage in "health-health tradeoffs" - and also to take account of costs
in setting national standards. In particular, I emphasize that EPA
should engage in more specific and quantitative assessments of the
hazardous effects of pollution at various levels, so as to increase the
transparency of its decisions. It could even make sense for EPA to
move in the direction of the "quality-adjusted life years" approach,
designed to provide a concrete sense of the benefits of regulatory
alternatives.2 4 Under such an approach, EPA would attempt to specify
the range of "quality-adjusted life years" likely to be saved by a
regulation, and it would also indicate the degree of savings that would
justify a regulation. But because of the harmful side effects of aggressive
judicial review, courts should play only a secondary and catalytic role
- embodied in certain recent and quite innovative procedural
developments in administrative law, above all the "remand without
invalidation." As we will see, this procedural route is administrative law's
newest species of minimalism, indeed a form of democracy-promoting
minimalism.2 The central point is that EPA should undertake such
inquiries on its own.</p>
      <p>23. See Cass R. Sunstein, Nondelegation Canons,U. CHI. L. REV. (forthcoming 2000),
for a catalogue. See also 'WilliamN. Eskridge, Jr. &amp; Philip P. Frickey, Quasi-Constitutional
Law: Clear Statement Rules as ConstitutionalLawmaking, 45 VAND. L. REv. 593 (1992)
(discussing clear statement principles in general).</p>
      <p>24. See American Trucking,175 F.3d at 1039-40 &amp; n.5.
25. For a general discussion ofjudicial minimalism, see SUNSTEIN, supranote 6.</p>
      <p>This Article comes in six parts. Part II deals with the Clean Air
Act and in particular with the artificiality of the inquiries that it
appears to make central to EPA's task. Part III explores the old
nondelegation doctrine, the development of the new nondelegation
doctrine, and the use of the doctrine in American Trucking and related
cases. Part IV evaluates the new doctrine, explains why the Clean Air
Act is constitutionally unproblematic, and suggests an alternative
approach. Part V discusses the proper approaches to the Act from
Congress, EPA, and reviewing courts. Part VI is a brief conclusion.</p>
      <sec id="sec-18-1">
        <title>THE CLEAN AIR Acr</title>
        <p>Overall, the benefits of the Clean Air Act since its enactment in 1970
clearly outweigh the costs.
-J. Clarence Davies and Jan MazurekO
Congress should not preclude decisionmakers from considering the
economic costs and benefits of different policies in the development of
regulations.</p>
        <p>Most environmental initiatives of the past seemed expensive and
questionable at the time, and today every one of them appears a bargain in
retrospect. Looking back on the present a few decades hence, society
will consider every environmental program running now to have been a
bargain, and wish more programs had been started sooner.</p>
        <p>-Gregg Easterbrook
-Kenneth Arrow et al.V</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-19">
      <title>A. SettingNationalStandards 1.</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-20">
      <title>The Key Provisions</title>
      <p>The Clean Air Act was enacted in 1970. Though many hundreds
of pages in length, some of them mind-numbingly specific and
detailed, 9 the Act offers two remarkably brief provisions designed to set
the statutory program in motion.</p>
      <p>26. DAVIES &amp; MAZUREK, supra note 7, at 147.</p>
      <p>27. KENNETH J. ARRow ET AL., BENEFrr-CosT ANALYSIS IN ENVIRONMENTAL,
HEALTH, AND SAFETY REGULATION: A STATEMENT OF PRINCIPLES 6 (1996).</p>
      <p>28. GREGG EAsTERaROOK, A MOMENT ON THE EARTH: THE COMING AGE OF
ENVIRONMENTAL OPTIMISM 210 (1995).</p>
      <p>29. Consider the acid deposition program, which goes so far as to list, by name, every
plant entitled to emit sulfur dioxide and its permitted emissions level (a flavor: 13,570 tons
for the Colbert plant, generator number one, in Alabama; 15,430 tons for the Armstrong
plant, generator number two, in Pennsylvania), see Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C. § 7651(c)
(1994), alongside an exceptionally specific program for the granting and trading of emissions
rights, see 42 U.S.C. § 7651(b).</p>
      <p>The first of these provisions, and the central focus here, involves
national primary ambient air quality standards.' Here EPA is asked
to set standards "the attainment and maintenance of which in the
judgment of the Administrator," based on air quality criteria
documents "and allowing an adequate margin of safety, are requisite to
protect the public health."31 The second of these provisions involves
national secondary ambient air quality standards, which EPA must set
at levels "requisite to protect the public welfare from any known or
anticipated adverse effects associated with the presence of such air
pollutant in the ambient air."'32 "Welfare" is defined to include
"effects on soils, water, crops, vegetation, manmade materials, animals,
wildlife, weather, visibility, and climate, damage to and deterioration
of property, and hazards to transportation, as well as effects on
economic values and on personal comfort and well-being .... I For
secondary standards, involving welfare rather than health, there is no
provision for an "adequate margin of safety." But the secondary
standards are anticipated to be more stringent than the primary ones;
notice in particular the statutory emphasis on plant and animal life.</p>
      <p>These provisions have three especially noteworthy features. First,
they seem at first glance not to contemplate any consideration of cost
in the standard-setting process.' Primary standards are based on
health, apparently to be assessed in a cost vacuum, while secondary
standards are based on welfare, also apparently to be assessed without
regard to cost. This is not at all an inevitable reading of the relevant
provisions; perhaps the level "requisite to protect the public health"
and "welfare" is a function of cost, not only benefit; but the prevailing
interpretation is otherwise.35 Second, the standards are fully national
- even though political judgments about air quality vary greatly from
state to state, and even though the effects of improved air quality (on
the cost and benefit sides) are highly variable from one state to
another. Finally, both provisions appear to contemplate the existence of
"safe thresholds." The basic idea is that EPA should ensure that air is
"safe" and that public welfare is "protected."</p>
      <p>
        What makes this last idea distinctive is its artificiality. To be sure,
we could imagine pollutants for which the evidence indicated a point
30. See 42 U.S.C. §7409(a)-(b).
31. 42 U.S.C. § 7409(b)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12 ref16 ref52 ref64 ref7">1</xref>
        ) (emphasis added).
32. 42 U.S.C. § 7409(b)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13 ref17 ref53 ref70 ref8">2</xref>
        ) (emphasis added).
33. 42 U.S.C. § 7602(h).
      </p>
      <p>35. See LeadIndus., 647 F.2d at 1148-56.
of "no risk" or "de minimis risk." At least in theory; it is possible to
construct a dose-response curve for which risks effectively vanish at a
certain defined point. But for most pollutants, there are diminishing
degrees of risk, associated with diminishing degrees of pollution. 6
"Safety" is not an off-on switch; it is a matter of degree. When it is
said that a certain level of pollution is "safe," what is really meant is
that the residual risk is acceptable or tolerable - not that there is no
risk at all. Consider, for example, this commendably direct testimony
from the Chair of EPA's Scientific Advisory Committee's panel on
ozone and particulates, unambiguously confessing the impossible
nature of the task imposed on EPA by the Act:</p>
      <p>Based on information now available, it appears that ozone may elicit a
continuum of biological responses down to background concentrations.
It is critical to understand that a biological response does not necessarily
imply an adverse health effect. Nevertheless, this means that the
paradigm of selecting a standard at the lowest-observable-effects-level and
then providing an "'adequate margin of safety"' is not possible. It
further means that risk assessments must play a central role in identifying an
appropriate level3 7</p>
      <p>How might we explain the enactment of provisions that seem at
once so vague, rigid, and artificial? Much of the answer lies in the
distinctive political dynamic of environmental debates in the late 1960s
and early 1970s, in which citizens wanted air to be "safe" and
politicians who failed to respond were at great risk." We might even
describe the result as "1970s environmentalism," a form of thinking that
accomplished a great deal of good, by producing rapid decreases in
pollution levels, but that also seems increasingly anachronistic, even
counterproductive. In the 1970s in particular, politicians would
proceed at their peril if they asserted that "safety" could be compromised
by other goals3 9 At the same time, politicians were affected by, and
doubtless catered to, the pervasive psychological urge for certainty, as
confirmed by evidence that people are willing to pay a great deal for
"no risk" and much less for "substantially less risk."' Thus, for
exam36. See, e.g., LANDY ETAL, supra note 13, at 55-56,78-79.
ple, people are willing to pay more for a reduction of a risk from 0.1 to
0.0 than from 0.3 to 0.1.41 The idea that the Clean Air Act would
produce "safety" rather than "reduced risk" made it far easier to support
and far harder to challenge.</p>
      <p>Undoubtedly Congress believed that it was delegating to EPA the
power to be reasonable rather than unreasonable, and in any case the
Act allowed various safeguards in the event that compliance proved to
be excessively costly.42 The most important safeguard has consisted in
a form of (implicitly authorized) civil disobedience on the part of all
relevant actors, including EPA. The result has been a complex
program for nonattainment areas43 and a number of illuminating episodes;
thus EPA was simply not prepared to shut down automobile traffic in
Los Angeles, a step that would have been necessary to produce
compliance with national air quality standards.'</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-21">
      <title>Problemsand Puzzles</title>
      <p>All of these points have created serious difficulties for EPA in
practice. The first problem has to do with expense. For nonthreshold
pollutants,45 it seems both natural and sensible to assess further
reductions in terms of their cost. If, for example, the expense of reducing
sulfur dioxide from 0.3 ppm to 0.2 ppm is trivial, then the reduction is
almost certainly worthwhile (unless the dose-response curve has a
most peculiar shape ). Even if there is little direct evidence of
adverse human health effects at 0.2 ppm, this is likely to be because of
the limited data, rather than because of an absence of such effects.
But matters look very different if the cost would run into the tens of
billions of dollars. When benefits are highly uncertain, it is peculiar to
say that EPA cannot consider cost, especially since health gains are
almost inevitable as permissible exposure levels decline.47
41. See Kahneman &amp; Tversky, supranote 40, at 268-69.
42. For an outline, see Union ElectricCo. v. EPA, 427 U.S. 246,266-69 (1976).
43. See Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C. §§ 7501-15 (1994).</p>
      <p>44. See Krier, supranote 11, at 335-41 (describing EPA's abandonment of a 1973 plan to
ration gasoline in the Los Angeles area).</p>
      <p>45. These are pollutants that have some possibility of some adverse health impact at any
exposure level above zero.</p>
      <p>46. For example, one that would show no health benefits from a reduction from 0.3 ppm
to 0.2 ppm, notwithstanding health benefits from a reduction from 0.4 ppm to 0.3 ppm.</p>
      <p>47. As noted below, it seems that cost considerations were relevant to EPA's decision
not to reduce the particulates standard further than it did, since some data indicated possibly
significant benefits from further reductions. See infra app. tbl.11.</p>
      <p>In light of this point, some critics have suggested that some kind of
cost-benefit balancing inevitably occurs at EPA.' At least publicly,
EPA denies this claim 9 Consider Administrator Browner's
suggestion:</p>
      <p>Costs of meeting the standards and related factors have never been
considered in setting the national ambient air quality standards themselves
....[T]he focus has been entirely on health, risk, exposure and damage
to the environment .... And the American public deserves to know
whether the air in its cities and counties is unsafe or not; that question
should never be confused with the separate issues of how long it may
take or how much it may cost to reduce pollution to safe levels. Indeed,
to allow costs and related factors to influence the determination of what
levels protect public health would be to mislead the American public in a
very fundamental way5</p>
      <p>Only insiders know for certain whether EPA does in fact consider
costs in issuing national ambient air quality standards 1 But consider,
by way of contrast and as a possible clue, the Administrator's
explanation of the 1979 revision of the ozone standard:</p>
      <p>The Clean Air Act, as the Administrator interprets it, does not permit
him to take factors such as cost of attainment or attainability into
account in setting the level of the standard; the standard is to be one that
will adequately protect public health ....[He] recognizes... that
controlling CO to very low levels is a task that can have significant impact on
economic and social activity. This recognition causes [him] to reject as
an option the setting of a zero-level standard ....However, it is public
health, and not economic impact, that must be the compelling factor in
the decision.52
48. See, e.g., George Eads, The Confusion of Goals andInstruments: The Explicit
Considerationof Cost in Setting NationalAmbientAir QualityStandards,in To BREATHE
FREELY: RISK, CONSENT, AND AiR 223,227-29 (Mary Gibson ed., 1985). See also the
suggestion in Farber, supranote 11, at 315-18, about the distinctive "slippage" between law and
reality in the context of environmental law.</p>
      <p>51. As noted, EPA's failure to require more stringent regulation of particulates provides
some evidence of cost consideration. On EPA's own numbers, more stringent regulation
might have provided $4 billion in increased benefits. See infra app. tbl.11. If these benefits
were possible, why did EPA not require greater stringency, if not because of some cost
consciousness?</p>
      <p>52. Carbon Monoxide: Proposed Revisions to the National Ambient Air Quality
Standards and Announcement of Public Meetings, 45 Fed. Reg. at 55,072.</p>
      <p>This explanation, difficult to follow though it is, is most naturally
taken as a suggestion that despite the nominal irrelevance of cost,
costs do matter in the context of standard-setting for nonthreshold
pollutants.</p>
      <p>The second problem has to do with federalism. The Act requires
uniform national standards; but in practice, EPA authorizes a
considerable amount of variation among states. For example, there is little
question that the exceedingly high costs of attainment will, for many
states, produce frequent violations of national requirements - and
this has in fact turned out to be the case5 Several decades after the
initial issuance of ambient air quality standards for ozone, for
example, over 50 million people live in areas that are frequently in violation
of national standards? 4 Smaller numbers - but still many millions
of people live in nonattainment areas for other pollutants.</p>
      <p>The upshot is that national standards have mostly served not as
real law, but as targets or aspirations6 - flexible goals to which the
federal government can point without, however, insisting on
compliance unless or until it is reasonable. This aspirational quality of
national standards has led Congress to enact an increasingly complex set
of provisions for nonattainment areas, provisions that anticipate
compliance in certain areas over a period of many years and that, in
practice, therefore recognize the existence of reasonable variations across
states5. 7 Indeed it is contemplated, by the 1990 revision of the Act,
that one of the nation's largest urban areas, Los Angeles, will not be in
compliance until 2010 at the earliest5.</p>
      <p>This point leads to a more general one, bearing on cost-benefit
balancing as well as on federalism. EPA's official position that
standard-setting is cost-blind is complemented by explicit statements
to the effect that cost, efficiency, and feasibility are relevant in making
45.</p>
      <p>57. The Clean Air Act, 42 §§7401-7671q (1994), contains these nonattainment
provisions at 42 U.S.C. §§ 7501-15, especially at § 7511.</p>
      <p>58. See 42 U.S.C. § 7511.
choices about compliance.5 9 In a way these statements are puzzling,
for the Supreme Court has held that cost, and infeasibility, are
irrelevant to EPA's decision whether to approve state implementation
plans.' But EPA appears to acknowledge that state implementation
plans will themselves consider costs, and also that cost will be relevant
in setting schedules for compliance.61</p>
      <p>Finally, EPA must make hard choices about how safe is safe
enough, an important question in light of the artificiality of the idea
that air is either "safe" or "unsafe." EPA's choices involve not merely
the facts, but also evaluative judgments about acceptable degrees of
risk. A central question has to do with the ingredients of any
judgment that a certain risk is too high. There are many important
questions here, which include:6'
*The size of the population at risk, that is, whether 100,000, a
million, or tens of millions of people are at risk.63
*The nature of the population at risk - for example, whether it
involves a large number of children, whether only elderly people
are affected, whether those affected have a preexisting condition,
such as asthma.' An important question is whether any "lives
saved" number would involve young people or old people; there
is less need for a policy that would (say) increase life expectancy
by one year for those over 80 than for a policy that would
increase life expectancy by sixty years for those under 10. This
point suggests that EPA might reasonably concern itself not with
lives saved, but with life-years saved, a point to which I will
return.6
*The likelihood of harm for particular members of the affected
population, that is, whether the likelihood of incurring harm is 1
in 1,000, 1 in 10,000, or 1 in a million.' Thus, for example, the
plurality of the Supreme Court held in Industrial Union
Depart59. See Clean Air Hearings,supra note 50, at 282-83 (statement of Carol M. Browner,
Administrator, EPA).</p>
      <p>60. See Union Electric Co. v. EPA, 427 U.S. 246,265 (1976).</p>
      <p>61. See ROBERT PERCIVAL ET AL., ENVIRONMENTAL REGULATION 123-24 (Supp.
1998) (outlining EPA's "Common Sense Implementation Plan").</p>
      <p>62. See American Trucking Ass'n v. EPA, 175 F3d 1027,1039 (D.C. Cir. 1999) (per
curiam).</p>
      <p>63. See, e.g., R. SHEv MELNICK, REGULATION AND THE COURTS: THE CASE OF THE
CLEAN AIR Acr 275-76 (1983) (discussing lead). The importance of considering population
size is stressed in JAMES T. HAMILTON &amp; W. KIP VISCUSI, CALCULATING RISKS? 91-108
(1999).</p>
      <p>64. See MELNICK, supra note 63, at 275-76.
65. See infraSection VLA.4.</p>
      <p>66. See Clean Air Hearings,supra note 50, at 280-81 (statement of Carol M. Browner,
Administrator, EPA).
ment v. American Petroleum Institute ("Benzene Case")67 that
OSHA may regulate only "significant risks," and that a risk of
one in a billion could not count as significant.' OSHA now
concludes that a lifetime annual risk of 1.64/1,000 would count as
significant. 9 But undoubtedly the importance of addressing such a
risk will depend on other factors, notably including the size of the
affected population.
oThe severity of the risk - for example, whether it involves cancer
or mortality risks, or increased hospital admissions, bronchitis,
respiratory symptoms, lost work days, or what EPA calls minor
restricted activity days."</p>
      <p>Although EPA considers all of these questions in issuing national
standards,71 it has developed no clear guidelines to discipline its
judgment about when one or another level of regulation is appropriate. It
has not said, for example, that if 100,000 people face a cancer risk of
1/1,000, regulation is presumptively desirable, but if 10,000 face a
1/1,000 chance of minor respiratory problems, regulation is
presumptively not desirable.7 2 A reading of EPA's voluminous documents on
the major air pollutants provides an enormous amount of data, but
little information on the answers that would trigger a decision to
increase or decrease regulation. As we will see, all of the various points
noted above might reasonably be turned into a kind of global figure,
for example "quality-adjusted life years," designed to quantify the
various benefits from regulation.73</p>
      <p>One final note: An obvious and important question has to do with
the distributional effects of national ambient air quality standards.
Who bears the costs? Who receives the benefits? Full information is
not available. But an early study finds that under the Act, poor
people, and African Americans, are net gainers, whereas wealthy people,
and whites, are net losers74 - perhaps not a shocking finding in light
of the fact that many of the adverse effects of air pollution are
concentrated in large cities.</p>
      <p>In sum: The Act has produced many improvements in air quality,
but the questions about federalism, cost-benefit analysis, and the
concept of "safety" raise serious concerns about the Act and about EPA
performance. As we will see, these criticisms have implications for the
constitutionality of the Act and the resurgence of the nondelegation
doctrine, as well as for more general concerns of democracy and
accountability.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-22">
      <title>B. Revising NationalStandards- and the Tyranny of the Status Quo</title>
      <p>In 1971, EPA issued six national standards, governing ozone,
particulates, sulfur oxides, nitrogen oxides, carbon monoxide, and total
suspended particulates IV' In 1978, EPA issued a seventh standard,
involving lead; it did so as a result of a court order.76 These seven
regulations amount to the centerpiece of EPA's regulatory system for
the control of national ambient air quality.</p>
      <p>Of course it would be extremely surprising if the standards
originally adopted in 1971 and 1978 turn out to survive new scientific
evidence, and many people have urged that adjustments are desirable, in
the direction of both tightening and loosening existing requirements.
Congress has thus created an "agency-forcing" mechanism designed to
require EPA reconsideration of primary and secondary standards.
Under the Act, EPA is required to review the relevant criteria and
standards at least once every five years, and to revise them "as
appropriate" under the statutory guidelines.' EPA is specifically required
to consider, and to explain any significant departures from, the
recommendations of the Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee
("CASAC"), an independent committee established specifically in
order to advise the Administrators on air quality criteria and standards.78
A great deal of time and expense is necessary to respond to new
scien74. See Henry M. Peskin, EnvironmentalPolicy and the Distribution of Benefits and
Costs, in CuRRENT IssuEs IN ENVIRONMENTAL POLIcY 144, 147-59 (Paul Portney ed.,
1978).</p>
      <p>
        75. See infraapp. for details.
76. See id
77. See CleanAir Act, 42 U.S.C. § 7409(d)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12 ref16 ref52 ref64 ref7">1</xref>
        ) (1994).
78. See 42 U.S.C. §§ 7409(d)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13 ref17 ref53 ref70 ref8">2</xref>
        )(B), 7607(d)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18 ref60 ref63 ref87">3</xref>
        ).
the agency can show that without such rules, people will face serious
risks of one kind or another; the "remand without vacating" approach
makes best sense when the agency may well be able to justify its action
on remand. Both of these ideas are designed to ensure that rules that
are highly likely to be reasonable are not struck from the books, in a
way that could produce serious problems. Properly understood, they
do not allow agencies to proceed with inadequately justified rules if it
appears unlikely that those rules could be lawfully explained, or if it
appears that little will be lost with invalidation.
      </p>
      <p>Hence we arrive at an appropriate approach to these cases, one
with general application: The rules should be held unlawful, and
remanded to the agency; but they should not be vacated, at least when
the agency can show (a) that it may be able to generate a justification
that will satisfy judicial review, and (b) that invalidation of the rule
may generate significant risks (by, for example, allowing people to be
exposed to nontrivial dangers, or by preventing the agency from
initiating a program for reducing such risks)?'° After the agency attempts
to justify its regulation on remand, its decision may be appealed to the
court, which can evaluate the new justification and uphold or
invalidate the regulation as appropriate. An approach of this kind seems
especially sensible for the particulates regulation, which is designed to
counteract what, on a reasonable reading of the evidence, count as
quite serious risks to life and health. The problem with invalidation is
that it would prevent the agency from beginning implementation and
require the agency to start largely from scratch, a process that may
require years or more of rulemaking activity. A remand without
invalidation would allow the agency to proceed if (as appears quite
possible) the regulation can be adequately defended by reference to the
criteria I have outlined. Things are more difficult for ozone, because
the risks are far lower, and because nonregulation may actually
produce health benefits; 1' but here as well, a remand without invalidation
would probably be the best way to proceed.</p>
      <p>It would be possible to object that the technique of "remand
without invalidation" creates unfortunate incentives for administrators,
above all because it permits the continued legality and even the
enF.3d 1129,1135 (D.C. Cir. 1995); ChemicalMfrs. Ass'n, 28 F.3d at 1268; Checkosky, 23 F.3d
at 462-65; Allied-Signal, Inc. v. NRC, 988 F.2d 146,150-51 (D.C. Cir. 1993) (announcing that
court will not vacate rules because of inadequacy in agency reasoning if agency has a serious
possibility of correcting the deficiency on remand and vacation may be disruptive); Mid-Tex
Elec Coop., 822 F.2d at 1132-34.</p>
      <p>300. Some support for EPA's choices here, though to be sure not decisive, comes from
the fact that California made quite similar decisions not less than a decade ago. See James
M. Lents, A Review of NationalOzone and ParticulateMatterAir Quality StandardsIn Light
of Long-Standing CaliforniaAir QualityStandards,11 TUL. ENViL. L.J. 415,421-23 (1998).
301. See infraSection VI.A.5.
forcement of rules that have been found to be inadequately justified
(and that may not ultimately survive review). The enforcement of
these rules may cost millions and even billions of dollars. If so, isn't
invalidation preferable? To be sure, a system in which inadequately
justified rules are invalidated would create more pressure to produce
adequate justifications in the first instance. But the proper response
to this concern is not to invalidate all inadequately justified rules, but
to restrict the "remand without invalidation" technique to special
circumstances, above all (a) to rules that might well turn out to be valid
(b) in conditions in which invalidation would produce serious
problems for the legitimate policies that underlie the rules in question. The
court of appeals for the D.C. Circuit has made considerable progress
in drawing the necessary lines.'</p>
      <p>There is a broader point in the background here. The techniques
of remand without invalidation, and of allowing interim rules, can be
seen as a form of administrative law "minimalism," akin to judicial
minimalism in constitutional law generally." 3 Such techniques do no
more than is necessary to resolve a case. Indeed, these forms of
minimalism are democracy-reinforcing insofar as they attempt to ensure
that agency decisions are based on grounds that are both transparent
to the public and sufficient to justify the regulation in light of statutory
criteria.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-23">
      <title>A Health-HealthWrinkle</title>
      <p>A difficult question, not addressed thus far, is raised by a particular
claim with respect to EPA's ozone regulation: that ground-level
ozone has health benefits, and that these benefits were not taken into
account by the agency. There is evidence that ozone reduces the risk
of both cataracts and cancers.3" If taken into account, the health
benefits of ozone at current levels may well be roughly equivalent to
the health costs. But EPA refused to consider those health benefits.
In an interesting application of "health-health" analysis, the court of
appeals held that the refusal was unlawful. 5</p>
      <p>In general, it is right to say that agencies should be required to take
account of the health problems sometimes produced by regulation
de302. See Davis County, 108 F.3d at 1457; AMA, 57 F.3d at 1135; Allied Signal, 988 F.2d
at 150-51 (announcing that a court will not vacate rules because of inadequacy in agency
reasoning if agency has a serious possibility of correcting the deficiency on remand and vacation
may be disruptive).</p>
      <p>303. See SUNSTEIN, supranote 6, at 3-72.
304. See Lutter &amp; DeMuth, supranote 8, at 10.</p>
      <p>305. See American Trucking Ass'ns v. EPA, 175 F.3d 1027, 1051-52 (D.C. Cir. 1999)
(per curiam).
signed to reduce health problems. This kind of health-health tradeoff
can take many different forms.' In typical cases, the regulation of
one risk, like that associated with asbestos, may give rise to further
risks as a result of the substituted products. The most adventurous
claims for "health-health" comparisons arise when a costly regulation
imposes health risks simply by virtue of its cost2l If a regulation
produces less employment and more poverty, it may result in worse
health as well. But these are adventurous claims, because they depend
on contentious projections about the disemployment effects of
particular regulations.</p>
      <p>For the ozone rule, the argument for taking health-health tradeoffs
into account seemed especially insistent, for the claim was far from
indirect, and there was nothing speculative or abstruse about the causal
chain. If ozone protects against cancers and cataracts, it is possible
that a regulation of ozone will cause serious health problems. The text
of the Act is quite ambiguous on the point, and the court was wrong to
say that it unambiguously required the agency to address the
beneficial effects of air pollutants.RE But the court was right to hold that
even if it was ambiguous, the agency interpretation was unreasonable.
The rule was properly found inadequately justified on this ground, and
it may well be that after remand, the agency will be unable to explain
any failure to take account of the effects of ozone in combating
cataracts and cancer.</p>
      <p>There is of course a commonality between the approach taken by
the American Trucking court and the approach I am suggesting.
Where the American Trucking court said that the ambient air quality
standards provisions of the Clean Air Act are unconstitutional unless
EPA imposes limits on its own discretion, I have argued that ambient
air quality standards are valid if, and only if, EPA is able to generate a
"benefits analysis" that operates to constrain EPA discretion and to
promote interregulation consistency. The goals of the two approaches
are quite close. The disadvantage of the American Trucking approach
is that it involves unnecessary, even reckless, use of the Constitution
- and does so in a way that threatens to raise too many questions
about too many statutes. By contrast, the approach I have suggested
has firm roots in the APA and in existing doctrine, and promises to
306. See JOHN D. GRAHAM &amp; JONATHAN B. WIENER, RISK vs. RISK 247-68 (1995);
CASS R. SUNsTEIN, Health-HealthTradeoffs, in FREE MARKETS AND SOCIAL JuSTICE 298,
298-317 (1997).</p>
      <p>307. See SUNSTEIN, supranote 306, at 298-317.
308. SeeAmerican Trucking,175 F.3d at 1051-52.
improve regulatory practice without calling for an excessive judicial
role.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-24">
      <title>Congress: Safety and Its Cost</title>
      <p>Should Congress amend the national ambient air quality provisions
of the Clean Air Act? This is not the place for an extended discussion
of that question; but the analysis thus far suggests three possibilities.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-25">
      <title>How Safe Is Safe Enough?</title>
      <p>As emphasized throughout, a crucial defect of the national
ambient air quality provisions is that they seem to assume that whether air
is "safe" can be assessed solely on the basis of the facts. The truth is
that the facts might be able to show the degree of risk (at least within a
range), but they cannot show whether any particular degree of safety
is "safe enough." Whether or not pollutants lack safe thresholds, "the
paradigm of selecting a standard at the lowest-observable-effects-level
and then providing an 'adequate margin of safety' is not possible."3" 9
The result of the statutory framework is to misframe the key question
and also to give EPA little guidance for answering and asking that
question. As we have seen, EPA has greatly struggled with the
resulting difficulties.</p>
      <p>Congress should amend the statute to identify the factors for EPA
to consider in making the judgment about appropriate national
standards. Congress might offer substantive guidance by saying, for
example, that EPA must consider risk severity, size of affected
population, and likelihood of adverse effects at various exposure levels. On
the procedural side, it might require EPA to identify, to the extent
possible, the nature of the risks that it is reducing, and at the same
time to attempt to quantify the relevant risk reductions. The strongest
argument against an amendment to this effect is that it is unnecessary;
if EPA moved in the directions suggested above, it would essentially
be interpreting the current statute as if it contained instructions of
exactly this sort. But an amendment of this kind would at least provide a
clear legislative signal, and move EPA judgments in the direction of
greater transparency.</p>
      <p>309. See EPA's Rulemakings on the NationalAmbient Air Quality Standardsfor
Particulate Matterand Ozone: HearingsBefore the Subcomm. on CommercialandAdmin. Law
of the House Comm. on theJudiciary,105th Cong. 89 (1997) (prepared statement of George
T. Woolf, Former Chairman, EPA's Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee).</p>
      <p>We now know that significant cost savings can be achieved by
using more flexible, market-oriented instruments, such as tradable
pollution permits rather than uniform national requirements?10 Sometimes,
however, EPA does not choose such instruments even when it is
legally authorized to do so.31 It would make sense to amend the statute
to require EPA, wherever feasible, to use economic incentives rather
than a "command-and-control" approach? 2</p>
      <p>It is clear that an approach of this kind could save substantial
resources, and if the instruments are properly chosen, it should do so
without at the same time compromising air quality goals."3 An effort
to encourage EPA to select less burdensome alternatives could send a
desirable signal to attempt the least-cost methods of obtaining
regulatory goals, and might in addition spur creative experimentation.
3.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-26">
      <title>Costs and Benefits</title>
      <p>A possible lesson of EPA experience with national standards is
that EPA should be required or at least permitted to consider costs
when setting such standards. Indeed, it is not entirely clear that the
statute should be construed to forbid cost-benefit analysis from
EPA, 14 though lower courts have unanimously concluded otherwise.1 5
If the Supreme Court does not reject the lower courts' view, it is worth
giving serious consideration to a statutory change.</p>
      <p>The basic reasoning here is straightforward. If a reduction from
0.08 to 0.07 would be a trivial expense, surely it should be required; if
it would cost billions of dollars, there had better be good grounds to
believe very substantial health benefits would follow. A possible
argument to the contrary is that national standards operate as
aspirations, not ordinary law, and aspirations, at least, should be set on a
health-only basis - not because there is a magic place where air
quality is "safe," but because it is valuable to obtain, and use, a
technocratic judgment that people should have air quality of a certain
specified sort 16 The problem is that it is impossible to assess "safety" in a
cost vacuum. In general, cost-benefit analysis should be followed,
acknowledging that it will raise some hard questions of value.317</p>
      <p>The best argument against an amendment to require cost-benefit
analysis is that the statute, complex as it is, actually embodies a better
accommodation of costs and benefits than would a statute that
required cost-benefit analysis at the level of standard-setting.31 On this
view, the optimal system is one in which EPA makes an initial, purely
health-based judgment, and then the process of implementation allows
costs to play a role at various stages, emphatically including an
expectation that implementation will not be immediate and will in fact be a
product of a continuing inquiry into whether compliance is
worthwhile, P things considered.1 9 A possible virtue of this state of affairs
is precisely the aspirational quality of the health-based standard,
setting a target against which various state performances can be
measured. The aspirational quality can also contribute to
technology316. See the quotation from Administrator Browner, supra text accompanying note 50.
Administrator Browner goes on to say:</p>
      <p>While cost-benefit analysis is a tool that can be helpful in developing strategies to implement
our nation's air quality standards, we believe it is inappropriate for use to set the standards
themselves. In many cases, cost-benefit analysis has overstated costs. In addition, many
kinds of benefits are virtually impossible to quantify - how do I put a dollar value on
reductions in a child's lung function or the premature aging of lungs or increased susceptibility to
respiratory infection?
CleanAir Hearings,supra note 50, at 282 (statement of Carol M. Browner, Administrator,
EPA). Ironically, the Regulatory Impact Analysis required by President Clinton engages in
monetization of just this kind. See generallyinfraapp.</p>
      <p>317. See Sunstein, supra note 274. A good treatment of some of the questions of value
can be found in recent testimony of Richard Revesz. See Clean Air Act Authorizations:
HearingsBefore the Subcomm. on CleanAir, Wetlands, PrivateProperty,and NuclearSafety,
106th Cong. (1999) (Testimony of Richard L. Revesz), availablein LEXIS.COM, Legislation
&amp; Politics Library, U.S. Congress Folder, Federal Document Clearing House Congressional
Testimony File.</p>
      <p>318. This seems to be the conclusion of William F. Pedersen, Science and PublicPolicy:
A Case Study of the CleanAirAct, 16 PACE ENVT'L L. Rnv. 15 (1998). Pedersen argues that
a purely health-based standard can force technological innovation, see id. at 23-24, and also
stimulate and focus public debate, see id. at 22-23; he ends with the interesting suggestion
that EPA should be required to set standards "tight enough to protect against all clearly
demonstrated health or welfare effects," but that EPA should be allowed to consider costs
and technical feasibility in choosing the "margin of safety," id. at 30.</p>
      <p>319. See Farber, supra note 11, at 315-18, for an illuminating discussion of this point.
forcing, an important and often highly desirable phenomenon in
environmental protection,3" and a phenomenon to which cost-benefit
analysis is, at least in practice,321 unlikely to contribute.</p>
      <p>In the abstract, it is hard to know whether this pragmatic argument
is valid.31 What is clear is that the statutory scheme, pragmatically
defensible as it may be, is far from transparent, and provides a set of
confusing signals to the American public.</p>
      <p>CONCLUSION</p>
      <p>Whenever an agency issues a regulation designed to diminish risks
to health, safety, or the environment, it should attempt to identify the
gains sought by the particular regulation it has chosen, and it should
compare these gains to those under at least two reasonable alternative
regimes, one stricter and one more lenient. In this light, the most
serious problem with EPA's performance in issuing national air quality
standards is that it usually fails to explain, in simple, concise terms, its
decision to require a particular level of ambient air quality.
Sometimes EPA acts as if it were pursuing "safety" and ensuring "safe
levels," without sufficiently acknowledging that for most pollutants, the
serious question is what degree of safety. To its credit, EPA
invariably offers extensive discussions of the underlying data, demonstrating
that there is a genuine health risk at current levels. But to the extent
that it provides an explanation of its particular choices, the discussion
often involves little more than evidence of nontrivial adverse effects at
those current levels - evidence that may well argue for a reduction
from current levels, but does not by itself call for any particular
regulatory standard.</p>
      <p>In this Article, I have argued that EPA (and other agencies
involved in similar tasks) should offer a detailed "benefits analysis."
The central goal of this approach would be to create a kind of federal
common law of environmental protection, generated in the first
in320. Technology-forcing is not desirable if the costs of the forcing exceed the benefits
if, for example, the new technology contributes little to air quality, but substantially
increases prices and diminishes wages.</p>
      <p>321. In principle, a competent cost-benefit analysis would include the costs (and
benefits) of new technological developments, and indeed this issue is discussed in the particulates
and ozone regulatory impact analysis. See RIA, supra note 70, ch. 11. The problem is that
government is likely to have very little information about the cost of technological
innovation, and industry is likely to overstate those costs by a significant amount. See W. Kip
Viscusi, FATAL TRADEOFFS 161-80 (1993) (discussing substantial overstatement of
compliance costs).</p>
      <p>322. See the valuable article by James E. Krier, On the Topology of NationalStandards
in a FederalSystem -And Why It Matters,54 MD. L. REV. 1226 (1995), a staunch and
longtime defender of cost-benefit analysis for the Clean Air Act, who acknowledges the
pragmatic possibility.
stance by administrative agencies, and designed to promote
consistency and rationality in the protection of health and safety. I have also
defended a form of democracy-promoting minimalism for
administrative law - the particular form of minimalism that is embodied in the
remand, often (and increasingly) unaccompanied by invalidation.</p>
      <p>The Clean Air Act should not be held unconstitutional, and EPA
should not be required, on pain of constitutional invalidation, to come
up with a "generic unit of harm" to encompass population affected,
severity, and probability. The new nondelegation doctrine is a large
mistake. On the other hand, ordinary judicial review should require
any national ambient air quality standard to be accompanied by an
adequate explanation of why that level, rather than one more or less
stringent, has been selected. By itself, this requirement calls (to the
extent feasible) for a high degree of quantification from EPA; it also
bears on the performance of other regulatory agencies entrusted with
the task of protecting health, safety, and the environment. It calls for
invalidation, and not merely remand, where the agency is unable to
offer an explanation of its choice of one level of regulation rather than
another. A requirement of this kind would mark a key moment in the
shift from the rigidity and simplicity of 1970s environmentalism
toward a new and more promising approach - one that places a high
premium on assessing the magnitude of problems, ensuring
consistency across regulations, limiting interest-group power, acquiring
better information, and authorizing democratic control of regulatory
choices.</p>
      <p>My principal claim here is that both courts and EPA should
construe the Act so as to prevent regulation of small risks and so as to
require regulation of substantial risks - and EPA should explain, as
quantitatively as possible, what must be shown in order for a risk to
qualify, or not to qualify, as substantial. It is excessive, a form of
rhetoric, to say that on EPA's view, it is entitled to choose any level
between zero risk and a level slightly below "London's Killer Fog."
But it is not a form of rhetoric to think that if EPA has not limited its
own discretion by speaking in less conclusory terms, the Clean Air Act
raises problems for both regulatory policy and democratic
selfgovernment. The ultimate goal of the forms of the
democracypromoting minimalism that I have endorsed here would be to ensure
better policy analysis and greater transparency of decision, in a way
that should simultaneously promote democratic, economic, and air
quality goals.</p>
      <p>APPENDIX
not to be exceeded more than once per year. 36 Fed. Reg.
8186, 8187 (1971).
b. September 13, 1985: EPA retains the primary standard and
revokes the secondary standard. 50 Fed. Reg. 37,484
(1985).
c. August 1, 1994: EPA announces its decision to retain the
current primary standard for carbon monoxide. There is no
secondary standard for carbon monoxide. 59 Fed. Reg.
38,906,38909-11 (1994).
6. Lead:
a. October 5, 1978: EPA promulgates standards for lead at
the level of 1.5 jig Pb/M3. 43 Fed. Reg. 46,246 (1978).
b. November 5, 1997: EPA publishes final rule for lead, 62
Fed. Reg. 59,813, 59,813-14 (1997), but withdraws it on Dec.
23, 1997, due to adverse comments, 62 Fed. Reg. at 67,009.
c. January 20, 1999: EPA issues final rule. 64 Fed. Reg. 3030,
3030-31 (1999).
(Note: The following tables are taken verbatim from the EPA's</p>
      <p>Regulatory Impact Analysis, as noted in the text.)
323. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-45, tbl.12.6. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
      <p>324. Only endpoints denoted with an * are aggregated into total benefits estimates.
325. Mortality estimates must be aggregated using either short-term exposure or
longterm exposure but not both, due to double-counting issues.</p>
      <sec id="sec-26-1">
        <title>INCIDENCE REDUCIONS32</title>
        <p>Estimates are incremental to the current ozone NAAQS (year = 2010)
Ozone Health:</p>
        <p>*1.Mortality
Hospital Admissions
*2. all respiratory (all ages)
all respiratory (ages 65+)
pneumonia (ages 65+)
COPD (ages 65+)
620
1
60
180
400
70
50
20
10
10
10
290</p>
        <p>Low- to
Highend Est.</p>
        <p>0-80
300 -300
2,330 - 2,330
870 - 870
260 -260
130 - 130
29,840 - 29,840
60 -60
650-650
1-1
0-80
0-250
0 -530
0-90
0 -60
0-20
0 -20
0-20
0-20
0-400</p>
        <p>Max
High-end</p>
        <p>Est.
120
420
1,570
600
200
180
42,070
90
920
2
110
340
690
120
80
30
20
20
20
530
326. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-47, tbl.12.8. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
        <p>327. Only endpoints denoted with an * are aggregated into total benefits estimates.
328. PM mortality estimates must be aggregated using either short-term exposure or
long-term exposure but not both, due to double-counting issues.</p>
        <p>ENDPOINTV327
*7. Lower Respiratory Symptoms
*8. Upper Respiratory Symptoms
shortness of breath
asthma attacks
*9. Work Loss Days
*10. Minor Restricted Activity Days
("MIRADs")
$2.50 per household per jig/m3
*See the Benefits TSD for citations (U.S. EPA, 1997a).
329. RIA, supranote 70, at 12-41, tb.123.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-26-2">
        <title>INCIDENCE REDUCTIONS330</title>
        <p>Annual PM,, (pgm)
Daily PM., (pgm)</p>
        <sec id="sec-26-2-1">
          <title>ENDPOINV 31</title>
          <p>*L Mortaity332: short-term exposure
330. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-46, tbl.12.7. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
          <p>331. Only endpoints denoted with an * are aggregated into total benefits estimates.
332. Mortality estimates must be aggregated using either short-term exposure or
longterm exposure but not both, due to double-counting issues.
TABLE 6: OZONE: NATIONAL ANNUAL MONETIZED HEALTH</p>
          <p>BENEFITS ESTIMATES333
Estimates are incremental to the current ozone NAAQS
(0.12 ppm, 1-hour)
(billions of 1990 $; year = 2010)</p>
          <p>ENDPOINT
$0.370
$0.004
$0.029
$0.014
$0.004
$0.001
$0.001
$0
$0
$0.003
$0.300
$0.870
$0.110
$0.001
$0.001
$0
$0
$0
$0
$0
$0
$0.000 - $0.380
$0.004 - $0.004
$0.029 - $0.029
$0.014 - $0.014
$0.004 - $0.004
$0.001 - $0.001
$0.001 - $0.001
$0 - $0.400
$0- $1.210
$0- $0.140
$0- $0.001
$0 - $0.001
$0- $0
$0 -$0
$0 - $0
$0- $0
$0 - $0
$0-s
$0.570
$0.006</p>
          <p>$0
$0.010
$0.003
$0.002
$0.001
$0
$0
$0.011
$0.520
$1.640
$0.180
$0.001
$0.001
$0
$0
$0
$0
$0
$0
333. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-48, tbl.12.9. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
          <p>334. Only endpoints denoted with an * are aggregated into total benefits estimates.
335. PM mortality estimates must be aggregated using either short-term exposure or
long-term exposure but not both, due to double-counting issues.</p>
          <p>ENDP
*8. Upper Respiratory Symptoms
shortness of breath
asthma attacks
*9. Work Loss Days
*10. Minor Restricted Activity Days
("MRADs")
$0.790
$1.400
$0 - $0
$0 - $0
$0 - $0
$0- $0.004
$0-$0.016
$0.056
$1.785
$0.020
$1.300
$2.400</p>
          <p>Annual PM2 , (pg/m3)
Daily PM. (pg/m)</p>
          <p>Partial Attainment Scenario</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-26-3">
        <title>High-end Est. d</title>
        <p>16
65
$83
$7.5
$90</p>
        <p>Low- to
HigEhs-te.nd
15
65
$15 to $96
$4.3 to $8.1
$19 to $104
igh-end</p>
        <p>Est.
50
$99
$9
$107
336. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-69, tbl.12.17. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.
99TH
PERCENTILE) SUMMARY OF NATIONAL ANNUAL MONETIZED</p>
        <p>HEALTH AND WELFARE BENEFITS337</p>
        <p>Annual PM0 (pgm 3)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-26-4">
        <title>Daily PM10 (pgm)</title>
        <p>337. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-69, tbl.12.18. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
        <p>338. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-70, tbl.12.19. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-26-5">
        <title>INCIDENCE REDUCTIONS339</title>
        <p>Annual PM,. (pgm)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-26-6">
        <title>ENDPONl[r Daily PM[ (pg/m)</title>
        <p>*1. Mortality1: short-term exposure
150
360
340
6,800
339. RIA, supra note 70, at 12-45, tbl.12.6. Numbers may not completely agree due to
rounding.</p>
        <p>340. Only endpoints denoted with an * are aggregated into total benefits estimates.
341. Mortality estimates must be aggregated using either short-term exposure or
longterm exposure but not both, due to double-counting issues.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-27">
      <title>Nondelegation and EPA</title>
      <p>ALTERNATIVES IN 2010 (1990 $)342
(high-end estimate)
Annual
Benefits of Partial</p>
      <sec id="sec-27-1">
        <title>Attainment4 3</title>
        <p>(billion$)
(A)</p>
        <p>Annual Costs</p>
        <p>of
Partial
Attainment
(billion $)
(B)</p>
        <p>Net Benefits</p>
        <p>of
Partial
Attainment
(billion $)
(A - B)</p>
        <p>Number of
Residual
Nonattainment
Counties
19-104
5.5
8.6
10-95
342. RIA, supra note 70, at 13-3, tbl.13.1. All estimates are measured incremental to
partial attainment of the current PM, standard (PM, 501150, 1 expected exceedance per
year). The results for 16165 and 15/50 are only for the high-end assumptions ranges. The
low-end estimates were not calculated for these alternatives.</p>
        <p>343. Partial attainment benefits based upon post-control air quality as defined in the
control cost analysis.
0.7- 1.0
12
17
27
344. RIA, supra note 70, at 13-4, tbl.13.2 All estimates are measured incremental to
partial attainment of the current ozone standard (0.12 ppm, 1 expected exceedance per
year). The results for 0.08, 5th max., and 0.08, 3rd max., are only for the high-end
assumptions. The low-end estimates were not calculated for these alternatives.</p>
        <p>345. Partial attainment benefits based upon post-control air quality as defined in the
control cost analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>ADMINISTRATIVE LAW .............................3.05............</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. BasicProposalsandFirstPrinciples...............</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>0</issue>
          .
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>..........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>B. The ClearAir Act ...........................3.07...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>C. A RemarkableDecision anda New</surname>
            <given-names>Doctrine.........</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>0</issue>
          .
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>..........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>D. GoalsandPlans............................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>1</issue>
          .
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>.......... II. THE CLEAN AIR ACT .................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>1</issue>
          .
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>..............</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. SettingNationalStandards.....................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>1</issue>
          .
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          1.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>The</given-names>
            <surname>Key</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Provisions.......................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>1</issue>
          .
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          2.
          <string-name>
            <surname>ProblemsandPuzzles......................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>31</year>
          .
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Status Quo ................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>32</year>
          .
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>C. The Record...............................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>2</issue>
          .
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
            <surname>Particulatesand</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Ozone at EPA: A Casein Point</article-title>
          ......
          <volume>3</volume>
          .
          <issue>2</issue>
          .
          <fpage>4</fpage>
          ......
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          1. The New Standards: Massive ScientificEvidence....
          <volume>3</volume>
          .
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          ...
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          2.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Insufficient</surname>
            <given-names>Considerationof the Alternatives.......</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>32</year>
          .
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>....... IH.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>THE PATH OF THE LAW .</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>3</issue>
          .
          <fpage>0</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>............</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Two</given-names>
            <surname>Hundredand Two Bad</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Years................3.30...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
            <surname>What</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,If Anything,
          <source>Is the NondelegationDoctrineFor?..3.3.5</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          1.
          <string-name>
            <surname>NondelegationValues ......................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>33</year>
          .
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          2.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Againstthe</surname>
            <given-names>NondelegationDoctrine............</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>3</issue>
          .
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>...........</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          3.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>The</given-names>
            <surname>Centralityof</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Floorsand Ceilings............</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>33</year>
          .
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>........... IV.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>THE NEW NONDELEGATION DOcTRINE ..</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>..............</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>3</year>
          .
          <issue>4</issue>
          .
          <fpage>0</fpage>
          <string-name>
            <surname>............</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          10. See 42 U.S.C. §
          <volume>7409</volume>
          (a) (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          11.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See James E. Krier</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The IrrationalNationalAir Quality Standards: Macro-</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Micro-Mistakes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,22 UCLA L. REV.
          <volume>323</volume>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          ).
          <article-title>For an instructive recent discussion of how the "slippage" between law on the books and law in the world actually allows a degree of flexibility, and converts seemingly rigid standards into a basis for negotiation and pragmatism, see Daniel A. Farber, Taking Slippage Seriously: Noncompliance and Creative Compliancein EnvironmentalLaw, 23 HARv</article-title>
          . ENVTL. L. REv.
          <volume>297</volume>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          12.
          <article-title>See American Trucking Ass'ns v</article-title>
          .
          <source>EPA</source>
          ,
          <volume>175</volume>
          F.3d
          <volume>1027</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1040</fpage>
          -41
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>(per curiam); Lead Indus. Ass'n v</article-title>
          .
          <source>EPA</source>
          ,
          <volume>647</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1130</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1148</fpage>
          -56
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          13.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See MARC K. LANDY</surname>
          </string-name>
          ET AL.,
          <article-title>THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY: ASKING THE WRONG QUESTIONS FROM NIXON</article-title>
          TO CLINTON 49-
          <issue>82</issue>
          ,
          <fpage>282</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(examining EPA's 1979 effort to revise the air quality standards for ozone and the Bush administration's attempt to win the support of the Science Advisory Board)</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          14. See id.;
          <string-name>
            <surname>C. Boyden Gray</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Clean Air Act Under Regulatory Reform</source>
          ,
          <volume>11</volume>
          TUL. ENvrL. L.J.
          <volume>235</volume>
          ,
          <issue>235</issue>
          (
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          15. 42 U.S.C. §
          <volume>7409</volume>
          (
          <article-title>b)(1).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          16.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>LANDY</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ET AL.,
          <year>supranote</year>
          13, at 282-
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>The criticism is not sound as applied to the particulates and ozone regulations, where EPA noted diminishing risk with diminishing exposure levels; but here too, EPA's explanation leaves many open questions</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          21.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>A.L.A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schechter Poultry</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Corp</article-title>
          . v.
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>295</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>495</volume>
          (
          <year>1935</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Panama Refining Co</article-title>
          . v. Ryan, 293 U.S.
          <volume>388</volume>
          (
          <year>1935</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          22. See International Union v.
          <source>OSHA</source>
          ,
          <volume>938</volume>
          F.
          <year>3d</year>
          1310
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          34. American Trucking confirms this reading.
          <source>See 175 F.3d 1027</source>
          ,
          <fpage>1040</fpage>
          -41
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>(per curiam). For the initial holding to this effect, see Lead Indus. Ass'n v</article-title>
          .
          <source>EPA</source>
          ,
          <volume>647</volume>
          F.
          <year>2d</year>
          1130
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          37.
          <string-name>
            <surname>EPA</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>'s Rulemakings on the NationalAmbient Air Quality Standardsfor Particulate Matterand Ozone: HearingsBefore the Subcomm</article-title>
          .
          <source>on Commercial and Admin. Law of the House Comm. on the Judiciary, 105th Cong</source>
          .
          <volume>89</volume>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>(prepared statement of George T</article-title>
          . Woolf, Former Chairman,
          <source>EPA's Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee).</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          38.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See E. Donald</surname>
          </string-name>
          Elliott et al.,
          <article-title>Toward a Theory of Statutory Evolution: The Federalization of EnvironmentalLaw, 1</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.L. ECON.</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <source>ORG</source>
          .
          <volume>313</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>333</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          )
          <article-title>(describing a "Politicians' Dilemma" that forced lawmakers to pass more stringent statutes than they originally wanted).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          39.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g., ida.t
          <volume>336</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          40. See Daniel Kahneman &amp; Amos
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tversky</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Prospect Theory: An Analysis of Decision Under Risk</source>
          ,
          <volume>47</volume>
          ECONOMETRIcA 263 (
          <year>1979</year>
          )
          <article-title>; George Loewenstein et al</article-title>
          .,
          <source>Risk as Feelings</source>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>(unpublished manuscript, on file with author).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          49. See Carbon Monoxide:
          <article-title>Proposed Revisions to the National Ambient Air Quality Standards</article-title>
          and Announcement of Public Meetings,
          <volume>45</volume>
          Fed. Reg.
          <volume>55</volume>
          ,
          <issue>066</issue>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          )
          <article-title>(to be codified at 40 C.F</article-title>
          .R. pt.
          <volume>50</volume>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          50. CleanAir Act:
          <article-title>Ozone and ParticulateMatter Standards: HearingsBefoie the Subcomm</article-title>
          . on CleanAir, Wetlands, PrivateProperty,and
          <article-title>NuclearSafety of the Senate Env't and Pub</article-title>
          .
          <source>Works Comm, 105th Cong</source>
          .
          <volume>282</volume>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>[hereinafter Clean Air Hearings] (statement of Carol M. Browner</article-title>
          , Administrator, EPA).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          53.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <source>Eads, supra note 48</source>
          , at 1228-
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          ; John Dwyer,
          <source>The Practiceof Federalism Under the Clean Air Act</source>
          ,
          <volume>54</volume>
          MD. L. REV.
          <volume>1183</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ); Farber, supra note 11, at 303-04; James Krier,
          <article-title>On the Topology of Uniform EnvironmentalStandardsin a FederalSystem -</article-title>
          And
          <string-name>
            <surname>Why It</surname>
          </string-name>
          Matters,
          <volume>54</volume>
          MD. L. REV.
          <volume>1226</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>; see alsoJames A</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Henderson</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr. &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pearson</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Implementing FederalEnvironmentalPolicies:
          <source>The Limits of Aspirational Commands</source>
          ,
          <volume>78</volume>
          COLJM. L. REV.
          <volume>1429</volume>
          (
          <year>1978</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          54.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>J. CLARENCE DAVIES</given-names>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>JAN MAZUREK, REGULATING POLLUTION: DoEs THE U</article-title>
          .S.
          <source>SYSTEM WoRK? 17 fig.1</source>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          55.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>iL (showing that about nine million people live in areas not meeting national standards for particulates, about eleven million live in areas not meeting national standards for carbon monoxide, and about five million live in areas not meeting standards for lead)</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          56. See Eads,supranote
          <volume>48</volume>
          , at 226; Henderson &amp; Pearson, supra note 53, at
          <volume>1429</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1442</fpage>
          -
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          67. 448 U.S.
          <volume>607</volume>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          68.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>IndustrialUnion</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,448 U.S. at 612.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          69.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>Building</given-names>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Constrs. Trade Dep't v.
          <source>Brock</source>
          ,
          <volume>838</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1258</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>1265 (D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          70.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See U.S. EPA INNOVATIVE</surname>
            <given-names>STRATEGIES</given-names>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>ECONOMICS GROUP, OFFICE OF AIR QUALITY PLANNING &amp; STANDARDS, REGULATORY IMPAcT ANALYSES FOR THE PARTICULATE MATTER</article-title>
          AND
          <string-name>
            <surname>OZONE NATIONAL AMBIENT AIR QUALITY STANDARDS AND PROPOSED REGIONAL HAZE RULE</surname>
          </string-name>
          12-
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>[hereinafter RIA]</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          71.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <article-title>The Science Behind EPA'sProposedRevisions to the NationalAmbient Air Quality Standardsfor Ozone and ParticulateMatter,PartsI-III: HearingsBefore the Subcomm</article-title>
          .
          <source>on Energy and Environment of the House Comm. on Science, 105th Cong</source>
          .
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>("I determined that setting an appropriate air quality standard for a pollutant for which there is no discernible threshold means that factors such as the nature and severity of the health effects involved, and the nature and size of the sensitive populations exposed, are very important."); see also LADY</article-title>
          ET AL.,
          <source>supra note 13</source>
          , at 44-82 (discussing ozone);
          <source>MELNICK, supra note 63</source>
          , at 269-76 (discussing lead).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          72.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Compare</surname>
            <given-names>OSHA</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>which has said that if a risk is 1.64/1,000, regulation will be presumed desirable and the risk will be found significant</article-title>
          .
          <source>See infra note 243.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          73. See Richard Zeckhauser &amp; Donald
          <string-name>
            <surname>Shepard</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Where Now for Saving Lives?, LAW &amp; CONTEMP</article-title>
          . PROBS.,
          <source>Autumn</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          , at 5, 11; see also American Trucking Ass'
          <article-title>ns v</article-title>
          .
          <source>EPA</source>
          ,
          <volume>175</volume>
          F.3d
          <volume>1027</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1039</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          &amp; n.5
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>(per curiam). 1</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          310.
          <article-title>See generally NATIONAL ACADEMY OF PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION, THE ENVIRONMENT GOES TO MARKET (</article-title>
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <source>See also supratext accompanying notes 88-90.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          311. See Gray,
          <source>supra note 14</source>
          , at 235-36.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          312.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cf Regulatory</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Reform: HearingsBefore the Senate Comm</article-title>
          .
          <source>on GovernmentalAffairs,104th Cong</source>
          .
          <volume>194</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>(statement of Jonathan B</article-title>
          . Wiener)
          <article-title>(urging general amendment to allow agencies to choose incentive-based regulation)</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref49">
        <mixed-citation>
          313.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          generally Robert W. Hahn &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gordon L. Hester</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Marketable Permits:
          <source>Lessons for Theory and Practice</source>
          ,16 ECOLOGY L.Q.
          <volume>361</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <mixed-citation>
          314.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>After</given-names>
            <surname>Chevron</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>U.S.A.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Inc. v. National Resources Defense Council, Inc., 467 U.S.
          <volume>837</volume>
          (
          <year>1984</year>
          ),
          <article-title>ambiguities in the statute are to be resolved by the agency, and there is a good argument that the key provision of the Act is ambiguous. Recall that the statute requires standards to be set at a level "requisite to protect the public health," and it is not unreasonable to say that that level is at least partly a function of the costs of the regulation</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>What level is "requisite" may well depend on the costs as well as benefits of getting there. Ironically, however, the view that the agency can choose, or fail to choose, cost-benefit analysis seems to aggravate rather than to diminish the old nondelegation doctrine, even though an agency choice of that kind would seem to satisfy the new nondelegation doctrine. See Industrial Union v</article-title>
          .
          <source>OSHA</source>
          ,
          <volume>37</volume>
          F.3d
          <volume>665</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>669</fpage>
          -70
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(concluding that the nondelegation problem would be eliminated if OSHA chose cost-benefit analysis).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <mixed-citation>315. See supranotes 34-35 and accompanying text</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <mixed-citation>
          1.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Particulate</given-names>
            <surname>Matter</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <mixed-citation>PM2.5:</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>a. July</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <year>1997</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA sets a public health standard for fine</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>particle pollution. 62 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>38</volume>
          ,
          <issue>652</issue>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>TotalSuspended Particulatesand PM10:</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <mixed-citation>
          a.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>28</volume>
          ,
          <year>1971</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates the primary and secon-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref58">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>dary standards for particulate matter</article-title>
          . Primary:
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>micro</fpage>
          -
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref59">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>grams per cubic meter - annual geometric mean; 260</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref60">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>pg/m3</source>
          , 24
          <article-title>-hour average not to be exceeded more than once</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref61">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>per year</article-title>
          .
          <source>Secondary: 150pg/m3 maximum 24-hour concen-</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref62">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>tration not to be exceeded more than once per year; 60</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref63">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>pg/m3 annual geometric mean. 36 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>8186</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>8187</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref64">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>b. July 1</source>
          ,
          <year>1987</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA changes the indicator for PM from total</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref65">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>suspended particles to PM10. 24-hour PM 0 of 150 ptg/n 3</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref66">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>nual PM0 standard of 50 pg/m3 expected annual arithmetic</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref67">
        <mixed-citation>
          52 Fed. Reg.
          <volume>24</volume>
          ,
          <issue>634</issue>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref68">
        <mixed-citation>
          c.
          <source>July</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <year>1997</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates regulation which is later</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref69">
        <mixed-citation>
          added,
          <source>set at 15 pg/in and 65 pg/na3. 62 Fed. Reg. at 38</source>
          ,
          <fpage>652</fpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref70">
        <mixed-citation>2. Ozone:</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref71">
        <mixed-citation>
          a.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          ,
          <year>1971</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates first NAAQS for photo-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref72">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>chemical oxidants. 160 pg/m; 0</source>
          .08 ppm maximum 1-hour
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref73">
        <mixed-citation>36 Fed. Reg. at 8187.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref74">
        <mixed-citation>
          b.
          <source>April 20</source>
          ,
          <year>1977</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA reviews and updates criteria docu-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref75">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ment. 42 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>20</volume>
          ,
          <issue>493</issue>
          (
          <year>1977</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref76">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>c. February 8</source>
          ,
          <year>1979</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA revises primary standard to 0.12</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref77">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>ppm and sets secondary standard identical to primary</article-title>
          . 44
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref78">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fed</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Reg.
          <volume>8202</volume>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref79">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>d. March 9</source>
          ,
          <year>1993</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA reviews air quality standards</article-title>
          and de-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref80">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>cides not to revise standards</article-title>
          .
          <source>58 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>13</volume>
          ,
          <issue>008</issue>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref81">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>e. February 3</source>
          ,
          <year>1994</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA announces it will review standards</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref82">
        <mixed-citation>
          59 Fed. Reg.
          <volume>5164</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref83">
        <mixed-citation>
          f.
          <source>July</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <year>1997</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates new standards which are</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref84">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>later struck down by the D.C. Circuit Court</article-title>
          . Primary:
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          -
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref85">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>hour standard at a level of 0.08 ppm</article-title>
          . Secondary: identical
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref86">
        <mixed-citation>
          0.08 ppm standard.
          <source>62 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>38</volume>
          ,
          <issue>856</issue>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
          <article-title>(A more complete history of ozone is presented in Section ll.B of the U.S. EPA OFFICE OF AIR QUALITY PLANNING AND STANDARDS, REVIEW OF NATIONAL AMBIENT AIR QUALITY STANDARDS FOR OZONE: ASSESSMENT OF SCIENTIFIC</article-title>
          AND
          <string-name>
            <surname>TECHNICAL INFORMATION</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).)
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref87">
        <mixed-citation>
          3.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Sulfur</given-names>
            <surname>Oxides</surname>
          </string-name>
          (Sulfur Dioxides):
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref88">
        <mixed-citation>
          a.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          ,
          <year>1971</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates primary</article-title>
          and secondary
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref89">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>NAAQS for sulfur oxides</article-title>
          .
          <source>Primary: 80 pg/m3, 0.03 ppm an-</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref90">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>nual arithmetic mean; 365 pg/m3; 0</source>
          .14 ppm maximum 24-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref91">
        <mixed-citation>
          year.
          <source>Secondary: 1300 pg/i 3; 0</source>
          .
          <article-title>5 ppm maximum 3-hour</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref92">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>60 pg/n 3; 0.02 ppm annual arithmetic mean; 260 pag/n; 0</source>
          .
          <fpage>1</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref93">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>ppm maximum 24-hour concentration not to be exceeded</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref94">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>more than once per year. 36 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>8186</volume>
          ,
          <issue>8187</issue>
          (
          <year>1971</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref95">
        <mixed-citation>
          b.
          <source>April 26</source>
          ,
          <year>1988</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA decides not to revise the existing pri-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref96">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>mary and secondary standards. 53 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>14</volume>
          ,
          <issue>926</issue>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref97">
        <mixed-citation>
          c.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          ,
          <year>1993</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA decides not to revise the existing sec-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref98">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ondary standards. 58 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>21</volume>
          ,
          <issue>351</issue>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref99">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>d. November 15</source>
          ,
          <year>1994</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA publishes a second proposal re-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref100">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>garding revision of primary standards for sulfur oxides</article-title>
          .
          <source>59</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref101">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Fed</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Reg.
          <volume>58</volume>
          ,
          <issue>958</issue>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref102">
        <mixed-citation>
          e. May 22,
          <year>1996</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA reviews and revises the air quality cri-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref103">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>several minor technical changes. 61 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>25</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>566</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref104">
        <mixed-citation>4. Nitrogen Oxides:</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref105">
        <mixed-citation>
          a.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          ,
          <year>1971</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA issues identical primary and secondary</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref106">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>standards for NO2 set at 0.05 ppm (100 pg/n 3) annual</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref107">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>arithmetic average. 36 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>8186</volume>
          ,
          <issue>8187</issue>
          (
          <year>1971</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref108">
        <mixed-citation>
          b.
          <source>December 12</source>
          ,
          <year>1978</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA announces the first review and</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref109">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>update. 43 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>58</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1117</issue>
          (
          <year>1978</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref110">
        <mixed-citation>
          c. June 19,
          <year>1985</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA decides to retain the same standard</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref111">
        <mixed-citation>
          50 Fed. Reg.
          <volume>25</volume>
          ,
          <issue>532</issue>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref112">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>d. April 26</source>
          ,
          <year>1988</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA publishes a second proposal regarding</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref113">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>revision of primary standards. 53 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>14</volume>
          ,
          <issue>926</issue>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref114">
        <mixed-citation>
          e.
          <source>October</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          ,
          <year>1995</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA proposes to retain national stan-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref115">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>dards for nitrogen dioxide</article-title>
          .
          <source>60 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>52</volume>
          ,
          <issue>874</issue>
          ,
          <issue>52</issue>
          ,
          <fpage>875</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref116">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>f. October 8</source>
          ,
          <year>1996</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA issues its final decision retaining</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref117">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>standard for nitrogen dioxide</article-title>
          .
          <source>61 Fed. Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>52</volume>
          ,
          <issue>852</issue>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref118">
        <mixed-citation>5. Carbon Monoxide:</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref119">
        <mixed-citation>
          a.
          <source>April</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          ,
          <year>1971</year>
          :
          <article-title>EPA promulgates the initial standard for</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref120">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>carbon monoxide at the level of 10 pg/n 3, 9 ppm maximum</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref121">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>8-hour concentration not to be exceeded more than once</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref122">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>per year; 40 pg/ 3, 35 ppm maximum 1-hour concentration 1.6 2.9 0.9 1.1 1.4 0.7 1</source>
          .
          <fpage>5</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

