<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Law's Expressive Function
Author(s): Cass R. Sunstein
Source: The Good Society, Vol.</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <contrib-group>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Penn State University Press is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to The Good Society</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1999</issue>
      <fpage>55</fpage>
      <lpage>61</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at http://www.jstor.org/page/ info/about/policies/terms.jsp JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org. http://www.jstor.org</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>This content downloaded from 131.172.36.29 on Mon, 21 Dec 2015 06:23:01 UTC</p>
      <p>All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Forum</title>
      <p>on Law
and the Good</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Society</title>
      <p>What ought tobe thecharacter of law ingood societies, and what role ought it toplay? There are several reasons why good society thinkers
mightwant to take thesequestions seriously.The rule of law ingeneral constitutesa powerful check on tyranny?be it the tyrannyof leaders
(elected or otherwise) or ofdemocraticmajorities. Constitutionalism,more specifically,plays a crucial role inany liberal regime in thatitnot
only empowers government but also limits itand protects the rightsof citizens. But it is not only liberals who should take law seriously.
Constitutional law,especially, is thecornerstone in thefoundation of thepolity, creatinga common set ofpolitical normsand values and thus
thebeginningsof a commonpolitical identityF.inally, democratsmightwant toconsider therole of lawfrom an Aristotelian perspective: Law
not only habituates us to certain typesof action (virtuous ones, in thegood regime) but, rightlyconceived and implemented,law can also
encourage us tocriticallyengage itand thusrefinethecircumstancesof our own habituation.Law in liberaldemocratic polities, then,always
entails a tension:Itmakes certain typesof libertypossible by constrainingothers.
?A.K.</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>Law's Function1</title>
        <p>Expressive</p>
        <p>Cass R. Sunstein
If I had known that not a single lunch counter would open as a result
ofmy action I could nothave done differentlythanI did. If I had
known violence would result, I could not have done differently than I
did. I am thankful for the sit-ins if for no other reason than that they
provided me with an opportunity formaking a slogan into reality, by
turning a decision into an action. It seems tome that this iswhat life
is all about.</p>
        <p>?James Miller. Democracy is in the Streets: From Port Huron to
theSiege ofChicago. (NewYork,SimonandSchuster,1987)p. 52.
We are all Expressionists part of the time. Sometimes we just want to
scream loudly at injustice, or to stand up and be counted. These are
noble motives, but any serious revolutionist must often deprive him
self of the pleasures of self-expression. He must judge his actions by
their ultimate effects on institutions.</p>
        <p>?Herbert SimonM.odels ofMy Life. (NewYork:</p>
        <p>Basic Books, 1991), p. 281.</p>
        <p>Actions are expressive; they carrymeanings. This is true for
nearly everythingwe do, fromthemost mundane to themost signif
icant.Thus, forexample, a lawyerwho wears a loud tie tocourtwill
be signaling somethingdistinctiveabout his self-conceptionand his
attitude toward others; so toowith a law professorwho teaches in
blue jeans; so toowith a studentwho comes to class in a business
suitW.hat can be said fornonverbal acts applies to purely verbal
statementsas well. A bank presidentwho uses the terms"Miss" and
"Mrs.," or who refers toAfrican-Americans
as "Negroes,"
will be
showingawide rangeof thingsabout his attitudesonmatters of gen
der and race. So toowith a politician, say in theSouth,who uses the
terms "Ms." and "African-Americans."</p>
        <p>In these and other cases, what the agentwill be communicating,
or be taken tomean, may ormay not have a greatdeal todo with his
particular intentions.In this sense, themeanings of actions are not
fullywithin thecontrolof agents. Indeed, some agentsmay not even
be aware of therelevantmeanings. Consider a foreignerw,hose for
eign state is often signaled by obliviousness to the social meanings
of his actions.What he says is verydifferentfromwhat hemeans.</p>
        <p>What can be said foractions can also be said for law.Many peo
ple supportlaw because of thestatemenmtade by law, and disagree
ments about law are frequentlydebates over theexpressive content
of law. For example, much of thedebate over school segregation
was also a debate about themeaning of laws calling for segregation.
Plessy v.Ferguson1 asserted that such laws did not "mean" black
inferiorityB;rown v.Board ofEducation1 tried to respond to this
assertionwith some empiricalwork suggesting thecontraryO.r con
sider debates over capital punishment.Many people who oppose
capital punishmentwould be unlikely to shiftposition even ifevi
dence showed thatcapital punishmentdoes have a deterrenteffect;
theircomplaint ismostly about theexpressive contentof acts of cap
italpunishment,not about the ineffectivenessof deterrence. So too
formany people who endorse capital punishment. Such people
would not be?are not?much moved by evidence thatcapital pun
ishmentdoes not deter.Their primary concern is the symbolic or
expressive contentof the law,not aggregatemurder rates.</p>
        <p>Much of thecontemporarydebate over hate speech regulation is
similar. It is above all about the social meaning of such regulations.
Do such regulations "mean" thatobjects of hate speech require spe
cial paternalisticprotections, areweak, thin-skinned,and unable to
take care of themselves?Or do they"mean" thatbigotry is utterly
unacceptable in a liberal society? Debates of thiskind could not
plausibly be focused on consequences, for
the stakes are relatively low, not justifying
the amount of time and energy devoted to
them. In thisway debates over flagburning
and debates over hate speech have a great
deal in common; they are expressive in
character.</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-1">
          <title>Or consider thesubject of riskregulation.</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-2">
          <title>In environmental protection, public debate</title>
          <p>is often focused on the perceived social
meaning of law. Thus the Endangered
Species Act has a special salience, as a sym
bol of a certain conception of the relation
ship between human beings and theirenvi
ronment,and emissions tradingsystemsare
frequentlychallenged because theyare said
to "make a statement" thatreflectsan inap
propriate valuation of the environment. In
the same way, mandatory recycling (as
opposed to curbside charges, which seem
far better from the economic standpoint)
may well receive public supporton expres
sive grounds.Outside of theenvironmental
context, the samemay be trueofmandatory
pro bono work (as opposed to a compulsory
donation from lawyers who refuse to do
suchwork).
^^^^^^J</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-3">
          <title>I.Definitional Note</title>
          <p>At theoutset it is importantto say thatwe might understand the
expressive function of law in two differentways. First, and most
straightforwardlyt,he law's "statement"may be designed to affect
social norms and in thatway ultimatelytoaffectboth judgmentsand
behavior.On thisview, an expressive approach to law isnot indepen
dentof an assessment of social consequences; certainexpressions are
favoredbecause theywill (ultimately)have good consequences. Here
there is a prediction about the facts:An appropriately framed law
may influence social norms and push
Much of the contemporary
debate over hate speech</p>
          <p>... isabove all
regulation
about the socialmeaning
of such regulations.Do
such regulations "mean'
thatobjectsofhate speech</p>
          <p>require special
paternalistic protections,
are weak, thin-skinned,
and unable to take care
of
themselves?Or do they
"mean that bigotry is</p>
          <p>in a
utterlyunacceptable
liberal society?
them in the rightdirection.For example,
if the lawmandates recycling,perhaps it
will affect social norms about the envi
ronmentinaway thatisdifferentfromthe
effectson norms of curbside charges.Or
if the lawwrongly treatssomething?let
a
us suppose reproductivecapacities?as
commodity,social normsmay be affected
in a troublesome</p>
          <p>way.</p>
          <p>Sometimes thisclaim isplausible; pre
vailing norms, like preferences and
beliefs, are not a presocial given, but a
product of a complex setof social forces,
possibly including law. And law moti
vated by norm-change will be my focus
here.But sometimespeople supporta law
not because of itseffectson norms, but
because it is believed intrinsicallyvalu
able for the relevant "statement" to be
made. (See theopening epigraph froma
1960s protester.A)nd sometimes lawwill
have littleor no effecton social norms.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-4">
          <title>Society is filled with legal provisions</title>
          <p>allowing market exchanges of goods and
services?like
pets and babysitting, for
are not seen as mere com</p>
          <p>In this essay I explore the expressive
function of law?the function of law in "making statements" as
opposed to thefunctionof law indirectlycontrollingbehavior. I do
so by focusing on theparticular issue of how legal "statements"
might be designed to change social norms. I catalogue a range of
possible (and inmy view legitimate)effortsto alternorms through
legal expressions about appropriateevaluative attitudes. I also urge
thattheexpressive functionof lawmakes most sense inconnection
with effortsto change norms, and that if legal statementsproduce
bad consequences, theyshould notbe enacted even iftheyseem rea
sonable or indeednoble. Empirical questions loom throughouta,nd I
do offerseveral empirical claims; butmy goal ismostly normative
ratherthandescriptive or positive.
56
thereforeremainswhether the claimed effecton social normswill
occur. It is fullyplausible, forexample, to say that,although a law
thatpermitsprostitutionreflectsan inappropriatevaluation of sexu
ality,any adverse effectof the law on social norms is so small as to
be an implausible basis forobjection.</p>
          <p>A societymight identifythenorms towhich it is committedand
insiston thosenorms via law, even iftheconsequences of the insis
tence are obscure or unknown.A societymight, forexample, insist
on an anti-discriminationlaw forexpressive reasons even if itdoes
not know whether the law actually helps members of minority
groups. A society might endorse or reject capital punishment
because itwants to express a certainunderstandingof theappropri
ate course of action afterone person has taken the lifeof another.
^H^
LAW AND THE
^^^^^^B
The point bears on thecultural role of law,adjudication, and even of
Supreme Court decisions. The empirical effectsof those decisions
are highly disputed. If theSupreme Court says thatsegregation is
unlawful, thatcertain restrictionson hate speech violate theFirst
Amendment, or thatstudentscannot be asked topray in school, the
real-world consequences may be much smaller than is convention
ally thought.But theclose attentionAmerican society pays to the
Court's pronouncements is connectedwith theirexpressive or sym
The most conventional example involves legalmandates thattake
theplace of good norms, by requiring certain forms of behavior
throughstatutoryrequirementsaccompanied by significantenforce
ment activity.In thearea of controlof industrialpollution, this is the
usual strategy,as environmental law accompanies legalmandates
with a large commitmentof enforcementresources.</p>
          <p>But there is a subtlerandmore interestingclass of cases, of spe
cial importance for understanding the expressive functionof law.
These cases arise when the relevant law is a signal or statement
bolic character.</p>
          <p>I do not claim thattheexpressive effects
of law, thus understood, are decisive or
thattheycannot be counteredby a demon
strationofmore conventional bad conse
quences. In fact, I believe otherwise and in
thatway endorse Simon's remark in the
epigraph to this essay. But it cannot be
doubted that the expressive function is a
largepart of legal debate.Without under
standing the expressive function of law,
we will have a hard time ingettingan ade
quate handle on public views with respect
to, for example, civil rights,prostitution,
theenvironment,endangered species, cap
italpunishment,and abortion.</p>
          <p>IL The Expressive Function and Collective Action</p>
          <p>Problems</p>
          <p>Many social norms solve collective action problems. Some of
these problems involve coordination; others involve prisoner's
dilemmas. Norms solve such problems by imposing social sanctions
on defectors.When defection violates norms, defectorswill proba
bly feel shame, an importantmotivational force.The community
may enforce its norms through informal punishment, themost
extremeofwhich is ostracism. But themost effectiveuse of norms
is ex ante.The expectation of shame?a kind of social "tax," some
timesa very high one?is usually enough toproduce compliance.</p>
          <p>But sometimesprivateeffortsfailW.hen thisis so, thelawmight be
enlisted as a corrective. In fact, the least controversial use of the
expressive functionof law operates in thisway. Here thegoal is to
reconstructexistingnorms and tochange thesocialmeaning of action
througha legal expression, or statement,about appropriatebehavior.
Insofaras regulatory law is concerned with collective action prob
lems, this is a standard idea, especially in theenvironmentalcontext,
but also in the settingof automobile safety,occupational safetyand
health, andmany otherproblems as well. What isperhaps less stan
dard is to see the law's role as correctingfor inadequate social norms.
Law might eitherdo thework of suchnormsor insteadbe designed to
work directlyagainst existingnorms and topush them innew direc
tions.The latteridea isgroundedon theview thatlawwill havemoral
weight and thusconvince people thatexistingnorms are bad.
... sometimes</p>
          <p>people
support a law not because
of its effectson norms, but</p>
          <p>because it is believed
intrinsicallyvaluablefor
the relevant "statement"
to bemade.</p>
          <p>unaccompanied by much in the way of
enforcementactivity.There is a large setof
instances inwhich laws that (a) aspire to
announce or signal a change in social
norms are nonetheless (b) accompanied by
littleenforcement activity. Consider, for
example, laws thatforbid litteringand laws
thatrequire people to clean up after their
dogs. In many localities such laws are
rarely enforced through the criminal law.</p>
          <p>But theyhave an importanteffect insignal
ingappropriatebehavior and in inculcating
theexpectation of social opprobrium and
hence shame in thosewho deviate fromthe
norm.With orwithout enforcementactiv
ity,such laws can help reconstructnorms and the social meaning of
action. Hence someone who fails to clean up afterhis dog may be
showing disrespect or even contempt forothers;many,most, or all
people may see thingsthisway; and theresultcan be largechanges
inbehavior. Eventually therecan be norm cascades, as reputational
incentivesshiftbehavior innew directions. It should be unsurprising
to find that inmany places, people clean up after theirdogs even
though this is not especially pleasant and even though the laws are
rarely enforced.</p>
          <p>When legally-induced shiftsinnormshelp solve collective action
problems, thereshould be no objection inprinciple. Here, then, is
the least controversialcase for theexpressive functionof law.</p>
          <p>III. Norms InvolvingDangerous Behavior</p>
          <p>Often theexpressive functionof law isbrought tobear on danger
ous behavior, including behavior that is dangerous only or princi
pally to self.Of course all behavior creates risks?driving a car,
walking on city streets,volunteeringformilitary serviceW.hen gov
ernment is trying to change norms that "subsidize" risk-taking
behavior, itmust do so because of a judgment thatwell-being will
therebybe promoted. This judgmentmight be rooted in an under
standing thatthe intrinsicvalue or utilityof theact is relatively low
and thatreputational incentivesare thereal source of thebehavior.
We are dealing, then,with classes of cases inwhich the danger
accompanying choicemeans thatintrinsicvalue isnot high but risk
takingbehavior persists because of social norms.
^^^^^^^^H^e^re^ ^as^e^ls^ew^h^e^re^, ^p^ri^va^te^e^f^fo^rt^sm^a^y^b^e^u^n^su^cc^e^ss^ful. In this
light,lawmight attempttoexpress a judgment about theunderlying
activityand do so in such a way as to alter social norms. Ifwe see
norms as a tax or a subsidy to choice, the lawmight attempt to
change a subsidy intoa tax,or vice-versa. In fact, this is a central, if
implicit,goal behind much risk regulation.Educational campaigns
often have thegoal of changing the social meaning of risk-taking
activity.Going beyond provision of information,coercionmight be
defended as a way of increasingsocial sanctionson certainbehavior.
Through time,place, andmanner restrictionsor flatbans, forexam
norm or goal. The prohibitionon vote-tradingis an example. So too
with certaincomplex social bans on theuse ofwealth tobuy services
or goods fromotherpeople. Some part of the intricatweeb of norms
covering theexchange ofmoney among both friendsand strangersare
connected with theprinciple of civic equality.Monetary exchange
would reflectformsof inequality thatare not legitimate in certain
spheres.Familiar objections to"commodification" are part and parcel
of social norms banning theuse ofmoney. The claim is thatpeople
ought not to trade (forexample) sexualityor reproductivecapacities
onmarkets because market exchange of these"things" is inconsistent
pie, the lawmight attempt tomake itseem
weak to smoke, or to use drugs, or to
engage inunsafe sex.</p>
          <p>Are such efforts illiberal or unaccept
ably paternalistic? They should not be so
regarded.Choices are a functionof norms
forwhich individualagents are not respon
sible and which, on reflection,many or
most agentsmay not endorse. This is con
spicuously so in the context of risk-taking
activity involvingcigarettes,drugs, unsafe
sex, and firearms.Much discussion of
whether law should respect "preferences"
or "choices" is confused by virtue of its
silence on the matter of social norms.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-5">
          <title>People may follow such norms despite the</title>
          <p>fact thattheydeplore them.</p>
          <p>Because information is the least intru
sive regulatory strategy, it should be the
Are sucheffortislliberal
or</p>
          <p>unacceptably
paternalisticiThey should
not be so regarded.Choices
are</p>
          <p>afunction ofnormsfor
which individual agents
are not and</p>
          <p>responsible
which, on reflectionm,any
ormost agents may not
endorse.
preferredoption.Whether more aggressive strategiesmake sense
depends on thedetails.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>IV.Norms Involving theUse ofMoney</title>
        <p>A complex network of social norms governs theacceptable uses
ofmoney. This is so in two differentrespects. First: Some social
norms impose sanctions on usingmoney as a reason foraction.Here
people are not supposed to engage incertain acts if theirreason for
doing so is financial gain. Second: Some social normsmake differ
entkinds ofmoney nonfungible; theprevailing norms requirediffer
ent kinds ofmoney tobe used fordifferentpurposes. These sets of
norms raisemany complexities. They are also entangled with the
expressive functionof law.They suggest, finally, that it is some
times inappropriate to infergeneral valuations from particular
choices, since those choices are a functionof norms thatare limited
to thecontext inwhich theygovern.</p>
        <p>There isoften a connection between norms thatblock exchanges
and ideas about equal citizenship. The exchange can be barred by
social normsbecause of a perception thatwhile theremay be dispari
ties in social wealth, the spheres inwhich people are very unequal
oughtnot to invade realms of social life inwhich equality is a social
58
proscriptions are thinking in expressive terms.One of theirgoals
may be to fortifyexisting social norms that insulate reproduction
from the sphere of exchange. Or theirargumentmay be less instru
mental: They may seek tomake a "statement" about reproduction
without also seeking to affectsocial norms.</p>
        <p>Often decisions aboutmoney can be made throughprivatemech
anisms thatdo not require special legal help. These mechanisms
may be as simple as amental notation.They may bemore complex,
takingtheformof differentbank accounts understood tobe used for
differentpurposes. Social norms in families and small communities
oftenfortifytheseeffortsw,ith certain formsofmoney being seen as
"for a rainyday" or as basically untouchable.</p>
        <p>Law can also play a role. Some measures thatmight be seen as
puzzling, or as objectionable paternalism,make more sense if they
are understood as precommitment strategies reflecting diverse
"kinds" ofmoney or as effortsto facilitatepeople's effortstoplace
theirmoney indifferentcategories. As a facilitative strategy,con
sider the IndividualRetirementAccount (IRA). IRAs, created by a
complex set of legal provisions, allow people more easily to sepa
rate theirmoney intodifferent"kinds." The Social Security system
labor; inmany places, women who refuse
to do so incur social sanctions and may
even feel ashamed. The social meaning of
a woman's refusalmay be a rejection of
her appropriate role.Hence itmay signal a
range of undesirable traits.In theareas of
both race and gender, prevailing norms
help constitute inequality. And here as
elsewhere, collective action is necessary
to reconstituteexisting norms.</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-1">
          <title>Of course private norm entrepreneurs</title>
          <p>may be able to accomplish a great deal.</p>
          <p>With respect to thedivision of domestic
labor between men and women, private
effortsat normmanagement have played
an importantrole. Individual acts thatare
expressive incharacter?a refusal tomake
dinner, for example?are an important part
ofmodern feminism. But the expressive
functionof law is often especially impor
tanthere, and itcan move to the fore in
public debates. If a discriminatory act is
consistent with prevailing norms, there
On one view, any effortat</p>
          <p>is
norm
management</p>
          <p>thisisa
illegitimate;
projectthatisofflimitsto
government. But it ishard
to see how thisargument</p>
          <p>be made
might persuasive.</p>
          <p>on social norms are
Effects
not easily avoided; any
systemofgovernment is</p>
          <p>likely to effectnorms,
including creation of the
basic systemsof contract,
tort,and private property.
will be more in theway of discriminatory
behavior. Ifdiscriminatorsare ashamed of themselves, thereis likely
to be less discrimination. The social meaning of an act of sexual
harassmentwill have a great deal to do with theamount of sexual
harassment.A large point of lawmay be to shiftsocial norms and
socialmeaning. Consider in thisconnection thefact thatmany restau
rantowners and inn-keepersactually supported theCivil RightsAct
of 1964,which would have prevented them fromdiscriminating.
How could people want thestate toact against them?The answer lies
in thefact thatthe lawhelped shiftsocial norms and thesocialmean
ing of nondiscrimination.Whereas nondiscrimination would for
merly signal a willingness toact on a race-neutralbasis?and hence
would</p>
          <p>trigger social norms that call for discrimination against
blacks?it would henceforthsignal a willingness toobey the law,and
hence fail to triggeradverse social norms.</p>
          <p>In Part IV, I dealt with cases inwhich social norms discourage
cash payments. But social norms help constitute a wide range of
qualitatively differentkinds of valuation, and these diverse kinds
much affect behavior and the social meaning of behavior. These
norms are omnipresent and are usually takenforgranted. Imagine,
ismandatory, not optional, but itbecomes more intelligible ifwe
understand thatpeople often like tohave help inputting theirmoney
intodifferentaccounts with differentuses.</p>
          <p>V. Equality, Social Norms, and Social Change</p>
          <p>Norms of partiality are an importantpart of social inequality.
Social normsmay requirewomen to engage inmost of domestic
forexample, thatJohn treatsa beautiful diamond in the same way
thatmost people treatfriends,or thatJanevalues a plant in thesame
way thatmost people value theirchildren,or thatSandy values her
car likemost people value artor literatureA. ntidiscrimination law is
often designed to change norms so as to ensure thatpeople are
treatedwith a kind of dignityand respect thatdiscriminatorybehav
ior seems todeny.</p>
          <p>The point is not limited to race and sex
equality. Consider, as an especially inter
esting example, themovement for animal
rights. Some people think that animals
should be treatedwith dignityand respect,
and not as if theyexisted solely forhuman
consumption and use. This view is very
much about social norms; itneed not entail
the furtherclaim that animal life is infi
nitely valuable. It is best takenas a recom
mendation of a shift in norms governing
the treatmentof animals, accompanied by a
judgment thatthenewmode will have con
sequences forwhat human beings do. The
recommendationmay be based on theview
that ifwe see animals (and nature) in this
way, we will solve collective action prob
lems faced by human beings inpreserving
animal life importantfor human lives; it
may be based on a noninstrumentaleffort
to extend ideals of basic dignity to all liv
ing things.</p>
          <p>VI. Constraints, Liberal and</p>
          <p>Otherwise</p>
          <p>What barriers should therebe to theexpressive functionof law?
The simplest answer is:The same barriersas thereare to any other
kind of governmental action. There is nothing distinctive to norm
management thatrequires a special setof constraints.</p>
          <p>Thus, forexample, government should not be permittedto invade
rightsw,hatevermay be our understandingof rightsT.he rightscon
straints thatapply to government action generally are applicable
here as well. If government tried to change social norms so as to
ensure thateveryone is a Christian, itwould violate therightto reli
gious liberty; ifgovernment tried to change social norms so as to
ensure thatwomen occupy domestic roles, andmen do not, itwould
violate theequal protectionclause.</p>
          <p>Quite apart from thequestion of rights,there is always a risk that
effortsat normmanagement will be futileor counterproductiveW.e
can imagine, forexample, thatwhen governmentattempts tomove
social norms in a particular direction, itmay failmiserably. Nancy
Reagan's "JustSay No" policy with respect todrugsmay well be an
example. It is necessary to ensure that thosewho engage innorm</p>
          <p>Moreover, intentional norm management
is a conventional and time-honoredpart of
government.Of course we could imagine
abuses, even unspeakable ones. But the
proper response is to insiston awide range
of rights-basedconstraintson themanage
ment of social norms throughlaw.</p>
          <p>There is a final point.The social mean
ing of lawwill constrain thepermissible
contentof law.The meaning, setas it isby</p>
          <p>make
social norms, may government
effortsunsuccessful. Debates over criminal sanctions are strongly
affectedby thisproblem. So-called intermediatesanctions forcrimi
nal violations are oftenunpopular because theyare taken to "mean"
somethingother thanpublic opprobriumW.hen a violator is told to
engage incommunity service, he appears have "gottenoff,"even if
the service is, to him,worse thana shortperiod in jail. Hence the
social meaning of the lawmakes the law unacceptable to thecom
munity at large. If intermediate sanctions are to be feasible, the
norms thataccompany themmust shiftas well.</p>
          <p>The point is a general one. The meaning of legal statements is a
functionof social norms, not of speaker's intentions.The govern
ment may take a range of steps todiscourage teenagersfrom smok
ing,but ifthose stepsmake smoking seem likea delicious forbidden
fruit,theymay be counterproductiveM.easures designed todiscour
age unwed parenthoodmay actually encourage unwed parenthood.
This is simply a special case of thegeneral phenomenon of unin
tended consequences. Of course, unintended effects?realized
because of existing norms, or in theformof unanticipated changes
inexistingnorms?may be good as well as bad.</p>
          <p>Conclusion</p>
          <p>There can be no doubt that law, like action in general, has an
expressive function.Some people do what theydomostly because of
the statement the actmakes; the same is true for thosewho seek
changes in law.Many debates over theappropriate content of law
are reallydebates over thestatementthatlawmakes, independentof
its (direct) consequences. I have suggested thattheexpressive func
tionof law has a great deal todo with theeffectsof law on prevail
60
management are trustedby thepeople whose norms are at issue.For
this reason itmay be best forgovernment to attemptto enlist inter
mediate organizations, so as to ensure thatpeople with authorityin
relevantcommunities are participating in theprocess.</p>
          <p>Some people would go furtherthan this.On one view, any effort
at normmanagement is illegitimate;this is a project thatisoff limits
to government. But it is hard to see how this argumentmight be
made persuasive. Effects on social norms are not easily avoided; any
ing social norms. Often law's "statement" is designed tomove
norms in freshdirections.</p>
          <p>Least controversially, lawmay attempt to generate norms that
will solve collective action problems. The central point here is that
from the standpoint of individual agents, norms are given rather
than chosen, and agents would sometimes like norms tobe other
thanwhat theyare.Often shifts innorms are a low-costmethod of
achieving widely or universally held social goals?as
value of choice stays constant while the
the intrinsic</p>
          <p>debates over the
Many
appropriate contentof lavo
are debates over the</p>
          <p>really
statement that law makes,
independenotfits(direct)
consequences.</p>
          <p>reputationalconsequences of choice begin
to shift.Far more controversial is theuse
of law to fortifysocial norms involving
the permissible use of money. A liberal
society ensures a measure of sphere dif
ferentiation,inwhich therealm ofmarkets
and market thinking is not coextensive
with therealms of politics and family life.</p>
          <p>Hence social norms regulating theuse of
money are an importantpart of a well
functioning liberal society. Sometimes
law is used to fortifythose norms or to
prevent them frombecoming atrophied.</p>
          <p>Bans on thesale of sexual and reproductivecapacities are an impor
tantillustration.</p>
          <p>For purposes of legalpolicy, some of themost interestingcases of
normmanagement throughlaw involve thecontrolof riskybehavior
and thepromotionof social equality.Risky behavior is oftena prod
uct of social norms thatpeople would verymuch like,on reflection,
tochange.And with respect to risk,American societyhas witnessed
dramatic changes inprevailing norms in the lastdecades. Cigarette
smoking is themost dramatic example, but similar shiftscan be seen
in theareas of alcohol use, drug use, seatbeltuse, carryingguns, and
diet and exercise. Ifgovernmentsees prevailing norms as a taxon or
a subsidy to choice, itmight seek to change norms as a way of
changing choices. Certainly thepoint helps account forantidiscrim
inationpolicy, where a goal is to alter norms associated with both
taste-baseddiscriminationand rational stereotyping.</p>
          <p>Are effortsat normmanagement unacceptably paternalistic or
illiberal? Inmany cases theyare not.As I have emphasized, norms
are generally given rather than chosen. Sometimes people would
like norms tobe changed; often theydo not have a considered view
about which norms are best, but theywould, if theyreflecteda bit,
wish norms to be somethingother thanwhat theyare.When this is
so, it is entirely legitimateto use law to alter norms that(forexam
ple) encourage people to shortentheirown lives, at leastwhen they
do so in order to avoid reputational cost and without much in the
way of increased intrinsicvalue. Certainly effortsat normmanage
ment aremore legitimate iftheyhave a democratic pedigree.More
generally, attention to the effects of social norms helps show that
"choices" should notbe takenas sacrosanct.</p>
          <p>All this leaves open a number of questions. Among themost
pressing are empirical ones. To what extent have shifts in norms
been a functionof law?How can law be made effective in shifting
norms?What variables account for effectivenorm-change? There
are also important theoretical issues about constraints
on norm man
agement. It is particularly importanttodecide how tohandle situa
tions inwhich lawsmotivated by expressive goals havemixed orbad
consequences. I have suggested that legal "statements" producing
bad consequences should not be endorsed. But my simplest sugges
tionhere is thatwe begin tomake sense of law's expressive function
ifwe attend to the role of law in themanagement of social norms.
No systemof law can entirelyavoid thatrole; evenmarkets them
much a creation</p>
          <p>of law?are
selves?very
agement. In thesecircumstances itisbest forgovernmenttoproceed
exercises
in norm man
pragmatically and contextually,seeingwhich norms are obstacles to
well-being, and using law when law is effective in providing</p>
          <p>Cass R. Sunstein is Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service
Professor in theLaw School and Department ofPolitical Science of</p>
          <p>Endnotes
1. 163US 537 (1896).</p>
          <p>Constitutionalism and Constitutional Failure*</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-2">
          <title>Mark E. Brandon</title>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>I.The Necessity ofFailure</title>
        <p>We are accustomed to thinkingof constitutionsas devices forcre
ating and holding togethera political world. That customarymode
of thoughmtakes a certain sense.After all,making andmaintaining
a politics are central objectives of constitutionalism.They are not
only partofwhat a constitutionostensiblydoes, but also partofwhat
it should do, ormust do, if it is to succeed. But this sensible notion
has taken on perverse forms,especially after theCivil War of the
United States,where constitutional success has sometimes come to
be viewed strictlyin termsof theperpetuation of a constitutionor a
regime.1It is almost as if longevityitselfwere sufficientevidence of
constitutional</p>
        <p>success.</p>
        <p>Such a view of thingsisunsatisfactoryh,owever, forreasons other
thanthesimple fact thatconstitutionscan and do fail.Constitutional
failure ismore than an empirical reality. It is also a theoretical
necessity. But the theoreticalnecessity arises fromempirical fact.
Constitutions are "made" things.The very facts thattheyappear on
the scene at a particular time and displace existing formsof poli
tics?perhaps even existing constitutions?subvert most claims to
perpetuityas a constituentelement of any constitutionalregime.Of
course, those factsneed not prohibita constitutionor constitutional
order fromaiming at perpetuityB.ut theydomean thatthemanner in
which constitutionsare born and justified leaves themnormatively
defenseless against some formsof fundamental alteration or even
displacement. Justas a constitutiondisplaces a prior constitutionor
order, ittoomay be displaced under thecertaincircumstances.</p>
        <p>But constitutionalfailure isnot always so grand as thebreakdown
of an orderor a constitution.Constitutional failurecan occur in sub
characterof constitutionalism,which is insensiblewithout a theory
or set of standards thatgive thepolitical world formand limits.Of
course, the "character of constitutionalism" is a trickymatter, for
constitutionalism ismultifaceted. For example, constitutionalism
may aim at any of severalbasic objectives. Itmay takeas itspurpose
themaking of a people, sustainingways of life,or creatingor autho
rizingpolitical power.But constitutionalismarises inhistoryprimar
ilyas an attemptto solve a persistentproblem inhuman experience:
how to constrainand directpolitical power.2That is, it is fundamen
tally,thoughnot exclusively, concernedwith theproblem of limits.</p>
        <p>The problemof limitspresentsitselftoWestern thought(aswe have
inherited it) in the form of a dialogue between Socrates and</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          2. 347 US
          <issue>483</issue>
          (
          <year>1954</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On law and social meaning, see Lawrence Lessig, "</article-title>
          <source>The Regulation of Social Meaning,"</source>
          61 University of Chicago Law Review943 (
          <year>1995</year>
          ),
          <article-title>towhich I ammuch indebted</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>This essay draws on Cass R. Sunstein, "On theExpressive Function of theLaw," 144V. Pennsylvania Law Review</source>
          <year>2021</year>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ) and Cass R.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Free Markets and Social Justice, Chapter</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

