<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "Professors and Politics," 148 University of Pennsylvania Law Review 191</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>1999</addr-line>
          ,
          <country country="US">USA</country>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>148</volume>
      <fpage>1999</fpage>
      <lpage>2000</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>In the last few years, a number of law professors have been
involved in some highly public issues, not least through the circulation
of letters with multiple signatories, expressing a view on some issue of
national importance. It is not clear that there is anything like a trend
in this direction; certainly teachers of law have participated in what
some would consider "partisan politics" for many decades. But Neal
Devins is right to raise questions about the legitimacy and
conse2
quences of political involvement by academics. It is also interesting
to consider the relationship between such involvement and academic
freedom; if law professors are not concerned with the pursuit of truth,
the case for academic freedom is certainly weakened. The Clinton
impeachment provides the immediate motivation for Devins's
discussion. I offer a few remarks here on academic involvement in the
impeachment debate, with a few references to my own experience,3 and
t Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor ofJurisprudence, Law School
and Department of Political Science, University of Chicago. Professor Sunstein
testified on the constitutional issues relating to the impeachment of President Clinton, see
Testimony Before the UnitedStates House ofRepresentatives, Comm. on theJudiciay,Subcomm.
on the Constitution (Nov. 9, 1998) (statement of Cass R. Sunstein, Professor of Law),
availablein LEXIS, News Library, Transcripts File. I am grateful to Martha Nussbaum
and Richard Posner for valuable comments on an earlier draft, and to Brooke May for
research assistance.</p>
      <p>I See, e.g., Constitutional Scholars' Conference, Joint Statement, Constitutional
Scholars' Statement on Affirmative Action After City of Richmond v. JA. Croson Co., 98
YALE L.J. 1711, 1712 (1989) (arguing that municipalities should not scrap affirmative
action programs in the wake of City ofRichmond v.J.A. Croson); An Open Letter to
Congressman Gingrich, 104 YALE L.J. 1539, 1539 (1995) (urging that Congressman Gingrich
rescind his proposal to amend the House Rules to require three-fifths vote for enacting
laws that increase income taxes); infra notes 6-7 (providing text of a one-sentence
letter o2 ppposing impeachment and a letter opposing Clinton's possible resignation).</p>
      <p>See Neal Devins, BearingFalse Witness: The Clinton Impeachment and the Future of
Academic Freedom, 148 U. PA. L. REV. 165, 166 (1999) (arguing that "when a significant
number of law professors and historians hold themselves out as experts when they are
not... allacademics pay a price").</p>
      <p>3 The editors have asked me to provide a few details for background; readers who
dislike this sort of thing are encouraged to skip the footnotes.</p>
      <p>(191)
with an eye toward drawing some general lessons about professors and
politics, including presidential politics.</p>
      <p>I. PARTICULARS</p>
      <p>With respect to the President, the United States has now had
three serious impeachment inquiries in its entire history. As the
nation began discussion of the impeachment of President Clinton in
1998, many constitutional law professors concluded that no legitimate
grounds for impeachment had been identified. On their view, the
House of Representatives had started to embark on a constitutionally
impermissible path, one with potentially significant consequences.
This seemed unfortunate not merely because of the potential removal
of the President, and hardly because of the nature of President
Clinton's particular policies, but because of the constitutional
illegitimacy and potentially destabilizing effect of resort to the
impeachment mechanism.</p>
      <p>Some law professors believed that, as a technical matter, the
constitutional question was not even close.4 They believed that this
interpretation was not a "partisan" view, that it had nothing to do with
approval of President Clinton in general, and that it was the best reading
of the Constitution-a reading that would attract support from a
variety of possible approaches to interpretation and that would apply
regardless of the political affiliation of the President. Before the
hearings, members of the House of Representatives-themselves quite
uncertain about the issue-asked, in private meetings with law
professors:5 What do law professors generally think? Where are they? Why
4 For a discussion of the Impeachment Clause, see Cass R. Sunstein, Impeaching the
President, 147 U. PA. L. REv. 279, 280-92 (1998). Devins is wrong to say that "scholars
who argued against the appropriateness of originalism at the Bork hearings made use
of originalism (and little else) in arguing against the Clinton impeachment." Devins,
supranote 2, at note 24. Professor Tribe's argument, for example, was largely textual,
see Defining "High Crimes and Misdemeanors": Basic Principles (visited Oct. 24, 1999)
&lt;http://www.house.gov/judiciary/22398.htn&gt; (advocating that defining
impeachment properly "means taking seriously exactly what the Constitution says"), and while I
did not argue against the appropriateness of originalism at the Bork hearings, my
argument was typical in stressing a range ofinterpretive theories. SeeSunstein, supra.</p>
      <p>5 I draw on personal experience here. There was a series of private, informal
meetings with several law professors who met, in small groups, with a large number of
representatives, many of whom were unsure about how to think about, or vote on, the
impeachment question. A vivid recollection: The representatives listened politely to
the constitutional arguments, and were clearly interested in them, but some of their
eyes really lit up only during discussion, in which law professors were not involved, of
the underlying political dynamics.
aren't they saying anything? An obvious question was whether it
might conceivably be useful for members of Congress, and the public,
to know that there was widespread professional opinion to the effect
that impeachment would be unconstitutional.</p>
      <p>These were the circumstances in which a number of professors
(including me) were willing to circulate and to sign two letters
opposing impeachment. One of the letters, not limited to teachers of
constitutional law but circulated to law professors generally, provided an
extended analysis of the legal issues; the other, limited to teachers of
constitutional law,6 offered a one-sentence conclusion to the effect
that impeachment would not be "appropriate" in light of the charges
made by Judge Starr.7</p>
      <p>Many of those who signed or circulated these letters accepted (as I
do) all or most of Devins's general views about the need to separate
professional opinion from partisan politics. To say the least, most of
those of us who were involved in all this really do not enjoy
participat</p>
      <p>It is a considerable overstatement for Devins to say that "members of Congress
were actively involved" in any academic anti-impeachment letter. Devins, supra note 2,
at text accompanying note 66. Certainly the remarks did not lead to the letters. But I
agree with Devins about the general importance of a degree of independence on the
part of academics involved in these matters. Those of us who agreed with the White
House on the inappropriateness of impeachment made very clear-especially in
several informal discussions with lawyers there involving the constitutional standard for
impeachment-thatwe were not working "with" or "for" the White House in anyway.</p>
      <p>Because this letter was limited to teachers of constitutional law, I think Devins is
wrong to say that none of the relevant letters "made expertise a prerequisite"-at least
if we assume that teachers of constitutional law generally have some expertise on the
topic of impeachment. Devins, supra note 2, at text accompanying note 45.</p>
      <p>I wrote and circulated the one-sentence letter after many discussions with other law
professors. Some people did not like this approach, on the ground that it was without
reasoning; others, including me, thought that it would be worthwhile and relevant, if
only because it would show a widespread judgment on the general constitutional
question without committing people to a particular argument about which they might have
reservations. Here is its content:</p>
      <p>The undersigned professors and teachers of constitutional law* have diverse
political convictions and disagree on many political and legal issues; but we
agree that the possible grounds for impeachment recently identified by
Kenneth Starr and David Schippers are not an appropriate basis for impeaching a
President under Article II, Section 4 of the Constitution.</p>
      <p>*All of the signatories to this letter have taught the general constitutional law
course or some aspect of constitutional law as part of their curricular
responsibilities.</p>
      <p>There was also a subsequent letter, circulated after impeachment, opposing
resignation on the ground that it would do damage to the constitutional structure. See
BernardJ. Hibbits, Law ProfessorsSolicit SignaturesforAnti-ResignationLetter (visited Oct.
27, 1999) &lt;http://juritlaw.pitLedu/resig.htm&gt; (containing the full text of the letter,
dated Dec. 19, 1998).
ing in petition drives. Most of us thought that the process of sending
and responding to emails and collecting signatures was a boring,
unpleasant, and tedious business'-part of a most unwelcome (even if
occasionally hilarious9) diversion from our academic jobs. Nothing
here seemed glamorous, a source of "fame,"10 or in anyone's
selfinterest. But the relevant law professors believed that this was an
exceedingly unusual event, that the House of Representatives was on the
verge of acting unconstitutionally, and that it was appropriate, and
maybe not inconceivably useful, for the public and elected
representatives to be aware of a widespread (though not universal) professional
opinion.</p>
      <p>I am not entirely sure what, in particular, Devins thinks was wrong
with all this, or what lesson he wants to draw from it. He does not
argue that the impeachment of President Clinton was constitutionally
acceptable (though he may believe this). He does not demonstrate
nor even claim that the law professors who signed one or another
letter were wrong on the merits. Nor does he argue for the
(implausible) proposition that on principle, law professors should never speak
publicly about important public issues.</p>
      <p>Devins suggests that developments of this kind may endanger
academic freedom, an empirical claim that seems to me quite doubtful,
even absurd. Is it imaginable that the tenure system for law professors
would be eliminated if law professors frequently signed petitions on
public issues? In any case, Devins does not discuss what academic
freedom is for, to wit, the power to speak controversially about the
8 A confession: The one-sentence letter was the first such letter I have ever written
and circulated, and because the process was so tedious, I hope never to have to do
such a thing again.</p>
      <p>9 See infranote 31 (discussing Burden ofProofandtelevision producers).
10 But see infranote 31 (discussing my dog).</p>
      <p>I Devins follows the familiar view in stating that "Republican witnesses at the
House impeachment hearings testified that the President's conduct was impeachable
whereas Democratic witnesses testified that it was not." Devins, supra note 2, at note
67. In a sense, this statement is accurate; but my hunch is that a majority ofwitnesses,
on both sides, did not consider themselves "Republican witnesses" or "Democratic
witnesses." What a strange way to conduct a hearing on the impeachment question-as if,
before the debate even became serious, all Republicans were for impeachment and all
Democrats against it.</p>
      <p>Perhaps the greatest peculiarity of the hearings was that a majority of the witnesses
said that the allegations in question pointed to legitimate grounds for impeachment,
thus giving the impression that teachers of constitutional law were evenly divided on
the question-when in fact the overwhelming majority of constitutional law teachers
believed that impeachment was constitutionally illegitimate or at least inappropriate.
The selection ofwitnesses gave a grossly distorted picture ofacademic opinion.
truth as one sees it, free of risks of political reprisal. I agree with
Devins that the principle of academic freedom is violated if those who
enjoy it are not acting in good faith or are not pursuing truth (not a
doubtful empirical claim about consequences but a sensible claim
about principle, which is what appears to me to underlie Devins's
essay). But nothing in this point argues against public statements by
professors.</p>
      <p>Devins's concerns appear narrower. It seems to me that they fall
in two categories. These categories are related but best treated
separately.</p>
      <p>His first point has to do with the possibly limited expertise of
many or some of those who signed the relevant letters. Devins says
that "it is doubtful that many had thought seriously about the
constitutional standards governing impeachment. He appears to believe
that at least by implication, some or many law professors held
themselves out as specialists or experts when, in fact, they lacked knowledge
about impeachment that would qualify them as such.</p>
      <p>For some of the signatories, perhaps this is true. But I think that
Devins'sjudgment is too harsh. Impeachment is hardly an obscure or
invisible issue in constitutional law, and in the wake of the Watergate
controversy, many law professors developed genuine, if fairly general,
views on the appropriate meaning of the phrase "high crimes or
misdemeanors." Certainly most teachers of constitutional law know
something about the governing legal standards; they know enough to
know, for example, that smoking marijuana or speeding would not
ordinarily count as a "high crime or misdemeanor." From there they
could reason by analogy to the view that, at least as a general rule, a
President cannot be impeached unless he has been charged with
large-scale abuse of the powers that he has by virtue of being
President.</p>
      <p>Those law professors who signed the longer letter but who do not
teach constitutional law probably believed that they knew
enoughfrom training and from substantive conversations with colleagues-to
have a reasonably informed opinion about the threshold question of
whether the charges against President Clinton made out an
impeachable offense. Law professors who do not teach constitutional law have
informed views about many constitutional issues-for example, about
whether racial segregation is generally unconstitutional, whether
quotas can make for an acceptable affirmative action program, and
12 Md at text accompanying note 21.
whether the Constitution protects the right to use contraceptives.
Many law professors believe that with respect to the charges against
President Clinton, impeachment falls in the same category.1 3 The
signatories likely thought, in good faith, that they knew enough about
the constitutional provision to conclude that an impeachable offense
had not been made out. It is hard to see why there is anything
untoward here. I agree with Devins that people should not sign petitions
when they are unable to defend the relevant position publicly; but I
would give the signatories the benefit of the doubt on this point.</p>
      <p>Devins's second point has to do with the motivations of those who
participated in the relevant events. He says that "[m]any of the law
professor and historian signatories were animated by partisanship and
self-interest ... ."14 This is certainly possible-and I know very little
about the historians involved-but it is very hard for Devins or anyone
else to have access to the motivations of strangers. Nor is it clear what
he means by "self-interest" and "partisanship." Academics "who want
to see their names in print" 5 surely have much better ways to achieve
that goal; it is hard to believe that publication was a significant
motivating factor here. And contrary to Devins's suggestion, "celebrity"16
hardly comes from signing such a letter. A few law professors may
care about celebrity, but most law professors care about the law and
about ideas.</p>
      <p>The allegation of "partisanship"17 raises many questions. Law
professors who signed this letter were offering a judgment about the
meaning of the Constitution, a judgment that they believed it to be
true. In what sense was their motivation "partisan"?' 8 A law professor
who testifies that a proposed statute would violate the Constitution
13 Judge Posner seems to me unfair in criticizing law professors for not publicly
deploring President Clinton's conduct, which, plausibly, included perjury and
obstruction ofjustice. See RICHARD POSNER, AN AFFAIR OF STATE 240-45 (1999) (lamenting
that "leaders of the legal profession might have been expected to emphasize the
importance of the rule of law in general and of telling the truth ... These expectations
would have been disappointed"). I know that many of those who opposed
impeachment on constitutional grounds believed that the relevant conduct was deplorable, and
certainly many of us emphasized, publicly and privately, the seriousness of perjury and
obstruction ofjustice. In any case, nearly everyone, including President Clinton's
closest friends and allies, as well as members of both parties, publicly deplored his
conduct, and an outpouring of statements to this effect by law professors would have been
largely pointless.</p>
      <p>14 Devins, supra note 2, at text accompanying note 31.
is Id. at text accompanying note 32.
16 Id.
17 Id. at text accompanying note 31.
is Id. at text accompanying note 32.</p>
      <p>PROFESSORSAND POLrTICS
should be taken to be addressing the constitutional issue and need
not have a political motivation; what is different about a law professor
who signs a public statement about what the Constitution means?
Perhaps Devins's claim is that the professors who signed this letter
were motivated not by a considered judgment about the Constitution,
but by their extra-legal political convictions (in favor, for example, of
government regulation and the welfare state, or in favor of President
Clinton generally). But I do not know how Devins can be confident of
this uncharitable judgment, and in any case, the anti-impeachment
conclusion would hold if President Reagan, or a future Republican
President, were subject to an impeachment inquiry on the basis of
similar allegations.'9 I very much doubt that the signatories would
change their view if the accused President had been Republican.
Perhaps Devins disagrees, but he offers little basis for any such
disagreement.</p>
      <p>Devins seems to think that partisanship is established by his claim
that the academy is "overwhelmingly left-liberal, overwhelmingly
Democratic." 20 But he does not note that many people not normally
characterized as "left-liberal" signed one or more of the impeachment
letters.2 ' For what it is worth, the University of Chicago Law School is</p>
      <p>I A possible point in support of Devins: If a group of law professors despised a
certain President, they might not go to the effort to circulate and sign a letter against
impeachment, even if they believed that the grounds for impeachment were invalid.
Perhaps some law professors did not sign the Clinton letters even though they agreed
with them, simply because they did not like President Clinton; perhaps some law
professors would not sign a similar letter on behalf of, for example, President Reagan,
even if they agreed with it.</p>
      <p>20Devins, supranote 2, at text accompanying note 33.</p>
      <p>21 These include Douglas Laycock, Stephen Macedo, and Andrzej Rapaczynski. I
am sure that there are many more and am happy to say that I do not know the political
views of the vast majority of signatories. Of course Devins is allowed to characterize
people as he chooses, but for what it is worth, I would not describe myself as a
"leftliberal," see Devins, supra note 2, at text accompanying notes 33-39, or indeed as a
Democrat, see id. at note 36 and accompanying text.</p>
      <p>Devins is misleading to suggest thatJudge Posner described the "law professor
antiimpeachment letter as 'a form of herd behavior... by the animal that likes to see its
name in print.'" Devins, supranote 2, at text accompanying note 54 (quoting RICHARD
A. POSNER, AN AFFAIR OF STATE 242 (1999)). ActuallyJudge Posner describes this as
the possible opinion of an "unkind critic," thus distancing himself from the charge,
which is not his own view. RICHARD A. POSNER, AN AFFAIR OF STATE 242 (1999). (I
owe this correction to judge Posner.)</p>
      <p>I also doubt that "many legal academics see Ken Starr... as their nemesis."
Devins, supranote 2, at text accompanying notes 36-37. I do know that many of those
(including me) who opposed Clinton's impeachment believe that Starr was a
distinguished judge and a distinguished Solicitor General and have not the slightest doubt
that he is an entirely honorable person. A number of us who strongly opposed
imnot usually characterized as "left-liberal," and while I cannot speak
officially or on behalf of the faculty, it seemed to me that at least a solid
majority of the faculty, including many strong critics of President
Clinton's policies, were opposed to impeachment on the ground that
it would be illegitimate or inappropriate from the constitutional point
of view. Indeed, my former colleague Michael McConnell, hardly a
left-liberal, went so far as to write a letter to Congressman Hyde,
sharply critical of President Clinton and suggesting that impeachment
would not be unconstitutional-but pleading with Hyde not to
support impeachment of the President in the midst of such partisan
divisions. 22 Was McConnell's letter inappropriate? Unacceptably
partisan? Illegitimate because (unlike the two widely distributed letters) it
did not directly address a purely legal question?</p>
      <p>The impeachment of President Clinton produced, on all sides,
more than enough challenges to other people's motivations.23 I am
not sure why Devins does not, with respect to law professors and
historians on all sides, indulge a principle of charity-suggesting that in
cases of doubt, we should assume that those with whom we disagree
are acting in good faith an d24 on the basis of evidence that they
honestly believe to be sufficient.
peachment, and who were quite critical of some of the decisions of the Office of
Independent Counsel, knowJudge Starr, like and respect him personally, and believe that
the 9ersonal attacks on him and his motivations were absurd and baseless.</p>
      <p>See Letter from Michael W. McConnell, Presidential Professor, The University of
Utah College of Law, to Henry J. Hyde, Jr., Chairman, Committee on the Judiciary
Committee of the House of Representatives 1-2 (Dec. 12, 1998) (on file with the
University ofPennsylvania Law Review) (indicating that while "the Constitution allows for
the possibility that an elected President may so abuse the public trust that he can and
should be removed," still "a President should [not] be impeached or removed from
office solely on the votes ofhis political rivals").</p>
      <p>23 This seems to me to infect RIcHARD A. POSNER, AN AFFAIR OF STATE (1999) as
well, where analysis of the constitutional issue seems to me remarkably casual and
offhand. See id. at 94-109 (discussing the history and scope of impeachment through a
"structural and pragmatic... approach to constitutional meaning").</p>
      <p>24 I share many of Devins's concerns about the political campaign against Judge
Robert Bork. But I do not think that the law professors who opposed Bork's
confirmation did so because they "saw Bork as a threat to their status and influence." Devins,
supranote 2, at text accompanying notes 51-53. I think that they did so on principle,
that is, because they believed thatJudge Bork's view about constitutional interpretation
would be a threat to constitutional ideals, properly understood. They may have been
wrong on the merits, and I agree with Devins that petitions of the sort circulated
againstJudge Bork should be rare. (In the interest offull disclosure, I should say that I
testified quite critically about Judge Bork's views on separation of powers questions,
but signed no petitions and took no public position on the question of whether he
should be confirmed.)</p>
      <p>II. GENERALTES</p>
      <p>There are much broader questions in the background. Devins
thinks that academic participation in the Clinton impeachment is part
of a larger trend and a more general problem, one that threatens
academic freedom itself. Thus he writes that "[t]oday, academics seek
fame through talk show appearances, op-ed pieces, and trade press
books."2 Devins also says that "the traditional image of the academic
has given way to 'postmodernism, multiculturalism, and political
correctness,'26 and hence that "there is good reason to doubt whether
academics still think of themselves as truth seekers." 7 His suggestion
appears to be that the involvement of law professors in the Clinton
impeachment signals a larger trend toward highly partisan, mostly
leftwing activity, in which law professors do not care about truth but
instead push some kind of political agenda. Devins suggests that if
professors are engaging in partisan politics, academic freedom is at risk. I
share many of his concerns, and I agree that the principle of academic
freedom is undermined if professors do not care about truth. But
there seem to me to be three problems with his claims here.</p>
      <p>The first problem is that there is no single way to be a law
professor. Most of us, most of the time, are devoted to teaching and
research; few of us "seek fame" or anything 6lse through talk shows,
oped pieces, and trade press books. But some professors sometimes do
express their views on talk shows, and a few more write op-ed pieces
and publish with trade presses. Why is this so terrible, or indeed
terrible at all? (Can anyone really object that Gerald Gunther published
his excellent book on Learned Hand 8 with Knopf rather than
Stanford University Press?) One of the purposes of academic freedom is
to permit professors to speak publicly without fear of reprisal, and
those who write op-eds or publish with a trade press are doing what
academic freedom is designed to permit them to do. My hunch is that
when law professors write op-eds or go on television, it is to express
the truth as they see it, not to "achieve their fifteen minutes of fame."2'
Some people spend all of their time on teaching and academic
projects; others testify before Congress and write an occasional amicus
brief; still others write op-eds and say what they think on radio or
tele</p>
      <p>Id. at text accompanying note 55.</p>
      <p>26 Id. at text accompanying note 75 (quoting David M. Rabban, CanAcademic
Freedom SurvivePostmodernism?,86 CAL L. REV. 1377, 1378 (1998)).</p>
      <p>27 I.
28 GERALD GUNTHER, LEARNED HAND: THE MAN AND THEJUDGE (1994).
29Devins, supranote 2, at text accompanying note 55.</p>
      <p>UNIVERS1TY OFPENNSYLVANIA LAWREVEW
vision shows. Of course some of us may not think so well of colleagues
who spend a lot of time on talk shows, especially in light of the
(ridiculous, hilarious"0 ) restrictions of the format,3' and above all if this
comes at the expense of their scholarship and teaching. But since
there are many ways to be a good law professor, and so long as
teaching and research are not cheapened or neglected, I do not quite see
Devins's objection here.</p>
      <p>The second problem with Devins's claims is that they overlook the
fact that it is perfectly responsible, maybe even a civic duty, for law
professors to participate in public affairs, at least some of the time, by
showing how what they know bears on public issues. (I do not believe
that Devins disagrees with this point.) If, for example, a teacher of
constitutional law thinks that a proposed law is unconstitutional, there
should be no taboo on her saying so, even through an op-ed piece. If
a teacher of criminal law believes that laws forbidding gang loitering
so For example: In one interview on CNN, I was required to try to stand on a stack
of extremely unsteady boxes, not as a scientific experiment or medical test or cruelty of
some kind, but so as to ensure a view of the Capitol building on the television screen.
Most of the time, it seemed likely that I would fall off. (This interview was live.) And
apparently all law professors on television are, by some firmly enforced unwritten rule,
required to try to hold a small piece of equipment in one ear, so as to be able to
communicate with other people on the show, including the host. (It isn't easy to hold
things in your ear.) Most of the time, the small piece of equipment does not fall out;
but some of the time, it does. (This is especially troublesome when you are trying to
balance yourself on a stack of extremely unsteady boxes.) See Burden of Proof (CNN
television broadcast, Nov. 9, 1998), availablein LEXIS transcript no. 98110900V12
(discussing the meaning of "other High Crimes and Misdemeanors," perjury, and Bills of
Attainder).</p>
      <p>A personal anecdote: I appeared on several shows to discuss impeachment
issues, but the format seemed so confining, and so conducive to ludicrous
oversimplification, and driving there and back seemed so time consuming, that after a while I
decided not to do it anymore. I told a producer of CNN's BurdenofProofthat I would no
longer discuss impeachment, and would appear on the program if and only if my new
dog Perry, a (photogenic) Rhodesian Ridgeback puppy, could appear with me. They
called my bluff. The show aired on December 31, 1998, and dealt with legal issues
relating to dogs. My dog did become at least somewhat famous; in the middle of the
show, the producer broke in to tell me that CNN was being "flooded" with calls and
compliments about Perry. Interested readers (can there possibly be any?), those who
think I'm joking, and Rhodesian Ridgeback enthusiasts can find the transcript at CNN
Burden ofProof(CNN television broadcast, Dec. 31, 1998), availablein LEXIS, transcript
no. 98123100V12. [Ed. Note: Perry's photo is available at
&lt;http://studentwww.uchicago.edu/orgs/law-phoenix/2bear.html&gt;].</p>
      <p>A small media notation: The producers who invite people to appear on their
shows seem to have the same style and character as that of the on-air hosts of those
shows (is this an antecedentjob qualification, or does it develop over time?). Thus the
most hilarious invitation came from the producer of the show Hardbal whose
invitation appeared in exactly the same staccato voice as that of Chris Matthews, the host of
the show: We-want-you-on-Hardball-know-about-it?
will or will not deter crime, and has reasons for the belief, it is
important for the public to know about this. This is an ordinary part of civic
discourse, and a nation is better off with it than without it. Indeed,
this kind of academic engagement is one of the things that academic
freedom is designed to allow.</p>
      <p>Of course silence about public issues can be legitimate too.
Whether or not professors should speak publicly depends at least
partly on the justice or injustice, and on the legality or illegality, of the
practices at issue. Since silence is a choice and not a neutral position,
professors, like other citizens, are properly criticized for failing to
speak out on certain questions, at least if they have relevant expertise.
Teachers of constitutional law would have been properly criticized, I
believe, if they had remained silent during the unconstitutional
impeachment of President Clinton.</p>
      <p>If it is legitimate for one professor to speak publicly, it is not
illegitimate for a group of them to do so, at least on rare occasions.
Surely it is relevant that law professors are by their very profession
concerned with highly public issues. They are unlike teachers of
French literature, for their daily life is likely to breed expertise on
issues that will, at one point or another, have public salience. I
emphatically agree with Devins's concluding suggestion-that academics
should not sign letters that they could not defend publicly.32 But this
is a test that could, I believe, be easily passed by those who signed the
anti-impeachment letters, and indeed I doubt that this test would be
flunked by many academics with respect to letters they have signed in
the past.</p>
      <p>The final problem is that it is unclear what Devins means to claim
with his invocation of "postmodernism, multiculturalism, and political
correctness."33 Very few of those involved in the Clinton impeachment
letters have any sympathy with postmodernism, a movement that (in
my view fortunately) has had only a sporadic influence on the
academic study of law-far less of an impact than, for example, that of
the economic analysis of law. "Multiculturalism" can be understood in
many different ways, and certainly no form of "multiculturalism" now
dominates law schools. "Political correctness," if understood as a
social taboo on the expression of unpopular opinions, is certainly to be
deplored.3 But so understood, it is hardly limited to left-leaning
aca32 Devins, supra note 2, at text accompanying note 109 (advocating this test as a
means of ensuring that academics do the necessary work before registering opinions).
33 Id. at text accompanying note 75 (internal quotations omitted).</p>
      <p>A qualification: Some unpopular opinions are properly subject to taboo;
condemics, and here too, I am not sure how the complaint about political
correctness bears on the points at hand. Instead of complaining
about what he appears to see as left-wing domination of law schools,
Devins might defend a substantive position that he believes is unjustly
devalued and that deserves a better hearing.</p>
      <p>I agree with Devins's concerns about skepticism with respect to
truth, as do many others; 5 but as a class, law professors are hardly
skeptical of the idea of truth, and I do not see why Devins believes that
there is, within the law schools, much "discomfort with
truthseeking."3 6 Law professors founded their overwhelming opposition to
the Clinton impeachment on a commitment to truth, not on
skepticism about truth. Nor is Devins entirely clear about the distinction
between "truth" and "political motivation." Suppose that someone
really believes that a proposed law is unconstitutional. Suppose
someone believes that some proposition about the Constitution is
true. Is there any problem with writing, or signing, a letter to that
effect? What makes that action inconsistent with academic freedom?</p>
      <p>It is time to conclude. Academics have a duty to pursue truth, and
for most academics, most of the time, participation in partisan causes
can be destructive to that endeavor. But legal academics sometimes
know things that are relevant to public life, and when this is so, they
are entitled, and sometimes obligated, to say what they know. They
may be wrong on the merits, but that is another matter.
sider the view that slavery was very good, or that the Holocaust should be celebrated as
a wonderful event.</p>
      <p>35 See generallyDANIEL A. FARBER &amp; SUZANNA SHERRY, BEYOND ALL REASON: THE
RADICAL ASSAULT ON TRUTH IN AMERIcAN LAW (1997); Martha C. Nussbaum, Skepticism
About PracticalReason in Literatureand the Law, 107 HARV. L. REV. 714 (1994); Cass K
Sunstein, On AnalogicalReasoning,106 HARV.L. REV. 741, 779-80 &amp;n.130 (1993).</p>
      <p>Devins, supra note 2, at text accompanying note 80. Of course there are
exceptions, discussed and addressed in FARBER&amp; SHERRY, supra note 35. (Ofcourse I do not
mean to endorse, by these brief comments, everything in Farber and Sherry's
controversial book.)</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list />
  </back>
</article>

