<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>17</issue>
      <fpage>115</fpage>
      <lpage>157</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at http://about.jstor.org/terms JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>Oxford University Press is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to American
Law and Economics Review</p>
      <p>This content downloaded from 132.174.255.223 on Wed, 27 Jul 2016 13:55:42 UTC</p>
      <p>All use subject to http://about.jstor.org/terms
Behavioral Law and Economics:
A Progress Report</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Cass R. Sunstein, University of Chicago</title>
      <p>The last decade has seen an outpouring of work in "behavioral law and
economics;" in the last few years, the outpouring has become a flood.1
This should not be surprising. Cognitive psychology and behavioral
economics have played a role in the work of many economists, including,
to name just a few examples, George Akerlof (1991), Kenneth Arrow
(1986), Colin Camerer (1990), Robert Frank (1999), Timur Kuran (1995),</p>
      <p>
        For parts of this review I have drawn, in some places quite heavily, on
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">Sunstein
(1997)</xref>
        and Jolis,
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">Sunstein, and Thaler (1998)</xref>
        . I am particularly grateful to Jolis and
Thaler for comments on this paper, for many helpful discussions, and for permission to
draw on our joint work; they should be given full credit for the use of our joint work
here, and no blame for mistakes on my part. I have tried to give credit to specific places
where I have drawn on Jolis et al., but the discussion there has had a more pervasive
influence than the particular citations suggest. I am also grateful to Daniel Kahneman
and David Schkade for helpful discussions, to Brian Lehman for excellent research
assistance and helpful comments, and to Jill Hasday, Saul Levmore, Eric Posner, Richard
Posner, and an anonymous reviewer for valuable comments on a previous draft. Many
of the topics discussed here are treated in detail in the papers in Behavioral Law and
Economics (Cass R. Sunstein ed., forthcoming, Cambridge University Press, 1999).
      </p>
      <p>Send correspondence to: Cass R. Sunstein, University of Chicago Law School,
111 E. 60th St., Chicago, IL 60637; Fax (773) 702-0730; E-mail: csunstei@ midway.
uchicago.edu.</p>
      <p>
        l.For a very partial list, see for example, Rachlinski (1996; 1998); Loewenstein et
al. (1993); Korobkin (1998a); Kelman (1996); Langevoort (1997); Jolis,
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">Sunstein, and
Thaler (1998)</xref>
        ; Hoffman and Spitzer (1993); Sunstein, Kahneman, and Schkade (1998);
McCaffery et al. (1995); Jolis (1996); Issacharoff (1996). A valuable symposium is
the "Legal Implications of Psychology: Human Behavior, Behavioral Economics, and
the Law," 51 Vanderbilt Law Review 1499 (1988). For an instructive literature review,
overlapping in some ways with that presented here, see Langevoort (1998).
©1999 American Law and Economics Association
Matthew Rabin (1994), and Richard
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">Thaler (1991)</xref>
        . In light of their
increasing influence on economics, behavioral approaches were bound to
affect economic analysis of law as well.2 The purpose of this essay is to
provide a survey and also a progress report - more particularly, to outline
the organizing themes of behavioral law and economics, to see how it
departs from standard law and economics, and to suggest some problems,
questions, and directions for the future.3
      </p>
      <p>The essay comes in five sections. Section 1 discusses the phenomenon
of "constructed" preferences, a phenomenon that lies at the heart of
disagreements between conventional and behavioral law and economics; an
important example involves "judgment reversals." Section 1 also deals
with fairness-related behavior, myopia, and bounded rationality. Section
2 explores fairness and in particular the phenomenon of reciprocity. This
phenomenon is exemplified by the fact that people are sometimes
willing to sacrifice their economic self-interest both to benefit those who have
been fair to them and to harm those who have been unfair to them. Section
3 deals with mental accounting, a mechanism by which people attempt to
overcome their tendency to myopia. Section 4, the longest section,
explores a number of problems in bounded rationality. These include loss
aversion, a finding of prospect theory with special importance for law,
including both contract and tort; biases in judgment; heuristics; and possible
differences between "decision utility" and "experience utility," differences
that suggest that people often do not maximize their own utility.</p>
      <p>Through these various discussions I hope to show how behavioral
economics might help to inform predictions about the effects of law and also
judgments about what the law ought to be doing. Often behavioral law and
economics suggests that the conventional approach misses a great deal. A
default rule, for example, may affect underlying preferences in the law of
employment and elsewhere (see Isacharoff, 1996; Korobkin, 1997); the set
of alternatives placed before a jury or judge may affect outcomes in
surprising ways; even if their expected value is the same (see Kelman et al.,
1997); a reliably imposed, lenient punishment should have far more
de2. Most recent issues of the American Economic Review , the Quarterly Journal of
Economics , and the Economic Review contain one of more article involving behavioral
economics.</p>
      <p>
        3. Good overviews of many of the issues here - not, however, discussing law - are
Rabin (1998) and Conlisk (1996).
terrent value than an infrequently imposed, severe punishment
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Jolis,
Sunstein, and Thaler, 1998)</xref>
        ; damage awards are vulnerable to
arbitrariness, because of "anchoring" effects and the pervasive problem of "scaling
without a modulus"
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Sunstein, Kahneman, and Schkade, 1998)</xref>
        ; some
cases will not settle because of the presence of spite, which can incline
people to sacrifice their own material self-interest in order to impose costs
on others (see Farns worth, 1999); because of mental accounting, and
contrary to the conventional wisdom, a redistributive tort rule may be more
effective than a redistributive tax (see Jolis, 1998).
      </p>
      <p>Of course, any large collection of anomalies and effects raises
obvious questions about whether behavioral economics, or behavioral law and
economics, can make predictions at all, or whether it is relegated instead
to offering merely plausible ex post descriptions of law-related events.
Section 5 thus discusses problems for the enterprise of behavioral
economics and some areas for future inquiry. It lays special stress on the
need for parsimony, the discipline imposed by markets, and the
possibility of "debiasing."</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>1. Theoretical Preliminaries</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>1.1. Constructed Preferences</title>
      <p>
        A primary claim of behavioral economics is that human preferences
and values are constructed, rather than simply elicited, by social situations
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref6">(see Slovic, 1995; Tversky, 1996)</xref>
        . "Observed preferences are not simply
read off one master list; they are actually constructed during the elicitation
process
options and suggest alternative heuristics, which give rise to inconsistent
responses"
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(Tversky, 1996, p. 371)</xref>
        . This proposition is not meant to deny
the possibility or the value of identifying utility functions in order to
analyze the consequences of law. It is instead the foundation for a set
of claims, empirical in character, about how certain contexts will push
judgment and decision in predictable directions.
      </p>
      <p>
        On this view, human beings do not generally consult a freestanding
"preference menu" from which they make selections at the moment of
choice; preferences can be a product of procedure, description, and
context at the time of choice. Moreover, it is possible to identify the
influence of different procedures, descriptions, and contexts. "Alternative
descriptions of the same choice problems lead to systematically different
preferences; strategically equivalent elicitation procedures give rise to
different choices; and the preference between x and y often depends on the
choice set within which they are embedded"
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(Tversky, 1996, p. 186)</xref>
        . One
goal of behavioral economics is to link specified features of context with
identifiable outcomes - showing, for example, that a choice set of a
specified type X will produce outcome A, whereas in an otherwise identical
situation, a choice set of some type Y will produce outcome B. A basic
goal of behavioral law and economics is to link a better understanding
of human behavior with a better set of predictions about the sources and
effects of law.
      </p>
      <p>Behavioral economics has special relevance to law, for the legal system
is pervasively in the business of constructing procedures, descriptions, and
contexts for choice. Most obviously, the legal system creates procedures,
descriptions, and contexts in the course of litigated cases. For example,
the alternatives selected to be placed before a jury or judge may matter
a great deal; liability or conviction on some count A may very much
depend on the nature of counts B, C, and D. A judge or jury may choose
A, and not B, when C is the only alternative; but when D is introduced,
a judge or jury may choose B instead. This outcome is predicted by the
phenomenon of extremeness aversion (discussed below), even though, on
conventional assumptions, the introduction of some unchosen alternative
ought not to affect choices. From this prediction we know a great deal
more than we otherwise would; it should be possible to learn a great deal
more. Eventually, observers may well be able to make robust predictions
about the effects, on juries, of the menu of possible alternatives placed
before them. In this respect the preferences and values of judges and
juries can be constructed, not elicited, by the legal system.</p>
      <p>
        Certainly something of this kind is true for the award of damages,
where special problems may arise; the plaintiff's demand, for example,
may serve as an "anchor" for the jury's choice, and different demands
can produce different outcomes
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(see Chapman and Bornstein, 1996)</xref>
        . A
demand of $100,000 may produce a much higher award than a demand
of $20,000, even if the case is otherwise identical, simply because the
$100,000 becomes the starting point from which adjustments are made.
Similar points hold outside of the courtroom. The legal system's
original allocation of entitlements, and the structures created for exchange (or
nonexchange) by law, may well affect people's preferences and values
(see Korobkin, 1998a). People who are originally given an entitlement
say, to be fired only for cause, or to be free from certain occupational
hazards - are likely to value the right more than if it were originally given
to someone else. The point much bears on the selection of default rules in
contract law; contrary to the Coase theorem, different default rules may
lead to dramatically different outcomes, even if transactions costs are
minimal. Thus, law can construct rather than elicit preferences internally, by
affecting what goes on in court, and externally, by affecting what happens
in ordinary transactions, market and nonmarket.
      </p>
      <p>Behavioral economists have devoted a good deal of attention to
"preference reversals," which occur when people change their choices with
different descriptions of options that, on conventional grounds, should
be regarded as identical (Thaler, 1992, p. 79). Building on earlier work,
Tversky and Thaler find, for example, that people may choose an option A
over option B, but also conclude that option B is worth more than option
A when the two are valued separately.4 Their example involves the choice
between two highway safety programs designed to reduce the 600
annual fatalities in a hypothetical Middle Eastern country. Program A would
reduce the number of fatalities to 570, at an annual cost of $12 million.
Program B would reduce the number of fatalities to 500, at an annual cost
of $55 million. When asked which program they would choose, about
twothirds of respondents favor program B. When given the same information
about the two programs, except the cost of Program B, and then asked to
state the cost that would make the two programs equally attractive, more
than 90% offer amounts under $55 million. These answers suggest that
the same people prefer Program B, thus producing a preference reversal.
Tversky and Thaler conclude by invoking the baseball umpire who says,
with respect to balls and strikes, "They ain't nothing till I call them"; they
find that preference is "a constructive, context-dependent process."
4. The earlier work involved gambles. People tend to choose a bet involving a high
chance of winning a small prize over a low chance to win a bigger prize. Thus, people
would choose a 7/8 chance to win $6 over a 1/8 chance to win $60. But when asked to
state the lowest price for which they would trade the gamble if they owned it, people
place a higher price on the lower chance-higher payoff bet. See Lichtenstein and Slovic
(1971).</p>
      <p>The question remains whether and how these findings are relevant to
law. Related research by Kahneman, Ritov, and Schkade (1999) has found
"valuation reversals" in two contexts of special importance to the legal
system: contingent valuation and punitive damage awards. The punitive
damage cases involved, respectively, financial harm and personal injury.
When the cases were viewed in isolation, people were willing to
support higher awards for the financial harm plaintiffs, partly because of the
relatively higher compensatory award in those cases. (The compensatory
award thus worked as an "anchor"; see below.) But when the two cases
were considered together, about three-quarters of people assessed larger
awards for the personal injury case, resulting in a dramatic reversal in
median awards. In short, the financial injury judgments plummeted when the
two cases were seen together. In cases without anchors, changes were also
observed, as the median awards for the financial cases decreased, whereas
the median awards for the personal injury cases increased (Kahneman et
al., 1999). Similar reversals of judgment were observed not only for
dollars but also for ratings, on a bounded numerical scale, of punitive intent.
Related findings were observed for contingent valuation problems, where
it is found that people's judgments are quite different if cases are
studied together rather than separately. More particularly, people's willingness
to pay to protect coral reefs is quite high when this issue is investigated
in isolation; it is lower when the coral reef problem is examined together
with the problem of skin cancer among the elderly (Kahneman, Ritov,
and Schkade, 1999). When the problems are taken together, willingness
to pay to protect against skin cancer increases, whereas willingness to pay
to protect coral reefs falls, sometimes producing valuation reversals.</p>
      <p>Kahneman and his coauthors believe that in many settings, dollar
responses to public questions express "attitudes" rather than "preferences"
and also that attitudes have distinctive properties, including a tendency to
valuation reversals and judgment reversals. If true, this claim has important
implications for many legal contexts, including not only jury judgments
in general but also criminal sentencing and expenditures in the regulatory
state. A possible implication is that judgments of cases and problems in
isolation - and isolation is typical of the legal system - will lead to many
problems. Isolated judgments may produce global or systematic
irrationality, as jurors (and perhaps judges and representatives) reach conclusions
that do not cohere with other judgments, simply because cases are
examined in isolation. In any case the constructed nature of judgments about
dollars, and the potential for "judgment reversals," bears much further
study.</p>
      <sec id="sec-4-1">
        <title>1.2. Fairness, Myopia, and Bounded Rationality</title>
        <p>
          Much of behavioral economics can be organized under the headings of
fairness-related behavior, myopia, and bounded rationality.
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref6">(These
categories are analyzed in depth under the rubric of "three bounds" - bounded
rationality, bounded willpower, and bounded self-interest - in an essay by
Thaler [1996] and an article by Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler [1998], and I
draw heavily on that analysis here.)</xref>
          The underlying evidence is not best
taken to demonstrate that people are "irrational" or that their behavior
is unpredictable and arbitrary. Thaler's term "quasi-rational" is a more
helpful description of real world agents. The notion of "quasi-rationality"
should be taken to suggest departures from standard economic
assumptions, but departures that are systematic and predictable, and thus a
legitimate basis for predicting human behavior.5 Among the consequences
for law is an appreciation of why government intervention may not be
necessary to solve collective action problems; an understanding of the
important and pervasive phenomenon of "compliance without
enforcement" (relevant, for example, to nonsmoking policy); a better
understanding of information-forcing default rules in the context of employment
law; a sense of how informational campaigns might actually achieve their
goals; and a rejection of the sometimes-dogmatic antipaternalism of
conventional law and economics. I present the underlying mechanisms very
briefly here; readers interested in more details, and responses to
counterarguments, might consult Goldstein and Hogarth (1997),
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">Thaler (1991)</xref>
          ,
Arkes and Hammond (1986), and Kahneman, Slovic, and Tversky (1982).
Fairness. The first point has to do with the ingredients of most people's
utility functions. Most people care, some of the time, about being fair and
about being treated fairly, and they will sacrifice their material self-interest
5. And not only human; pigeons and rats have been found to behave in accordance
with prospect theory rather than expected utility theory. See Kagel, Battalio, and Green
(1995).
in order to promote these goals.6 In response to perceived antisocial
behavior, people sometimes sacrifice their own economic interest in order to
impose punishment. Cooperation sometimes exists even without legal
constraints on uncooperative behavior, and spitefulness can produce serious
problems, as in vengeful behavior before and during litigation (consider a
bad divorce).
        </p>
        <p>
          As emphasized in Jolis,
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">Sunstein, and Thaler (1998)</xref>
          and earlier work
in behavioral economics, the content of "fairness" depends on existing
social norms and in particular on the reference point
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref5">(see Jolis, Sunstein, and
Thaler, 1998, pp. 1511-12; Thaler, 1991)</xref>
          . A deviation from a reference
point, as in an increase in the price of snow shovels after a snowstorm,
is likely to trigger a judgment of unfairness. Thaler suggests, in a set of
arguments with many implications for law, that interindustry wage
differentials are partly a product of "perceived equity in setting wages" (Thaler,
1992, p. 49). The basic point here is that predictions and prescriptions will
sometimes go wrong if they disregard the effects of fairness-related
judgments in producing social outcomes. Moreover, the demand for law often
reflects not only or even mostly interest-group pressure, but widespread
fairness judgments
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler, 1998, pp. 1493-97, 15
1016)</xref>
          .
        </p>
        <p>
          Myopia. Many people are myopic, at least some of the time. As Thaler
and Shefrin have emphasized, people - in their capacity as "doers" rather
than "planners" - overemphasize the short term and care less about the
future than conventional theory would predict
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(see Thaler, 1991)</xref>
          .
Myopia helps account for impulsive behavior and for people's inability, some
of the time, to stop smoking or drinking, to spend wisely, or to save
money over time. Sometimes people take steps to overcome their own
myopia. Conventional analysis might explain the underlying phenomena
by reference to tastes; perhaps people have strong preferences for early
consumption and simply discount the future.7 In many settings, the
conventional and behavioral accounts will offer similar predictions. But some
anomalies - in particular, precommitment strategies, practices of mental
6. Some of this work overlaps with that based on "signaling"; see Eric Posner
(1998). The difference lies in the suggestion that sometimes people will act fairly even
if no one is observing.
        </p>
        <p>
          7. This is the tendency in Becker (1997).
accounting, and different effects of punishments with the same expected
value - seem hard to explain without introducing behavioral factors
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(see
Thaler, 1991, pp. 77-90)</xref>
          . These points are relevant to law insofar as they
help explain cooling-off periods and compulsory savings programs and
also insofar as they help make sense, on normative grounds, of apparently
paternalistic regulation.
        </p>
        <p>Bounded rationality. The idea of bounded rationality includes several
different points. The first involves the kinds of cognitive errors that can
come from biases in judgment and from efforts to economize on
decision costs ("heuristics")- Biases fall in various categories; they include
hindsight bias, optimistic bias, and extremeness aversion. Efforts to
economize on decision costs are responsible for rules of thumb , or heuristics.
Rules of thumb - as in the process of deciding on appropriate numbers (for
many things, including real estate prices or pain-and-suffering awards) by
choosing an "anchor" and then making adjustments - reduce the costs of
making decisions, but they may not be fully rational if people could make
far fewer errors by acting as good Bayesians.</p>
        <p>A second form of bounded rationality comes from framing effects.
People's reaction to a choice may depend on how it is described; hence
identical, but differently worded, problems can elicit quite different responses.
Consider clients deciding whether to settle or to go to trial. If they are
told that, of 100 litigants, 90 who go to trial win, they may be far more
likely to go to trial than if they are told that of 100 litigants, 10 who go
to trial lose (cf. Redelmeier, Rozin, and Kahneman, 1993).</p>
        <p>Some aspects of bounded rationality are modelled by prospect theory ,
which is intended as a more accurate description of behavior than expected
utility theory. For purposes of law, the first key feature of prospect theory,
departing from expected utility theory, is that people are loss averse , that
is, they dislike losses more than they like corresponding gains (a topic
taken up below). It follows that the value function is less steep for losses
than for gains. The second key finding is that people care a great deal
about certainty (thus people would prefer a reduction of risk from 0.1 to
0.0 to a reduction of 0.3 to 0.1). The value function identified by prospect
theory is defined over some reference point, which appears natural but
can be manipulated (a topic also discussed below). The value function is
also concave for losses and convex for gains, a shape based on the finding
that the difference between 0 and 100 appears greater than the difference
between 1,000 and 1,100, no matter what the sign of the magnitudes. An
important implication is that people are risk seeking for losses (they would
choose an 80% chance to lose $4,000 over a certain loss of $3,000) and
risk averse for gains (they would prefer a certain gain of $3,000 over an
80% chance to gain $4,500).</p>
        <p>A recent survey collects a wide range of real world practices or
analogies tending to support prospect theory; many of them are relevant to law
(see Camerer, forthcoming). Drawing on that survey (and the studies cited
there), consider the following examples:</p>
        <p>• There is a longstanding puzzle about the reason for the "equity
premium," by which investors sacrifice a great deal by their choices of bonds
as compared to stocks; stocks have a much higher average return. The
equity premium seems best explained by the fact that people are not averse
to variable returns but are (consistently with prospect theory) especially
averse to losses in a given year (see Benartzi and Thaler, 1995).</p>
        <p>• Prospect theory predicts that, since people dislike incurring losses,
investors will be willing to hold onto stocks that have lost value (compared
to purchase price) and will be eager to sell stocks that have risen in
value. This result has been confirmed by a careful field study (see Odean,
forthcoming).</p>
        <p>• Pennsylvania and New Jersey offered the same basic insurance
packages, including an inexpensive one without a right to sue and a more
expensive one with a right to sue. In Pennsylvania, the default option was
the less costly one; in New Jersey, the default option was the more
expensive one. Consistently with loss aversion, a majority selected the default
option in both states.</p>
        <p>• If consumers are loss averse, they will dislike price increases more
than they like the gain from price cuts, and the amount by which they
will reduce purchases when prices rise will be greater than the amount by
which they will increase purchases when prices fall. Studies have shown
this asymmetry in price elasticities for both eggs and orange juice.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 125</title>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>2. Fairness and Homo Reciprocam: Sacrificing Material</title>
        <p>Self-interest, with Special Reference to Kindness
and Spite</p>
        <p>
          Economists sometimes assume that people are self-interested, in the
sense that they are focused on their own welfare rather than that of
others and in the sense that material welfare is what most concerns them.
For some people some of the time, this is certainly true, and it is a
useful simplifying assumption; for many projects in the economic analysis of
law, it is unexceptionable. But people also want to be treated fairly, and
they may be willing to punish people who treat them unfairly, even at the
expense of their material self-interest. People may also want to act fairly,
and, perhaps even more important, they want to be seen to act fairly,
especially but not only among nonstrangers. For purposes of understanding
law, what is especially important is that people may sacrifice their
economic self-interest in order to be, or to appear, fair. As Robert Axelrod
showed more than a decade ago, reciprocal fairness - or kindness,
understood as a willingness to sacrifice material self-interest - can be quite
important (see Axelrod, 1984). People may meet kindness with kindness
and unkindness with spite.8 It follows that rather than being homo
economicus , people may be homo reciprocans
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Fehr and Gachter, 1998,
and unpublished study; Fehr and Schmidt, unpublished study)</xref>
          , in the sense
that people respond kindly to gifts and retaliate when mistreated, even at
the expense of their material self-interest.9 Those interested in behavioral
law and economics have only begun to explore the implications of this
phenomenon for law.
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-2">
        <title>2. 1 . A Simple Game</title>
        <p>Consider, for example, the ultimatum game.10 The people who run
the game give some money, on a provisional basis, to the first of two
players. The first player is instructed to offer some part of the money to
8. For a formal discussion, see Rabin (1993).</p>
        <p>9. With respect to homo reciprocans , I am simplifying here some complex
arguments. An early discussion of kindness and retaliation in the labor market is Akerlof
(1982).</p>
        <p>
          10. An outline of the game and results can be found in
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">Thaler (1991)</xref>
          . For recent
discussion, see Slonim and Roth (1998), which found a slight decline with very high
stakes, but offers still far above what conventional analysis would predict.
the second player. If the second player accepts that amount, he can keep
what is offered, and the first player gets to keep the rest. But if the second
player rejects the offer, neither player gets anything. Both players are
informed that these are the rules. No bargaining is allowed. Using standard
assumptions about rationality, self-interest, and choice, economists predict
that the first player should offer a penny and the second player should
accept. But this is not what happens. Offers usually average between 30%
and 40% of the total. Offers of less than 20% are often rejected. Often
there is a 50-50 division. These results generally cut across the level of
the stakes (in poor countries, the game has been played for several months
in wages, with no difference in results) and also across diverse cultures
(see Thaler, 1992).
        </p>
        <p>The results of the ultimatum game are highly suggestive. Perhaps
people will not violate norms of fairness, even when doing so is in their
economic self-interest, at least if the norm violations would be public.11
There are several reasons why they might fail to violate such norms:
anticipated spite (note the behavior of the responders in the ultimate game);
internalized norms; or adverse reputational effects.12 Some people may
exhibit a form of "inequity aversion," in the sense that they will sacrifice
material payoffs in order to produce more equitable outcomes.13 Rabin
(1993) has developed a formal model designed to show the role of
fairness in individual judgments. He shows that people may sacrifice material
self-interest to help people who have been kind; that they may sacrifice
their material self-interest to publish unkind people; and that these
motivations have a smaller effect if the material consequences of sacrificing
becomes larger.</p>
        <p>As emphasized by Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler (1998, p. 1511), of
special importance to fairness-related behavior is the selection of a reference
1 1 . An especially striking set of experimental outcomes can be found in Fehr and
Tougareva (unpublished study).</p>
        <p>12. Compare the results in the Dictator Game, where an owner of a sum is permitted
to allocate it as he wishes; here there is a some tendency toward sharing the proceeds,
though it is far less pronounced than in the ultimate game; note also that sharing
decreases with anonymity (see Bohnet and Frey, 1999; Kagel and Roth, 1994, pp.
298-302).</p>
        <p>13. See Fehr and Schmidt (unpublished study). This paper shows how a certain
number of inequity-averse people can help produce what the authors call cooperative,
competitive, and noncooperative outcomes.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 127</title>
      <p>
        point or reference transaction. Price increases in the event of unanticipated
events - for example, a snowstorm - are likely to be perceived as unfair,
insofar as they represent a departure from the status quo, which provides
the relevant reference point
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Kahneman, Knetsch, and Thaler, 1986;
Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler, 1998, pp. 1510-15)</xref>
        . What counts as unfair
depends on what it is (perceived as) a deviation from, and the perception
may be manipulable by participants in markets or in law.
      </p>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>2.2. Implications for Law</title>
        <p>
          This account bears on a variety of questions of relevance to law. It
helps explain why in close-knit communities legal intervention may not
be required to solve collective action problems, and indeed law may not
much matter, as people organize their affairs via norms rather than law
(see Ellickson, 1991). Norms of reciprocity may well develop because
people have the ability to impose social sanctions on those who do not
comply with those norms, thus creating a self-enforcing system of
reciprocity. In the same vein, experimental work shows a high degree of
cooperation in prisoners' dilemma situations, especially when people are
speaking with one another.14 Experimental work also shows a large role
for reciprocal altruism in labor markets
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(Fehr and Gachter, 1998)</xref>
          . A
possible general conclusion is that legal intervention is not always necessary
to solve prisoners' dilemmas. Social norms may well do the work of law,
producing cooperation where materially self-interested agents would fail
to do so. The agents who populate behavioral economics are, in this
important respect, less likely to need government help than are the agents
who populate conventional economics.
        </p>
        <p>Some experimental work suggests too that markets may not work the
way they are supposed to, because people's judgments of fairness
operate to discipline and constrain market behavior. It appears, for example,
that people would like to punish companies that violate perceived
fairness, even when they are acting rationally, as, for example, by increasing
the price of snow shovels after a snowstorm (see Kahneman, Knetsch, and
14. See Kagel and Roth (1994, pp. 111-73), for an overview. There is thus a close
relation between some behavioral research and the growing and apparently independent
interest in regulation via social norms. See Ellickson (1991). I believe that ultimately
these two lines of inquiry will merge into a unitary field of inquiry.
Thaler, 1986b).15 Such increases are widely perceived as unfair.
Departures from the reference point that is relevant for fairness judgments - the
presnowstorm price - are strongly disapproved. This point may help
explain the existence of otherwise puzzling legal barriers to self-interested
behavior. Here there is much room for future work. Do companies always
raise prices when circumstances create short-term scarcity? Are there, in
fact, social constraints on price increases for snow shovels after a
snowstorm, or for umbrellas during a rainstorm? Do these seemingly small
examples bear on the setting of wages and on interindustry wage
differentials (see Thaler, 1992, pp. 36-49)? It may well be that contracting
parties are reluctant to take advantage of the misfortunes of another, partly
because of social constraints on self-interested behavior; thus, the idea of
the "efficient breach" may misdescribe contracting reality, especially when
reputational interests are involved. Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler suggest the
possibility that fairness judgments help account for the content of law, by
outlawing unfair departures from a reference point (1998, pp. 1510-16).</p>
        <p>A particular finding of the ultimatum game is that people are
sometimes willing to sacrifice their economic self-interest in other to punish
wrongdoers. Indeed, there are familiar circumstances in which a gain to
another person is a loss to an agent (consider a bad divorce), and this
point - the starting point for an economic analysis of spite - may bear on
the prospects for settlement. Suggestive data have been gathered by Ward
Farnsworth, indicating that bargaining does not occur in part because of
spite (see Farnsworth 1999). Investigating approximately twenty nuisance
cases in which injunctive relief was sought and either granted or denied
after full litigation before a judge, Farns worth found no case in which the
parties tried to contract around the judge's order. Farnsworth's interviews
suggested a behavioral explanation. The victorious parties felt specially
entitled to the right that they won, and they did not want to confer any
benefit on the party they had bested, even if the benefit might turn out to
be mutual.</p>
        <p>15. A study at the University of Chicago Law School found, however, that Chicago
law students do not share this widespread fairness judgment. See Houston and Sunstein,
(forthcoming 1999). It would be interesting to know if this is a law student effect or a
University of Chicago Law School effect.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 129</title>
      <sec id="sec-7-1">
        <title>2.3. Might Increased Costs Sometimes Increase Behavior?</title>
        <p>Behavioral work involving reciprocity bears on the effects of
financial incentives. Usually it is assumed that people will do less of some
activity X if they are forced to pay for doing it. But in an intriguing
real-world study, it has been shown that this is not the case (see Gneezy
and Rustichini, forthcoming). The introduction of small fines for lateness
in picking up children at school actually produced more, not less, in the
way of lateness. The behavioral explanation would be that when no fine
is in place, parents do not wish to impose on teachers, perhaps for
reputational reasons, perhaps for reasons of conscience. Parents will rarely be
late, and even more rarely very late, because the reputational and psychic
cost of doing so is high (if teachers will not be paid in the event of
lateness). Or a system of reciprocal altruism may be in place: Teachers agree
to spend a little extra time at work, and parents agree to do what they can
to arrive on time, so as to minimize the burden. But when a fine is
introduced, parents believe that they can "buy" the extra labor, and hence
the cost (reputational and psychic) associated with lateness is reduced or
removed. Hence, there is more lateness; the introduction of a fine
actually reduces the costs of lateness. It would be valuable to see under what
circumstances this result could be replicated. (If the economic cost of
lateness is quite high, one would not expect to see the fine resulting in more
lateness.)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-7-2">
        <title>3. Myopia: The Case of Mental Accounting</title>
        <p>
          A simple and apparently uncontroversial assumption of most
economists is that money is "fungible." Indeed, if anything is fungible, money is.
But the assumption appears to be false, at least some of the time. As Thaler
suggests, many people act as if their money resides in compartments
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(see
Thaler, 1991, pp. 25-47)</xref>
          . In other words, people create "frames" that
result in mental accounts through which losses and gains, including losses
and gains in simple monetary terms, are not fungible with each other. To
some extent, mental accounting can be viewed as a response to, and an
example of, myopia. Frequently mental accounting works as a method
by which people can overcome their own impulsiveness or tendency to
overlook the long term.
        </p>
        <p>A glance at ordinary practice shows that people often organize
decisions in terms of separate budgets and accounts, and they often segment
these accounts. Some money is for retirement; some is for vacation; some
is for college tuition; some is for mortgage or rental payments. Mental
accounting is an important aspect of financial self-control; it can be
understood as a kind of precommi tment strategy.16</p>
        <p>What are the implications of mental accounting for law and policy?
There appears to be a demand for publicly created mental accounts,
perhaps as a self-control strategy, as, for example, with Social Security and
other programs with an apparent paternalistic dimension. One reason for
mental accounting is to help with possible problems of self-control, and
people may enlist law in this endeavor. If so, it is hard to object to the
resulting enactments as "paternalistic." The better view would be that they
reflect a form of autopaternalism. Some statutes that appear to prevent
people from making choices as they wish may be best understood as
responsive to the widespread desire to have separate mental accounts. Of
course, there are private mechanisms for accomplishing this goal; lawyers
will not understand those mechanisms well unless they see that money
itself is not fungible.</p>
        <p>The practice of mental accounting suggests that that government may
be able to create certain mental accounts by creative policy making. If
government wants to encourage savings, for example, it may seek to give
distinctive labels to certain accounts, so as to discourage people from
dipping into those accounts too readily. This idea suggests the possibility
of restructuring social security, not by abolishing any effort to promote
savings for old age but by facilitating the creation of specified private
accounts, perhaps accompanied by penalties for current use.</p>
        <p>The practice of mental accounting also suggests that redistributive
legal rules may be more effective than they seem (see Jolis, 1998). Jolis
suggests that, although taxes operate "as a direct charge against incomes,"
the costs of redistributive rules "may be viewed as expenditures out of
income . . . and heightened expenditures out of income may produce fewer
16. Mental accounting is also a familiar strategy among people winning in a casino
or gambling house who subsequently differentiate between "house money" (i.e.,
winnings) and "their" money. Continuing to play with the money won and losing (with
almost certain probability) does not appear to involve the same type of "waste" as
playing with and losing the same amount of money that had been obtained in another way
(see Dawes, 1998).</p>
        <p>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 131
work disincentives than direct charges against income" (1998, p. 1670). If
this is so, those who receive money (from tort law or taxation) and those
who give money (from tort law or taxation) may respond differently,
depending on whether tort law or taxation is responsible. Those who are
taxed may face a stronger work disincentive than those who are faced
with a redistributive legal rule.</p>
        <p>Most of behavioral work involving mental accounting deals with
money, but the phenomenon is far broader. In the moral domain, for
example, there is reason to think that people engage in a form of accounting
as well (see Kuran, 1998), treating actions of which they are ashamed,
or proud, as falling in distinct compartments and possibly as requiring a
kind of compensation from future acts in the same compartment.
Someone who has acted uncharitably toward a student or a friend might, for
example, act quite generously to another student or friend, so as to even
out the account. This effect can be felt at the social level as well, as the
demand for law reflects a desire to produce sensible accounts (by, for
example, going slow on clean water legislation after having gone quickly
on clean air legislation). Of course, much more work would be necessary
to turn these speculations into something more systematic.</p>
        <p>
          Because people are myopic, and have high and sometimes hyperbolic
discount rates, it may be necessary to rethink conventional economic
analysis of the criminal law
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler, 1998, pp.
153841)</xref>
          . If criminals do not concern themselves with the future, and focus
on the short term, a system of reliable but relatively lenient punishments
may have far more deterrent power than a system of infrequently enforced
but stringent punishments. And for young people who greatly discount
the future, an increase in punishment from, say, twenty years to
twentyfive or thirty years may have little effect at all on the level of criminal
activity.
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-7-3">
        <title>4. Bounded Rationality</title>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>4.1. Loss Aversion</title>
      <p>A great deal of work in behavioral law and economics emphasizes a key
finding of prospect theory (see Kahneman and Tversky, 1979): in many
contexts, people are averse to losses (Thaler, 1992, pp. 70-74). People are
more displeased with losses than they are pleased with equivalent gains
roughly speaking, twice as displeased. Contrary to conventional economic
theory, out-of-pocket costs can loom much larger than opportunity costs.</p>
      <p>Loss aversion has many implications for positive and prescriptive
analysis of law, and it therefore deserves separate treatment here. Consider the
following:</p>
      <p>
        • Many people interested in behavioral law and economics have
noticed that loss aversion suggests that the Coase theorem is in one respect
quite wrong
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see, e.g., Hoffman and Spitzer, 1993; Jolis, Sunstein, and
Thaler, 1998)</xref>
        . 17 Recall that the Coase theorem says that, when
transactions costs are zero, the allocation of the initial entitlement will not matter,
in the sense that it will not affect the ultimate state of the world, which
will come from voluntary bargaining. The theorem can lead to
inaccurate predictions because the allocation of the legal entitlement may well
matter to the ultimate outcome. This is because those who are initially
allocated an entitlement are likely to value it more than those without the
legal entitlement.
      </p>
      <p>
        Endowment effects have been shown for both coffee mugs and
chocolate bars; the initial allocation of the right much affects the ultimate
outcome (see Thaler, 1992, pp. 63-78). The legal entitlement creates an
endowment effect
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(a term originally coined by Thaler, 1991, pp. 7-10)</xref>
        ; that
is, a greater valuation stemming from the mere fact of endowment. In
experimental research, for example, an endowment effect has been shown for
default rules in the law of contract. The parties' understanding of the
default rule much affected their ultimate outcome, and different default rules
produced different outcomes (see Korobkin, 1998a). As noted, a natural
experiment in the real world, involving choice of insurance policies,
pro17. Loss aversion does not suggest that the Coase theorem is wrong insofar as it
suggests that when transactions costs are zero, the result will be efficient regardless
of who gets the initial entitlement; it suggests only that even when transactions costs
are the zero, the allocation of the initial entitlement can affect the ultimate outcome.
Different results can both be efficient. Note also that conventional analysis predicts
one circumstance under which the result under zero transaction cost bargaining will
differ with the initial assignment of rights: wealth effects. When there are only two
people in a desert, and they are stranded, the initial allocation will be final, regardless
of transaction costs (see Richard Posner 1998, p. 56). The contribution of behavioral
law and economics is to show that the initial assignment may matter even when wealth
effects are small or zero.
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 133</title>
      <p>duced a similar result (see Camerer, forthcoming); in both cases citizens
could change from the default policy, but in both cases, the default
option tended to stick. There is a great deal of evidence that prospect theory
captures real-world behavior (see Camerer, forthcoming).</p>
      <p>
        From this research, it is reasonable to hypothesize, for example, that
workers allocated a (waivable) right to be discharged only for cause may
well value that right far more than they would be if employers were
allocated a (waivable) right to discharge employees at will. The ultimate
result of the bargain may be quite different depending on the initial
allocation of the entitlement (see Issacharoff 1996). Thus, breathers of air may
well value their (tradable) right to be free from air pollution far more than
they would if polluters had been given a (tradable) right to emit
polluting substances into the air. Especially large endowment effects have been
shown in the environmental area, for reasons that remain ill-understood
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">(see Sunstein, 1997, chap. 10)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>• Loss aversion raises serious questions about the tort system. Should
damages measure the amount that would restore an injured party to the
status quo ante, or should they reflect the amount that an injured party
would demand to be subject to the injury before the fact? An intriguing
experiment by McCaffery, Kahneman, and Spitzer (1995) suggests that
people serving as jurors believe that the amount that would be demanded
preinjury is far greater than the amount that would restore the status quo
ante. The legal system appears generally to see the compensation question
as the latter one, though it does not seem to have made this choice in any
systematic way.</p>
      <p>
        • Loss aversion also bears on appropriate remedies for violations of
tort law. When should courts award injunctions, and when should they
award damages? The answer may be affected by an understanding of the
circumstances in which people would demand a great deal - perhaps a
lot more than market value - to part with their good. It has been
suggested that the legal system shows an awareness of loss aversion insofar
as it awards specific performance for certain losses
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Rachlinski and
Jourden, 1998)</xref>
        . There is also reason to think that the legal system
recognizes that a loss will be valued differently from an equivalent gain (see
Cohen and Knetsch, 1992). And in an experimental setting, an
endowment effect was shown for goods protected by a property rule, but not
for goods protected by a liability rule, in a way that has important
iming of choice matters; the introduction of (unchosen, apparently irrelevant)
alternatives into the frame can alter the outcome.
      </p>
      <p>Extremeness aversion suggests that a simple axiom of
conventional economic theory - involving the irrelevance of added, unchosen
alternatives - is wrong. It also has consequences for legal advocacy and
judgment as well as for predictions about the effects of law. How can
a preferred option best be framed as the "compromise" choice? When
should a lawyer argue in the alternative, and what kinds of alternative
arguments are most effective? Other things being equal, juries and judges
may well try to choose a compromise solution, and what "codes" as the
compromise solution depends on what alternatives are made available.
And in elections, medical interventions, and policy making, compromise
effects may matter a great deal, as people tend to choose the approach
that seems to fall between the extremes.</p>
      <p>
        Optimistic Bias and the Law of Risk. Ordinarily, human beings tend to
be optimistic about themselves. Even factually informed people, aware of
aggregate data, tend to think that risks are less likely to materialize for
themselves than for others. Thus, for example, more than 90% of drivers
think that they are safer than other drivers and less likely to be involved
in serious accidents
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">(see Taylor, 1989, pp. 10-11)</xref>
        . Owners of companies
have an exaggerated sense of the likelihood that they will continue to be
in business; in experiments and in the real world, entry into markets seems
affected by excessive optimism (see Camerer and Lovallo, 1999). People
also believe that they are peculiarly unlikely to get divorced (see Baker
and Emery, 1993). There is systematic overconfidence in risk judgments,
as the vast majority of people believe that they are less likely than other
people to be subject to infection from AIDS, heart attacks, asthma, and
many other health risks
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">(see Weinstein, 1989)</xref>
        . Reflecting illusions about
their own practices, gay men appear systematically to underestimate the
chance that they will get AIDS, even though they do not lack information
about AIDS risks in general (see Bauman and Siegel, 1987). One of the
most depressing findings in cognitive psychology is that only one group
of people have an accurate sense of their own capacities and of what other
people think of them: the chronically depressed
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">(see Taylor, 1989, pp.
3940)</xref>
        . In an illustration of special poignancy in the academic setting, about
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 137</title>
      <p>94% of college professors rate themselves as better than their average
colleagues at their jobs (see Baumeister, 1998).</p>
      <p>
        If people are unrealistically optimistic, an understanding of risk-related
facts may not produce the anticipated changes in behavior. If the goal is
to induce less in the way of drug use or drunk driving, government should
attend to the problem that people will exaggerate the safety of their own
behavior; hence the slogan, "drive defensively; watch out for the other
guy" had a high degree of behavioral ingenuity. On the normative side,
those interested in behavioral law and economics have noticed that
unrealistic optimism creates a distinctive problem for conventional objections to
paternalism in law
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler, 1998, pp. 1541-43)</xref>
        . If
people tend to believe that they are relatively free from risks, they may lack
accurate information even if they know statistical facts. A great deal of
further work remains to be done on this problem. Unrealistic optimism may
well be counteracted by markets and market-like forces, though even here
there is contrary evidence (see Langevoort, 1997). And optimistic bias
may help explain why so many people enter "winner-take-all" markets
those in which the fortunate few do enormously better than most - even
when the probability of success is quite low and the discounted value of
the investment is also low (see Frank and Cook, 1995). Legal
intervention, perhaps in the form of information, perhaps in the form of corrective
taxes, may be necessary to supply a corrective.
      </p>
      <p>Self-Serving Bias and Settlements . We have seen that people sometimes
care about fairness, but their judgments about fairness are systematically
self-serving. In any random couple, it is highly likely that addition of
answers to the question, "What percentage of the domestic work do you
do?" will produce a number greater than 100%. The point bears on the
otherwise largely hard-to-explain phenomenon of bargaining impasses (see
Babcock and Loewenstein, 1997). Why do some cases fail to settle? Why
does the legal system spend so much on dispute settlement?</p>
      <p>As suggested by Jolis et al., part of the answer lies in the fact that
self-serving bias - a belief that one deserves more than other people tend
to think - affects both parties to a negotiation, and this makes agreement
very difficult.20 Babcock, Wang, and Loewenstein (1996) have studied
the consequences of self-serving bias for negotiation impasse in public
school teacher contract negotiations in Pennsylvania. They show that
selfserving bias, in the form of fairness judgments about what
communities are "comparable," help account for impasse and strikes. Experimental
studies reach a similar conclusion, as students, including law students,
reach quite disparate judgments about what would be fair after they have
been assigned to one or another side in a tort dispute (see Babcock et
al., 1995; Loewenstein et al., 1993). Thus, there were large self-serving
biases in assessments of the judge's award. The subjects acting as the
plaintiffs guessed an average $14,527 higher than the defendants, and the
plaintiffs' fair settlement values averaged $17,709 higher than those of the
defendants.</p>
      <p>Hindsight Bias and Legal Mistakes. According to a familiar cliché,
hindsight has 20-20 vision. The cliché has important truth, one with
considerable relevance to law (see Rachlinski, 1998). People often think, in
hindsight, that things that happened were inevitable, or nearly so. Of course,
the fact that something happened provides some information about the
risky behavior. But people tend to believe that something was nearly
inevitable if it actually happened, even if this is quite false. The resulting
"hindsight bias" can much distort legal judgment if, for example, juries
end up thinking that an accident that occurred would inevitably have
occurred. Judgments about whether someone was negligent may well be
affected by this bias; if a bad outcome occurred, juries are likely to
believe that it was inevitable. For decision makers prone to hindsight bias,
the line between strict liability and negligence may be quite thin.</p>
      <p>It is possible that many rules in the law are attuned to hindsight bias.
An extensive study by Rachlinski (1998) finds a number of illustrations, as
in patent law, where courts are asked to assess whether an invention was
"nonobvious" by examining the time of invention, with certain factors
designed to ensure that present judgments about what is "obvious" do
not interfere with the judgment. To take another example, the "business
judgment" rule in corporate law prevents legal authorities from
secondguessing managerial decisions in contexts in which the second-guessing
may be systematically biased. Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler (1998, pp.
152731) suggest that an understanding of hindsight bias might show that legal
rules should be changed in cases involving alleged negligence, in order</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 139</title>
      <p>to counteract the judgment that because an unfortunate event happened, it
was bound to happen.</p>
      <sec id="sec-11-1">
        <title>4.3. A Note on Framing and Legal Ethics</title>
        <p>Loss aversion and extremeness aversion suggest possible "framing"
effects. A change can be framed as a loss or a gain, and whether an option
looks extreme depends on the comparison set, which can be manipulated.
Cognitive psychologists, above all Kahneman and Tversky, have shown
many such framing effects. An especially important one involves drawing
the subject's attention to good outcomes or bad outcomes. Thus, if people
are told, "of 100 people who have this operation, 90 are alive five years
later," they will respond far more favorably than if they are told, "of 100
people who have this operation, 10 are dead five years later." The point
bears on government information campaigns and also on legal ethics. It
would be easy for a lawyer to draw attention to the percentage of victories
or losses (even if the lawyer has aggregate data), and it may matter a great
deal which the lawyer chooses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>4.4. Heuristics</title>
      <p>Behavioral economists and cognitive psychologists have uncovered a
wide array of heuristic devices that people use to simplify their tasks.
Heuristics are not biases, and often they are good, because they
economize on decision costs; but they can lead to several mistakes. The major
implications have to do with the demand for law (fueled, often, by the
availability heuristic), the nature of legal reasoning (often conducted by
reference to precedent), and the setting of damage awards (much affected
by anchoring, and prone to the distinctive problems that come from
"scaling without a modulus").</p>
      <p>Availability, with a Note on Social Influences , Dupes , Freeloaders , and
Cascades. People tend to think that events are more likely if an
example is readily called to mind or "available" (see Kahneman and Tversky,
1979). If pervasive, the availability heuristic will produce systematic
errors. For example, assessments of risk will be pervasively biased, in the
sense that people will think that some risks (of a nuclear accident, for
example) are high, whereas others (of a stroke, for example) are
relatively low. There is evidence that people's judgments about risk levels are
much affected by the availability heuristic (see Baron, 1994). The
availability heuristic appears to affect the demand for law, especially in the area
of risk regulation; Noll and Krier (1990) and Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler
(1998, pp. 1518-21) have discussed this point in considerable detail.</p>
      <p>Of course, the availability heuristic operates in an emphatically social
environment, and social influences may "amplify" the effects of the
heuristic, in a way that helps account for much behavior, including that behavior
that produces the supply of and demand for law (see Kuran and Sunstein,
1999). People often think what (they think) other people think. Sometimes
they do what (they think) others do. Partly this is because when a person
lacks much personal information, he will sensibly rely on the information
of others (see Hirshleifer, 1995). If you do not know whether pesticides
cause cancer, or whether hazardous waste dumps are a serious social
problem, you may as well follow what other people seem to think. And partly
this is because of reputational influences. If most people think that
hazardous waste dumps are a serious social problem, or that laws should ban
hate crimes, you might go along with them so that they do not think that
you are ignorant, malevolent, or callous.21</p>
      <p>For the most part, an emphasis on informational and reputational
influences is entirely consistent with conventional economics, though it has
implications that have not been sufficiently exploited. An analyst attuned
to informational and reputational influences might predict, for example,
that people are more likely to vote if they think that most people are
voting; that tax compliance is more likely if people think that most people
comply; that college students are more likely to drink heavily, or to use
unlawful drugs, if they think that this is what most college students are
doing; and that teenagers in poor neighborhoods are more likely to join
gangs if they think that most teenagers are gang members.22 Behavioral
economics adds two points. The first is an understanding of how the
availability heuristic interacts with these influences; sometimes a salient event
or anecdote can interact with informational and reputational forces so as
to create cascade effects (see Kuran and Sunstein, 1999). In addition,
behavioral economics emphasizes the role of reciprocity in producing these
effects. People do not want to be either dupes or freeloaders, and hence
21. Compare the discussion of signaling and witch-hunts in Eric Posner (1998).
22. For evidence, see Perkins (1997, pp. 177-206).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-13">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 141</title>
      <p>they are most likely to contribute to some social goal if they believe that
others are doing so as well.</p>
      <p>
        These points have a wide range of implications for the content of law.
They help explain the supply of, and the demand for, government
regulation. "Availability cascades" help drive law and policy in both fortunate
and unfortunate directions. They can eliminate public torpor by drawing
attention to problems that, although serious, have long been overlooked.
On the other hand, they can produce public concern or outrage about
problems that have little claim to the public fisc. An important task for
the legal system is therefore how to promote better priority setting.
Anchoring , with Special Reference to Damage Awards. Often people
make judgments about appropriate numbers, including probabilities, on
the basis of an initial value, or "anchor," for which they make
insufficient adjustments (see Kahneman and Tversky, 1979). When people lack
information, this may be the best that they can do. The problem is that
the initial value may have an arbitrary or irrational source. When this
is so, the assessment may go badly wrong. Jury judgments about damage
awards, for example, are likely to be based on an anchor; this can produce
a high level of arbitrariness. There is considerable experimental evidence
to this effect; in particular, the plaintiff's demand makes a great deal of
difference, in a process of "the more you ask for, the more you get"
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(see
Chapman and Bornstein, 1996)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>If the plaintiff's demand influences jury awards, it is possible that the
legal system should take corrective steps by, for example, allowing
appellate courts to exercise greater control in the interest of preventing
unjustified unequal treatment, or by preventing the jury from hearing demands
that are legally unacceptable, for constitutional or other reasons. It is quite
possible that an unlawfully high demand from the plaintiff will greatly
inflate the resulting award, and even if that award is itself within legal limits,
there is something troublesome about allowing such a demand to be its
"anchor" or basic source. A great deal of work remains to be done on
the real-world effects of anchors when juries and judges are dealing with
dollar amounts.</p>
      <p>Case-Based Decisions and Decision Costs. Legal reasoning is
pervasively analogical in character; judges often reason by reference to past
cases. Conventional economics offers some explanations; analogical
reasoning, or at least respect for the past, can increase predictability and at the
same time reduce decision costs for judges. But conventional approaches
have yet to explain why reasoning "by analogy" is so pervasive.23</p>
      <p>Behavioral law and economics provides some insight into why this
might be so. If decision costs are put to one side, expected utility theory
is demanding, simply because it is difficult to calculate the expected costs
and benefits of alternatives. People often simplify their burdens by
reasoning from past cases and by taking small, reversible steps. Economists
have offered an account, behavioral in spirit but independent of law, of
an alternative to expected utility theory: case-based decision theory (see
Gilboa and Schmeidler, 1995). The account should be counted as a
genuine (though apparently inadvertent) contribution to jurisprudence. Those
who reason from past cases can reduce the burdens of thinking problems
through from the ground up, and in a way that may minimize the sum of
error costs and decision costs. An understanding of behavioral economics
may in this sense illuminate some important aspects of legal reasoning.</p>
      <sec id="sec-13-1">
        <title>4.5. Mapping Judgments Onto Dollars: "Scaling</title>
        <p>Without A Modulus"</p>
        <p>
          Often the legal system requires judges or juries to make judgments
of some kind and then to translate those judgments into dollar amounts.
How does this translation take place? Can it be done well? Behavior
evidence suggests that, in many contexts, normative judgments of a sort are
both predictable and nonarbitrary
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Sunstein, Kahneman, and Schkade,
1998)</xref>
          . With respect to bad behavior that might produce punitive
damages, for example, people come up with relatively uniform judgments on
a bounded numerical scale. At least it can be said that the judgment of
any group of twelve people is a good predictor of the judgments of other
groups of twelve people
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Sunstein, Kahneman, and Schkade, 1998)</xref>
          .
Similar findings have been made for environmental amenities in the
context of contingent valuation
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Kahneman, Schkade, and Sunstein, 1998)</xref>
          .
But the act of mapping those normative judgments onto an unbounded
dollar scale produces considerable "noise" and arbitrariness. When people
are asked how much a defendant should be punished for reckless conduct
23. See the skeptical remarks in Richard Posner (1990, pp. 86-100).
        </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-14">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 143</title>
      <p>
        leading to personal injury, the numbers they generate are highly variable,
and the decision of any particular group of twelve people cannot well
predict the judgments of other groups of twelve people
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Sunstein,
Kahneman, and Schkade, 1998)</xref>
        . This finding has been confirmed for
deliberating juries, where the relevant effects are extremely pronounced.24
      </p>
      <p>Insofar as this problem infects the award of damages, conventional
economists need not be troubled, but many economists are enthusiastic
about the process of contingent valuation, where similar problems have
been shown to arise. When people are asked how much they are willing
to pay to protect 2,000 birds, or 200 birds, the same kind of arbitrariness
has been found (see Kahneman and Ritov, 1994). The apparent reason is
that people have great trouble "scaling without a modulus," that is, they
are not in a good position to generate predictable dollar amounts when
they are not given a modulus, or standard, to compare with the case at
hand. The problem of scaling without a modulus occurs in many areas in
which juries (and judges) are asked to generate dollar amounts. It appears
in areas not involving dollars as well. Consider, for example, the
Americans with Disabilities Act, which makes it necessary to decide whether
a suggested accommodation is "reasonable" and whether it creates an
"undue hardship." There is great deal of variability in the law, not least
because it is extremely hard to decide whether a particular
accommodation is reasonable, or a particular hardship undue, without a modulus to
cabin the inquiry. (Cost-benefit analysis would work as well.) Or consider
the question of whether an occupational hazard creates a "significant risk"
within the meaning of judicial interpretations of the Occupational Safety
and Health Act. Without some kind of modulus, the bare idea of
"significance" is a recipe for arbitrariness.</p>
      <p>
        The legal system, however, frequently relies on the resulting highly
variable and unreliable measures. Thus, the award of damages for libel,
sexual harassment, and pain and suffering are infected by severe
difficulties, as is the award of punitive damages in general. An understanding
of those difficulties may well lead to concrete reform proposals. Perhaps
the "mapping" can occur by a legislative or regulatory body that decides,
in advance, on how a normative judgment made by a bounded numerical
24. The data have been collected and analyzed and will appear in a work in progress
by Schkade, Sunstein, and Kahneman (forthcoming).
scale can be translated into dollars. From the theoretical point of view,
the most ambitious work on these topics suggests that, in some settings, it
is best to assume that people have "attitudes" rather than preferences and
that attitudes have a distinctive structure and distinctive propensities
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see
Kahneman, Schkade, and Sunstein, 1998)</xref>
        . As noted, one of the
propensities of attitudes is toward a kind of "judgment reversal," as when, for
example, two cases are seen one way in isolation (with injury A
eliciting a higher punitive damage award than injury B, or harm A producing a
higher contingent valuation than harm B), but a quite different way when
the two cases are seen together (as the number for B becomes higher than
the number for A) (see Kahneman, Ritov, and Schkade, 1999).
4.6. Decision Utility and Experience Utility, with General Notes
on Paternalism
      </p>
      <p>In conventional economics, it is often assumed that the utility of
experience is best measured by the anticipated utility shown by people's
decisions. But a good deal of recent research (see Kahneman, 1996;
Loewenstein and Schkade, forthcoming) shows that there may well be
systematic differences between the utility expected at the time of decision
and the utility actually experienced as a result of decision. People's
judgments about their experience at the time of decision can be mistaken; they
may have a hard time assessing what the experience will actually be like.</p>
      <p>
        There are many examples of this divergence between decision utility
and experience utility. We can infer from the phenomenon of loss
aversion that people value goods more when they own them than when they
do not. This "endowment effect" has been observed in many settings
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(see
Thaler, 1991, pp. 167-86)</xref>
        . But in recent experiments, people have been
unable to predict the endowment effect, and thus unable to predict their
own tastes (see Loewenstein and Adler, 1995; Loewenstein and Schkade,
forthcoming). Behaviorally informed analysts have argued that this point
bears on when and whether to take workers' waivers of their legal rights
as sufficiently informed (see Issacharoff, 1996). This finding is paralleled
by many studies showing that people do not accurately predict the
consequences of certain major events, such as winning the lottery or becoming
paraplegic. (Winning the lottery produces much lower hedonic gains than
expected, and people adjust to becoming paraplegic much more easily
than expected [see Loewenstein and Schkade, forthcoming].)
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-15">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 145</title>
      <p>An especially important example of inaccurate anticipated utility comes
from a study dealing with HIV testing. People are quite terrified of their
reaction if they find that they are HIV positive; they predict a high
degree of panic and depression. But evidence suggests that people are able
to adapt fairly well to the bad news, and their panic and depression are
far less severe than they feared (see Sieff, Dawes, and Loewenstein,
forthcoming). Pessimistic expectations about how they would react to a positive
result might therefore lead people to "undertest"; people are likely to be
especially averse to undergoing a process of which they are very fearful. It
might follow that regulatory approaches - education, persuasion, financial
incentives, conceivably coercion - would make a good deal of sense.</p>
      <p>Some economists have urged that people have adequate information
about the risks of smoking and that additional regulation is therefore
inappropriate (see Viscusi, 1993). Perhaps most people do know many of
the basic "facts." But a study of high school students suggests a
problem. About one-third of adolescent smokers believed that there was no
risk from smoking a pack of cigarettes daily for the first few years
after starting to smoke. Young people who smoked believed that they were
personally less at risk from smoking. And 85% of high school teenagers
who smoked occasionally believed that they would not be smoking in five
years, whereas only 58% had actually quit after five years, and 37% had
increased their consumption. About 32% of those who smoked one pack
daily believed that they would quit in five years, but only 13% did in fact
(see Slovic, 1998).</p>
      <p>When people's decisions mispredict their experience, a common
argument against paternalism - to the effect that ordinary people choose
what will promote their welfare - is no longer plausible. Frank (1999),
for example, has argued that people often make purchases with the (false)
thought that these purchases will make them happier; the fact of the
systematic misjudgment makes him argue for a progressive consumption tax,
which will lead people in more productive directions. The question is
whether it will ultimately be possible to be systematic about issues of
this kind - to know, with some precision, when people's decisions will
produce bad experiences.</p>
      <p>From what has been said thus far, it would be possible to think that
behavioral law and economics leads to general sympathy for paternalism. If
people make mistakes about probabilities, because of various biases and
heuristics, should the law not help them? And if people mispredict their
own experience, is there not a great deal of room for paternalistic
assistance, even or especially if we care about utility? But behavioral law and
economics offers ambiguous answers to these questions, and certainly no
full-blown defense of paternalism. To be sure, people's "revealed
preferences" may not promote their well-being, and people are prone to make
mistakes. But government is subject to similar errors. Indeed, the demand
for law may produce the same kinds of problems that we find at the
individual level, and it is even possible that those problems will be
amplified by social influences and interest-group mobilization (see Kuran and
Sunstein, 1999). The cognitive errors made by ordinary people do seem
to be replicated in statutory and administrative law (see Viscusi, 1992, p.
149).</p>
      <p>
        It is probably best to think that behavioral economics produces less
basis for paternalism than for anti-antipaternalism, or in other words for a
pragmatic and empirical, rather than a dogmatic and a priori, inquiry into
whether government should disrupt individual choices
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(see Jolis, Sunstein,
and Thaler, 1998, pp. 1541-44)</xref>
        . There is also good reason to consider
institutional arrangements that might insulate government from some of
the unfortunate effects of cognitive and motivational errors. One of the
chief advantages of bureaucracy, at least in principle, is that it can ensure
that judgments will be based on facts rather than intuitions, in such a way
as to reduce the problems introduced by biases and heuristics (see Kuran
and Sunstein, 1999).
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-16">
      <title>5. The Future</title>
      <p>Behavioral law and economics remains in its early stages, and an
enormous amount remains to be done. For example, it is important to know the
circumstances in which people act quasi-rationally or instead rationally.
Perhaps markets, or market-like institutions, can lead people in the
direction of rationality. There is also a question whether behavioral law and
economics might not be too unruly to count as a "theory" at all; perhaps
it is simply a collection of effects. Finally, it is important to know what
strategies might be used to "debias" agents, or to help them to overcome
cognitive and motivational limitations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-17">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 147</title>
      <sec id="sec-17-1">
        <title>5.1. Parsimony and Predictions</title>
        <p>A possible objection to behavioral law and economics is that it is not
a theory at all but an unruly collection of phenomena and effects, often
based on ad hoc or unreliable evidence, and in any event lacking predictive
power. If behavioral law and economics points to a long list of heuristics,
and an equally long list of biases, and a complicated utility function, isn't
it doomed to ex post accounts? Isn't it better to work with the simpler
tools of conventional economics, just because of their simplicity? 25</p>
        <p>Probably the best brief conclusion is that it is unproductive to see a
general struggle between economic analysis of law and behavioral law
and economics. The question is what kinds of assumptions produce good
predictions about the effects of law, and this will vary with context.
Sometimes the simple assumptions of conventional analysis work entirely well;
sometimes it is necessary to introduce complications by, for example,
saying a bit more about what is counted in the utility function (such as a
desire to be treated fairly, and a willingness to punish those who act
unfairly), or incorporating bounded rationality (in the form, for example, of
optimistic bias or anchoring).</p>
        <p>Parsimonious assumptions have helped to identify the effects of (to take
just a few examples) rent control; increases in the cost of labor (through
the minimum wage, occupational safety and health, and related
legislation); statutes forbidding discrimination on the basis of age, race, and sex;
legal controls on new (as opposed to old) pollution sources; and much
more. In some settings, a great deal can be learned with the conventional
tools, and it is not necessary to introduce further complications. For
example, it is far from clear that behavioral economics can add much to
analysis of the effects of the minimum wage.26</p>
        <p>Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler (1998, pp. 1487-89) suggest, however, that
conventional economics sometimes achieves parsimony at the expense of
predictive power, which is absent when predictions are false or when no
predictions are offered at all. Behavioral law and economics promises to
25. This section borrows from and adapts some of the discussion in Jolis, Sunstein,
and Thaler (1998, pp. 1487-89); here, as elsewhere, Jolis and Thaler should not be
blamed for errors.</p>
        <p>26. Of course, this cannot be determined a priori. For example, an announcement
of an increase in the minimum wage might have a more-than-expected effect on the
supply of labor, because of information-processing issues.
be an improvement when it offers better predictions, even if with less
parsimonious tools.</p>
        <p>
          The most ambitious goal of conventional economics of course is to
provide a unitary theory of behavior. By itself, however, the notion of
"rationality" (the centerpiece of traditional analysis) provides no unitary
theory. The term is quite ambiguous, at least until it is specified. In
conventional economic analysis of law, it is sometimes unclear whether the
term means that people respond to incentives; that their decisions promote
their welfare; that they are self-interested; that they choose the best means
to achieving their goals, whatever their goals are; that they are consistent;
that they behave in accordance with expected utility theory; that they are
in some sense optimizers. Behavioral research has raised serious questions
about most of these, at least as an empirical matter
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(see Tversky, 1996)</xref>
          .
        </p>
        <p>For many uses of rationality in law, the crucial task is to specify what
counts as a cost and a benefit for the relevant agents. Is it a puzzle that
people vote? That they vote in snowstorms? That they use drugs in
college? That they use drugs more if they think most of their friends use
drugs? That they engage in unprotected sex? That they engage in more,
or less, unprotected sex when the risk of HIV infection increases? These
are questions about the content of the relevant utility function; without
knowing what people count as costs and benefits, the idea of
responsiveness to incentives is empty.27</p>
        <p>These puzzles cannot be evaluated in the abstract. In many areas
relevant to law, it is not necessary to worry a great deal about the content
of people's utility functions or about quasi-rationality; as I have noted,
conventional theory has enjoyed important successes. Whether it is
sufficient depends on the particular prediction and what the evidence shows.
The point here is that sometimes the theory leads to false predictions and
sometimes (when the underlying notions are not specified and disciplined)
to no predictions.</p>
        <p>27. Jolis, Sunstein, and Thaler write: "For example, consider whether it is a paradox
(as many economists think) if many people vote. If it is a paradox, so much the worse
for the rationality assumption; if it is not a paradox, what does the assumption predict?
Does it merely predict that people will respond to changes in conditions - for example,
fewer people will vote when it is snowing? If so, the prediction is not bad, but surely
it would be possible to say, after an unusually large vote amidst the storm, that more
people voted simply because voting seemed expecially valiant in those circumstances
(so much for predictions based on this form of rationality)" (1998, p. 1489).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-18">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 149</title>
      <p>But none of this supports behavioral economics. And it is true that in
its current state, behavioral economics is not a unitary theory, and partly
because of the sheer number of biases and heuristics, there are contexts
in which it is unable to make firm ex ante predictions. Might a
lossaverse person succumb to unrealistic optimism and engage in some kind
of otherwise inexplicable gamble? And do we know what to predict when
unrealistic optimism and loss aversion point in different directions?</p>
      <p>From the standpoint of positive theory, problems are certainly caused
by the sheer number of the effects that make up behavioral economics.
Some social theorists believe that, in the social sciences, the search for
lawlike generalizations is futile and that it is possible only to come up
with "mechanisms," which do not permit reliable predictions.28 It may
well be that some of behavioral law and economics will consist of ex post
descriptions of outcomes rather than genuine predictions. Analysis of this
kind is hardly worthless. And if this pessimistic view is not justified, the
only solution is to acquire more information, and to go back and forth
between data and theory, so as to see whether it is possible to know the
circumstances in which one or another effect is more likely to be at work.
A great deal remains to be done, not least in predicting conduct when
more than one effect is likely to be at work.</p>
      <p>But even for the moment, those interested in behavioral law and
economics do not lack predictions. For example, they will predict that, other
things being equal, the incidence of some cooperative activity (voting,
recycling, not smoking, not abusing drugs) is likely to increase when it is
perceived that most people are contributing. There is strong evidence to
this effect (see Perkins, 1997, pp. 177-206). They will also predict that
highly publicized incidents will have an extremely large effect on the
public demand for regulation. There is strong evidence to this effect as well
(see Kuran and Sunstein, 1999). They will predict, finally, that losses from
the status quo will register as more important than equivalent gains and
that this will affect individual reactions to law and also the demand for
law. There is also evidence that this is true (see Section 3 above).29
28. Jon Elster is the most influential advocate of this view. See Elster (1998,
chap. 1).</p>
      <p>29. A set of predictions about the effects of dollar responses can be found in
Kahneman, Ritov, and Schkade (1999).</p>
      <sec id="sec-18-1">
        <title>5.2. From Quasi-Rationality to Rationality?</title>
        <p>A second objection has to do with the domain of behavioral law and
economics. Might it not be the case that markets, for example, will turn
quasi-rational agents into fully rational agents? Work on the endowment
effect has shown that there is no such effects for tokens. The point
suggests that where goods are fully fungible - as in ordinary markets? - the
endowment effect may be irrelevant. It is also clear that markets will tend
to counteract some of the tendencies that we have discussed. It might
seem, for example, that people who are unrealistically optimistic, or who
are readily manipulated, will not do well in managing large companies.</p>
        <p>In some circumstances, market forces are indeed strong enough to make
behavioral economics irrelevant for predictive purposes. Then the question
becomes whether it is possible to identify those circumstances. This is a
large question, and we lack authoritative answers. When there are repeated
decisions, and when people have an opportunity to learn, the conventional
approach is more likely to be successful. But this statement leaves many
questions unanswered, and, as I have suggested, behavioral economics has
a role to play in markets and market-like settings as well. A great deal of
work remains to be done on this topic.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-18-2">
        <title>5.3. Debiasing and Institutional Solutions</title>
        <p>A final question involves the extent to which education or other
debiasing strategies can counteract cognitive and motivational distortions so as
to eliminate some of the effects described above. Is it possible for those
involved in law to push people toward greater rationality, in the process,
perhaps, lengthening human lives? What institutions work best at reducing
the effects of biases? Would a broader understanding of behavioral
economics produce learning and thus make it less necessary to use behavioral
economics?</p>
        <p>There is some work on these questions. Unfortunately, the relevant
work tends to show that quasi-rationality is robust and that it is hard to
do much about it. Even experts are susceptible to most of the effects
discussed here (see Baron, 1994). With respect to self-serving bias, it
does not do much good to ask people to read and consider both sides of
an argument; once people know what side they are on, their views seem
entrenched, and a reading of competing views seems only to strengthen
their convictions (in a form of "confirmatory bias"). The only intervention</p>
        <p>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 151
that seems to work is to require people to make their own arguments for
the other side (see Babcock, Loewenstein, and Issacharoff, 1993). The
good news is that some of these effects, such as a taste for fairness, should
not be characterized as distortions; on the contrary, such tastes may help
solve prisoners' dilemmas, and it is striking to see that economics majors
are less likely to adhere to fairness norms that produce solutions (see
Frank, 1993). (Perhaps economics majors, and law students immersed in
conventional economics, need to be "debiased"!)</p>
        <p>If debiasing generally does not work, we might think that social forces,
market and nonmarket, might press individuals and institutions in the
direction of metadecisions, or second-order decisions, that will make it more
likely that things will go well. We might expect, for example, boundedly
rational agents to come up with institutions that will overcome their own
bounded rationality. They might, for example, make a second-order
decision in favor of rules, so as to reduce the errors produced with on-the-spot
decisions (see Sunstein and Ullmann-Margalit, 1999). We might expect
social institutions to help counteract some of the relevant problems; certainly
an evolutionary account would so suggest.</p>
        <p>There is some affirmative evidence here. For example, the legal system
contains mechanisms to reduce the problems associated with hindsight
bias (see Rachlinski, 1998). It also appears responsive to the difference
between out-of-pocket costs and opportunity costs (Cohen and Knetsch,
1992). Many legal institutions might be investigated in an effort to see
whether and how they overcome some of the difficulties discussed here.
Such an investigation might even reveal an implicit understanding of
behavioral economics on the part of those involved in the legal system.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-19">
      <title>5.4. The Future</title>
      <p>Behavioral law and economics is obviously flourishing; but it remains,
in its early stages, perhaps not so different from that of conventional law
and economics in, say, 1971. No treatise organizes the field, and a great
deal of further research remains to be done, theoretical and empirical. For
example, there is no systematic work on the relationship between damage
awards and the various ingredients of cases involving libel, sexual
harassment, and intentional infliction of emotional distress. There is only
preliminary work on the role of "anchors" in awards by juries and judges. Nor
is there much work on the relationship between legal rules and reciprocity
and on the important question whether and how legal rules might solve
prisoner's dilemmas without requiring large levels of public enforcement
activity. Under what circumstances does a legal provision (for example,
one that bans smoking or requires recycling) become self-enforcing? We
lack much information about whether and how legal rules change
preferences themselves; this is a promising area for both experimental and
empirical work. Nor do we know a great deal about the effects of social
institutions in overcoming cognitive and motivational limitations.</p>
      <p>There can be no question that human beings care about fairness, that
they can be myopic, and that they exhibit bounded rationality. The
questions for the future are whether an understanding of the underlying
phenomena can lead to better predictions about the effects of law, more
reliable prescriptions about how law might promote social goals, and more
refined judgments about when the legal system should respect or reject
individual choices.
Akerlof, George. 1982. "Labor Contracts as Partial Gift Exchange," 97 Quarterly
Journal of Economics 543-69.</p>
      <p>University Press.</p>
      <p>1-19.</p>
      <p>Arkes, Hal, and Kenneth Hammond. 1996. Judgment and Decision Making: An</p>
      <p>Interdisciplinary Reader. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
Arrow, Kenneth. 1986. "Rationality of Self and Others in an Economic System,"
59 Journal of Business S385-99.</p>
      <p>Axelrod, Robert M. 1984. The Evolution of Cooperation. New York: Basic.
Babcock, Linda, and George Loewenstein. 1997. "Explaining Bargaining Impasse:
The Role of Self-Serving Biases," 11 Journal of Economic Perspectives
10936.</p>
      <p>Babcock, Linda, George Loewenstein, and Samuel Issacharoff. 1993. "Creating</p>
      <p>Convergence: Debiasing Biased Litigants," 23 Law and Social Inquiry 913-25.
Babcock, Linda, George Loewenstein, Samuel Issacharoff, and Colin Camerer.
1995. "Biased Judgments of Fairness in Bargaining," 85 American Economics
Review 1337-43.</p>
      <p>Babcock, Linda, Xianghong Wang, and George Loewenstein. 1996. "Choosing the
Wrong Pond: Social Comparisons in Negotiations that Reflect a Self-Serving
Bias," 111 Quarterly Journal of Economics 1-19.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-20">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 153</title>
      <p>Baker, Lynn, and Robert Emery. 1993. "When Every Relationship Is Above
Average: Perceptions and Expectations of Divorce at Time of Marriage," 17 Law
and Human Behavior 439-50.</p>
      <p>Baron, Jonathan. 1994. Thinking and Deciding. 2nd ed. Cambridge: Cambridge</p>
      <p>University Press.</p>
      <p>Bauman, Laurie, and Karolyn Siegel. 1987. "Misperception among Gay Men of
the Risk for AIDS Associated with Their Sexual Behavior," 17 Journal of
Applied Social Psychology 329-50.</p>
      <p>Baumeister, Roy F. 1998. "The Self," in Daniel T. Gilbert et al., eds., 1. The</p>
      <p>Handbook of Social Psychology. New York: Oxford University Press.
Becker, Gary. 1997. Accounting for Tastes. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University</p>
      <p>Press.</p>
      <p>Benartzi, Shlomo, and Richard Thaler. 1995. "Myopic Loss Aversion and the</p>
      <p>Equity Premium Puzzle," 110 Quarterly Journal of Economics 73-92.
Bohnet, Iris, and Bruno Frey. 1999. "Social Distance and Other-Regarding
Behavior in Dictator Games," 89 American Economics Review 335-39.</p>
      <p>Camerer, Colin. 1990. "Behavioral Game Theory," in Robin Hogarth, ed., Insight
in Decision Making. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</p>
      <p>in Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky, eds., Choices, Values, and Frames.
Camerer, Colin, and Dan Lovallo. 1999. "Overconfidence and Excess Entry: An</p>
      <p>Experimental Approach," 89 American Economics Review 306-18.
Chapman, Gretchen, and Brian Bornstein. 1996. "The More You Ask For, The</p>
      <p>More You Get," 10 Applied Cognitive Psychology 519-40.</p>
      <p>Cohen, David, and Jack Knetsch. 1992. "Judicial Choice and Disparities between</p>
      <p>Measures of Economic Values," 30 Osgoode Hall Law Journal 737-70.
Conlisk, John. 1996. "Why Bounded Rationality?" 34 Journal of Economic
Literature 669-700.</p>
      <p>Dawes, Robyn M. 1998. "Behavioral Decision Making and Judgment," in Daniel
T. Gilbert et al., eds., 1 The Handbook of Social Psychology. New York: Oxford
University Press.</p>
      <p>Ellickson, Robert. 1991. Order without Law. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University</p>
      <p>Press.</p>
      <p>Elster, Jon. 1998. Rationality and the Emotions. Cambridge: Cambridge University</p>
      <p>Press.</p>
      <p>Farnsworth, Ward. 1999. "Do Parties to Nuisance Suits Bargain after Judgments?"
6 University of Chicago Law Review 373-436.</p>
      <p>Fehr, Ernst, and Simon Gachter. 1998. "How Effective Are Trust- and
ReciprocityBased Incentives," in Avner Ben-Ner and Louis Putterman, eds., Economics,
Values, and Organization. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
Frank, Robert. 1993. "Does Studying Economics Inhibit Cooperation?" 7 Journal
of Economics Perspectives 159-71.
Frank, Robert, and Phillip Cook. 1995. The Winner-Take -All Society. New York:</p>
      <p>Free Press.</p>
      <p>Gilboa, Itzhak, and David Schmeidler. 1995. "Case-Based Decision Theory" 110</p>
      <p>Quarterly Journal of Economics 605-39.</p>
      <p>Gneezy, Uri, and Aldo Rustichini. Forthcoming. "A Fine Is a Price," Journal of</p>
      <p>Legal Studies.</p>
      <p>Goldstein, William, and Robin Hogarth. 1997. Research on Judgment and
Decisionmaking. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p>
      <p>Gregory, Robin, Sarah Lichtenstein, and Donald MacGregor. 1993. "The Role of
Past States in Determining Reference Points for Policy Decisions," 55
Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes 195-206.</p>
      <p>Hirshleifer, David. 1995. "The Blind Leading the Blind: Social Influence, Fads,
and Informational Cascades," in Mariano Tammasi and Kathryn Ierulli, eds.,
The New Economics of Human Behavior. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
Hoffman, Elizabeth, and Matthew Spitzer. 1993. "Willingness to Pay vs.
Willingness to Accept: Legal and Economic Implications," 71 Washington University
Law Quarterly 59-1 14.</p>
      <p>Houston, Christopher, and Cass R. Sunstein. 1999. "Risk Allocation among Law</p>
      <p>Students," Journal of Legal Education (forthcoming).</p>
      <p>Issacharoff, Samuel. 1996. "Contracting for Employment: The Limited Return of
the Common Law," 74 Texas Law Review 1783-1812.</p>
      <p>Jolis, Christine. 1996. "Hands Tying and the Age Discrimination in Employment
Act," 74 Texas Law Review 1813-46.</p>
      <p>51 Vanderbilt Law Review 1653-77.</p>
      <p>Jolis, Christine, Cass R. Sunstein, and Richard H. Thaler. 1998. "A Behavioral</p>
      <p>Approach to Law and Economics," 50 Stanford Law Review 1471-1550.
Kagel, John H., Raymond C. Battalio, and Leonard Green. 1995. Economic Choice
Theory: An Experimental Analysis of Animal Behavior. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.</p>
      <p>Kagel, John, and Alvin Roth, eds. 1994. Handbook of Experimental Economics.</p>
      <p>Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel. 1996. "New Challenges to the Rationality Assumption, m
Kenneth J. Arrow, Enrico Colombatto, Mark Perlman, and Christian Schmidt,
eds., The Rational Foundations of Economic Behavior. New York: St. Martin's
Press.</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, Jack L. Knetsch, and Richard Thaler. 1986a. "Fairness and the</p>
      <p>Assumptions of Economics," 59 Journal of Business S285-324.</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, Jack L. Knetsch, and Richard Thaler. 1986b. "Fairness as a
Constraint on Profit-Seeking: Entitlements in the Market," 76 American
Economics Review 728-41.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-21">
      <title>Behavioral Law and Economics: A Progress Report 155</title>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, and liana Ritov. 1994. "Determinants of Stated Willingness to</p>
      <p>Pay for Public Goods," 9 Journal of Risk and Uncertainty 5-30.</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, liana Ritov, and David Schkade. 1999. "Economic Preferences
or Attitude Expressions? An Analysis of Dollar Responses to Public Issues,"
Journal of Risk and Uncertainty (forthcoming).</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, David Schkade, liana Ritov, and Cass R. Sunstein. 1999.
Reversals of Judgment: The Effect of Cross-Category Comparisons on lntendedly
Absolute Scales (unpublished manuscript).</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, David Schkade, and Cass R. Sunstein. 1998. "Shared Outrage
and Erratic Awards: The Psychology of Punitive Damages," 16 Journal of Risk
and Uncertainty 49-86.</p>
      <p>Kahneman, Daniel, Paul Slovic, and Amos Tverskey, eds. 1982. Judgment under</p>
      <p>Uncertainty: Heuristics and Biases. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
Kahneman, Daniel, and Amos Tversky. 1979. "Prospect Theory: An Analysis of</p>
      <p>Decision Under Risk," 47 Econometrica 263-92.</p>
      <p>Kelman, Mark, Yuval Rottenstreich, and Amos Tversky. 1996.
"Context</p>
      <p>Dependence in Legal Decisionmaking," 25 Journal of Legal Studies 287-318.
Korobkin, Russell. 1998a. "Inertia and Preference in Contract Negotiation," 51
Vanderbilt Law Review 1583-1651.</p>
      <p>Law Review 608-87.</p>
      <p>Kuran, Timur. 1995. Private Truths, Public Lies. Cambridge, MA: Harvard
University Press.</p>
      <p>Organization," in Avner Ben-Ner and Louis Putterman, eds., Economics , Values
and Organizations. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p>
      <p>Kuran, Timur, and Cass R. Sunstein. 1999. "Availability Cascades and Risk
Regulation," 51 Stanford Law Review 1 131-92.</p>
      <p>Langevoort, Donald. 1997. "Organized Illusions: A Behavioral Theory of Why
Corporations Mislead Stock Market Investors (And Cause Other Social
Harms)," 146 University of Pennsylvania Law Review 101-72.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-22">
      <title>Scholarship: A Literature Review," 51 Vanderbilt Law Review 1499-54.</title>
      <p>Lichtenstein, Sarah, and Paul Slovic. 1971. "Reversals of Preference between Bids
and Choices in Gambling Decisions," 89 Journal of Experimental Psychology
46-55.</p>
      <p>Loewenstein, George, and Daniel Adler. 1995. "A Bias in the Prediction of Tastes,"
105 Economic Journal 929-37.</p>
      <p>Loewenstein, George, Samuel Issacharoff, Colin Camerer, and Linda Babcock.
1993. "Self-Serving Assessments of Fairness and Pretrial Bargaining," 22
Journal of Legal Studies 135-59.</p>
      <p>Loewenstein, George, and Nachum Sicherman. 1991. "Do Workers Prefer
Increasing Wage Profiles," 9 Journal of Labor Economics 67-84.
Loewenstein, George and David Schkade. Forthcoming. "Wouldn't It Be Nice?
Predicting Future Feelings," in E. Diener, N. Schwartz, and D. Kahneman,
eds., Hedonic Psychology: Scientific Approaches to Enjoyment, Suffering, and
Well- Being, New York: Sage.</p>
      <p>McCaffery, Edward J., Daniel Kahneman, and Matthew Spitzer. 1995. "Framing
the Jury: Cognitive Perspectives on Pain and Suffering Awards," 81 Virginia
Law Review 1341-1420.</p>
      <p>Noll, Roger G., and James E. Krier. 1990. "Some Implications of Cognitive
Psychology for Risk Regulation," 19 Journal of Legal Studies 747-79.
Odean, Terranee. 1998. "Are Investors Reluctant to Realize Their Losses?" 53</p>
      <p>Journal of Finance 1775-98.</p>
      <p>Perkins, H. Wesley. 1997. "College Student Misperceptions of Alcohol and Other
Drug Norms among Peers: Exploring Causes, Consequences, and Implications
for Prevention Programs," in Designing Alcohol and Other Drug Prevention
Programs in Higher Education: Bringing Theory into Practice.</p>
      <p>Posner, Eric A. 1998. "Symbols, Signals, and Social Norms in Politics and the</p>
      <p>Law," 27 Journal of Legal Studies 765-98.</p>
      <p>Posner, Richard A. 1990. The Problems of Jurisprudence. Cambridge, MA:
Harvard University Press.</p>
      <p>Rabin, Matthew. 1993. "Incorporating Fairness into Game Theory and
Economics," 83 American Economics Review 1281-1302.
nomic Behavior and Organization 1 77-94.</p>
      <p>1 1-46.</p>
      <p>Rachlinski, Jeffrey J. 1996. "Gains, Losses, and the Psychology of Litigation," 70
Southern California Law Review 113-85.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-23">
      <title>University of Chicago Law Review 571-625.</title>
      <p>Rachlinski, Jeffrey, and Forest Jourden. 1998. "Remedies and the Psychology of</p>
      <p>Ownership," 51 Vanderbilt Law Review 1541-82.</p>
      <p>Redelmeier, Donald A., Paul Rozin, and Daniel Kahneman. 1993. "Understanding</p>
      <p>Patients' Decisions," 270 Journal of the American Medical Association 72-76.
Schkade, David, Cass R. Sunstein, and Daniel Kahneman. Forthcoming. "Are
Juries More Erratic than Individuals?" Columbia Law Review.</p>
      <p>Sieff, Elaine M., Robyn M. Dawes, and George Loewenstein. Forthcoming.
"Anticipated versus Actual Reaction to HIV Test Results," American Journal of
Psychology.</p>
      <p>Slonim, Robert, and Alvin Roth. 1998. "Learning in High Stakes Ultimatum
Games," 66 Econometrica 569-96.</p>
      <p>Viscusi, W. Kip. 1992. Fatal Tradeoffs. New York: Oxford University Press.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Slovic</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Paul.
          <year>1995</year>
          .
          <article-title>"The Construction of Preference,"</article-title>
          <source>50 American</source>
          Psychologist 364-71.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>1997a</year>
          .
          <article-title>"Behavioral Analysis of Law,"</article-title>
          64 University of Chicago Law Review 1
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
            , Cass R., Daniel Kahneman, and
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schkade</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1998</year>
          .
          <article-title>"</article-title>
          <source>Assessing Punitive Damages," 107 Yale Law Journal</source>
          <year>2071</year>
          -
          <volume>152</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Taylor</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Shelley.
          <year>1989</year>
          .
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Positive</given-names>
            <surname>Illusions</surname>
          </string-name>
          . New York: Basic Books.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Thaler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Richard H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>1991</year>
          . Quasi- Rational
          <string-name>
            <surname>Economics</surname>
          </string-name>
          . New York: Sage. Medema and Warren J. Samuels, eds., Foundations of Re s each in Economics. New York: Elgar Publishing.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tversky</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Amos.
          <year>1996</year>
          .
          <article-title>"Rational Theory and Constructive Choice," in Kenneth Arrow et al</article-title>
          ., eds.,
          <source>The Rational Foundations of Economic Behavior</source>
          . London: MacMillan.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Weinstein</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Neil D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>1989</year>
          .
          <article-title>"Optimistic Bias about Personal Risks," 246 Science 1232</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

