<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cass R. Sunstein, "Six Theses on Interpretation Symposium,"</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1989</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>91</volume>
      <issue>1989</issue>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>SIX THESES ON INTERPRETATION</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein *</p>
      <p>This discussion will come in two parts. First, I will make a
somewhat unconventional constitutional argument about how the
privacy cases should be understood. Second, I will venture a few
observations about the character of this argument and about the
nature of legal interpretation.</p>
      <p>In essence, my substantive argument is that the Supreme
Court's privacy cases should be understood as involving not only
privacy, but also, and much more fundamentally, discrimination,
usually on the basis of sex. The applicable constitutional provision
is the equal protection clause, not the due process clause. I suggest
that this claim should be understood as a legal argument; that
interpretation is critical rather than conventional, and inevitably so; that
the claims of legal indeterminacy depend on crudely positivist
notions of interpretation; that analogies to interpretation in theology,
literature, and philosophy offer limited help; and that it is time to
turn away from questions about the nature of interpretation and
toward more in the way of substantive legal argument.</p>
      <p>I</p>
      <p>The statute at issue in Griswold v. Connecticut forbade the use
of contraceptives by married couples. The statute was defended as
a means of preventing extramarital sex. Its origins suggested that it
was intended to ensure that sex would occur only for purposes of
procreation.</p>
      <p>In the real world, it is principally women rather than men who
are responsible for contraception. The consequences of a
prohibition on use of contraceptives are visited principally on women. A
system that denies use of and access to contraceptives will
disadvantage women uniquely, and relative to men, by forcing them to
choose between carrying the child to term with the attendant
disabilities, or having an abortion with its emotional and physical risks.</p>
      <p>* Karl N. Llewelyn, Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago, Law School
and Department of Political Science. Some of the arguments offered here are spelled out in
more detail in Sunstein, Revisiting Constitutional Privacy (unpublished manuscript).
Such a system calls for a powerful defense by the state. In the
Griswold case, no such defense was forthcoming.</p>
      <p>Under current law, of course, the equal protection clause is
aimed primarily at impermissible motivations, not primarily at
social subordination as such. Anti-contraceptive laws do not classify
on the basis of sex; it is therefore necessary to prove discriminatory
motive on the part of the state. Under the best reconstruction of
current law, a discriminatory motive exists if and only if a state
would not have done what it did if the distribution of benefits and
burdens among the relevant groups were reversed., If the state's
decision would have been the same regardless of which group was
helped and which hurt, it would be fair to say that it was neutral
with respect to sex (or race). If the state's decision would have been
different, it is infected by a discriminatory motive. This analysis of
impermissible motivation has the advantage of being a fully
plausible approach to the constitutional criterion of equality.</p>
      <p>In the context at hand, the question of discriminatory intent
becomes: Would a state have imposed restrictions on the right to
use contraceptives if the costs of pregnancy were visited on men
rather than women? There are two possible answers to this
question. The first is, Clearly no. No legislature would punish men in
this way for having had sex.</p>
      <p>Another response is that the question is itself not susceptible to
an answer. Most counterfactuals are based on situations that have
some analogue in the real world. But in the counterfactual in
question, the problem is that if men could become pregnant, they would
not be men. The inability to become pregnant is one of the defining
characteristics of being a man. In this view, the question is so
speculative and otherworldly that it is not sensible even to pose it.</p>
      <p>Undoubtedly this view has a good deal of plausibility to it. But
it also suggests reasons to be extremely skeptical about-perhaps to
abandon altogether-the inquiry into discriminatory intent. In a
large class of cases, the intent inquiry, phrased as an equality
question, will suffer from precisely these problems. A plausible
substitute for the discriminatory intent test, one also having roots in
constitutional law, would ask whether the practice at issue
contributed to the social subordination of a disadvantaged group. Under
that substitute approach, which I cannot spell out in detail here,
Griswold was rightly decided as an equality case.</p>
      <p>It is time to summarize what has been a quite simple point.
The disabilities imposed by laws that restrict access to
contracep1. I rely in the next few paragraphs on the analysis in Strauss, Discriminating Intent
and the Timing of Brown, 55 U. CHi. L. REv. (forthcoming 1989).
tives are visited principally on women. If social subordination is the
target of the equal protection clause, such laws are presumptively
unconstitutional, and the presumption cannot easily be rebutted. If
the equal protection clause is aimed at discriminatory motive, there
is good reason to believe that such laws are also unconstitutional. If
the discriminatory intent standard is not satisfied, the problem is
with the standard itself, and such laws are unconstitutional under
the most plausible alternative approach as well.</p>
      <p>Arguments of this sort apply not only to Griswold, but to
Eisenstadt and Carey as well. Roe v. Wade and its successor cases are
easier in some ways but harder in others. Antiabortion statutes are
of course directed exclusively at women. Thus they amount to de
jure discrimination on the basis of sex. It will not do to suggest that
the discrimination is merely in terms of effects. The disadvantaged
class consists exclusively of women. There is authority in the
Supreme Court distinguishing sex discrimination from
discrimination against pregnant people, but this distinction is hard to take
seriously.</p>
      <p>It is sometimes suggested that antiabortion laws do not treat
people who are similarly situated differently; hence they are said not
to discriminate on the basis of sex. But the Aristotelian criterion
("treat likes alike") is unhelpful when biological differences are at
work, or when the claim is that equality requires the differently
situated to be treated differently. In cases of biological difference, legal
disabilities that make those differences count raise questions of
discrimination, at least when the removal of those disabilities would
tend in the direction of equality. If women were permitted to
control their own reproductive processes, more in the way of equality
would result: neither men nor women would be subject to the risk
of pregnancy from sex. Antiabortion laws thus represent a legal
disability that removes a possible source of equality, or that create a
source of inequality. They are therefore a form of sex
discrimination, unconstitutional unless this can be defended quite
persuasively.</p>
      <p>Here too the case can be understood in terms of social
subordination or, more conventionally, discriminatory intent. There is no
doubt that compulsory childbearing is an element of the social
subordination of women, imposing on them a burden nowhere imposed
on men; and the burden has significant consequences in the real
world. Under an intent test, the simple point is that it is highly
doubtful that antiabortion laws would exist if men could become
pregnant. If this conclusion is to be resisted, it is because the
question is itself an implausible one, not susceptible to reasoned answer;
and in that case we have reason to reject the test itself.</p>
      <p>Even if the case is understood in this way, it is not clear that
Roe was rightly decided. Perhaps the state could justify the
disability placed on women as a means of protecting an extremely
important interest: fetal life. But the absence of the imposition of any
comparable burden on men, and the real-world consequences of
selective abortion regulation, increase the state's difficulties in
defending its statute. Selective restrictions of abortion, varying from one
state to another, would produce an economically and racially
skewed system that would preserve far fewer fetal lives, and impose
more disabilities on women, than might be expected.</p>
      <p>I might add that the central problem in Bowers v. Hardwick
was also one of equal protection. Justice Stevens rightly struck this
theme in his dissent. Prohibitions on homosexual conduct deny to
gay people sexual liberty that the majority allows to itself: it is
principally for this reason that anti-sodomy laws are constitutionally
problematic.</p>
      <p>II</p>
      <p>What does it mean to say that the argument just offered is a
constitutional argument? In what sense do arguments of this sort
represent "law"? Notably missing from the argument is explicit
emphasis on some of the conventional sources of constitutional
argument-language, history, structure. On the other hand, the
argument is not simply moral theory or normative argument in the
abstract. The claim that the privacy decisions should be understood
as involving sex discrimination is not a claim that the best political
theory would understand them as such. The claim is instead that
the equal protection clause is best interpreted to treat the cases in
these terms. That claim in turn depends on a theory of the meaning
of the notion of constitutional equality. That theory attempts to
link race and sex discrimination-understanding both practices, for
constitutional purposes, as a reflection either of a kind of prejudice
or of social subordination. The argument offered above receives
some support from cases suggesting that neutrality as between
blacks and whites and women and men is a constitutional
requirement, at least outside of the setting of affirmative action. It is
buttressed as well by cases suggesting that the equal protection clause
is designed to combat social subordination.</p>
      <p>Considerations of this sort lead me to six basic claims about
constitutional interpretation.</p>
      <p>1. The asserted dispute between constitutional
"perfectionism"-embodied perhaps in the idea that the Constitution should
be interpreted so as to coalesce with the best political and moral
ideals-and "hard law" approaches to constitutional law is based
on confusions that might be cleared up by paying attention to actual
constitutional argument. It would be a large mistake to suggest that
constitutional claims of the sort made here-even if,for example,
the intent of the framers, narrowly understood, is put to one
sideput everything up for grabs. Whether the argument is to be
accepted or rejected will depend on the reasons offered in its behalf.
Those reasons-as in Brown v. Board of Education-involve the
meaning of constitutional equality in light of the decided cases and
the appropriate conception of the constitutional text. To ask
whether Brown is "hard law" or personal preference is to assume a
dichotomy that misdescribes the process. The same is true of
constitutional argument quite generally.</p>
      <p>2. There is little difference between law in the ordinary
sense-as understood in the common law and in many cases of
statutory construction-and constitutional law as represented in
arguments like that offered above. The sources of legal argument are in
both cases the same, broadly speaking. The principal difference is
that institutional constraints make the Supreme Court quite
reluctant to invalidate legislative and executive decisions, and properly
so. Moreover, precedent plays a different role in constitutional and
common law cases; there are other differences as well. But in terms
of interpretive methodology, there is no sharp break.</p>
      <p>3. The "indeterminacy" thesis, at least as frequently
understood, misconceives the process of constitutional argument (and
legal argument generally). I assert that the argument offered above
is correct. So to assert is not to deny that the argument depends
partly on judgments of value. It is sometimes said, as against
interpretive approaches to law, that if something depends on judgments
of value, all bets are off. But this idea turns on crudely positivist
notions of social science. The argument made above is not in any
simple sense a mere assertion of personal preference. If it is wrong,
it must be because constitutional argument, properly understood,
makes it wrong; and that is a question that must be discussed.</p>
      <p>4. There are large differences between legal interpretation on
the one hand and religious interpretation, literary criticism, and
moral argument on the other. In some respects these analogies may
be illuminating. But one cannot think about questions of
interpretive practice in the abstract. The appropriate nature of
interpretation turns on the purposes for which one is interpreting. Law is
coercive; federal judges are unelected; some sources of
interpretation are permissible and others are not; the Supreme Court operates
in a highly pluralistic society; the rulings of the Court are
authoritative-all of these features distinguish legal interpretation from
interpretive practices in literature, theology, and philosophy.</p>
      <p>5. Legal interpretation is critical rather than conventional;
and this is inevitable. It is often misleading or unhelpful to
understand legal interpretation as an appeal to an "interpretive
community" or to conventional understandings of what words mean. The
interpretive community is usually quite diverse. There is no
conventional understanding of whether the equal protection clause is
violated by a law banning abortion. The courts must choose among
competing plausible understandings. But to repeat: to say this is
not to say that judges are at sea, or that there are not right and
wrong answers. And it is important to emphasize that correctness
and incorrectness will be highly contextual. The privacy cases raise
equal protection issues only contingently; they might be analyzed
quite differently in a world of gender equality.</p>
      <p>6. What is needed for the immediate future is less discussion
of whether constitutional interpretation is law, and more attention
to how constitutional argument operates in concrete cases. A
related point: What is needed is more and better in the way of
substantive constitutional argument. The privacy cases, I claim,
involve impermissible discrimination. Why should they not be
understood in those terms?</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list />
  </back>
</article>

