<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>J.L. Econ &amp; Org.</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "Political Economy, Administrative Law: A Comment Comment," 6 Journal of Law</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1990</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>306</volume>
      <issue>1990</issue>
      <fpage>298</fpage>
      <lpage>306</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>CASS R. SUNSTEIN
University of Chicago
In the last generation, writings on the regulatory state have taken three
principal forms. The first, coming mostly from academic lawyers, consists of
efforts to discern the logic of judge-made public law and to make
recommendations to federal courts reviewing administrative action. The second,
coming mostly from economists, consists of efforts to explain regulatory law by
reference to the self-interest of participants in the legislative process. The
third, coming from a quite eclectic group, consists of efforts to compare the
current administrative state with approaches that show a better appreciation
of the appropriate nature of government intervention and, especially, of the
proper relationships among democratic self-government, bureaucracy, and
private rights.</p>
      <p>Jerry Mashaw's paper on the different "stories" of legal development
attempts to mediate among what he sees as the rival claims of these three
different kinds of work. Mashaw suggests that the three schools generate
different explanations or predictions about the administrative process; he
wants to compare and test their claims. His conclusion is that none of the
predictions ultimately holds up.</p>
      <p>I agree with a large number of Mashaw's particular arguments, and I find
many of his criticisms of the three approaches both valuable and entirely
persuasive. What I want to ask here is whether the task of mediation, as
Journalof Law, Economics, and Organizationvol. 6, Special Issue 1990
© 1990 by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. ISSN 8756-6222</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 299 1990
Mashaw understands it, might not be misguided. If it is, there is a simple
reason: only one of the different efforts amounts to an effort at explanation or
prediction at all. There are no competing hypotheses here. For this reason,
the task of mediation comes at a high price. It converts a large amount of
work on the regulatory state into positive social science, when in fact it is
something quite different.</p>
      <p>I also want to suggest, however, that Mashaw has provided an important
service in bringing the three forms of work into contact with one another and
in suggesting some of their tensions and interrelations. In Section 2 of this
comment, I make some observations about what participants in the three
enterprises might be able to learn from one another. In the process, I hope
to join Mashaw in suggesting some of the ingredients of a unified political
economy for the regulatory state.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>1. REGULATORY STORIES</title>
      <p>Let me begin by attempting to characterize the three "stories" around which
Mashaw's efforts revolve. I will stay with his basic categories, but, as we shall
soon see, in some ways my descriptions will depart from his.</p>
      <p>What Mashaw describes as the work of the "legal idealist" might be seen
as the ordinary, day-to-day, mid-level enterprise of the legal academic
operating largely within the existing legal culture. For the internal expositor or
critic of administrative law, the central task is to discern the logic of
judgemade doctrines, to unpack their assumptions, and to evaluate them. In this
category one can find a large number of claims, amounting to the staple of
academic work in administrative law. Herewith a sample, taken randomly
from recent writing on judge-made public law: the courts' hostility to ex
parte contacts in notice-and-comment rule-making reflects on emerging,
quasi-adjudicative model of administration; the courts have been far more
hospitable to administrative decisions that comport with traditional
principles of compensatory justice than with decisions that reject those
principles; post-1980 doctrines of standing and reviewability embody
pre-NewDeal assumptions and indeed reflect hostility to government regulation;
judicial deference to administrative interpretations of law reflects an
understanding that the resolution of statutory ambiguities is actually a decision of
policy; judicial requirements of elaborate explanations from administrators
bring about substantial delays in the rule-making process or (alternatively)
serve to decrease the risk of factionalism in government.</p>
      <p>These sorts of claims do have serious limitations, for reasons suggested by
Mashaw and taken up further below. But do they even attempt to "explain"
administrative processes? To the extent that the evaluations they offer are
favorable, some of this work indeed tends to describe administrative law
doctrines as if they were "designed" to accomplish some desirable social end.
But these claims should not, I think, be taken as explanatory ones in the
HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 300 1990
sense indicated by Mashaw. They are more on the order of the claim that
Brown v. Board of Education was "designed" to impose a general principle
of color blindness. In other words, they are interpretive rather than positive
claims. They attempt to make the best possible sense out of a line ofjudicial
decisions. They are falsifiable in the sense that they attempt to fit their
claims with the data (i.e., with existing judicial decisions). Among the
various possible accounts that have a plausible claim to fit, however, the choice is
made on value-laden grounds. In this respect, interpretive claims are not
positive in the sense that Mashaw understands the term.</p>
      <p>When doctrinal analysts describe what a doctrine is "intended" to do,
they should not be thought to be making a claim about the subjective
motivations of the judges or, much less, about what really accounts for that
doctrine as a matter of social science. They are not making the functionalist
error of explaining a result by reference to its consequences. Instead, they
are attempting to bring out the logic of legal doctrine by positing the sorts of
claims that might be invoked in its favor. This is a time-honored approach to
law. It should hardly be disparaged, but it is not positive social science.</p>
      <p>If this is right, Mashaw goes wrong in treating efforts of this sort as an
effort to provide a predictive or positive guide at all. More fundamentally, I
think that Mashaw is mistaken in suggesting that what he calls the idealist
conception would predict a range of judicial (rather than legislative and
bureaucratic) controls on the administrative process. For the most part, the
academic lawyers are not engaged in that enterprise at all. 1</p>
      <p>What Mashaw describes as the "CLS description of administrative law" I
prefer to see as a far broader effort, from a range of starting points, to
evaluate regulatory substance and process by reference to first principles
with respect to (a) democratic theory and (b) substantive ideas about the
proper extent and form of regulatory controls. In this category fall a number
of claims about the democratic or antidemocratic character of the modern
regulatory state and about the ways in which that state does more or less
than it ought to do. Thus, for example, it might be said that the category of
public-interest justifications for legislation is very large, including not simply
responses to market failures but also a recognition of the endogenous
character of certain preferences; an endorsement, through law, of social
aspirations; a powerful antidiscrimination principle; and certain forms of
redistribution. In one version, coming from the far left, the administrative
state is said to have been defended on the basis of a number of ultimately
unsuccessful strategies of legitimation. 2 On this account, administrative
1. Of course, it would be possible to recast some such claims in those terms and then to test
them: for example, do the courts consistently defer to political choices? Do they systematically
disfavor regulatory beneficiaries? I do not deny that some claims of academic lawyers take the
form of falsifiable predictions.</p>
      <p>2. In fact, there is no developed work from the critical legal studies movement on
administrative law. Mashaw relies on Frug.</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 301 1990
dominance and discretion are concealed by arguments that attempt,
unsuccessfully, to discern a pedigree for modern administration in the form of
democratic self-governance or neutral legal constraint.</p>
      <p>Mashaw attempts to translate this latter sort of claim into an argument
"predicting" that administrative law doctrine will "maintain the relatively
unconstrained power of bureaucratic officials to exercise state power." I
doubt, however, that the critics have made any such predictive argument.
Normative arguments about failed efforts at legitimation should not be taken
as positive claims about what it is that administrative law doctrines will do. It
would be perfectly plausible to say that efforts at the legitimation of
bureaucratic authority fail, while at the same time taking no position on the
question whether administrative law will, in general or in particular, maximize,
minimize, or take some middle course on the question of bureaucratic
discretion. Much depends, of course, on what the notion to "relatively
unconstrained power" is intended to comprehend. But unless any amount of
discretionary authority at all is thought to fall in this category-and perhaps
Frug and others can be read to make this puzzling suggestion-the
predictive claim is difficult to find in the literature.</p>
      <p>Indeed, it would be extremely surprising if the critics attempted to make
a positive claim to the effect that administrative law will maintain
unconstrained bureaucratic discretion. That claim would be hard to sustain. There
are multiple actors in the administrative state, and, even if failed
legitimation is the ultimate point of one's story, it would be peculiar indeed if all of
those other actors-courts, Congress, the president-were simultaneously
embarking on the pursuit of unconstrained bureaucratic power.</p>
      <p>All this suggests that the critics, taken as a broad group or as participants
in something more narrow like CLS, are not making a claim with any
powerful positive implications about the structure of bureaucratic
decision-making. As in the case of the legal idealist, Mashaw seems to me to be mistaking
a set of essentially normative claims for predictive or explanatory
judgments. 3</p>
      <p>With respect to positive political theory, Mashaw is, of course, on firm
ground. Here the task is indeed to explain why administrative process takes
the form that it does. Moreover, a number of Mashaw's criticisms of positive
work on administration seem to me correct. I think, however, that Mashaw
may be mischaracterizing the relevant work when he suggests that it posits
"legislative control" as the overarching theme of positive political science in
this area. Any positive theory of the regulatory state will acknowledge that
there are other actors, with other agendas, in the process. And, as several
positive analysts have argued, legislative control may be something that
3. Of course, these sorts of normative claims do involve some views about the data,
including the decided cases.</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 302 1990
legislators themselves will work against-in favor of, for example,
bureaucratic or state authority, which in some contexts will be in the interest of
legislators focused on reelection. It would be a mistake to think that all
positive political science in this area is designed to prove that administrative
processes can be explained as if they were an effort to increase legislative
control of the administrative process.</p>
      <p>If I am correct on this, the three enterprises with which we are dealing
are in fact incommensurable, not because they have different
methodologies, but because they set for themselves different tasks. Only one ol
them amounts to an "explanation" in the positive sense at all. Both the
idealist and the critical approaches are largely normative. To the extent that
they offer explanations, it is with an eye toward describing, respectively, the
logic around which some of the cases might be organized and evaluated, and
the foundations from which one might understand the correspondence or
noncorrespondence between the administrative state and ideals of
democratic self-governance. These are explanations in a sense, but of a quite different
order from those involved in positive social science. They do not predict
judicial or administrative control at all.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>2. NOTES TOWARD A UNIFIED POLITICAL ECONOMY</title>
      <p>OF ADMINISTRATIVE LAW
The considerations treated thus far do not suggest that the three enterprises
might not learn something from one another, nor do I deny that all of them
might be making serious mistakes that an engagement with the others might
help to remedy. In this section, I want to say a few words about some of the
limitations of each of these enterprises, and to speculate on how work in each
of them might be enriched through an understanding of the others.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>2.1. THE MYOPIA OF ACADEMIC ADMINISTRATIVE LAW</title>
      <p>Administrative law in the law schools remains largely in the grip of the
tradition set by Kenneth Culp Davis and Louis Jaffe. Focused on judicial
control of administrative behavior, it sees the purposes of administrative law
as embracing a constellation of related concerns: to guarantee legality; to
promote procedural regularity; and to ensure against irrationality and
injustice, defined by reference to common-sense intuitions.</p>
      <p>These ideas are far too vague to provide a full sense of the appropriate
nature of judicial controls on the regulatory state. An understanding of
positive political science might provide significant help. Some regulatory
statutes should, for example, be seen as "deals" among self-interested
private groups; they are not public-regarding at all. Moreover, regulatory
stat</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 303 1990
utes have a variety of malfunctions, some of them counterintuitive. 4 Statutes
are often poorly coordinated with one another. Sometimes they become
obsolete. They also have complex systemic effects. Overregulation produces
underregulation; concentration on new risks perpetuate old risks;
redistributive regulation often hurts those at the bottom of the economic
ladder; legal requirements of the "best available technology" can, ironically,
retard technological development.</p>
      <p>An understanding of these various phenomena could prove most helpful
to doctrinal analysis in administrative law. It might show, for example, that
the consequences of regulatory statutes are quite different from what is
anticipated, and an understanding of the consequences might well bear on
statutory interpretation and on the decision about what courses of action are
"arbitrary" within the meaning of the Administrative Procedure Act. For
example, an understanding of the ways in which regulatory controls on new
risks perpetuate old risks might well affect judicial analysis. 5 The fact that
statutes are sometimes "deals" among private actors might also bear on
statutory construction, although here the implications are uncertain.
Furthermore, if problems in aggregating multiple views in the legislature
produce irrationality or incoherence, perhaps there is much to be gained by
ensuring regulation via the president rather than the Congress.</p>
      <p>To the extent that criticisms of administrative legitimacy have weight,
those criticisms, too, might play a role in judge-made doctrines. For
example, attacks on policy-making by bureaucrats (again, if they are persuasive)
might lead to a reinvigoration of the nondelegation doctrine or at least to
"clear statement" principles, forbidding administrators to engage in certain
activity unless Congress has expressly authorized it. In such cases,
administrative doctrines always depend on understandings about political
legitimacy, even if such understandings are tacit; and an engagement with
theories about legitimacy and legitimation will inevitably enrich such
understandings. This is true even if judge-made doctrines are highly
unlikely to respond in a serious way to the most extreme versions of the
"legitimation" complaint.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>2.2. THE NARROWNESS OF POSITIVE POLITICAL SCIENCE</title>
      <p>
        A considerable amount of positive political science on the subject of
regulation is organized around the notion of "rent-seeking." The notion is not
always clearly explicated; at least in some hands, it seems to refer to the
wasteful expenditure of funds on the redistribution of resources through
politics rather than the healthy production of resources through markets.
Thus, for example, efforts to obtain environmental controls, or to obtain a
4. See
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">Sunstein (1990</xref>
        a,b).
5. See
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">Sunstein (1990</xref>
        b:407-41).
      </p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 304 1990
"fairness" doctrine to control broadcasting, are thought to represent the
diversion of resources into an unproductive place.</p>
      <p>So described, the notion of rent-seeking rejects most of the basic
workings of politics. It treats citizenship itself as an evil. And while it is intended
as a tool of positive analysis, in fact it is based on a set of premises that arc
rarely disentangled and that amount to tacit, and exceedingly peculiar,
understandings of democratic theory. It assumes that the status quo-existing
distributions-are not themselves a product of politics or in need of defense.
It treats politics as a system for the transfer of wealth rather than for
deliberation about values. Indeed, it assimilates the second to the first, and thu,
renders it invisible.</p>
      <p>More generally, the notion of rent-seeking represents a peculiar reversa
of the liberal tradition, which has seen political behavior not as an evil, but a!
an important arena for education, for deliberation and discussion about th(
nation's direction, for the development of the faculties, and for the cultiva.
tion of feelings of altruism. On all of these scores, the liberal traditior
remains reasonably vibrant in the United States; and it continues to describ(
a wide range of individual and collective behavior. It would, of course, b(
foolish to deny that much political conduct is an effort to use governmenta
power to serve selfish ends. But to collapse all political behavior into th(
category of "rent-seeking" is grotesquely to devalue the activities of cit
izenship. An effort by those who practice positive political science to engag(
with the literature of democratic theory would be most helpful here.</p>
      <p>As Mashaw properly points out, moreover, much of positive politica
science represents a crude form of functionalism. Prominent in such divers(
areas as Marxism, economics, and sociology, work of this sort deduces
cause of a phenomenon from its effects. But this is bad social science. I
amounts to the telling of plausible stories, but it is really no more than that
The fact that a regulatory system has the effect of, for example, helpin t
Eastern industry does not demonstrate that the system was enacted becaus(
of that effect.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>2.3. CRITICAL WORK AND POLITICS</title>
      <p>Some work in the critical tradition seems naive about a range of issues
including the consequences of governmental intervention in the mar
ketplace. Such intervention does not create simple ex post winners an(
losers. It has a range of distributive consequences, some of them unantici
pated and perverse. An understanding of the complex systemic effects o
regulatory enactments-inevitable in a market (or nonmarket)
economywould be extremely helpful here.</p>
      <p>Moreover, positive political science helps to produce a healthy skepticisn
about the possibilities of democratic politics, at least in any polity that we ar
likely to have. Social choice theory has revealed a number of difficulties ii</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 6 J.L. Econ &amp; Org. 305 1990
describing any outcome in a multimember body as reflecting a unitary
"public will." An understanding of collective action problems, cycling, strategic
behavior, agenda manipulation, and economies of scale should at least
weaken the enthusiasm of some critical theorists for small-scale systems of
participatory democracy.</p>
      <p>To say this is not at all to suggest that an engagement with positive work
on the regulatory state leads directly to any particular set of ideas on the
appropriate relationship between bureaucracy and democracy. But it does
suggest that critical approaches to that question would be much improved if
they took account of that work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>3. CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>It is a mistake, I think, to translate either the work of the doctrinal analyst or
the various critiques of the democratic theorist into a set of positive claims
about how administrative processes actually come about. At most, the
doctrinal analyst is arguing, for example, that there is a discernible logic behind
otherwise mysterious developments in the case law; and the democratic
theorist is arguing that, for example, participants in modern liberal states
make unsuccessful claims by which they attempt to legitimate the exercise of
discretionary power by bureaucrats. But neither of these arguments is a
prediction or explanation at all.</p>
      <p>To say this is not to say that the three perspectives on administrative law
have nothing to learn from each other. On the contrary, there is a pressing
need for a more unified political economy of administrative law. Such a
political economy would reflect an understanding of the principles and
pathologies of the regulatory state; of the forces that have brought it about; of
the devices by which various actors have attempted to discipline it; and of
the failures and successes of regulation, assessed by reference both to its
real-world performance and to democratic theory. A unified political
economy would indeed attempt to mediate among different perspectives on the
regulatory state. It would do so not by seeing which one is more sound than
the others, but instead by appreciating that each of them attempts important
(although quite different) tasks, and by taking advantage of the work that
performs each of those tasks well rather than poorly.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Frug</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Gerald E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>1984</year>
          .
          <article-title>"The Ideology of Bureaucracy in American Law,"</article-title>
          <source>97 Harvard Law Review</source>
          <volume>1276</volume>
          -388.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <year>1990a</year>
          .
          <article-title>After the Rights Revolution</article-title>
          . Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          --.
          <year>1990b</year>
          .
          <article-title>"Paradoxes of the Regulatory State,"</article-title>
          57 University of Chicago Law Review 407-41.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

