<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cass R. Sunstein, "Three Civil Rights Fallacies,"</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Three Civil Rights Fallacies</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1991</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>751</volume>
      <issue>1991</issue>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>From the early 1950s until the present day, three propositions have
permeated the arguments of lawyers and others interested in advancing
the cause of civil rights.</p>
      <p>The first proposition is that the target of the civil rights movement is
discrimination, which is always or usually a product of irrational hatred,
fear, or prejudice. In this view, the purpose of civil rights law is to
eliminate these forms of irrationality from the public and private realms.</p>
      <p>The second proposition is that the principal function of civil rights
law is compensatory. Just as an injured person in a tort action has a
right to be made whole, so victims of a history of discrimination
(including slavery) are entitled to be put into the place they would have
occupied if discrimination had never occurred. Restoration of the status quo
ante is a substantial part of the reasoning and rhetoric of civil rights law.</p>
      <p>The third proposition is that the judiciary is the appropriate
institution for the making and enforcement of civil rights law. Reliance on the
courts, principally through interpretation of the Constitution, has been a
distinctive feature of the civil rights movement since the middle of this
century.</p>
      <p>In this essay, I argue that these three propositions, which are
mutually reinforcing, are fallacies. They misconceive the nature of
discrimination and offer prescriptions that are ill-adapted to its elimination. This
was so even in the period in which they arose and helped to accomplish
considerable good. But their fallacious character will be especially
conspicuous in the last decade of the twentieth and the early decades of the
twenty-first century. In this period, the consequences of the fallacies will
probably be pernicious.</p>
      <p>I do not mean at all to deny that prejudice still plays a major role in
many realms of social and economic life, that the history of
discriminat Karl N. Llewellyn Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago School of Law and
Department of Political Science. B.A. 1975, Harvard University; J.D. 1978, Harvard University.
Mary Becker, Anne-Marie Burley, Jon Elster, and Abner Greene provided helpful comments on an
earlier draft. For financial support, I am grateful to the James H. Douglas, Jr., Fund for the Study
of Law and Government, the Pritzker Family Faculty Fund, and the Jerome F. Kutak Faculty
Fund.</p>
      <p>Some of this essay unites, draws on, and redirects arguments presented elsewhere: Sunstein,
ConstitutionalPoliticsand the Conservative Court,AM. PROSPECT, Spring 1990, at 51; Sunstein, The
Limits of Compensatory Justice, in NOMOS XXXIII: COMPENSATORY JUSTicE (forthcoming);
Sunstein, Why MarketsDon't Stop Discrimination,8 SOC. PHIL. &amp; POL. - (forthcoming).
tion is relevant to present problems, or that courts have a continuing role
to play in the area of civil rights. But surely these claims are thin and
unhelpful in a period when civil rights policy must concern itself with
such problems as lack of opportunities for education, training, and
employment; inadequate housing and health care; vulnerability to and
incentives for participation in crime; and teenage pregnancy and
singleparent families. For these problems, the traditional claims of the civil
rights movement provide at best limited guidance. I conclude with some
brief remarks on future directions for civil rights theory and practice.</p>
      <p>I
FALLACY # 1: DISCRIMINATION Is ALWAYS A PRODUCT OF</p>
      <p>HOSTILITY, IRRATIONALITY, OR PREJUDICE</p>
      <p>In the last generation, it has frequently been suggested that
discriminatory behavior is a product of irrational bigotry or hostility. In this
account, people treat blacks differently from whites, or women differently
from men,1 because of a form of prejudice. The term "prejudice" is, of
course, not self-defining. As conventionally used, the term includes not
simply hatred, but also a wide variety of negative judgments about a class
of people defined by race or gender.</p>
      <p>For present purposes, perhaps we can understand "prejudice" to
encompass three sorts of mistakes.2 The first consists of a belief that
members of a group have certain characteristics when in fact they do not.
Here the relevant belief has no basis in reality, and its irrationality is
especially conspicuous. The second consists of a belief that many or
most members of a group have certain characteristics when in fact only
some or a few do. Here the error is an extremely over-broad
generalization. The third mistake consists of reliance on fairly accurate
groupbased generalizations when more accurate (and not especially costly)
classifying devices are available. Here the members of the group actually
have an undesirable characteristic in comparatively large
numbers-suppose, for example, that they weigh less, or are less well educated-but it
is possible and more rational to use other, more direct devices to filter out
that characteristic. The failure to use those more direct devices reflects a
kind of prejudice.</p>
      <p>In all these cases, it is reasonable to say that someone is acting on
the basis of irrational prejudice. Indeed, taken together, these cases
1. My focus here is on discrimination against blacks, women, and (to a lesser extent) the
handicapped. Of course, other groups are and should be protected by antidiscrimination laws, but at
least some of these groups raise distinctive considerations that I cannot discuss here.</p>
      <p>2. Cf PosnerAn EconomicAnalysis ofSex Discrimination,56 U. CmI. L. REV. 1311, 1318-21
(1989) (discussing the various forms of prejudice that cause sex-based discrimination in the work
place); K. Greenawalt, Law and Objectivity ch. 7 (unpublished manuscript) (on file with author).
probably exhaust the category of prejudice as that term is generally
understood.'</p>
      <p>The theory of civil rights law has often identified "discrimination"
with prejudice, and defined an act as discriminatory when it is caused by
prejudice. To understand the importance of identifying discrimination
with prejudice, it is necessary to understand "discrimination," which is
also, of course, a contested concept. For present purposes, I will
understand discrimination to include a decision to treat a black person or a
woman differently from a white person or a man, regardless of the
motivation.</p>
      <p>An influential approach attributes the practice of discrimination to
the existence of prejudice or irrationality, in the form of a "taste" for
discrimination.4 In the workplace, for example, employers might
discriminate because they do not like to associate with blacks, women, or
others. The engine that drives discrimination is employer irrationality or
prejudice-not economic self-interest, narrowly defined as monetary
gain. Indeed, economic self-interest conflicts with employers' taste for
discrimination. According to a traditional understanding, discriminators
will ultimately be driven from the market because they indulge their
prejudices at the expense of profits.'</p>
      <p>This idea has some truth to it; in some situations, discrimination is
costly. But sometimes discrimination is caused by employer practices
that stem directly from economic self-interest rather than from the
employer's prejudice or irrationality.' Indeed, discrimination may be
fueled by considerations unrelated to the animus of the employer or
discriminator. It may, instead, reflect (1) the desires of third parties; (2)
statistically accurate generalizations; or (3) the consequences of an
unequal status quo for investments in human capital and for preference
formation. To disregard these points is to produce understandings and
3. Strauss, DiscriminatoryIntent and the Taming of Brown, 56 U. CHI. L. REv. 935, 956-59
(1990), suggests that there may be prejudice in the selection of the criteria used to make
judgmentsthat is, the decisionmakers might not have selected the same criteria to make the contested decision
had the shoe been on the other foot. This might well count as another form of prejudice, and if so,
the category is broader than what I have described here. It is difficult, however, to incorporate this
notion of prejudice into antidiscrimination law (as Strauss emphasizes), and Strauss' efforts go well
beyond conventional understandings of "prejudice" and "discrimination."</p>
      <p>4. This view finds its origins in G. BECKER, THE ECONOMICS OF DISCRIMINATION 14 (2d ed.
1971).</p>
      <p>5. But see Akerlof, The Economics of Caste and of the RatRace and Other Woeful Tales, 90
Q.J. ECON. 599, 608-10 (1976) (despite its apparent inefficiency, a caste system may remain in
equilibrium through the use of powerful sanctions against those who threaten the social system).</p>
      <p>6. Becker in fact recognizes this point, describing those with a "taste" for discrimination as
including fellow workers and customers as well as employers. G. BECKER, supra note 4, at 14-15;
see also Arrow, Models ofJob Discrimination,in RACIAL DISCRIMINATION IN ECONOMIC LIFE 83,
88 (A. Pascal ed. 1972) (fellow workers and customers may also discriminate).
ultimately prescriptions that are ill-suited to the problem of
discrimination in the United States in the late twentieth century.</p>
      <p>A.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Third Parties</title>
      <p>The clearest illustration of discrimination not driven by economic
irrationality occurs when third parties are in a position to impose
financial punishments on nondiscriminatory employers. 7 Suppose, for
example, that purchasers or fellow employees refuse to buy from or to work
for a company that does not discriminate. Even if employers would
themselves choose not to discriminate or have no particular view about
whether or not to discriminate, third parties can pressure employers to
discriminate.</p>
      <p>The phenomenon is hardly unusual. Consider, for example, the case
of a shopkeeper whose customers do not like dealing with blacks or
women, a commercial airline whose patrons react unfavorably to female
pilots, a law firm whose clients prefer not to have black lawyers, or a
hospital whose patients are uncomfortable with female doctors or black
nurses. The persistence, for a long period, of private segregation in major
league baseball is a familiar example of this basic phenomenon. 8</p>
      <p>In all these cases, an employer who introduces norms of equality
into the work force will be punished, not rewarded. For the employer
faced with consumers or employees who prefer discrimination, a decision
to engage in discrimination is in an important respect neutral. He is
simply maximizing his profits by respecting consumer demand. Indeed, an
employer who refuses to discriminate will be engaging in what is, from
his point of view, a form of affirmative action. If he must become a
nondiscriminator, it will be to promote the long-range goal of race and
sex equality. 9</p>
      <p>All this suggests that discrimination can be a product not of
prejudice, but of responses to market pressures from third parties. Of course,
prejudice is in some sense at work-by customers or fellow
employeesbut the discriminator is not himself acting from prejudice or irrationality.</p>
      <p>7. Here I largely follow Akerlof, supra note 5, at 608-10 (threat of sanctions by third parties
may keep apparently inefficient caste system in equilibrium); see also id. at 610 ("those who fail to
follow ... the caste customs do not gain the profits of the successful arbitrageur but instead suffer the
stigma of the outcast").</p>
      <p>8. Customer discrimination also has become apparent quite recently in the market for
baseball cards, which shows a 10% to 13% "racial discount" for the cards of black players. See
Nardinelli &amp; Simon, Customer Racial Discriminationin the Marketfor Memorabilia:The Case of
Baseball, 105 Q.J. ECON. 575, 594 (1990).</p>
      <p>9. The idea that discrimination is a result of hostility or prejudice lies at the root of attacks on
affirmative action. In fact, discrimination is sometimes based on rational self-interest. If this is so,
the distinction between affirmative action and an antidiscrimination principle becomes much
thinner. See infra text accompanying notes 16-18.
It is here that the traditional understanding is misconceived. 10</p>
      <p>Sometimes discriminatory behavior is a result of generalizations or
stereotypes that, although over-broad and perhaps invidious, provide an
economically rational basis for employment decisions. 1 Stereotypes and
generalizations are, of course, a common ingredient in day-to-day
decisions. There are informational costs in making distinctions within
categories, and sometimes people prefer to avoid the often far more costly
examination of the merits of the particular employee.</p>
      <p>Such categorical judgments are not only pervasive, but they are also
entirely legitimate in most settings. We all depend on them. Employers
rely on "proxies" of many sorts, even though those proxies are
overbroad generalizations and far from entirely accurate. Test scores,
previous employment, college or high school education, prestige of college
attended-all these are part of rational employment decisions. Emphasis
on these factors is a common form of stereotyping, and at least in
ordinary circumstances, it would be odd to say that such factors reflect
hostility or prejudice of the invidious kind.</p>
      <p>At least in some contexts, race and sex operate as similar proxies.
In various ways, blacks differ from whites and women from men. There
are real differences between the two groups. Indeed, in light of past and
present discrimination against blacks and women, it would be shocking if
there were no group-based differences. Women, for example, are more
likely than men to be the primary caretakers of children and more likely
to leave the employment market because of that role. 2 Along every
indicator of social welfare-poverty, education, employment, vulnerability to
private (or public) violence, participation in violent crime-blacks are
proportionally less well off than whites. In light of those differences, it is
fully possible that in certain settings, race- and sex-based generalizations
10. In one respect, courts have acknowledged this point. In title VII litigation, customer
preferences do not count as a "bona fide occupational qualification" (BFOQ) sufficient to justify
facially discriminatory hiring practices. See, eg., Diaz v. Pan Am. World Airways, 442 F.2d 385,
389 (5th Cir.) (holding that customer preference for male flight attendants was not a BFOQ), cert.
denied, 404 U.S. 950 (1971); Fernandez v. Wynn Oil Co., 653 F.2d 1273, 1276-77 (9th Cir. 1981)
(customer preference not BFOQ); see also 29 C.F.R. § 1604.2(a)(1)(iii) (1990) (preferences of
coworkers or customers not BFOQ).</p>
      <p>11. Arrow, supra note 6, at 96-97 (stating that costs of acquiring more accurate information
may make discrimination economically "rational"); Strauss, The Myth of Colorblindness, 1986 Sup.
Cr. REv. 99, 108-10 (defining and illustrating concept of"rational" discrimination); see also Phelps,
The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism, 62 AM. ECON. REv. 659, 660 (1972) (presenting a
model for "economically rational" discrimination).</p>
      <p>12. This phenomenon of course does not mean that differential treatment is permissible.
Whether such treatment should be allowed need hardly depend solely on its being economically
rational. See infra text accompanying notes 63-64.
[V/ol. 79:751
are economically rational as proxies for relevant characteristics.
Moreover, race or sex in some contexts may be every bit as accurate a
predictor of job performance as, say, test scores, education, and previous
employment. And in some cases, reliance on more direct and
individualized devices might be too costly to be worthwhile.</p>
      <p>If race or sex can be a good predictor of performance, an employer
may discriminate not because he hates or devalues blacks or women, or
because he has a general desire to avoid them, or is prejudiced in any of
the senses I have discussed, but because he believes (on the basis either of
plausible assumption or actual experience) that the relevant stereotypes
have sufficient truth to provide a rational basis for employment decisions.
An employer might, for example, believe that women are more likely to
leave a high-pressure job than men, or that blacks are less likely to have
the necessary training. For the handicapped, the same scenario is of
course readily predictable; real differences call for differential treatment.
Ordinary prejudice and irrationality are thus not at work.</p>
      <p>It is important to be careful with this point. As I understand it,
statistical discrimination occurs when the employer does not harbor
irrational hatred or discriminatory feelings, but instead acts according to
stereotypes of the sort market actors typically rely on, which are of course
false in some or many cases, but which cannot readily be abandoned for
more direct inquiries. I do not mean to deny that ordinary, irrational
prejudice accounts for a significant amount of discrimination. Nor do I
deny that it is hard both in practice and in principle to distinguish
between ordinary prejudice and economically rational stereotyping.</p>
      <p>Sometimes, of course, employers who refuse to follow a stereotype
may find job candidates who will move them far ahead in the
marketplace. Moreover, the decision about what kinds of economically rational
stereotypes to adopt might itself reflect prejudice. 3 People are highly
selective in creating and using the very categories through which they
view people-as college graduates? as children of successful parents? as
nonreligious? as white males? as tall? as good-looking? by what criteria?</p>
      <p>People are also selective in deciding which categories ought to count
in various sectors. Thus, for example, the use of sex as a proxy for
flexibility with respect to overtime work may be fully rational; but as I have
noted, selectivity in the choice of the proxy is a product of prejudice if, as
is usual, other equal or better proxies are available. Indeed, like the
selection of stereotypes, the selection of criteria might itself be a product
13. Cf G. LAKOFF, WOMEN, FIRE, AND DANGEROUS THINGS: WHAT CATEGORIES REVEAL
ABOUT THE MIND 12-57 (1987) (discussing processes of categorization); M. MINOW, MAKING ALL
THE DIFFERENCE 19-48 (1990) (discussing use of categories as lens through which difference is
viewed).
of a kind of prejudice.14 Finally, people tend to notice events that are
consistent with previously held stereotypes and to disregard events that
are inconsistent with them. 5 Here there is a built-in obstacle to changes
in social norms even when those norms decreasingly mirror reality.</p>
      <p>One might agree with all this and still acknowledge what seems
undoubtedly true, that discrimination sometimes persists because it is
economically rational to rely on a race- or sex-based generalization. And
because contemporary law singles out one kind of rational stereotyping
to ban it, the distinction between affirmative action and
antidiscrimination norms becomes extremely thin and perhaps invisible in principle. 6
The antidiscrimination principle-of course, widely accepted-forbids
government from*discriminating against blacks and women, even when
such discrimination is economically rational. Affirmative action-of
course, a highly controversial practice-calls for employment and other
preferences for members of disadvantaged groups. The two ideas are
often thought to be in severe tension,1 7 and indeed, for advocates of
affirmative action, the antidiscrimination principle sometimes seems an
embarrassment.</p>
      <p>In some settings, however, an antidiscrimination norm, conceived as
a barrier to economically rational behavior, has the same purposes and
effects as affirmative action. Affirmative action is controversial partly
because it can be economically irrational, can impose serious social costs,
and harms innocent victims." But an antidiscrimination principle often
does precisely the same as what affirmative action does, and also does it
in the interest of long-term social goals. For example, an
antidiscrimination norm may require innocent victims to sacrifice-customers may be
required to pay higher prices-in order to produce long-term equality.</p>
      <p>A great failure of the assault on affirmative action is its inability to
account for the ways in which a requirement of nondiscrimination
involves very much the same considerations. Indeed, the distinction
between affirmative action and antidiscrimination is sharp only to those
who see discrimination as always grounded in hostility and irrationality,
which it clearly is not.</p>
      <p>14. See Strauss, supra note 3, at 957-58 (suggesting a "reversing the groups" test to determine
whether the choice of classification criteria reflects discriminatory intent).</p>
      <p>15. See E. ARONSON, THE SOCIAL ANIMAL 174-76 (1972). "Prejudice[d] people see the world
in ways that are consistent with their prejudice." Id. at 174.</p>
      <p>16. See Strauss, supra note 11, at 130 ("There are fundamental similarities between
nondiscrimination and affirmative action.").</p>
      <p>17. See Van Alstyne, Rites of Passage"Race, the Supreme Court,and the Constitution, 46 U.
CHI. L. REv. 775, 802-03 (1979) (equating affirmative action with discrimination); id. at 809
(referring to affirmative action as a "suggestion to relicense racial discrimination").</p>
      <p>18. See, e-g., id. at 801-02 (affirmative action program in Regents of the University of
California v. Bakke, 438 U.S. 265 (1978), harmed innocent victims); id at 805-08 (no rational way to
determine racial eligibility for affirmative action program); see also Strauss, supra note 11, at 110-11.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>The Effects of Discriminationon Human Capitaland Problems of</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>Preference Formation</title>
      <p>Suppose that there has been widespread discrimination for any
number of reasons: employers have a taste for discrimination; third
parties impose pressure on employers to discriminate; employers use
statistical generalizations that are rational. Once the discrimination becomes
established, members of disadvantaged groups will suffer from harmful
effects on investment in human capital and on preference formation. t9
L</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>Human Capital</title>
      <p>The productivity of participants in the labor market is endogenous
to, or partly a product of, discrimination in that market. It is a mistake
to take productivity within any social group as static or unaffected by
employer decisions. Such decisions will have important dynamic effects
on how blacks and whites, or women and men, choose to invest in
human capital. Decisions about education, child care, training, drug use,
employment programs, and tradeoffs between work and leisure will be
affected by existing patterns of discrimination. In a market having such
discrimination, members of disadvantaged groups will invest relatively
less in education and training programs. Indeed, lower investments on
their part are perfectly rational. As market actors, women should invest
less than men in training to be (for example) pilots, economists,
politicians, lawyers, or law professors if these professions discriminate against
women and thus reward their investment less than that of men.</p>
      <p>The result will often be a vicious circle or even a spiral. Because of
existing discrimination, the relevant groups will invest less in human
capital; because of this lower investment, the discrimination will persist or
perhaps increase as its statistical rationality itself increases; because of
this effect, investments will decrease still further, and so on.</p>
      <p>Undoubtedly, this picture is too bleak in many situations. Other
proxies, not rooted in sex and race, have frequently evolved and
employers have used them. Such proxies are ordinarily far more accurate, and
employers who use them sometimes prosper. More generally, the
extraordinary persistence of blacks and women in attempting to enter
professions dominated by white men is one of the most striking
phenomena of the post-World War II period. Blacks and women frequently
appear to invest huge amounts in human capital, even in sectors that
treat them inhospitably.20 But there is little question that discrimination
does have a large effect on investments in human capital in many
con19. Arrow, supra note 6, at 88; Lundberg &amp; Startz, Private Discrimination and Social
Intervention in Competitive Labor Markets, 73 AM. ECON. REv. 340, 342 (1983).</p>
      <p>20. In fact, some people in some circumstances respond to discrimination by increasing rather
than decreasing their investments in human capital. In Western history, some racial and ethnic
texts, and that the hostile reception given to disadvantaged groups
perpetuates their exclusion from certain sectors of the economy. In that
case, inequality will be the result of discrimination that is itself the
product not only of past irrational hostility or prejudice, but also of a far more
complex system of interactions with economically rational employment
decisions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>Preferences</title>
      <p>An additional problem is that private preferences, of both
discriminators and their victims, tend to adapt to the status quo, and to do so in
such a way as to make significant change hard to achieve. The reduction
of cognitive dissonance is a powerful motivating force: people attempt to
bring their beliefs and perceptions in line with existing practice.2 1 The
victims of inequality tend to reduce dissonance by adapting their
preferences to the available opportunities. Consider the story of the fox who
concludes that he does not want unavailable grapes because he considers
them sour: he considers them sour because they are unavailable.2 2 Or
people may adapt their aspirations to the persistent and often irrationally
held belief that the world is in fact just.23 The beneficiaries of the status
quo tend to do the same, concluding that the victims deserve their fate,
that they are responsible for it, or that the current situation is part of an
intractable, given, or natural order.24</p>
      <p>There is extremely powerful evidence in the psychological literature
to support these claims. 25 For example, people who behave cruelly
change their attitudes toward the objects of their cruelty and thus
devalue them. Observers of cruelty and violence tend to do the same.
The phenomenon of blaming the victim has clear cognitive and
groups have prospered as a result of such investments, notwithstanding discriminatory tastes on the
part of employers, customers, and fellow employees.</p>
      <p>21. See L. FESTINGER, A THEORY OF COGNITIVE DISSONANCE 18-19 (1957). On the
phenomenon in this particular context, see Arrow, supra note 6, at 97. See generally J. ELsTER,
SOUR GRAPES 15-26 (1983).</p>
      <p>22. See AESOP'S FABLES 21 (Hague ed. 1985); see also J. ELSTER, supra note 21, at 110-40
(describing "sour grapes" response as a way to reduce cognitive dissonance).</p>
      <p>23. See J. ELSTER, supra note 21, at 101-08 (asserting that the search for explanations for
injustice stems from theology and biology); M. LERNER, THE BELIEF IN A JUST WORLD: A
FUNDAMENTAL DELUSION 123-26 (1980) (because of the belief that the world is just, victims may
blame themselves in order to assert control over their otherwise meaningless misfortune).</p>
      <p>24. See generally M. LERNER, supra note 23, at 50 (results of experiment show that people
tend to condemn an apparently blameless victim to reassert their belief in a just world and to lessen
cognitive dissonance).</p>
      <p>25. See, eg., sources cited supra notes 21 &amp; 23; E. ARONSON, supra note 15, at 89-137
(discussing numerous experiments of people trying to reduce cognitive dissonance); Furnham &amp;
Gunter, Just World Beliefs andAttitudes Towards the Poor,23 BRrr. J. Soc. PSYCHOLOGY 265, 268
(1984) (noting that observers tend to view the poor as responsible for their fate); Janoff-Bulman,
Timko &amp; Carli, Cognitive Biases in Blaming the Victim, 21 J. EXPERIMENTAL SOC. PSYCHOLOGY
161 (1985) (discussing sources of the phenomenon of "blaming the victim").
motivational foundations. The notion that the world is just, and that
existing inequalities are deserved or desired, plays a large role in forming
preferences and beliefs. All these phenomena have played an enormous
part in the history of racial and sexual discrimination.</p>
      <p>The inevitable effect of a discriminatory status quo on preferences
and beliefs is closely related to the phenomenon of decreased investment
in human capital. In both cases, the response to discrimination is
endogenous rather than exogenous and has the consequence of perpetuating
existing inequalities. But with respect to preferences and beliefs, the
effect is especially pernicious. And when there are harmful effects on the
development of preferences and beliefs, discrimination will occur for
reasons that are not directly traceable to acts of irrationality or prejudice.26</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>D. In General:Reinforcing Effects</title>
      <p>The arguments I have offered thus far build on standard economic
accounts of discrimination. It is notable that none of the various effects
reflects an uncontroversial market failure in the conventional sense.
The incorporation of racist or sexist preferences is efficient, if the
efficiency criterion is based on private willingness to pay; 28 the same applies
with profit-maximizing reactions to the desires of third parties and with
statistical discrimination. In all these cases, governmental interference
will probably produce an efficiency loss, at least in the short term.2 9</p>
      <p>The most likely exception is the effect of discrimination on human
capital and preference formation. 0 In that case, it is possible that
discrimination will produce a serious externality in the form of harmful
effects on prospective labor market entrants, with a corresponding
efficiency loss. If discrimination discourages members of disadvantaged
groups from investing in human capital, it will produce large social losses
by decreasing potentially large sources of productivity. Ideas of this sort
may provide the basis for a fully plausible efficiency justification for
antidiscrimination law.</p>
      <p>26. Of course prejudice and irrationality are in the background here, in that they helped create
the conditions under which the relevant acts take place. In this sense, prejudice and irrationality are
hardly irrelevant. But to say that existing distributions of benefits and burdens between blacks and
whites is in significant part a legacy of prejudice is quite different from saying that particular acts of
present discrimination are produced by prejudice or irrationality on the part of the discriminator.
See supra text accompanying note 10.</p>
      <p>27. My use of the term "market failure" here builds on the conventional economic analysis.
28. But cf. Donohue, Is Title VII Efficient?, 134 U. PA. L. Rav. 1411, 1430 (1986) (concluding
that title VII increases "total social welfare," apparently relying on a conception of efficiency based
on a notion of social output or production). The same criterion can be found in Schwab, Is
StatisticalDiscrimination Efficient?, 76 AM. ECON. REV. 228, 233 (1986) (noting that statistical
discrimination may be "socially inefficient").</p>
      <p>29. But see Donohue,supra note 28, at 1420-21, 1430; Schwab, supra note 28, at 233.
30. See Lundberg &amp; Startz, supra note 19, at 342.</p>
      <p>There is, however, an optimal level of investment in human capital,
and it is not entirely clear why and to what extent investments that are
adaptive to employer behavior in the labor market should be seen as
suboptimal. Any generalization relied on in the labor market will have a
signaling effect that will shift investments in human capital. It is not easy
to develop a model to explain which of those signals produce suboptimal
investments. Often, then, markets will perpetuate discrimination for
reasons that are unrelated to the market failures that provide traditional
economic grounds for legal intervention.</p>
      <p>More importantly, each of these effects reinforces the others in
potentially powerful ways. If there is ordinary prejudice, it will interact
with statistical discrimination to produce more of both. People tend to
notice events consistent with their prejudice and to disregard events that
are inconsistent with them, thus resulting in more prejudice and more
statistical discrimination. If third parties attempt to promote
discrimination, they will increase both prejudice and statistical discrimination.
Employers will hire fewer members of disadvantaged groups, who will in
turn appear less frequently in desirable positions, with consequent
reinforcing effects on both prejudice and statistical discrimination.</p>
      <p>In addition, if there is prejudice and statistical discrimination, and if
third parties promote discrimination, there will be decreased investments
in human capital and increasing adaptation of preferences and beliefs to
the status quo. These will be perfectly reasonable responses. And if
there are decreased investments in human capital, the result will be
increases in prejudice, statistical discrimination, and third-party effects.
Statistical discrimination will become all the more rational; prejudice will
continue; and consumers and employers will be more likely to
discriminate.</p>
      <p>Of course, it would be necessary to compile detailed factual evidence
to assess the magnitude of these effects. Analysis of that issue is difficult
in the abstract. But the general point should be clear. Discrimination is
not a simple result of prejudice or hostility, but instead reflects a far more
complex interplay of past and present discrimination, social and
economic factors, and economically rational decisions. If civil rights law
treats decisions to discriminate as based on prejudice or irrationality, it
will badly misconceive the problem and produce remedies that are
illsuited to its elimination.</p>
      <p>II
FALLACY #2: PRINCIPLES OF COMPENSATORY JUSTICE SHOULD</p>
      <p>PLAY A GUIDING ROLE IN CIVIL RIGHTS POLICY</p>
      <p>Much of the rhetoric of the civil rights movements is built on
principles of compensatory justice. According to these principles, those who
have caused harm to a person or group must repair the harm. For
example, slavery and segregation have played a large role in producing
secondclass citizenship for blacks in America. A principal purpose of civil
rights law is to undo the historical wrong, thus returning to the status
quo ante.</p>
      <p>Those who base civil rights law on principles of compensatory
justice attempt to link public and private law, assimilating the problem of
discrimination to the problems that arise in ordinary tort actions. And
there is certainly something valuable to the effort. If a person is in a
subordinate position because of wrongs done to her, or even to her
parents, that person's inequality is a product of a morally irrelevant factor3 1
in the form of an injustice, and for that reason she has a legitimate claim
to redress. In this way, the compensatory rhetoric of the civil rights
movement properly links contemporary efforts to past injustices.</p>
      <p>In important respects, however, the model of compensatory justice
inadequately captures the nature of the problem and is therefore a recipe
for confusion. The confusion arises in the many cases in which courts
approach questions of equality by way of traditional principles of
compensatory justice. For example, the requirement of "discriminatory
intent"3 might well be understood as an effort to adhere to
compensatory principles in this setting. The question, thus conceived, is whether
an identifiable actor has harmed an identifiable person in an identifiable
way. To abandon the touchstone of intent would lead courts far from the
compensatory model. It would lead courts to require redress of social
wrongs committed by third parties in the distant past, which would
involve conspicuous social reordering and harms to innocent persons,
rather than a restoration of some well-defined status quo ante.3 3</p>
      <p>To be sure, the approach of the courts-and especially of the
Supreme Court-has been based on a narrow conception of
compensation. A broader compensatory principle would promote far more legal
victories for members of disadvantaged groups.34 In this more expansive
view, the redress of harms other than those created by the particular
practice in question would be the goal of the equality principle. The
notion of compensation would remain, but it would require public and
private employers to ensure that the distribution of benefits and burdens
31. See J. RAwLS, A THEORY OF JUSTICE 100-04 (1971); see also infra text accompanying
note 61.</p>
      <p>32. E.g., Village of Arlington Heights v. Metropolitan Hous. Dev. Corp., 429 U.S. 252, 265
(1977); Washington v. Davis, 426 U.S. 229, 239 (1976).</p>
      <p>33. The point is suggested by the Court in Davis, 426 U.S. at 248.</p>
      <p>34. The Court's discriminatory intent test has been subject to criticism. See, e.g., Lawrence,
The Id, the Ego, and EqualProtection:Reckoning With UnconsciousRacism, 39 STAN. L. REv. 317
(1987); Strauss, supra note 3, at 954-56.
between blacks and whites would be roughly what it would have been
without the legacy of discrimination.</p>
      <p>It is doubtful, however, that such an approach would be feasible.
What would the world look like if it had been unaffected by past
discrimination on the basis of race and sex? The general problem is that the
compensatory model, in any form, is based on notions of causation,
injury, and restoration to the status quo ante that are well adapted to tort
or contract setting, but singularly ill-suited to the problem of
discrimination in the United States.</p>
      <p>We might begin with the issue of school desegregation, where
compensatory ideas play a prominent role. Suppose that a school district
engaged in de jure segregation until 1954, and that in 1958, 1968, or
1978, a judge issues a finding to that effect. What remedy ought to be
imposed? The Supreme Court's cases are exceptionally complex on this
point.35 The Court's basic approach seems to be an attempt to restore
the status quo ante. In desegregation cases, the Court asks whether the
proposed remedy will restore the system to what it would have been were
it not for past acts of segregation. Under this rationale, the Court has
invalidated "freedom of choice" desegregation plans, emphasizing that
they will bring about less desegregation than would have occurred if
there had been no segregation in the first instance.3 6</p>
      <p>Principles of compensatory justice play a prominent, indeed central
role here. They define the very nature of the inquiry. Some Justices, for
example, emphasize the difficulty of finding a good causal connection
between post-1970 or 1980 practices and pre-1954 discrimination.37 For
them, the weak causal connection means that the law should not make
people restructure present practices. By contrast, other Justices
emphasize the legacy of past discrimination and what they see as its undeniable
causal connection to present patterns of segregation. 38</p>
      <p>Both sides appear, however, to miss the fact that issues of causation,
and the compensatory principles that underlie them, have little
coherence in this context. An inquiry into the amount of racial integration
that would have occurred in a world unaffected by racial segregation is
likely to be empirically unanchored, indeed, chimerical. Social scientists,
let alone judges, are simply not equipped to answer that question-not
because they lack appropriate tools, but because the question itself is of
uncertain epistemological status. One simply cannot sort out the
connection between legal segregation in 1950 and educational patterns in 1990.
The status quo ante-whatever it might have been--cannot be
conceptualized. To try to resolve issues bearing on desegregation remedies in
terms of compensatory principles is to ask unanswerable questions.</p>
      <p>The problem is far more general. What would our practices be in a
world without race and sex discrimination? How would one treat (for
example) veterans' preferences in the absence of sexism, or literacy tests
for voting and employment in the absence of racism? In all these cases,
the restoration of a status quo ante is a conceptually incoherent task.
Moreover, it is not even clear whether past discrimination presents the
basic reason for the legal responses to the present status of blacks.
Whether such discrimination is a necessary or sufficient condition for
"remedial" efforts is by no means self-evident.3 9</p>
      <p>Similar problems arise in cases involving affirmative action. The
Supreme Court has frequently indicated that race-conscious measures are
permissible only as a "remedy" for identifiable acts of purposeful
discrimination undertaken within the jurisdiction of the governmental
institution engaging in affirmative action. 4' Here, too, compensatory
principles are in the forefront, allowing affirmative action only as a
response to tort-like acts. By contrast, affirmative action grounded in an
effort to overcome "societal discrimination" is generally impermissible."
In so holding, the Court has emphasized that the victims of affirmative
action are either employers or, much more frequently, white people or
men who never engaged in discriminatory conduct.</p>
      <p>The problem of innocent victims4 2 appears to be a principal impetus
behind the requirement of a showing of past discrimination. Under
current law, affirmative action can thus be defended most easily in tort-like
terms as an effort to restore a status quo ante that has been unsettled by
identifiable acts producing identifiable harms to identifiable actors. The
problem here, as elsewhere, is that affirmative action does not fit the tort
model. Although the redress of past discrimination is an important
element in the theory and practice of civil rights law, there is no
welldefined status quo against which compensatory principles can operate.</p>
      <p>To put the point most generally: It is true that past acts of
discrimination help account for the socially subordinate status of disadvantaged
groups, and when this is so, some sort of remedial principle should play a
39. See Sullivan, Sins of Discrimination,100 HARV. L. REv. 78, 83-84, 96 (1986) (suggesting
that the Court could have justified "remedial" affirmative action plans by reference to exclusively
forward-looking goals, such as improving education or promoting diversity in the workplace).
40. See, eg., City of Richmond v. J.A. Croson Co., 488 U.S. 469, 509 (1989).
41. See, eg., id. at 499.</p>
      <p>42. By this term, I mean whites or men who may benefit from but are not responsible for past
and present discriminatory practices.
role in civil rights theory. But to try to decide questions about the scope
and nature of antidiscrimination policy by reference to compensatory
notions is a recipe for confusion and for unproductive-because
unresolvable--disagreements.</p>
      <p>III
FALLACY #3: COURTS ARE THE APPROPRIATE INSTITUTION FOR
BRINGING ABOUT SOCIAL CHANGE IN THE AREA OF CIVIL RIGHTS</p>
      <p>During and after the period of the Warren Court, it has been
commonplace to suggest that federal courts should set much of civil rights
policy through the process of constitutional adjudication.43 The courts'
insulation-from an electoral process that is often said to have produced
civil rights violations in the first place-is considered a comparative
virtue, allowing the judges to implement antidiscrimination principles
without being affected by political biases. There can be no question that
because of their insulation, judges have often been in an unusually good
position to elaborate and implement principles of antidiscrimination.
But for several reasons, reliance on the judiciary may have been a
mistake. It may have diverted attention from more productive alternatives
and at the same time disserved the very causes at issue. In any case, such
reliance seems a poor strategy for the future. Three considerations are
relevant here.</p>
      <p>Judicial decisions are of limited efficacy in bringing about social
change. Study after study has confirmed this basic conclusion. 4 Brown
v. Board ofEducation15 is usually offered as a counter-example, but it is
in fact the most conspicuous confirmation of the point.46 Ten years after
the decision, no more than about two percent of black children in the
South attended desegregated schools.47 It was not until 1964, after
Congress and the executive branch became involved, that widespread
desegregation actually occurred. The Court is far more effective at
vetoing a decision of another government entity than it is at effecting social
change on its own. Of course, it is possible that the legislative and
executive actions would not have occurred without the spur of Brown, but
43. See, eg., Fiss, Foreword: The Forms of Justice, 93 HARV. L. REv. 1 (1979).
44. See D. HoRowrrz, THE COURTS AND SOCIAL POLICY 56-62 (1977); R. MELNICK,
REGULATION AND THE COURT: THE CASE OF THE CLEAN AIR ACT 110-12 (1983); G.
ROSENBERG, THE HOLLOW HOPE: CAN COURTS BRING ABOUT SOCIAL CHANGE? (forthcoming
Oct. 1991).</p>
      <p>45. 347 U.S. 483 (1954).
46. See G. ROSENBERG, supra note 44, at 42-71.</p>
      <p>47. See G. STONE, L. SEIDMAN, C. SUNSTEIN &amp;M. TUSHNET, CONSTITUTIONAL LAW 474
(1986).
even this seems uncertain.48</p>
      <p>The decision in Roe v. Wade 4 9 may be another illustration, though
the picture here is more complex. It is undoubtedly true that the
decision increased women's access to safe abortions, and to some extent it
may have increased the legitimacy of abortion. By 1973, however, state
legislatures were moving firmly to expand legal access to abortion,5 ° and
it is likely that a broad guarantee of access would have been available
even without Roe. However surprising the point may be, Roe did not
dramatically increase the actual number or rate of abortions. 1 Perhaps
more fundamentally, the decision may well have created the Moral
Majority, helped defeat the equal rights amendment, and undermined the
women's movement by spurring opposition and demobilizing potential
adherents5. 2 At the same time, Roe may have taken national policy too
abruptly to a point toward which it was groping more slowly, 5 3 and in
the process may have prevented state legislatures from working out
longlasting solutions based upon broad public consensus.</p>
      <p>We might in this regard contrast Roe v. Wade with the Civil Rights
Act of 1964, a legislative enactment brought about through general
public support. The foundational civil rights law in the United States has a
kind of legitimacy and support that makes it extremely hard to amend at
48. See G. ROSENBERG, supra note 44, at 107-56.
49. 410 U.S. 113 (1973).</p>
      <p>50. See Morgan, Roe v. Wade and the Lesson of the Pre-Roe Case Law, 77 MICH. L. REV.
1724, 1726 (1979).</p>
      <p>51. There is good reason to believe that in the early 1960s, there were between 1.0 and 1.5
million abortions in the United States each year. That is, at least 20% and perhaps as many as 30%
of all pregnancies ended in abortion. See, eg., L. LADER, ABORTION 2 (1966) (referring to the
"recent" estimate of 1.5 million); R. SCHWARTZ, SEPTIC ABORTION 7 (1968) (in the late 1960s, over
20% of pregnancies terminated in illegal abortions, resulting in approximately 1.2 million unlawful
abortions per year); J. VAN DER TAK, ABORTION, FERTILITY, AND CHANGING LEGISLATION: AN
INTERNATIONAL REVIEW 72-73 (1974) (referring to "the wide acceptance of a round figure of 1
million induced abortions per year (of which only an estimated 8,000 were legal), corresponding to
... an abortion ratio of almost 30 per 100 live births"); Whittemore, The Availability ofNon.Hospital
Abortions, in 1ABORTION IN A CHANGING WORLD 217 (R. Hall ed. 1970) ("the oft-quoted figure of
one million criminal abortions in the United States is a fairly reasonable estimate"); see also H.
RODMAN, B. SARVIS, &amp; J. BONAR, THE ABORTION QUESTION 23 (1987) (estimate of 1 million
illegal abortions per year prior to Roe); Fox, Abortion Related Deaths, in 98 AM. J. OBSTETRICS &amp;
GYNECOLOGY 645, 645-46 (1967) (estimating that between 35,000 and 100,000 women annually had
unlawful abortions in California alone during this period). Police reports reveal that in 1960, illegal
abortion was the third largest illegal enterprise in the United States, after gambling and narcotics.
See E. SCHUR, CRIMES WITHOUT VICTIMS, DEVIANT BEHAVIOR AND PUBLIC POLICY 25 (1965).
But see N. LEE, THE SEARCH FOR AN ABORTIONIST 5-15 (1969) (describing the difficulty of finding
accurate data on the numbers of illegal abortions because they are carried out in a decentralized
way).</p>
      <p>52. See J. MANSBRIDGE, WHY WE LOST THE ERA 122-28 (1986) (documenting some of these
propositions).</p>
      <p>53. See Morgan, supra note 50, at 1726.
all except to broaden it. At least in part because of its judicial source,
Roe has no such status.</p>
      <p>We have seen some evidence for all these propositions in the recent
past, with the extraordinary public reaction to the Supreme Court's
Webster decision. 4 The Court's partial retreat from Roe may well have
galvanized the women's movement in a way that will have more
favorable and fundamental long-term consequences for sexual equality
than anything that could have come from the Court. This is not to say
that Roe was necessarily wrong, either as a matter of constitutional
interpretation or as a matter of principle. But its effectiveness has been
limited, largely because of its judicial source. The civil rights movement has
been similarly spurred by recent Supreme Court decisions, which have
led in turn to an aggressive civil rights bill supported in large measure by
a Republican President."5</p>
      <p>More generally, it is not clear that the United States has developed
significantly different antidiscrimination principles from those in other
liberal democracies that lack judicial review (most notably France,
England, and until recently, Canada) or that have such review but have
quite different constitutions (most notably, Germany). Of course,
judicial review has in some settings accomplished considerable good and
even introduced important changes into American society. But the
evidence suggests that judges are less effective than the elected branches of
the government in attempting to reform systems of discrimination.</p>
      <p>B.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>Democracy, Citizenship, Compromise, and Legitimacy</title>
      <p>For achieving sensible and effective reform, political channels are
often far better than the courts. The resort to politics can produce a kind
of citizen mobilization that is a public and private good, and can
inculcate political commitments, broader understanding, feelings of
citizenship, and dedication to the community. All these may in turn spur
deeper and wiser social change in the area of civil rights than reliance on
the judiciary would provide. Martin Luther King, Jr., may well have
been a more important catalyst for constitutional change than any or
54. Webster v. Reproductive Health Servs., 492 U.S. 490 (1989).</p>
      <p>55. The Civil Rights Act of 1990 was introduced in the U.S. Senate and House of
Representatives in February 1990. S. 2104, 101st Cong., 2d Sess., 136 CONG. REC. S1018-21 (daily
ed. Feb. 7, 1990); H.R. 4000, 101st Cong., 2d Sess., 136 CONG. REc. H364 (daily ed. Feb. 7, 1990).
President Bush did veto the Civil Rights Restoration Act, but his disagreement actually focused only
on one part of the Act, not exactly a trivial provision, but one that should be seen as a mere piece in
an extremely broad and far-ranging measure. President Bush approved ofalmost all other aspects of
that measure. See President's Veto of S. 2104-Civil Rights Act of 1990, 1990 U.S. CODE CONG. &amp;
ADMIN. NEWS D36. The fight over the Act is not yet over; Congress reintroduced the Act in
January 1991. H.R. 1, 102d Cong., 1st Sess., 137 CONG. REC. H53 (daily ed. Jan. 3, 1991).
even all of the Warren Court's race decisions.5 6</p>
      <p>It is often thought that the very fact that courts are unrepresentative
is one of their strengths; they serve as an available alternative to
democratic channels. But reliance on the courts has large and hidden
disadvantages. It may divert energy and resources from political processes,
and the substitution effect imposes large costs on these processes. And if
questions of morality -tend to become questions of constitutional law,
their resolution before nine judges can harm the practice of citizenship.
As noted, some of this effect is already visible in the abortion
controversy. The same may also be true for racial discrimination, though the
evidence is more ambiguous here.</p>
      <p>This is not to deny that judicial review can make up for systemic
inequalities in majoritarian processes and impose the kind of principled
deliberation that comes to such processes only with difficulty. But
reliance on an aggressive Court is, from the standpoint of civil rights policy,
the furthest thing from an unambiguous good; and this is so even if the
Court's goals are sound.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>C. The NarrowingFocus of Adjudication</title>
      <p>Despite innovative theories and practices,5 7 adjudication remains an
extremely poor system for achieving social reform. Courts are rarely
expert in the area before them. Moreover, the focus on the litigated case
hampers judges' efforts to understand the complex systemic effects of
legal intervention. A decision to require expenditures on school busing
might, for example, divert resources from an area with an equal or
greater claim to the public fisc.</p>
      <p>More fundamentally, legal thinking and legal procedures are most
suited to ideas growing out of the tradition of compensatory justice,
which is poorly adapted to the achievement of serious social reform.
Adjudication is ill-suited to undertaking the necessary changes. Many of
the most important problems in current civil rights policy are systemic
and complex. The lack of adequate schools, job training, or jobs creates
a cycle of poverty, vulnerability to drugs and to crime, teenage
pregnancy, and single-parent households." Courts simply lack the tools to
respond to these problems. Of course, they might make things better
56. The common view that the Court's decisions helped to mobilize political actors and
protest, or paved the way for King, has surprisingly little empirical support. See G. ROSENBERG,
supra note 44, at 112-13.</p>
      <p>57. R. COVER, 0. Fiss &amp; J. RESNIK, PROCEDURE (1988), can be understood as an attempt to
revise the subject of civil procedure through a conception that takes social reform as a central project
of the judiciary. It collects a wide range of theories and practices directed to that end.</p>
      <p>58. See generally W. WILSON, THE TRULY DISADVANTAGED 21-46 (1987) (analyzing
statistics about violent crimes, family incomes, employment, and out-of-wedlock births that
contribute to the problems faced by inner-city racial minorities).
rather than worse. But the legislative and executive branches must
provide the principal initiative for the necessary programs.</p>
      <p>These criticisms of the judiciary are hardly novel. Though voiced
most recently by conservatives during and after the period of the Warren
Court, critics voiced analogous complaints during the New Deal period,
when it would have seemed extremely peculiar to suggest that courts
should shape social reform for the disadvantaged. Indeed, the rise of
modem regulatory agencies was largely a product of a belief that the
judiciary lacked the will, the means, and the democratic pedigree to
create social reform on its own.5 9 With respect to civil rights, we should see
a similar constellation of ideas in the period we are now entering.</p>
      <p>IV</p>
      <p>NEW FOUNDATIONS</p>
      <p>Thus far, the discussion has been largely negative. I have argued
that three of the major claims of the civil rights movement, from the
1950s to the present, are at best incomplete. Frequently, discrimination
is not a reflection of irrationality or devaluation in the ordinary sense. It
is instead rational economic behavior in light of the desires of third
parties, statistical discrimination, or the effects of past and existing practices
on human capital and existing preferences. Moreover, compensatory
principles are poorly adapted to the civil rights setting, since they require
courts and other public officials to answer impossible questions. Finally,
reliance on the judiciary carries with it a host of problems. Among other
things, the courts are ineffective at achieving large-scale social reform.</p>
      <p>The three problems are closely linked. Judicial institutions are well
matched to the achievement of compensatory justice, and legal remedies
are especially suitable if discrimination is a product of individual
irrationality or prejudice. An understanding that discrimination is
economically rational, or not readily captured in compensatory terms, would call
for large institutional and substantive changes in existing civil rights law.
In particular, it would emphasize the systemic or structural character of
race and sex discrimination and the need for institutions to undertake
systemic or structural reform. Our current understandings of the
problem are extremely ill-adapted to this project.</p>
      <p>I have not yet proposed alternative understandings of the problem of
discrimination, understandings that might lead to different remedies or
institutional arrangements. Indeed, one of the largest gaps in present
59. See Sunstein, ConstitutionalismAfter theNew Deal, 101 HARV. L. REv. 421, 424-25 (1987)
(New Deal reformers sought to avoid the checks and balances that limited the powers of each branch
of government); id. at 437 (Progressives saw judiciary as antidemocratic and aligned with interests of
powerful); id. at 443 (New Deal reformers preferred agencies over courts in part because agencies
could act more swiftly).
civil rights theory consists of the absence of a full-fledged explanation of
just how to characterize a claim of discrimination and why we should
eliminate it. In this highly tentative Section, I will say something about
these inquiries.</p>
      <p>Provisionally, we might define discrimination to include any
decision to treat an otherwise similarly qualified black person, woman, or
handicapped person less favorably than a white, able-bodied male,
whether the reason for the decision lies in malice, taste, selective
empathy or indifference, economic self-interest, or rational stereotyping. This
understanding of discrimination covers not merely covert unequal
treatment but also facially neutral requirements that would not have been
adopted if the group membership of the two parties had been reversed.60
It does not cover measures merely having discriminatory effects unless
those effects are, in the sense I have just indicated, tied up with racial or
sexual bias.</p>
      <p>It follows that one who claims discrimination does not seek the
prevention of certain irrational acts, or of "prejudice," but asks instead for
the elimination, in places large and small, of something like a caste
system. Indeed, a large mistake of civil rights policy has been to treat the
issue as one of discrimination at all, since the term tends to connote
irrational differentiation-an unacceptable practice to be sure, but not an
appropriate description of the problem at hand, which is second-class
citizenship. The concept of second-class citizenship, or caste, is hard to
define, and I will have to be somewhat vague about it. I do not mean to
suggest that the caste-like features of current practices are the same-in
nature or extent-as those features of genuine caste societies. I do mean
that the similarities are what should make current practices a reason for
collective concern.</p>
      <p>The motivating idea behind an anti-caste principle is Rawlsian in
character: Without very good reason, legal and social structures should
not turn differences that are irrelevant from the moral point of view into
social disadvantages.6 1 They certainly should not be permitted to do so if
the disadvantage is systemic. A systemic disadvantage is one that
operates along standard and predictable lines, in multiple important spheres
of life, and that applies in realms like education, freedom from private
and public violence, wealth, political representation, and political
influence, all of which go to basic participation as a citizen in a democratic
society.62 Of course, past discrimination is a morally irrelevant factor,
60. See Strauss, supra note 3, at 956-57 (suggesting such a "reversing the groups" test as the
standard for discriminatory intent).</p>
      <p>61. See J. RAWLS, supra note 31, at 59, 100-04.</p>
      <p>62. See C. MACKINNON, FEMINISM UNMODIFIED 30-31 (1987) (discussing systemic
disadvantages suffered by women); J. RAWLs, supra note 31, at 102 (discussing need to justify
but it is one of a large set of such factors that play a role in the
distribution of social benefits and burdens.</p>
      <p>In the areas of race and sex discrimination, and of disability as well,
the problem is precisely this sort of systemic disadvantage. When
combined with social practices, difference has the effect of systematically
subordinating the relevant group and of doing so in multiple spheres and
along multiple indices of social welfare: poverty, education, political
power, employment, susceptibility to violence and crime, and so forth.
That is the caste system to which the legal system should respond. As we
have seen, among the many problems created by such a system are
adverse effects on human capital and on preference formation, and
general demoralization of group members.6 3</p>
      <p>Differences are usually invoked as the justification for
disadvantage-for example, as in the claim that blacks, in important respects and
as a group, are different from whites, or women are different from
menand therefore properly receive different treatment. But different
treatment need not follow from the fact of difference. For purposes of policy
and law, the question is not whether there is a difference-often there
certainly is-but whether the legal and social treatment of that difference
can be adequately justified. By itself, the fact of difference does not
supply an adequate justification.</p>
      <p>Differences that imply inequality are the result of legal and social
practices, not of nature, and not of the differences themselves. The
problems faced by the handicapped, for example, are a function not of
handicap alone (a most ambiguous idea) but instead of the interaction
between physical or mental capacities on the one hand and a set of
human obstacles made by and for the able-bodied on the other. (In the
pervasive use of white and male norms, there are analogies in the areas of
race and gender.) It is those obstacles, rather than the capacities taken as
brute facts, that create a large part of what it means to be handicapped
(and unequal). For these purposes, it is not decisive whether a present
disadvantage can be tightly connected to an intentionally discriminatory
act by a public "tortfeasor," which antidiscrimination efforts would
require.</p>
      <p>A few disclaimers are necessary here. The anti-caste principle, if
taken seriously, would call for significant restructuring of social
practices. For reasons suggested above, the principle is better elaborated and
institutions that make natural differences have social consequences). An anti-caste principle is not
"egalitarian." Egalitarianism calls for equality in the resources of different citizens; this principle is
indeed foreign to American public law. But the desire to eliminate caste systems has played an
important role in American constitutionalism from its inception. See L. HARTZ, THE LIBERAL
TRADITION IN AMERICA 1-32 (1965).</p>
      <p>63. These points are stressed in Strauss, RacialDiscriminationin Employment, 79 GEo. L.J.
(forthcoming 1991).
implemented by legislative and executive bodies, with their superior
democratic pedigree and factfinding capacities, than by constitutional courts.
Moreover, it is important to acknowledge that for good Rawlsian reasons
a wide range of differences are morally arbitrary, and in a market
economy those differences are quite frequently and for fully legitimate reasons
translated into social disadvantages. Consider, in this regard,
educational background, intelligence, strength, existing supply and demand
curves for various products and services, height, perhaps even willingness
to work hard.</p>
      <p>An anti-caste principle that would attempt, through law, to
counteract all these factors would be difficult indeed to sustain. In general, the
recognition of such factors is inseparable from the operation of a market
economy, and a market economy is an important source of freedom,
prosperity, and respect for different conceptions of the good. The use of
such factors is at least sometimes in the interest of the less or even least
well off, and in that case, an anti-caste principle that would bar their use
seems perverse. Moreover, an anti-caste principle that would override all
morally irrelevant factors would impose extraordinary costs on society,
both in its implementation and administration and in its infliction of
losses on a wide range of people. Those costs are high enough to make
such a global principle immensely unappealing.</p>
      <p>The principle therefore has greatest weight in discrete contexts,
most notably those concerning race, sex, and disability, where gains by
the least well off from current practice are hard to imagine, where
second-class citizenship is systemic and occurs in multiple spheres and
along easily identifiable and sharply defined lines, where the consequence
of current practice is to create continuous developmental harms to
members of well-defined groups, where there will be no global threat to a
market economy, and where the costs of implementation are not terribly
high.</p>
      <p>If an anti-caste principle is accepted, the most general question is
whether members of the disadvantaged group, or people who might find
themselves in that category, could be persuaded that there are good
reasons for the practice under attack." To pose that question is to place
64. An idea ofthis sort is at work in the original position set out in J. RAwLs, supra note 31, at
103; see also City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Cent., 473 U.S. 432, 455 (1985) (Stevens, J.,
concurring) ("I cannot believe that a rational member ofthis disadvantaged class could ever approve
of the discriminatory application of the city's ordinance in this case."); Okin, Reason and Feelingin
Thinking About Justice, in FEMINISM AND POLrrICAL THEORY 15, 27-30 (C. Sunstein ed. 1990)
(discussing original position as requiring people to "think from the point of view ofeveryone"). An
excellent example of anti-caste legislation is the Violence Against Women Act, see 136 CONG. REC.
S8263 (daily ed. June 19, 1990), which contains various measures designed to reduce and remedy
gender-related violence. Such a measure cannot easily be understood in compensatory terms; and it
could not be initiated by courts.
into doubt unconscious discrimination as well as selective empathy and
indifference on the part of those who created the practice; and the answer
will frequently be negative. Of course, there will be severe difficulties in
administering a system built on a question of that sort. But this is the
best inquiry in this context.</p>
      <p>I do not suggest that a principle of this sort leads to a particular
specification of substantive rights or institutional arrangements. It needs
to be supplemented with a range of other considerations in order to
become a plausible basis for civil rights policy. It does, however, have
several implications by itself. It suggests that compensation for past
wrongs is not the guiding principle for civil rights policy; compensation
and restoration of the status quo are not the basic issues at all. It
suggests that often, discrimination fueled by factors other than prejudice or
irrationality is also the target of civil rights policy, because of the
consequences of those forms of discrimination for the relevant group. It
suggests that a system with sufficient opportunities for education, training,
or employment, without race- and sex-related violence, and without
incentives for teenage childbearing or participation in crime, is a
principal goal of civil rights policy. It suggests, finally, that the elaboration
and implementation of the relevant policies should be undertaken, at
least in the first instance, by legislative and executive bodies and not by
the courts. In all these respects, this principle represents a renovation of
all that has guided civil rights policy over the last generation.</p>
      <p>CONCLUSION</p>
      <p>I have suggested that three of the principal claims that underlie civil
rights law and policy are in important respects fallacies. Discrimination
is not always the product of prejudice or irrationality. Moreover, to
understand the antidiscrimination principle in compensatory terms leads
to questions that are unanswerable. Finally, reliance on constitutional
adjudication is a large mistake for civil rights law.</p>
      <p>The three fallacies fit well together. Each of them fortifies the
others. The compensatory principle is well adapted to reliance on
judicial institutions. The notion that discrimination is a product of prejudice
or irrationality also helps to promote reliance on the courts, enabling
them to build antidiscrimination principles on the foundations of tort
law. But if discrimination cannot be well understood in these terms, all
the fallacies must yield. They provide a poor foundation for civil rights
law and practice in the coming generation.</p>
      <p>I have also suggested, though more tentatively, that civil rights law
should be informed by a principle that forbids morally irrelevant
differences from being turned, without very good reason, into a systemic
source of social or legal disadvantages. Thus understood, the
antidiscrimination principle becomes an anti-caste principle. To be sure,
elaboration of that principle is a large task, one that leaves open a wide
range of questions concerning both substance and institutional
arrangements. But if I am correct, such a principle provides a better foundation
for civil rights policy than the three fallacies that have burdened the law
for so long.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          35.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , eg.,
          <source>Dayton Bd. of Educ</source>
          . v.
          <source>Brinkman (Dayton 11)</source>
          , 443 U.S.
          <volume>526</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>537</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>39</lpage>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          )
          <article-title>(intentional establishment of dual school system before 1954 creates continuing obligation to undertake affirmative acts to desegregate school district); Columbus Bd</article-title>
          . of Educ. v. Penick, 443 U.S.
          <volume>449</volume>
          ,
          <issue>458</issue>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          )
          <article-title>(same). These issues, of course, lie behind Board of Education of Oklahoma City Public Schools v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Dowell</source>
          , 111
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>630</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          36. E.g.,
          <article-title>Green v</article-title>
          . County School Bd., 391 U.S.
          <volume>430</volume>
          ,
          <issue>440</issue>
          (
          <year>1968</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          37.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , eg.,
          <source>Dayton Bd. of Educ</source>
          . v.
          <source>Brinkman (Dayton I)</source>
          ,
          <volume>433</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>406</volume>
          ,
          <issue>417</issue>
          ,
          <issue>420</issue>
          (
          <year>1977</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          38.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , eg., id. at 423 (Brennan, J., concurring).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

