<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>On Analogical Reasoning
Author(s): Cass R. Sunstein
Source: Harvard Law Review</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>106</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>741</fpage>
      <lpage>791</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at . http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp . JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>The Harvard Law Review Association is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to
Harvard Law Review.
http://www.jstor.org</p>
      <p>Reasoningby analogyis the most familiarform of legal reasoning.</p>
      <p>It dominatesthe first year of law school;it is a characteristicpart of
brief-writingand opinion-writingas well. But exactly what is
analogical reasoning,as it operatesin law?</p>
      <p>The subject receives little attentionin the most influentialworks
in Anglo-Americanjurisprudenceand legal theory.' Often lawyers
themselvesare unenthusiasticabout analogicalreasoning,urgingthat
this wl.v of thinking about law is unconstrainedor not a form of
reasoning at all.2 As a result, the legal culture lacks a sympathetic
depictionof its own most characteristicway of proceeding.3</p>
      <p>* Karl N. Llewellyn Professor of Jurisprudence, Law School and Department of Political
Science, University of Chicago. For helpful comments, I am very grateful to members of the
audience at a lecture on this topic at Harvard University's Program in Ethics and the Professions;
to participants in legal theory workshops at Stanford Law School and the University of Southern
California Law Center; and to Bruce Ackerman, Scott Brewer, Daniel Brudney, Joshua Cohen,
Jon Elster, Richard Fallon, Abner Greene, Dennis Hutchinson, Laurence Friedman, Elena
Kagan, Larry Lessig, Frank Michelman, Michael McConnell, Jennifer Nedelsky, Martha
Nussbaum, Richard Pildes, Richard Posner, Margaret Jane Radin, Frederick Schauer, Lawrence
Solum, David A. Strauss, Mark Tushnet, Edna Ullmann-Margalit, and Lloyd Weinreb.</p>
      <p>1 See RONALD DWORKIN, LAW'S EMPIRE (I986); RONALD DWORKIN, TAKING RIGHTS
SERIOUSLY (Ig77); and H.L.A. HART, THE CONCEPT OF LAW (Ig6I). The various essays in
JUDITH J. THOMSON, RIGHTS, RESTITUTION, AND RISK 78-i i6, 257-260 (I986), are prominent
nonlegal examples of the method of analogy, as I understand it here. Thomson's comments on
her method are also relevant. Id. at 25I.</p>
      <p>2 See PETER GOODRICH, READING THE LAW 77-78, i6o-6i, I84-86, I97-98 (I986);
RICHARD A POSNER, THE PROBLEMS OF JURISPRUDENCE 86-ioo (IggO); ROBERTO M. UNGER, THE
CRITICAL LEGAL STUDIES MOVEMENT 8 (I983); James A. Boyle, The Anatomy of a Torts Class,
34 AM. U. L. REv. I003, I05I, I054-55 (I985); Mark V. Tushnet, Following the Rules Laid
Down: A Critique of Interpretivism and Neutral Principles, 96 HARV. L. REV. 78i, 8I8-Ig
(I983).</p>
      <p>3 The leading discussion of analogical reasoning in law is EDWARD H. LEVI, AN
INTRODUCTION TO LEGAL REASONING (I947), discussed below in note 63. Helpful descriptions appear in
STEPHEN F. BARKER, THE ELEMENTS OF LOGIC I86-95, 225-29 (5th ed. I989); STEVEN J.</p>
      <p>BURTON, AN INTRODUCTION TO LAW AND LEGAL REASONING 25-40 (I987); MARTIN P.
GOLDING, LEGAL REASONING 97-I43 (I984); MARK T. KEANE, ANALOGICAL PROBLEM SOLVING I
I37 (I988); JOSEPH RAz, THE AUTHORITY OF LAW 20I-o6 (I979); J.F. ROSS, PORTRAYING
ANALOGY 202-II (Ig8I); and STEPHEN TOULMIN, RICHARD RIEKE &amp; ALLAN JANIK, AN
INTRODUCTION TO REASONING I48-I50 (I979). For useful collections, see ANALOGICAL
REASONING: PERSPECTIVES OF ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE, COGNITIVE SCIENCE, AND PHILOSOPHY
(David H. Helman ed., I988) [hereinafter ANALOGICAL REASONING]; SIMILARITY AND
ANALOGICAL REASONING (Stella Vosniadou &amp; Andrew Ortony eds., I989). For short, suggestive
treatments, see HILARY PUTNAM, THE MANY FACES OF REALISM 73-75 (I987); DAVID TRACY,
PLURALITY AND AMBIGUITY 20-22 (I987); W.V. QUINE &amp; J.S. ULLIAN, THE WEB OF BELIEF
[Vol. i06:74I</p>
      <p>In the face of this odd combination of general indifference and
critical attack, analogical reasoning maintains its status as an
exceedingly prominent means by which both lawyers and nonlawyers think
about legal and moral questions. The principal goals of this
Commentary are to offer an account of analogical reasoning and to suggest
that, at least for law, it has distinctive advantages over forms of
thought that seem to be far superior. The discussion will bear on the
role of analogical thinking in ethics and politics as well.</p>
      <p>I also hope to say something about the nature and possibility of
normative argument in law and to suggest how and when certain
views about legal disputes can be shown to be persuasive or even
correct.4 What does it mean to say that a difficult case is "rightly
decided"? How, if at all, does such a judgment differ from a political
or moral claim about what the law should be? What is the difference
between a legally correct decision and a morally correct decision? An
understanding of analogical reasoning should provide some clues.</p>
      <p>The Commentary is divided into three parts. Part I describes
analogical reasoning, primarily by comparing it to other methods of
thinking that also have a place in law. Part II tries to make the
description more concrete by showing how analogies might be helpful
in thinking about the problems raised by legal restrictions on
crossburning. The Supreme Court's decision in R.A. V. v. City of St. Paul5
provides a focal point for the discussion.</p>
      <p>Part III, evaluating analogical reasoning, is divided into two
sections. The first explores the most prominent criticisms of this way of
thinking. Here I challenge the view that analogical reasoning is
indeterminate and that it depends on an apparatus - a set of principles
- that it is unable to supply. The second section explores the vices
and especially the virtues of analogical reasoning by contrasting it
with some especially prominent approaches to legal reasoning,
including those offered by Ronald Dworkin and economic analysts of law.
83-95 (2d ed. 1978); Brian Barry, On Analogy, 23 POL.STUD.86, 93-99 (1975); cf. ALBERTR.</p>
      <p>JONSEN&amp; STEPHENTOULMIN,THE ABUSEOF CASUISTRY279-303 (I988) (defending
particularistic case analysis - "casuistry"- against the view that morality consists of the application
of a code of general rules).</p>
      <p>4 Skepticism about normative argument has become prominent in law. See, e.g., Richard
Delgado, Norms and Normal Science: Toward a Critique of Normativity in Legal Thought, 139
U. PA. L. REV. 933, 960 (i99i) ("Normative discourse is indeterminate; for every social
reformer's plea, an equally plausible argument can be found against it."); Robert W. Gordon,
"Of Law and the River," and Of Nihilism and Academic Freedom, 35 J. LEGALEDUC. I, 2
(I985) ("[B]ecause ... [law] is founded upon contradictory norms, its principles cannot constrain
a single set of outcomes even if intelligently, honestly and conscientiously applied. Lncontract
law, for example, there is always a legitimate argument for maintaining one party's freedom of
action and a contrary argument for protecting the other party's security; for every argument for
enforcing the deal . . . there is a counterargument for voiding the deal .</p>
      <p>5 112 S. Ct. 2538 (1992).
In this section, I reject, as only part of a complex story, the view that
analogical reasoning is a crude and incomplete version of the lawyer's
search for "reflective equilibrium."6 I also claim that analogical
reasoning has important advantages over general theories, because those
who use analogies are especially attuned to the diverse and plural
goods that are at stake in legal and ethical decisions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>I. ANALOGICAL REASONING AND SOME ALTERNATIVES</title>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>A. Analogical Reasoning in the Law</title>
        <p>Outside of law, analogical reasoning often helps to inform our
judgments. I have a German shepherd dog who is gentle with
children. When I see another German shepherd dog, I assume that he,
too, will be gentle with children. I have a Toyota Camry that starts
even on cold days in winter. I assume that my friend's Toyota Camry
will start on cold winter days as well. This kind of thinking has a
simple structure: (i) A has characteristic X; (2) B shares that
characteristic; (3) A also has characteristic Y; (4) Because A and B share
characteristic X, we conclude what is not yet known, that B shares
characteristic Y as well.7</p>
        <p>This is a usual form of reasoning in daily life,8 but it will readily
appear that it does not guarantee truth. The existence of one or many</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>6 See JOHN RAWLS, A THEORY OF JUSTICE I9-22, 46-5I (I97I); infra p. 756.</title>
      <p>7 What I am describing in the text is a form of inductive analogy, in the sense that it
depends on predictive conjectures about an unknown case that are based on but go beyond
stated premises. See BARKER, supra note 3, at I9I-93; Theo A.F. Kuipers, Inductive Analogy
by Similarity and Proximity, in ANALOGICAL REASONING, supra note 3, at 299, 30I-09.
Inductive analogy is different from the usual case of induction, which occurs by enumeration.
An example of nonanalogical inductive reasoning is: I have seen ioo German shepherds, and
they are all gentle with children. From the large number of gentle German shepherds, I infer
that the latest German shepherd is also gentle with children.</p>
      <p>I deal throughout with analogical reasoning that is roughly propositional in a sense that
should emerge from the discussion at pp. 744-49 below. I spend little time on the growing
work dealing with analogy and metaphor at nonpropositional levels. See, e.g., GEORGELAKOFF,
WOMEN, FIRE AND DANGEROUS THINGS 68-76 (I987); Mark Johnson, Some Constraints on
Embodied Analogical Understanding, in ANALOGICAL REASONING, supra note 3, at 25, 39
("[A]nalogiescannot be understood as propositional or conceptual mechanisms for reflecting on
already-determinate experiences; rather, we can actually speak of them as constitutiveof our
experience, because they are partially constitutive of our understanding, our mode of
experiencing our world. Analogy is a basic means by which form, pattern, and connection emerge in
our understanding and are then articulated in our reflective cognition and in our language.").
See also the brief discussion of metaphor and analogy below in note 26.</p>
      <p>8 See Mary Hesse, Theories, Family Resemblances and Analogy, in
ANALOGICALREASONING, supra note 3, at 3I7, 3I7-I8. Hesse writes:</p>
      <p>It has long been obvious that the human problem solver does not generally think
deductively or by exhaustive search of logical space. Propositional logic relies upon enumeration
of premises, univocal symbolization, and exclusively deductive connections, and these
cannot be either a good simulation of human thought or an efficient use of computers.
shared characteristics does not mean that all characteristics are
shared.9 Some German shepherd dogs are not gentle with children.
Some Toyota Camrys do not start on cold days in winter. For
analogical reasoning to work well, we have to say that the relevant,
known similarities give us good reason to believe that there are further
similarities and thus help to answer an open question. Of course this
is not always so. At most, analogical thinking can give rise to a
judgment about probabilities, and often these are of uncertain
magnitude.</p>
      <p>Analogical reasoning has a similar structure in law. Consider some
examples. We know that an employer may not fire an employee for
refusing to commit perjury;10it is said to follow that an employer is
banned from firing an employee for filing a workers' compensation
claim."1 We know that a speech by a member of the Ku Klux Klan,
advocating racial hatred, cannot be regulated unless it is likely to
incite, and is directed to inciting, imminent lawless action;12it is said
to follow that the government cannot forbid the Nazis to march in
Skokie, Illinois.13 We know that there is no constitutional right to
welfare,14 medical care,15 or housing;16 it is said to follow that there
is no constitutional right to government protection against domestic
violence.17</p>
      <p>In real humanthinking,the meaningsof conceptsare constantlymodifiedand extended
by parallels,modelsand metaphors,and the rationalsteps frompremisesto conclusion
are generallynon-demonstrativeb, eing carriedout by inductive,hypotheticaland
analogicalreasoning.</p>
      <p>From a brief glance at these examples, we can get a sense of the
characteristic form of analogical thought in law. The process appears
to work in four simple steps: (i) Some fact pattern A has a certain
characteristic X, or characteristics X, Y, and Z; (2) Fact pattern B
differs from A in some respects but shares characteristics X, or
characteristics X, Y, and Z; (3) The law treats A in a certain way; (4)
Because B shares certain characteristics with A, the law should treat
B the same way. For example, someone asking for protection against
domestic violence is requesting affirmative government assistance, just
like someone asking the government for medical care; it is said to
"follow"from the medical care case that there is no constitutional right
to protection against domestic violence.</p>
      <p>As in the nonlegal examples,18 it should readily appear that
analogical reasoning does not guarantee good outcomes or truth. For
analogical reasoning to operate properly, we have to know that A and
B are "relevantly"similar, and that there are not "relevant"differences
between them. Two cases are always different from each other along
some dimensions. When lawyers say there are no relevant differences,
they mean that any differences between the two cases either (a) do
not make a difference in light of the relevant precedents, which
foreclose certain possible grounds for distinction, or (b) cannot be
fashioned into the basis for a distinction that is genuinely principled. A
claim that one case is genuinely analogous to another - that it is
"apposite" or cannot be "distinguished"- is parasitic on conclusion
(a) or (b), and either of these must of course be justified. 19</p>
      <p>The major challenge facing analogical reasoners is to decide when
differences are relevant. To make this decision, they must investigate
cases with care in order to develop governing principles. The
judgment that a distinction is not genuinely principled requires a
substantive argument of some kind. For example, one difference between
the Nazi march and the Klan speech is that the Nazi Party is
associated with the Holocaust. This is indeed a difference, but American
law currently deems it irrelevant. It appears unprincipled - or
excessively ad hoc - for the states to ban prohibitions on political
speech except when the speaker is associated with the Holocaust.20
we are dealing with non-inductive analogical reasoning. We are not making a prediction about
likely facts in an unknown case, but are instead making claims about how an as-yet undecided
case should be resolved in light of its similarity to a decided or clear case. See BARKER, supra
note 3, at 225-29.</p>
      <p>18An important difference is that the dog and automobile cases involve analogies as a crude
guide to statistical probabilities, whereas the legal examples involve normative judgments.</p>
      <p>19It should be clear from the text that in analogical argument, precedents cannot be said to
be uncontroversially binding or "on all fours." An argument from analogy depends on the fact
that there are both plausibly relevant differences and plausibly relevant similarities between the
precedent and the case at hand.</p>
      <p>20 The distinction between the principled and the excessively ad hoc is sometimes a matter
As we will see, analogical reasoning goes wrong when there is an
inadequate inquiry into the matter of relevant differences and
governing principles. But what are the defining characteristics of a
competent lawyer's inquiry into analogies?</p>
      <p>In law, analogical reasoning has four different but overlapping
features: principled consistency; a focus on particulars; incompletely
theorized judgments; and principles operating at a low or intermediate
level of abstraction. Taken in concert, these features produce both
the virtues and the vices of analogical reasoning in law.</p>
      <p>First, and most obviously, judgments about specific cases must be
made consistent with one another. A requirement of coherence, or
principled consistency, is a hallmark of analogical reasoning (as it is
of reasoning of almost all sorts). It follows that in producing the
necessary consistency, some principle, harmonizing seemingly
disparate outcomes, will be invoked to explain the cases.</p>
      <p>Second, analogical reasoning focuses on particulars, and it
develops from concrete controversies. Holmes put it this way: a common
law court "decides the case first and determines the principle
afterwards."'21 Ideas are developed from the details, rather than imposed
on them from above. In this sense, analogical reasoning, unlike many
forms of reasoning,22 is a version of "bottom-up"thinking.23</p>
      <p>Despite the focus on particulars, the analogizer's description of a
particular holding inevitably has some general theoretical components.
One cannot even characterize one's convictions about a case without
using abstractions, and without taking a position on competing
abstractions.24 We cannot fully describe the outcome in case X if we do
of social convention. See e.g., Fredrick Schauer, Exceptions, 58 U. CHI. L. REV. 871, 886-9I
(I99I) (discussing the effect of social conventions on free speech principles and claims for
exceptions).</p>
      <p>21 Oliver W. Holmes, Jr., Codes and the Arrangementsof Law, 44 HARV. L. REV. 725, 725
(I93I) (reprinted from 5 AM. L. REv. i (I870)). In a way this suggestion is misleading. To
decide the case at all, one has to have the principle in some sense in mind; there can be no
sequential operation of quite the kind Holmes describes. See T.M. Scanlon, The Aims and
Authority of Moral Theory, 12 OXFORD J. LEGAL STUD. I, 9 (I992).</p>
      <p>22 See, for example, the discussion of racial discrimination in DWORKINc,ited above in note
I, at 38I-89, in which the principles are first generated at a high level of generality, and then
applied to particular disputes - an example of "top down" reasoning. A similar method is at
work in Ronald Dworkin, The Coming Battles over Free Speech, N.Y. REV. BOOKS, June ii,
I992, at 55 [hereinafter Dworkin, The Coming Battles over Free Speech]. An interesting contrast
is provided by Ronald Dworkin, The Original Position, in READING RAWLS i6, 28-37 (Norman
Daniels ed., I989) [hereinafter Dworkin, The Original Position], in which the search for reflective
equilibrium is described in a way that does not have this "top down" aspect.</p>
      <p>23 See Richard A. Posner, Legal Reasoning from the Top Down and From the Bottom Up,
59 U. CHI. L. REV. 433, 434-35 (I992); cf. JON ELSTER, LOCAL JUSTICE I89-94 (I992)
(distinguishing between "hard"and "soft" theories in the same way that Posner distinguishes
between "top down" and "bottom up" approaches).</p>
      <p>24 See BRIAN BARRY, THEORIES OF JUSTICE 264 (I989); Scanlon, supra note 2I, at 9; see
not know something about the reasons that count in its favor. We
cannot say whether decided case X has anything to do with undecided
case Y unless we are able to abstract, a bit, from the facts and holding
of case X. The key point is that analogical reasoning involves a
process in which principles are developed with constant reference to
particular cases.</p>
      <p>Third, analogical reasoning operates without a comprehensive
theory that accounts for the particular outcomes it yields. The judgments
that underlie convictions about, or holdings in, the relevant case are
incompletely theorized, in the sense that they are unaccompanied by
a full apparatus to explain the basis for those judgments. Lawyers
might firmly believe, for example, that the Constitution does not create
a right to welfare or that the state cannot regulate political speech
without a showing of immediate and certain harm. But it is
characteristic of reasoning by analogy, as I understand it here, that lawyers
are not able to explain the basis for these beliefs in much depth or
detail, or with full specification of the theory that accounts for those
beliefs. Lawyers (and almost all other people) typically lack any
largescale theory.25 They reason anyway, and their reasoning is often
analogical.</p>
      <p>Finally, analogical reasoning produces principles that operate at a
low or intermediate level of abstraction. If we say that the state
cannot ban a Nazi march, we might mean that the state cannot stop
political speech without showing that the speech poses a clear and
immediate harm. This is a principle, and it does involve a degree of
abstraction from the particular case; but it does not entail any
highlevel theory about the purposes of the free speech guarantee or about
the relation between the citizen and the state. Analogical reasoning
usually operates without express reliance on any general principles
about the right or the good. Some such principles may of course be
also RAZ, supra note 3, at 203 ("By its very nature the justification of a rule is more abstract
and more general than the rule it justifies").</p>
      <p>25 Consider in this connection a famous story of the early days of law and economics at the
University of Chicago Law School. Edward Levi - the great champion of analogical reasoning,
see infra note 63 - decided to introduce economics into his antitrust course, by allowing every
fifth class to be taught by the economist Aaron Director, one of the fathers of modern law and
economics. As the story goes, Levi would spend four classes in the lawyer's fashion, brilliantly
rationalizing the seemingly inconsistent judicial holdings. In the fifth class, Director would
explain, with the economist's tools, why everything Levi said was wrong. Eventually even Levi
was converted. (The story is summarized in Ronald H. Coase, Law and Economics at Chicago,
J.L. &amp; ECON.(forthcoming I993)). The supposed moral of the story is that lawyers' reasoning,
even by its most able practitioners, is inferior to economics, primarily because it lacks clear
criteria or specified governing values. In antitrust, this may well be true; but it is not true
everywhere. And if this is so, there are places in which those now occupying the place of Levi
should not be converted by those now occupying the place of Director. See infra pp. 787-90
(discussing diverse and plural goods).
an implicit or even necessary basis for decision, but the lawyer who
engages in analogical reasoning is not self-conscious about them.</p>
      <p>Reasoning by analogy, understood in light of these four
characteristics, is the mode through which the ordinary lawyer typically
operates. He has no abstract theory to account for his convictions, or for
what he knows to be the law. But he knows that these are his
convictions, or that this is the law, and he is able to bring that
knowledge to bear on undecided cases. For guidance, he looks to
areas in which his judgment is firm. Analogical reasoning thus works
when an incompletely theorized judgment about case X is invoked to
come to terms with case Y, which bears much (but not all) in common
with case X, and in which there is as yet no judgment at all.26</p>
      <p>We need to distinguish here between analogies that depend on a
contestable substantive argument and analogies that are simply
constitutive of the thinking of people in the relevant community. Some
analogies, or perceptions of likeness, do not depend on arguments,
but rest instead on the widely shared way that human beings order
their world. We do not need an argument in order to say that one
car is relevantly "like"other cars; we take the point for granted; it is
part of our language. This form of categorization is different from
the view, plausible but in need of an argument, that a ban on the
work of Robert Mapplethorpe is "like"a ban on Ulysses. Of course
the distinction between analogies that depend on contestable
arguments and analogies that constitute how people arrange their world
is only contingent and conventional - a function of existing social
judgments.27 Sometimes the two operate more like poles on a
continuum than a sharp dichotomy, and there are important shifts over time
from one category to another. Consider, for example, the current
26 A good deal of recent attention has been devoted to the relationship between analogy and
metaphor. See generally ON METAPHOR (Sheldon Sacks ed., I979). In much of this work,
metaphor is said to have epistemic value, in science and elsewhere. Here there is much room
for further thought about both analogy and metaphor in law. I make one brief point here.
Consider the statement: "Abortionis murder,"a statement that in the abstract, could be intended
and received as a literal truth, a metaphor, or an analogy. If it is a metaphor, we know that
the speaker believes that abortion is not literally murder, but is seeking to cast some light on
the subject precisely by departing from literal description. ("Holmes was a lion of the law."
"Michael Jordan is God.") But if the statement is an analogy, the speaker is claiming, and
should be understood to be claiming, that abortion really is murder in the relevant respects;
there is no acknowledgement that the statement is literally untrue. I believe that this is a large
difference between metaphor and analogy, though I must be tentative on this point. See Donald
Davidson, What Metaphors Mean, in ON METAPHOR, supra, at 29, 29-36 (challenging this
conception of metaphor); Dedre Gentner, Brian Falkenhainer &amp; Janice Skorstad, Viewing
Metaphor as Analogy, in ANALOGICAL REASONING, supra note 3, at I7I, I72 (claiming that metaphor
is a kind of analogical process); Mark Johnson, Some Constraints on Embodied Analogical
Understanding, in ANALOGICAL REASONING, supra note 3, at 25, 25 (same).</p>
      <p>27 See also infra note 53 (discussing the analytic-synthetic distinction).
consensus that Brown v. Board of Education28 is "like" Loving v.
Virginia,29 to the point that the similarity between the two cases can
almost be taken as constitutive of how lawyers arrange their world,
rather than as a controversial proposition that requires a substantive
argument. Much creativity in law consists of the effort to show that
a judgment about likeness that seems constitutive of thought actually
depends on contestable substantive arguments - or vice-versa.</p>
      <p>These statements leave many ambiguities, and I will return to
them shortly. For the moment it will be useful to try to get a better
sense of analogical reasoning by comparing it with five other forms
of reasoning that have a prominent place in law.30 These alternative
conceptions are general theories, the search for reflective equilibrium,
reasoning from incompletely theorized practices, classification, and
means-ends rationality.</p>
      <p>B. Other Forms of Legal Reasoning
i. Top-Down General Theories. - Legal problems are often
discussed in terms of some general theory - indeed, this method seems
to be increasingly popular in law schools, if not in courts. By a
general theory, I mean an approach to law that is simple and unitary,
operates at a high level of abstraction, has a distinctive "top down"
character, brings the general theory to bear on particular cases, and
disregards the fact that people are disturbed by particular outcomes
that seem counterintuitive but that have been compelled by the general
theory. Utilitarianism and economic analysis of law are especially
familiar examples of this form of reasoning.</p>
      <p>Top-down general theories operate deductively. Analogy plays no
role. Legal outcomes in particular cases are the logical consequence
of the general theory. For example: The law should maximize
efficiency; a negligence regime is more efficient than one of strict liability;
the law should therefore require a showing of negligence.</p>
      <p>Many general theories give little weight to convictions about
appropriate outcomes in particular cases, which are sometimes dismissed
as "intuitions." Some Kantian approaches, for example, are famously
indifferent if the approach will compel truth-telling even if many
people will be killed as a result. The utilitarian analogue is the
apparent obligation to kill an innocent person if social welfare will
thereby be promoted. Economic approaches to law find a similar case
in the acknowledgement that, on economic grounds, rape should
per28 347 U.S. 483 (1954).
29 388 U.S. i (i967).</p>
      <p>30 Of course I do not mean to canvass all or most forms of human reasoning; I select those
that are pervasive in the legal culture.
haps be legalized if rapists would pay more to rape than victims
would pay to avoid rape.31</p>
      <p>These examples can make believers in general theories seem
fanatical; indeed, we might understand fanaticism in law and politics
to consist precisely in the insistence on applying general principles to
particular cases in which they produce palpable absurdity or palpable
injustice.32 The point is not that exponents of any of these views
cannot avoid the seemingly bizarre counterexample.33 It is instead
that general theories usually do not make existing convictions about
particular cases a constituent part of the method through which
principles are constructed.</p>
      <p>There are conspicuous differences between top-down theories and
analogical reasoning. In top-down thinking, particular cases are not
the source of principles; all judgments are completely theorized, in the
sense that they are accompanied by a full explanation of their basis;
and the relevant judgments operate at a high level of abstraction and
generality. General systems are for these reasons a natural ally of
codification, and a natural enemy of the common law. It is therefore
no surprise that Jeremy Bentham was both the founder of
utilitarianism and the most vigorous advocate of codification, a word that in
fact he coined.34 Thus Bentham wrote with palpable disgust about
the disadvantages and irrationality of the common law approach, in
which general inferences are deduced from particular decisions 35
2. The Search for Reflective Equilibrium. - Legal problems are
also evaluated by comparing apparently plausible general theories with
31 See Richard A. Posner, An Economic Theory of the Criminal Law, 85 COLUM. L. REv.
II93, II98-99 (I985).</p>
      <p>32 Sometimes the judgment that a particular outcome is palpably absurd or unjust should
not be given much weight, because that judgment should itself be subject to critical scrutiny.
See infra note 67 and accompanying text (suggesting that considered judgments about particular
cases should count as such only if they have survived encounter with a good deal else that is
both general and particular).</p>
      <p>33 It is interesting that advocates of general theories often work very hard to show that
deductions from the theory are indeed consistent with our judgments about particular cases.
See, e.g., ROBERT H. BORK, THE TEMPTING OF AMERICA 74-83 (I990) (attempting to explain
why a reliance on the original understanding of the Constitution is consistent with the outcome
in Brown v. Board of Education). Note also that a large part of the argument for the economic
analysis of law is that economic analysis appears to "account for" or "explain"a large number
of well-established and apparently satisfactory common law principles. See, e.g., RICHARD
POSNER, ECONOMICANALYSIS OF LAW ? 2.2, at 23-25 (4th ed. I992).</p>
      <p>34 See JOHN DINWIDDY, BENTHAM 58 (I989).</p>
      <p>35 See 3 JEREMY BENTHAM, THE WORKS OF JEREMY BENTHAM 206 (J. Bowring ed., I843).
Barker, cited above in note 3, at 286-9o, contains a useful discussion, implicitly responsive to
Bentham and highly relevant to lawyers, of how noninductive reasoning by analogy is necessary
when deductive and inductive reasoning are not able to give us answers that we need. Barker
offers the case of a bad check written by a student who is claimed to have violated an honor
code that bars lying and cheating. How, Barker asks, could this case be resolved without resort
to analogical thought? See also infra note I47 (discussing affirmative action).
apparently plausible outcomes in particular cases. Drawing on Rawls'
notion of reflective equilibrium,36 we might understand much
reasoning, in law and elsewhere, to entail an effort to produce both general
theories and judgments in individual cases by close engagement with
a range of general theories and a range of considered judgments about
particular disputes. Those considered judgments may serve as
provisional "fixed points" for inquiry, in the sense that we have a high
degree of confidence in them and cannot readily imagine that they
could be shaken. In searching for reflective equilibrium, what we
think tentatively to be the general theory is adjusted to conform to
what we think to be our considered views about particular cases. In
other words, the particular views are adjusted to conform to the
general theory and vice-versa. Through this process, we hope finally
to reach a form of equilibrium.</p>
      <p>Many different conceptions of reflective equilibrium are possible.
We might accord greater or lesser weight to particular situational
judgments or to intermediate-level principles; make different decisions
about what counts as a distortion of judgment; stress or downplay
the role of philosophical arguments; evaluate in different ways the
appropriate or possible amount of congruence between the general and
the particular; bring to bear a few general theories or a large number;
reject or value apparently emotional reactions;37and counsel deference
or indifference to very high-level theories.38</p>
      <p>Some versions of the search for reflective equilibrium play a large
role in law. Thus, for example, the notion that only political speech
receives special constitutional protection might be abandoned if and
36 See RAWLS, supra note 6, at 19-2I, 46-5 I (I97I); John Rawls, The Independence of Moral
Theory, 48 PROC.&amp; ADDRESSES OF THE AM. PHIL. Ass'N 5, 7-10 (I974-75).</p>
      <p>37 Rawls suggests that considered judgments count as such only if reached when we are
calm and disinterested, see RAWLS, supra note 6, at 47-48. In general this seems right, but it
may be that anger, indignation, and other emotions sometimes reflect better thinking rather
than distorting influence. See Norman Daniels, Wide Reflective Equilibrium and Theory
Acceptance in Ethics, 76 J. PHIL. 256, 258 n.3 (I979); MARTHA C. NUSSBAUM, Perceptive
Equilibrium: Literary Theory and Ethical Theory, in LOVE'S KNOWLEDGE I68, i68-93 (I990);
cf. RAWLS, supra note 6, at 440-46 (suggesting that shame and guilt are highly cognitive rather
than referring to them as products of distortion).</p>
      <p>38There is thus a dispute about the real role, in the search for reflective equilibrium, of
judgments about particular situations. See generally Daniels, supra note 37, at 258 n.3. Ronald
Dworkin describes the search for reflective equilibrium in a way that relies heavily on particular
judgments about particular situations, and this is closer to how I understand things in this
essay. See Dworkin, The Original Position, supra note 22, at 28-30. It is interesting that the
search for reflective equilibrium, if understood to require a great deal of attention to low-level
judgments, plays little or no role in Rawls's book itself. The examples offered are "that religious
intolerance and racial discrimination are unjust." RAWLS, sup-ranote 6, at I9. There is little
reference to particular judgments, and little testing of the general principles against those
judgments. See i BRIAN BARRY, A TREATISE ON SOCIALJUSTICE: THEORIES OF JUSTICE
28082 (i989). We should understand the search for reflective equilibrium to be a general concept
of which Rawls's own version is a particular conception.
when it appears that that notion allows censorship of great art and
literature. The goal of the resulting method would be to produce a
full set of confident judgments about specific cases, accompanied by
an abstract theory, or a set of principles, that is able to account for
all of them.</p>
      <p>There is an important commonality between analogical reasoning
and the search for reflective equilibrium. In sharp contrast to
topdown theories, both of these approaches depend heavily on judgments
about particular cases. Here is a source of controversy. Sometimes
lawyers rebel against the idea that theories should be adjusted if they
lead to unacceptable particular outcomes.39 For them, the adjustment
is a form of brinkmanship, or strategic thinking, and a violation of
the necessary commitment to general principle and neutrality itself.</p>
      <p>This is an objection to both analogical reasoning and the search
for reflective equilibrium; perhaps judgments about particular cases
should not play a large role in developing theories or principles. The
objection raises large issues that I cannot fully discuss here. But if
judgments by human beings are inevitably a product of what human
beings think, nothing need be wrong with changing one's general
theory when that theory brings about results that seem to be an
unacceptable part of one's approach to the subject.40 To understand
39 Herbert Wechsler, Toward Neutral Principles of Constitutional Law, 73 HARV.L. REv.
I, I5-I7, 3I-34 (I959), is the mostnotableexampleof suchcriticisms.The searchfor reflective
equilibrium is criticized as unacceptably dependent on existing intuitions in, among other places:
RICHARD B. BRANDT, A THEORY OF THE GOOD AND THE RIGHT I6-23 (1979); R.M. Hare,
Rawls' A Theory of Justice - II, 23 PHIL. Q. 241, 249-50 (1973); Joseph Raz, The Claims of
Reflective Equilibrium, 25 INQUIRY 307, 3I8-I9 (I982); Peter Singer, Sidgwick and Reflective
Equilibrium, 58 MONIST 490, 5I5-I7 (I974). But see Daniels, supra note 37, at 264-67
(defending the search for reflective equilibrium if it is sufficiently "wide"). A helpful treatment can
be found in ELIZABETH ANDERSON, VALUE IN ETHICS AND ECONOMICS ? 5.3 (forthcoming
1993) (qualifying coherence theories by acknowledging and incorporating criticisms while
maintaining many of the best features of coherentist accounts).</p>
      <p>Jon Elster makes the interesting suggestion that the "empirical foundations" of theories of
justice should be not only "the intuitions of the philosopher,"but also the results of (a) empirical
studies of perceptions of justice and (b) investigations into the actual practices of institutions
allocating scarce resources. JON ELSTER, LOCAL JUSTICE 192-94 (I992); see also NORMAN
FROHLICH &amp; JOE A. OPPENHEIMER, CHOOSING JUSTICE (I992) (providing such an empirical
study). An approach of this kind would result in a quite different conception of reflective
equilibrium than that presented by Rawls. In Rawls's conception, particular judgments are
revisable; this would not be so under Elster's suggestion. See Scanlon, supra note 2I, at io
(describing the connection between revisability of judgments and Rawls's method).</p>
      <p>40 I am drawing in this paragraph on various discussions of coherence in moral and ethical
thought. See, e.g., ELIZABETH ANDERSON, VALUE IN ETHICS AND IN ECONOMICS ch. 5
(forthcoming I993); GILBERT HARMAN, CHANGE IN VIEW 29-63 (I986); RAWLS, supra note 6,
at I9-22, 46-5I; Rawls, supra note 36, at 5; John Rawls, Outline of A Decision Procedure For
Ethics, 6o PHIL. REV. I77 (195I). To accept what I say here, it is not necessary to endorse all
the details of these different and controversial accounts. Coherence accounts are criticized in
Joseph Raz, The Relevance of Coherence, 72 B.U. L. REV. 273, 275-82 (1992).
what morality requires, or what the law is in hard cases, we need to
explore what we - each of us - actually believe; there is no other
place to look. For example, many people could not accept a system
of free expression that would allow suppression of a relatively harmless
political protest. The judgment in that case is indeed a fixed point
for inquiry. For some people, any general theory about the
Constitution must fail if it entails the incorrectness of Brown v. Board of
Education,41 or the validation or overruling of Roe v. Wade,42 or a
particular consequence for affirmative action.</p>
      <p>It may well be wrong for any of these particular outcomes to have
such foundational status. Disagreement in law is often based on
disagreement about what are the appropriate fixed points for analysis.
Some particular outcomes do, however, occupy so central a role that
they constrain the category of permissible general theories. This is a
conventional feature of practical reason, as it operates in law and
elsewhere.</p>
      <p>So much for an important commonality between analogical
reasoning and the search for reflective equilibrium; there are important
differences as well. The search for reflective equilibrium places a high
premium on, first, the capacity to develop a complete understanding
of the basis for particular judgments and, second, the development of
abstract and general principles to account for those judgments. When
reflective equilibrium is obtained, both horizontal and vertical
consistency among cases are achieved. Every particular judgment becomes
fully theorized, and at a highly general level.</p>
      <p>Analogical reasoning is far less ambitious,43 for it does not require
anything like horizontal and vertical consistency. But because
analogical reasoning requires at least a degree of generality, it is probably
best to think of the difference between the two as one of degree rather
than of kind. There is a continuum from the one to the other rather
than any sharp discontinuities. This is so especially in view of the
existence of many possible conceptions of reflective equilibrium,
allowing for very different extensions in the direction of both particular
judgments and high generality. Analogical reasoning might therefore
be understood as a sharply truncated form of the search for reflective
4" 347 U,S. 483 (I954).
42 410 U.S. 113 (I973).</p>
      <p>43 On whether analogical reasoning can even occur without much more in the way of theory,
see infra pp. 78I-83; see also Rush Rhees, The Language of Sense Data and Private Experience
- II, 7 PHILOSOPHICAL INVESTIGATIONS IOI, I39 (I984) ("Suppose people are playing chess.
I see queer problems when I look into the rules and scrutinise them. But Smith and Brown
play chess with no difficulty. Do they understand the game? Well, they play it." (quoting a
Wittgenstein lecture)). For examples of analogical reasoning that do not purport to search for
reflective equilibrium, see the essays in Thomson, cited above in note i.
equilibrium, with the truncation starting at just the point when the
relevant principles go beyond a low level of generality.44
3. Reasoning by Analogy - Incompletely Theorized
Practices.Sometimes reasoning by analogy works by reference to incompletely
theorized practices rather than incompletely theorizedjudgments. One
might, for example, know that merchants behave a certain way in
the world, or that men and women tend to have a certain relationship
in most families. One form of analogical reasoning would involve the
effort to bring to bear, on disputed cases, social practices that seem
similar to those under review.45</p>
      <p>Ideas of this kind are built on a time-honored view of law.46 The
common law -the product and the most celebrated locus of
analogical reasoning -has often been understood as a result of social custom
rather than an imposition of judicial will. According to this view, the
common law implements the customs of the people; it does not impose
the judgment of any sovereign body.47 Judges need not theorize about
or evaluate these customs to work from them.48</p>
      <p>In some ways, reasoning by analogy to incompletely theorized
social practices resembles reasoning from incompletely theorized
judgments. The difference is that it builds on existing practices, not
judgments. To that extent, it has a conspicuous Burkean caste.49
Reasoning from incompletely theorized practices is founded on the
assumption that those practices have a kind of legitimacy and sense
that ought to be brought to bear on current dilemmas.50 Here lies
the source of its appeal but also of great controversy. Those who
believe that existing practices are often a result of arbitrariness or
force, rather than deep wisdom or rationality, will be quite skeptical.
As I describe reasoning by analogy, it operates by reference to
particular convictions or judicial holdings, rather than social practices. It
44 I deal below with the comparative virtues of the two forms of reasoning. See infra
pP. 78I-83.</p>
      <p>45 I think that something of this general sort underlies Charles Fried, The Artificial Reason
of the Law or: What Lawyers Know, 6o TEX. L. REV. 35, 54-58 (I98I).</p>
      <p>46 See, e.g., MORTONJ. HORWITZT,HE TRANSFORMATIOONFAMERICANLAW, I870-I960,
at I20 (I992).</p>
      <p>47 A usual response is that customs are not prelegal or prepolitical; they are themselves a
function of law, and not independent of it. But see ROBERT C. ELLICKSON, ORDERWITHOUT
LAWI23-55 (I99I) (providing a basis for thinking that something like customary law is indeed
possible).</p>
      <p>48 This view of the common law has played a large role in fending off codification movements
in the United States. Moreover, these systems account for a prominent and influential academic
response to the Benthamite attack on judge-made law. Intriguingly, they appear to retain
considerable appeal today.</p>
      <p>49 See EDMUNDBURKE,REFLECTIONOSN THEREVOLUTIOINN FRANCE348 (Gateway 1962)
(1790).</p>
      <p>50 See Robert C. Clark, Contracts, Elites, and Traditions in the Making of CorporateLaw,
89 COLUM. L. REV. I703, 1726-30 (I989).
may be true, however, that these convictions or holdings are also the
product of arbitrariness or force, and this problem may push us in
the direction of a preference for reflective equilibrium or general
theories.51</p>
      <p>4. Classification. - Legal reasoning relies heavily on classification.
Classification plays a large role in both analogical reasoning and the
application of general theories.52 In using the notion of classification
here, I mean to refer to something far narrower and more mechanical
- the effort to resolve a case solely by reference to purely semantic
principles. By semantic principles, I mean the basic rules of grammar
and diction. When someone says that a cat is an animal, he is using
purely semantic principles. Substantive principles, by contrast,
require an argument rather than a language lesson.53 When people say
that the term "liberty"includes the right to seek an abortion, they are
resorting to substantive principles, not mere semantics.</p>
      <p>Lawyers sometimes act as if semantic principles are all that is
required to decide cases.54 Because some cases can be resolved simply
by deduction, a mundane version of legal formalism is indeed
unobjectionable. For example, if a driver drives a Toyota Camry go miles
per hour (mph) in a 6o mph zone, syllogistic reasoning can resolve
the case: the Toyota Camry is a motor vehicle, the state has a speed
limit ordinance of 6o mph; the driver violated the ordinance.</p>
      <p>Classification of this sort is not always adequate. Suppose that
the driver of the Camry claims that she was escaping a murderer who
was shooting at her from his vehicle, or that she was a police officer
51I discussthis point in Partm. See infrapp. 770-7I.</p>
      <p>52 Hence SamuelBeckett'sresponseto criticsof his friendJamesJoyce:'The dangeris in
the neatnessof identifications.... Mustwe wringthe neckof a certainsystemin orderto stuff
it into a contemporarypigeon-hole,or modify the dimensionsof that pigeon-holefor the
satisfactionof the analogymongersL?iterarycriticismis not book-keeping."SAMUEL BECKETT,
DANTE. . . BRUNO.Vico ... JOYCE, in I CAN'TGo ON, I'LL Go ON I07, I07 (Richard W.
Seaver ed., I976). (I am gratefulto Scott Brewerfor providingthis reference.)Law is not
book-keeping,either;but this is an argumentfor analogicalreasoningratherthan againstit.
See iifra pp. 787-90.</p>
      <p>53 I am oversimplifyinghere. W.V. Quinefamouslyarguesthat a familiarversionof this
distinctiontums out to be untenable. See W.V. Quine, TwoDogmasof Empiricism,60 PHIL.
REV. 20 (i95i). Adaptedto the legalcontext,Quine'sargumentmaybe describedin this rough
way: There is no such thing as interpretationby referenceto purelysemanticprinciples(or
purelyanalytictruths). Manysubstantiveprinciples(ornonanalyticideas)are at workin every
case. In cases in which they are invisible, as they often are, and when we seem able to rely
only on semantics,it is only becausethere is a consensusabout the substantiveprinciples(or
nonanalyticideas). See id. at 34. I believethat Quine'sargumentis relatedto the following
point, stated very briefly:"Theapplicationof the conceptof 'followinga rule'presupposesa
custom." LUDWIG WITTGENSTEIN, REMARKS ON THE FOUNDATIONS OF MATHEMATICS 322
(G.H. von Wright, R. Rhees &amp; G.E.M. Anscombeeds., G.E.M. Anscombetrans., rev. ed.
1983). The distinctionI am drawingin the text should thus be understoodas a matterof
custom or convention.</p>
      <p>54 With the qualificationnotedabove. See supranote 53.
attempting to arrest a fleeing terrorist. To evaluate the guilt of a
defendant found in either of these situations, classification in the
purely semantic sense is inadequate. Both defendants may well have
a legally sufficient excuse as a result of statute or judge-made law. If
the speed limit statute is all the court invokes, we have what might
be called spurious classification. It is spurious because to decide the
cases, the court must actually be resorting to something other than
the speed limit law. It must use an additional form of reasoning, or
invoke some other cases or statutes.</p>
      <p>Often reasoning by classification is indeed a sham, in the sense
that some judgment of value is being made but not disclosed. This
is a familiar kind of bad formalism, at least if we understood
formalism as an effort to decide all cases in law solely by reference to
decisions made by someone else. Consider, for example, the view that
the liberty to contract is necessarily, and purely as a matter of
semantics, part of the "liberty"protected by the Due Process Clause.55
The problem here is that a supplemental value judgment is necessary.
To conclude that liberty of contract is part of constitutional "liberty,"
the dictionary is insufficient. One has to make claims about morality,
history, or probably both. The case is quite different from one in
which someone decides that the category "dog" necessarily includes
German shepherds.56</p>
      <p>Spurious classification, or bad formalism, often masquerades as
analogical reasoning. Sometimes people believe that case A is
analogous to case B, and attribute the belief to pure deduction, when a
supplemental judgment of some kind is necessary.57 They find
similarities between the two cases, ignore possible differences, and then
announce the outcome of the case. In doing so, they fail to identify
and defend the requisite supplemental judgment.</p>
      <p>Formalist analogical thinking is no better than any other kind of
bad formalism. Different factual situations are inarticulate; they do
not impose order on themselves. Patterns are made, not simply found.
Whether one case is analogous to another depends on substantive
55 See Lochner v. New York, I98 U.S. 45, 53 (I905).</p>
      <p>56 I take the examples in this paragraph from Frederick Schauer, Formalism, 97 YALEL.J.
509, 512-13 (1988).</p>
      <p>57 William James described this phenomenon as "vicious abstractionism":
We conceive a concrete situation by singling out some salient or important feature in it,
and classing it under that; then, instead of adding to its previous characters all the
positive consequences which the new way of conceiving it may bring, we proceed to use
our concept privatively; reducing the originally rich phenomenon to the naked suggestions
of that name abstractly taken, treating it as a case of 'nothing but' that concept, and
acting as if all the other characters from out of which the concept is abstracted were
expunged. Abstraction, functioning in this way, becomes a means of arrest far more
than a means of advance in thought. It mutilates things ....</p>
      <p>WILLIAM JAMES, THE MEANING OF TRUTH I35-36 (I975) (footnote omitted).
ideas that must be justified.58 The method of analogical reasoning
that I am describing here is insistently antiformalist in the sense that
it always stands ready to explain and justify the claim that one thing
is analogous to another.</p>
      <p>In comparing analogical thinking with classification, we should
see, too, that analogical reasoning can go wrong not simply because
it is formalist, but also because it is illogical. Consider, for example,
Justice Holmes's notorious argument on behalf of compulsory
sterilization of the feeble-minded in Buck v. Bell.59 Holmes suggested that
if people can be conscripted during wartime, or can be forced to
obtain vaccinations, it follows that the state can require sterilization
of the "feeble-minded."60 But this is a casual and unpersuasive claim.
Many principles may cover the first two cases without also covering
the third. Holmes does not explore the.many possibly relevant
similarities and differences among these cases. He does not identify the
range of possible principles, much less argue for one rather than
another. Instead, he invokes a principle of a high level of generality
"the public welfare may call upon the best citizens for their lives"
-that is not evaluated by reference to low- or intermediate-level
principles that may also account for the analogous cases.</p>
      <p>The example shows that analogical reasoning can go wrong when
one case is said to be analogous to another on the basis of a unifying
principle that is accepted without having been tested against other
possibilities, or when some similarities between two cases are deemed
decisive with insufficient investigation of relevant differences. These
are pervasive problems, linked to bad formalist thinking. When these
problems occur, the right response is to say that the court has not
properly engaged in analogical reasoning. It is a part of the analogical
method, as I understand it here, that judges must identify and test
the possible available principles, and evaluate them against one
another.61</p>
      <p>58 To the extent that analogical reasoning is not propositional but instead constitutive of our
thinking, see supra note 7, however, we cannot make arguments, but must rest content with
how it is that we think. For present purposes, I do not believe that this is an important
qualification.</p>
      <p>59 274 U.S. 200, 207 (I927) ("Wehave seen more than once that the public welfare may call
upon the best citizens for their lives. It would be strange if it could not call upon those who
already sap the strength of the State for these lesser sacrifices, often not felt to be such by those
concerned . . . The principle that sustains compulsory vaccination is broad enough to cover
cutting the Fallopian tubes. Three generations of imbeciles are enough." (citation omitted)).
60 See id.</p>
      <p>61 See supra pp. 744-45; infra pp. 774-75. A related problem is that analogical reasoning
can distract attention from the particular matter at hand by persuading judges to grapple with
other cases and hypothetical examples that actually raise quite different issues. Resort to analogy
can deflect the eye from the specific problem and thus induce a kind of blindness to what is
really at stake.</p>
      <p>Note here Bishop Butler's phrase, "Everything is what it is, and not another thing," which
5. Means-Ends Rationality. - Sometimes legal reasoning is simply
a form of instrumental rationality. Suppose, for example, that a court
must decide whether to impose an implied warranty of habitability
on landlords. The court should consider the effects of the warranty
on the housing market. Will such warranties increase rents, decrease
available housing, or otherwise have disproportionately severe
consequences for the poor? Or suppose a court is asked to rule that the
First Amendment forbids the use of the libel law in any case involving
a public official. A relevant question is the extent of the "chilling
effect" of libel law on public discussion. In cases of this sort, courts
must look at the facts. Reasoning operates simply by figuring them
out, or at least by speculating as best we can.</p>
      <p>Means-ends rationality should play a large role in law, both in the
courts and elsewhere; indeed, it should play a much larger role than
it now does. In the law of tort, contract, and property, for example,
legislatures and judges should anticipate the effects of their decisions
on, among other things, the allocation and distribution of resources.
Conventional legal tools are ill-suited to this task.62 Frequently, courts
approach questions about consequences as if they could be answered
by reference to other judicial holdings.</p>
      <p>Analogical reasoning is often silent or unhelpful on the question
of social consequences. To be sure, it may be possible to say that if
X has certain consequences, Y, which closely resembles X, will have
the same consequences; in this way one can indeed learn something
about consequences through thinking analogically. But this is usually
not the most systematic or reliable way to evaluate the effects of laws.
To the extent that courts do attempt to consider consequences, they
will not be engaging in distinctly legal reasoning. Lawyers might as
well be doing something else, such as economics; analogical reasoning
usually plays little role.</p>
      <p>Here, then, is a basic account of analogical reasoning. Without
relying on general theories, and without achieving reflective
equilibrium, lawyers develop low-level principles to account for particular
judgments, and apply those low-level principles to new cases in which
there is as yet no judgment at all.63 As we will see in Part III, this
Wittgensteinconsideredas a mottofor his book,PhilosophicalInvestigations.See RAYMoNK,
LUDWIGWITTGENSTEINT:HE DuTY OF GENIUS451 (I99o). At its best, analogical reasoning
is especially alert to this fact. See infra pp. 784-90 (comparing analogical reasoning to general
theories).</p>
      <p>62 For a good discussion of the failure to examine means-end rationality in the legislative
context, see Edward L. Rubin, LegislativeMethodology8,o GEO. L.J. 233, 268-81 (I99I).</p>
      <p>63 In his classicessay,An Introductionto LegalReasoning,Edward Levi also describes the
process as analogical. See EDWARDH. LEVI, AN INTRODUCTIONTO LEGALREASONING 1-2
(1949). My account diverges from Levi's on the important question of what happens when
analogies appear to point in different directions. In my view, a judge must make some judgment
about the best controlling low-level principle. By contrast, Levi says that in such cases, "words
method has important limits, but it is admirably well-suited to a
system in which certain judgments must be taken as relatively fixed,
and in which participants must deal with political dissensus and moral
flux.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>II. AN EXAMPLE: CROSs-BURNING</title>
      <p>Thus far the discussion has been quite abstract, but analogical
reasoning is best understood by reference to examples. The law of
free speech is an especially good area for investigation, because most
of the reasoning in that area is analogical in nature. It will be useful
to explore an issue of current controversy - the legal response to
cross-burning and similar forms of expressive activity. I build the
example from the recent case of R.A. V. v. City of St. Paul,64 in which
analogies played an important role.</p>
      <p>I outline a set of responses to the cross-burning issue, attempting
to show how much progress might be made by working from analogies
and low-level principles. Large theoretical issues, and assessments of
facts and incentives, are studiously avoided. We will see that
analogies provide constraints on reasoning in a way that makes the correct
legal outcome different from the correct moral outcome. But the key
points involve method, not outcomes.</p>
      <p>It may be tempting to begin with the suggestion that cross-burning
is action, not speech, and is therefore outside of the First Amendment
altogether. We might suggest a low-level proposition:
change to receive the content which the community gives to them." Id. at 104. "The process
is one in which the ideas of the community and of the social sciences, whether correct or not,
as they win acceptance in the community, control legal decisions." Id. at 6. For Levi, reasoning
by analogy therefore has a crucial democratic component, found through the use of public
desires (and social science). Levi did not, however, specify the mechanism by which community
wishes help settle the play of analogies. There may be an historical explanation for this seemingly
odd suggestion. Levi's book can be understood as a response to the legal realist attack on the
autonomy of legal reasoning and to the associated claim, prominent after the New Deal, that
legal reasoning is fatally undemocratic. When Levi was writing, it seemed crucial to establish
the relative autonomy of law and especially of the common law method - to show that it had
a logic and integrity of its own, but also to establish that it was not wholly independent of
social desires. The enduring influence of Levi's account may stem from its apparent success in
this endeavor.</p>
      <p>It would, however, be most surprising if one could identify any mechanism for translating
community wishes into analogical reasoning. In hard cases, moreover, the community is badly
divided. There may be no communal desire to which courts can look in making decisions.
Reliance on community views is complicated further by the fact that the views of the community
may be in part a function of what the courts say. The persuasiveness of any argument by
analogy must turn on something other than community desires. Instead the process works by
seeing to what principles people in positions of decision are most deeply committed.
64 II2 S. Ct. 2538 (I992).
ready exists. Very little can be said on behalf of something so
unambitious as that.</p>
      <p>To some degree this objection is valid. If someone denies that a
problem would be created by a prohibition of flag-burning, or of any
expressive conduct, the inquiry into cross-burning will have a hard
time getting off the ground. (Note, however, that it may be possible
to undermine this very denial with analogies.) If someone thinks that
the government can punish political speech whenever that speech
poses any risk to the government, it will be hard to reason with them
through analogies to a sensible system of free expression.101 In this
sense, it is correct to think that reasoning by analogy depends on a
degree of commonality - even homogeneity - among participants in
the discussion. 102 Analogical reasoning, it might be concluded, works
most easily in these circumstances; it has a tendency toward bias or
excessive complacency.</p>
      <p>Some of these claims are undoubtedly true. We might begin,
however, by asking whether they really amount to objections at all.
The need for a degree of consensus is hardly a problem distinctive to
analogy. It applies to all forms of reasoning.103 In coming to terms
with this objection, we need to distinguish between analogical
reasoning in law and analogical reasoning elsewhere. Law imposes greater
constraints on the analogical process. Existing legal holdings
sometimes provide the necessary commonality and the necessary consensus.
People who disagree with those holdings usually agree that they must
be respected; the principle of stare decisis so requires. Within the
legal culture, analogical reasoning imposes a certain discipline, and a
widespread moral or political consensus is therefore unnecessary. We
101 On this score reasoning in science is no different from reasoning elsewhere. Both depend
on a certain degree of consensus. The perceived differences between scientific and other thought
may stem partly from the fact that we tend to compare ethical or legal issues in which judgments
are contested (affirmative action, the death penalty) with scientific issues in which matters are
settled (the earth goes around the sun, dropped objects will fall). This is probably misleading;
we might do better to compare the settled scientific judgments with the settled ethical ones
(slavery is wrong, purposeless human suffering cannot be justified). See Alan Gewirth, Positive
"Ethics"and Normative"Science,"69 PHIL. REV. 311, 3I2-13 (1960).</p>
      <p>102 The point may be put in another way. Sometimes case A is found analogous to case B,
rather than case C, simply because the relevant judges are homogenous, and the homogeneity
may damage judicial thinking. Analogical reasoning can go wrong for this reason. Some people,
for example, think that a prohibition on homosexual sodomy is like a prohibition on incest, see,
e.g., Bowers v. Hardwick, 478 U.S. i86, 195-96 (I986); others think that the right analogy is
a prohibition on the use of contraceptives within marriage. It is at least possible that the former
group thinks as it does in part because of its homogeneity, that is, because it has not been
systematically confronted with other views and perspectives.</p>
      <p>103 Cf. LUDWIG L. WITTGENSTEIN, PHILOSOPHICAL INVESTIGATIONS ? 242, at 88 (G.E.M.
Anscombe trans., 3d ed. 1958) ("If language is to be a means of communication there must be
agreement not only in definitions but also (queer as this may sound) in judgments. This seems
to abolish logic but does not do so.").
have seen several examples of this in our examination of the
crossburning issue. 104</p>
      <p>Things are different outside of law, simply because of the absence
of precedents that can help generate an "overlapping consensus"105on
outcomes. The differences lead to two important conclusions. First,
the method of analogy may indeed be less determinate outside of law.
In law, we have a wide range of "fixed points" for inquiry, and this
makes the analysis easier. Second, there will be a real difference
between the legally correct outcome and the morally correct outcome.
The difference lies in the fact that analogies operate as fixed points
in legal reasoning, whereas in morality they are either revisable or
entirely open-ended. Consider, for example, the fact that lawyers
must take Roe v. Wade as authoritative as long as it stands, even if
they think the decision abhorrent.'06</p>
      <p>Even outside of law, the indeterminacy objection is not entirely
persuasive. Very diverse people may have sufficient commonality on
fundamental matters to permit considerable progress. Even if such
commonality appears not to exist, a good deal of movement can occur
through simultaneous engagement with what various participants in
the discussion say and think - an engagement that would include
narratives about diverse experiences or history, personal and
otherwise, as well as more conventional "reasons."107(Note that the case
method operates in part through narratives.)'08</p>
      <p>In order to provide relevant information, and to counteract
parochialism and bias, it is important to ensure that, in law and elsewhere,
people with different perspectives and experiences are permitted to
participate.'09 It is equally important to ensure that judges are alert
to the range of possible low-level principles, and that they attempt to
compare those principles with one another. But through some such
route, people who initially disagree so strongly as to make
conversation seem difficult can sometimes be brought together, at least to the
point where analogical reasoning can start. Nearly everyone has had
this experience.</p>
      <p>In any case, we cannot know that the optimistic view is false until
we try to talk.110 And here the very concreteness of analogical
reasoning is a large advantage. In cases in which there are major
differences in starting points, people can often think far better about
particular problems than about large-scale approaches to the world.</p>
      <p>In this regard, we might consider a sharply disputed constitutional
question, one related to the cross-burning problem: whether the
government can regulate "hate speech." For some people, the proper
analogy, in thinking about hate speech, is physical assault.1"' To
them, hate speech is a form of visceral attack that has little or no
connection to free speech values and produces severe and unique
harm. For those who disagree, the proper analogy is speech by
members of dissident political groups.112 Hate speech is merely a form of
controversial expression, subject to a risk of censorship, as is much
expression, by people who want to use the arm of the law to enforce
a particular orthodoxy.</p>
      <p>A dispute of this sort may seem intractable. Perhaps people simply
disagree. But it is necessary to ask people on both sides what features
of hate speech make it analogous either to physical assault or to
political dissent. Once that is specified, we are well on our way
toward a discussion. For example, it might be said that hate speech
is like an assault because the relevant words are not intended as a
contribution to rational thought, because they deeply hurt, because
they reflect and lead to second-class citizenship, or because they are
inconsistent with prevailing, hard-won political convictions in relevant
communities.</p>
      <p>All of these claims can be evaluated. In the ensuing discussion,
we might ask when words are not intended as a contribution to
rational thought, when such words are properly excluded from
protection as speech, and when expression can be banned because it is
harmful or because (or although) it is inconsistent with prevailing
Supreme Court, 1985 Term- Foreword: Traces of Self-Government, ioo HARV. L. REV. 4,
7677 (I986) (defending plurality on courts).</p>
      <p>110It follows that the process of reasoning by analogy carries with it a pragmatic conception
of truth. See WILLIAM JAMES, PRAGMATISM91-105 (Bruce Kuklick ed., I198I) (1907); John
Dewey, Propositions, WarrantedAssertibility, and Truth, 38 J. PHIL. 169, 169-72 (I94I).</p>
      <p>II' See Charles R. Lawrence HII,If He Hollers Let Him Go: Regulating Racist Speech on
Campus, I990 DUKE L.J. 431, 462.</p>
      <p>112 See Nadine Strossen, Regulating Racist Speech on Campus: A Modest Proposal?, I990
DUKE L.J. 484, 537-39.
convictions. We might think about cases in which our convictions
seem firm. We might agree, for example, that government can ban
obscene telephone calls, or that it cannot ban even offensive and
dangerous political speech.</p>
      <p>An approach of this kind might well lead us to make distinctions
between different forms of "hate speech." The racial epithet might
seem similar to an obscene phone call; but racist speech, made as part
of a statement of political view, might seem like protected expression.
This is at best a start. But even this seemingly least tractable of
disputes may well be soluble in this way. Surely the field of legitimate
disagreement can be narrowed and better understood.</p>
      <p>All this helps suggest the weakness in the view that analogical
reasoning depends on a deep social consensus. Even without such a
consensus, there is usually sufficient agreement, with respect to some
matters of importance, to allow the process of reasoning to begin.
None of this means that people will always be able to reach closure.
Sometimes they really do disagree. But analogical reasoning can at
least help to discover where they do, and why."13</p>
      <p>3. The Search for Relevant Differences - The Inevitable Need for
Criteria Never Supplied by Analogical Reasoning. - The final
objection to analogical reasoning is that the process has yet to be
adequately specified, and that when it is, it will emerge as a primitive
and failed substitute either for a more general theory or for the effort
to reach reflective equilibrium. This is, I believe, the most powerful
objection to analogical reasoning; in an important sense, it is correct.
But the nature of the objection, and the possible responses, are
surprisingly complicated.</p>
      <p>The objection begins with a simple point. The method of analogy
is based on the question: Is case A relevantly similar to case B, or
not? Is a ban on homosexual sodomy like a ban on the use of
contra113Note that it does not followfromthe merefact of disagreementhat thereareno correct
answersto disputedquestionsin law or ethics, any morethan it does in science. Nor does it
follow,fromthe fact thatlegalcategoriesareourcategories,andrevisableby us, thateverything
is up for grabs,or that we are in some sort of abyss. It is truethat humanbeings,including
lawyers,do not have unmediatedaccessto the world;we seethingsthroughhumanframeworks.
But this need not entailany formof skepticismor relativism. It would do so only if the only
possibleknowledgewereexternalortranscendentala,ndthereis no reasonto thinkthat. Indeed,
peoplewho thinkthat the absenceof externalor transcendentafloundationsleadsto relativism
or skepticismoften have a greatdeal in commonwith theirpurportedadversaries.They have
the same odd conceptionaboutwhat correctanswersmustbe, to countas such.</p>
      <p>Stanley Fish makes this importanterrorin Doing What ComesNaturally,in which he
suggeststhat becauseall categoriesare humancategories,all we are left with is conventions.
See STANLEY FISH, DOING WHAT COMES NATURALLY 215-45, 342-55, 436-70 (I989). Richard
Rorty comes very close to the same unfortunateposition,see RichardRorty,Feminismand
Pragmatism30 MICH. QUART. REv. 231, 234-36 (i99i), and is criticizedpersuasivelyfor this
reasonby DonaldDavidson,see DonaldDavidson,TheStructureand Contentof Truth,87 J.
PHIL. 279, 279-82 (i99o), andby HilaryPutnam,see HILARYPUTNAM, RENEWING PHILOSOPHY
104 (1992). See also infranote 130 (discussingpostmodernismin law).</p>
      <p>HARVARD LAW REVIEV
ceptives in marriage, or like a ban on incest? Is a restriction on
abortion like a restriction on murder, or like a compulsory kidney
transplant? To answer such questions, one needs a theory of relevant
similarities and differences. By itself, analogical reasoning supplies
no such theory. It is thus dependent on an apparatus that it is unable
to produce.114</p>
      <p>In short: Everything is a little bit similar to, or different from,
everything else. Perhaps better: Everything is similar in infinite ways
to everything else, and also different from everything else in the same
number of ways."15 At the very least one needs a set of criteria to
engage in analogical reasoning. Otherwise one has no idea what is
analogous to what.</p>
      <p>By themselves, factual situations tell us little until we impose some
sort of pattern on them."16 We say that something is like something
else only because we have a principle that tells us so (or because we
simply perceive the world this way). If this is true, it might seem
better simply to identify the principle and the criteria, if we have
them, rather than to proceed through analogies.</p>
      <p>Thus, for example, if we are asking what sorts of speech are
protected by the First Amendment, we might ask some questions
about the purposes of that amendment, or the scope of its coverage,
114 Cf. POSNERs,upranote 2, at 88-92 (arguingthat "reasoningby analogy . . . is not
actuallya methodof reasoning,that is, of connectingpremisesto conclusions.")R;obertoM.
Unger,THE CRITicALLEGALSTUDIEMSOVEMENT8 (I986) ("Withoutsuch a guidingvision,
legal reasoningseemscondemnedto a gameof easy analogies.").</p>
      <p>115 Westenmakesthe same argumentagainstthe notionof equality. See PeterWesten,The
Empty Idea of Equality, 95 HARv. L. REV. 537, 540-42 (1982). Equality is parasitic on
substantiveideas about relevantdifferences;so too with analogy. See Golding,supranote 3,
at 102 ("Wfnfact two things may resembleeach otherin any numberof respectsand yet also
be differentin any numberof respects")s;ee also NELSONGOODMANSe,ven Strictureson
Similarity,in PROBLEMSAND PROJECTS 437 (1972) ("SimilarityI, submit, is insidious....
Similarity,ever readyto solve philosophicalproblemsand overcomeobstacles,is a pretender,
an impostor,a quack.").</p>
      <p>116See suprap. 746(remarkingon Holmes). The pointsuggestssomereasonsfor skepticism
aboutthe intriguingeffortsto programcomputersto engagein analogicalreasoning.See KEVIN
D. ASHLEY,MODELINGLEGALARGUMENT(i99o); Kevin D. Ashley, Arguing By Analogy in
Law: A Case-Based Model, in ANALOGICARLEASONINGs,upra note 3, at 205, 212-22. The
programmersact as if computerscan be taught to decide what case a new fact situationis
"moreanalogousto,"butthis dependson a crudepictureof analogousreasoning.It is inadequate
to treat"analogousnessa"s a kindof quantity,with somethingsbeingmoreanalogousto others,
and othersthingsless so. Any such formulationtendsto disguisethe needto developlow-level
principleswith whichto thinkanalogiesthrough;andit is unclearthatthe computerexperiments
have placedenoughweight on this point. We shouldnot, however,rejectthe possibilitythat
in the long run (or the shortrun?),computerswill indeedbe able to makethe good normative
argumentsthat underlieassessmentsof analogousnessa,nd that in the end it will be valuable
for humanbeingsto listen carefullyto what they have to say. See ASHLEY, supra,at 238-47;
cf. PuTNAm, suPranote 113, at i-i8 (criticizingthe analogybetweenthe human mind and
artificialintelligence).
and then apply our answers to various cases - rather than refusing
to specify the general theory in advance and spending time examining
the endless cases that are the staple of free speech law: perjury,
misleading commercial speech, conspiracies, false cries of fire in a
crowded theater, and so forth. On this view, reasoning by analogy is
necessary only because of our failure to develop general principles,
which ought to be evaluated in their own right.</p>
      <p>The first and most modest response to all this is that analogical
reasoning is helpful even if the criticism is fundamentally right. Even
if we do need principles to decide cases, this is not an objection to
analogical reasoning, which is an important part of the development
of those principles. Without analogies, relevant principles often
cannot be described in advance except at an uninformatively high and
crude level of generality. The cross-burning case provides an example:
How could a general theory be helpful on a problem of this sort?
Any relevant criteria for free speech problems will emerge largely
from the process of comparing various cases. Moreover, the criteria
will not have any source other than what we think. There is no other
source of criteria. We cannot know what it is that we think until we
explore a range of cases. Principles are thus both generated and tested
through confrontation with particular cases.</p>
      <p>This humble response may establish only that analogies help us
discover principles, which are in an ultimate sense freestanding.
Analogies are like a ladder that can be discarded once we have climbed
to the top. I think that this metaphor is misleading because it suggests
that analogies are dispensable in a way that they are not; analogies
are not a ladder to be tossed away, but rather an important basis for
our judgments. But a fuller response to this criticism must go deeper.
The fuller defense would start with the claim that our considered
judgments about particular cases have a kind of priority in deciding
what the law is or should be. My suggestion is that because of the
distinctive requirements of a legal system, correct answers in law
might consist precisely of those particular judgments, once they have
been made to cohere.117</p>
      <p>117Cf. THOMSON, supra note I, at 257 ("[I]tis precisely our moral views about examples,
stories, and cases which constitute the data for moral theorizing."). Thus Thomson writes as if
we can "falsify"general propositions by "testing"them against particular judgments. See also
DWORKIN, supra note 22, at 28-37 (treating judgments as data points); cf. T.M. Scanlon, The
Aims and Authority of Moral Theory, I2 OX. J. LEGAL STUD. I, 9 (I992) ("[W]e are very
unlikely to have a considered judgement that a certain action would be wrong without having
in mind some more 'theoretical' reason why it would [be] wrong. 'Considered moral judgements'
are in this respect quite unlike 'data points': in the case of simple empirical observations we can
be quite certain that something is the case without having any idea why it is so."). Scanlon's
position may ultimately be right; but there are some uncertainties. Is it clear that there is a
sharp difference between an observation that dropped objects fall, or for that matter that the
earth is flat, unaccompanied by "any idea why it is so" and an observation that slavery or</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>HARVARD LAW RE VIEW</title>
      <p>At least it seems clear that general principles and general theories
are sometimes inadequate for legal reasoning. Often too many factors
are relevant, and too many variations are possible, to allow a general
formulation adequately to capture the range of right results in the
cases.118 More particularly, any general theory will sometimes be too
rigid and crude to account for the diversity and plurality of relevant
goods. 119</p>
      <p>On this view, correct answers plausibly consist not of deductions
from general theory, but instead of coherent convictions about
particular cases. In the law of free speech, for example, the Court has not
fully explained what speech counts as "high value" and what speech
falls in a lower tier.120 It is tempting to say that this is a major
failure in constitutional law, and that the Court would do much better
to tell us in plain terms what "test"it is using. But perhaps any test,
described at a high level of generality, will be either vacuous or subject
to decisive counterexamples. Perhaps this is not true for the First
Amendment; it is possible that if we thought well enough, we would
come up with a perfect general theory, or - a quite different point
- that the advantages of an inadequately precise test might outweigh
the disadvantages of having no general theory at all. All I mean to
suggest is that sometimes analogical reasoning might, in principle, be
crueltyis wrong, unaccompaniedby "anyidea why it is so"? It may be that simpleempirical
observationsand consideredjudgmentsaboutparticularcases have the same(pragmaticp)lace
in humanreasoning.</p>
      <p>118It is possible,however,that one will toleratemanyparticularmistakes,and thus seek a
generalrule, becausecase-by-casedecisionsproduceeven moremistakesin light of the errors
of humanjudgmentin case-by-casesystems. Wecan seethe pointby comparingthe firstRestate
of Conflictof Laws with the second. The firstRestatementis filled with rules, most of them
susceptibleto mechanicalapplication,but the mechanicscreate many errorsin the form of
arbitraryrigidity. By contrast,the secondRestatementuses lists of factors,in the effort to
produceindividualizedjudgments;but it createssomethingof a messforthosewho must'apply"
it. See also Schauer,Formalism,supra note 56, at 538-44 (defendingrule-baseddecisions);
AntoninScalia, TheRule of LawAs a Law of Rules, 56 U. CHI.L. REV.II75, II80-82 (I989)
(describingproblemswith "reasonableness"tandardsand judicialbalancingtests).
119 See ANDERSONs,upranote 39, at ch. i; infrapp. 786-90.</p>
      <p>120 CompareCass R. Sunstein,Free SpeechNow, 59 U. CHI.L. REv. 255, 315-I6 (1992)
(defendinga politicalconceptionof FirstAmendmentw)ith Dworkin,TheComingBattles over
Free Speech, supranote 22, at 55 (arguingthat free speech cases should be resolvedon the
basisof a "constitutivea"pproachthatwouldforbidgovernmento intrudeon listeneror speaker
autonomyexcept underthe rarestof conditions). UndoubtedlyDworkinis correctthat ideas
about autonomyshouldplay a majorrole in First Amendmentlaw. But the questionremains
how much progresscan be madein hardfree speechcaseswithoutconsultinga wide rangeof
particularsettings. A "topdown"approachthatappliedthe notionof autonomywouldprobably
prove inadequatein cases involvingrestrictionson commercialadvertising,unlicensedmedical
and legal advice, child pornographyp,rivatelibel, threats,and so forth. See T.M. Scanlon,
Jr., Freedomof Expressionand Categoriesof Expression,40 U. PITT.L. REV.5I9, 532 (i979)
(rejectinghis own earlierautonomyprinciplebecause.ofits inabilityto accountfully for
judgmentsin particularcases).
preferred to a general theory, simply because no such theory can
adequately account for particular convictions, and because those
convictions deserve priority in thinking about good outcomes in law.</p>
      <p>The objection and the response might be put in another way. It
is tempting to think that with deductive reasoning, we can come up
with truth. If, for example, utilitarianism is true, we can decide cases
by figuring out how to maximize utility. But what is the relationship
between analogical thinking and truth? Use of analogies produces
principled consistency, at best, and not truth at all.</p>
      <p>The response is that sometimes there may be no criteria for truth
in law except for our considered judgments about particular cases,
once those judgments have been made to cohere with each other. I
have noted that there is obscurity in this suggestion. The obscurity
comes in at least two places: What are considered judgmenits? How
do we know when they cohere? Let me address a few of the
ambiguities.</p>
      <p>At a minimum, considered judgments include the judgments that
serve as fixed points for moral or legal analysis (although we must
note, as above, that we will not know what the fixed points are in
advance). Some particular judgments do operate as fixed points in
this sense. For some people, the notion that government may ban
bribery or perjury has the status of a fixed point for free speech law.
We might also understand the category of considered judgments to
include those that have survived a degree of scrutiny through
comparison with other cases and a good deal of other low-level
principles.121 Through some such route, we may come up with a catalogue
of reliable particular judgments. Coherence in law might then be
defined as consistency among particular judgments and low-level
principles.</p>
      <p>It would be good to achieve this kind of coherence;122but in the
end, even this may be inadequate, because it is insufficiently
ambitious. Judgments about particular cases probably deserve to be
counted as considered only if they have survived encounter with
principles of various levels of generality. To qualify as considered
judgments, we should probably test our convictions about particular
cases not simply by reference to other cases and low-level principles,
but also by reference to principles described at higher levels of
abstraction. On this view, reasoning by analogy should indeed be seen
121In his discussionof reflectiveequilibrium,Rawls does not understandthe categoryin
quitethis way, and insteademphasizesjudgmentsin whichwe have a greatdealof confidence.
See RAWLS, supranote 6, at 48-5i. But it is unclearhow we would have a greatdeal of
confidencein a particularjudgmentif we have not submittedthatjudgmentto scrutinyof this
generalkind.</p>
      <p>122But see infra pp. 778-79, 782-84 (questioningthe desirabilityof doing this in a legal
system).
as an incomplete and truncated version of the search for reflective
equilibrium. And on this view, we have not achieved real coherence
unless a great deal is done both vertically and horizontally, that is,
unless we have tested our particular convictions against many
judgments of general principle as well as against many other particular
convictions. If this is so, we do not have either considered judgments
or coherence until we have thought through our high-level principles
in far more detail than analogical thought ordinarily requires.</p>
      <p>This argument suggests that some version of reflective equilibrium
is indeed the appropriate end-state of analogical reasoning in morality
and, under ideal conditions, in law.123 An important qualification,
however, is necessary for law: Some of the fixed points in law are
precedents reached by others, not judgments genuinely accepted by
oneself. These points may be fixed either because the legal culture
genuinely renders them unrevisable (for the particular judge on, say,
a lower court), or because the principle of stare decisis imposes a
strong barrier to revision.</p>
      <p>Unlike morality, in which revisability is a key aspect of the search
for reflective equilibrium,124 the law tends to fix many particular
judgments. This point has major implications for the possibility that
lawyers or judges can reach reflective equilibrium. Because of the
sheer number of judges in a position to create fixed points in many
particular cases, no single participant in the legal culture is at all
likely to be able to achieve equilibrium.125</p>
      <p>This fact should not be entirely lamented; it is a virtue as well as
a vice. Because of the need for predictability and stability in law,
many questionable outcomes must be taken as fixed. With this point
in mind, analogical reasoning might be defended on the ground that
the best approach to certain areas of law is principled consistency
with respect to individual cases and low-level principles. At least
under real-world constraints, this form of principled consistency may
be what we mean by truth, or right answers, in law or even
morality.126 This point bears on the claim that analogical reasoning requires
criteria that analogies cannot themselves supply. Of course one needs
criteria to engage in such reasoning. But those criteria will emerge
from the process of comparing various cases; often they are not given
or even describable in advance, except at an unhelpful level of
generality.</p>
      <p>123 See also infra p. 785 (discussing "conceptual ascent").
124 See supra p. 75 I.</p>
      <p>125 The point counts against Dworkin's use of Hercules as a metaphor for a legal system.
See infra p. 786 (discussing the advantages of analogical reasoning over the search for reflective
equilibrium).</p>
      <p>126 See supra note 63 (describing the discussion of Director and Levi); see also Davidson,
supra note II3, at 279-82, 325-326 (offering a pragmatic conception of truth).</p>
      <p>The same point can be made in another way. The critics of
analogical reasoning sometimes act as if analogies were "things," which
either resolve or do not resolve contested cases.127 If they do resolve
contested cases, they are not mere analogies but genuine rules; if they
do not, they are nothing at all.128 But analogies should not be seen
in this way. Their meaning lies in their use. They are not simply
unanalyzed fact patterns; they are used to help people think through
contested cases and to generate low-level principles. In this way they
have a constitutive dimension, for the patterns we see are a product
not simply of preexisting reality, but of our cognitive structures and
our principles as well. 129 The principles and patterns we develop and
describe are in turn brought to bear on, and tested through
confrontation with, other cases.</p>
      <p>This process is not a game or a joke. It does not evade
responsibility. It does not involve tricks. "Irony"is not its most distinctive
feature.130 It does not treat moral seriousness as an anachronism to
127 See POSNER, supra note 2, at 89-90; Tushnet, supra note 2, at 825 (criticizing the view
that the search for neutral principles is a constraint on "judicial choices"). Wittgenstein wrote:
When we say that by our method we try to counteract the misleading effect of certain
analogies, it is important that you should understand that the idea of an analogy being
misleading is nothing sharply defined. No sharp boundary can be drawn round the cases
in which we should say that a man was misled by an analogy. The use of expressions
constructed on analogical patterns stresses analogies between cases often far apart. And
by doing this these expressions may be extremely useful. It is, in most cases, impossible
to show an exact point where an analogy begins to mislead us. Every particular notation
stresses some particular point of view.</p>
      <p>LUDWIG WITTGENSTEIN, THE BLUE AND BROWN BOOKS 28 (I958).</p>
      <p>128 Posner appears to make this particular argument. See POSNER, supra note 2, at 89-90.
129 See Mark Johnson, Some Constraints on Embodied Analogical Understanding, in
ANALOGICAL REASONING, supra note 3, at 25, 26-28; supra notes 57, II0, II3; infra note I30
(discussing pragmatism);</p>
      <p>130See, e.g., RICHARD RORTY, CONTINGENCY, IRONY, AND SOLIDARITY73-I37 (I989). The
method of analogy has a close connection with pragmatism, see generally JAMES,supra note
Iio (discussing irony); but it is not allied with "postmodernism,"a constellation of ideas with
increasing influence on the study of law. The relationship between postmodernism and law
raises some complex issues, and I restrict myself to two brief observations here.</p>
      <p>First, any position about law and politics, in order to be worth holding, must be justified
by reference to reasons. We should not understand the category of reasons to be a narrow one,
or to be strictly Cartesian; but a view unsupported by reasons is unlikely to deserve serious
consideration. Many postmodernists, however, appear to reject reason-giving altogether, putting
in its place power, or play, or conventions. See, e.g., JACQUESDERRIDA, OF GRAMMATOLOGY
50 (Gayatri C. Spivak trans., 1976) (play); FISH, supra note II3, at 40, ii6 (conventions);
MICHEL FOUCAULT, POWER/KNOWLEDGEI I9 (Colin Gordon ed. &amp; Colin Gordon, Leo Marshall,
John Mephan, Kate Soper trans., I98I) (power). The substitution ensures that many
postmodernists "can give no account of the normative foundations of [their] own rhetoric." JURGEN
HABERMAS, THE PHILOSOPHICALDISCOURSE OF MODERNITY 294 (Fredrick Lawrence trans.,
I987) (I985).</p>
      <p>Second, some of postmodernism appears to depend on the claim that if claims cannot be
vindicated or grounded in some transcendental or extra-human way, we are left with chaos, or
the free play of perspectives, and certainly without a discussion that can be mediated through
be understood as one of the endless number of "social constructs" to
be observed from the appropriate distance. It is not a substitute or a
disguise for some other, preferable form of reasoning. Much less does
it conceal something called "politics."'131 On the contrary, it treats
both law and politics as forms of moral reasoning, and it attempts to
engage in precisely that.</p>
      <p>We might conclude that in hard cases in law, any "choice,"if made
well, is not a black box, but is instead founded on policies or principles
that usually play a part in legal reasoning as it currently stands. And
if the relevant grounds for choice are not in the current resources of
legal reasoning, so much the worse for (current) legal reasoning. We
should then change legal reasoning to ensure that it contains the
appropriate resources for choice.</p>
      <p>The process of reasoning by analogy is not science,132and it cannot
be anchored in anything other than what human beings actually
believe. But surely this does not disqualify it as a mode of reasoning. It
may even be said to be the central feature of the common law method,
prevalent of course in American constitutional law. And when
analogical reasoning is working well, it provides a deep challenge to
ordinary understandings of the rule of law - and to the occasionally
prominent movements toward codification and the replacement of
analogical reasoning with clear rules, to be laid down by the legislature
or courts133in advance.</p>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>B. Alternative Accounts and the ComparativeAdvantages of Analogical Thinking</title>
        <p>We are now in a position to compare analogical reasoning with
some other prominent approaches to law. I deal here with the search
for reflective equilibrium; Ronald Dworkin's conception of law as
"integrity";and general theories, with special reference to the economic
analysis of law.</p>
        <p>i. The Search for Reflective Equilibrium. - Throughout I have
emphasized that analogical reasoning is not fully theorized and that
those who engage in this form of reasoning have not developed a
comprehensive theory to account for their particular convictions. This
limitation has emerged as a serious one. It seems plausible that the
search for a relatively wide or extended version of reflective
equilibrium is superior to analogical reasoning, and that the latter is a kind
of crude, incomplete version of the former. Perhaps lawyers should
ultimately abandon analogical reasoning and attempt to bring their
particular judgments in accord with theories of varying levels of
generality.</p>
        <p>In some respects this is true, and something like it may well be
the correct final assessment. Once one has reached reflective
equilibrium, one has fully rationalized all particular judgments, and surely
this is a major gain. Moreover, reflective equilibrium, once obtained,
is likely to be better than analogical reasoning in the important sense
that it subjects to scrutiny both particular convictions (that one holds)
and particular holdings (of some court), and thus allows us to see if
these results can fully survive encounter with a great deal else that is
both particular and general. Once in reflective equilibrium, one is able
to account in depth and detail for all of one's convictions.
experiences, the realization that there are samenesses; and from this awareness of
similarities in number and form both science and mathematics were born.</p>
        <p>CARLB. BOYER&amp; UTA C. MERZBACHA, HISTORYOFMATHEMATIC3S(2d ed. I99I); see also
G. POLYA,How To SOLVEIT 37 (I957) ("Analogy pervades all our thinking, our everyday
speech and our trivial conclusions as well as artistic ways of expression and the highest scientific
achievements. ").</p>
        <p>133See Scalia,supranote ii8, at 1179.</p>
        <p>Precisely because of its lack of ambition, analogical reasoning is
inferior on these counts. On the other hand, reasoning by analogy has
four distinct advantages. Each of these advantages is especially
important for people engaged in legal reasoning. They suggest that
analogical reasoning may be a second-best alternative to the search
for reflective equilibrium in light of the multiple constraints imposed
on any legal system in the real world.</p>
        <p>First, reasoning by analogy may be the best approach available
for people of limited time and capacities. The search for reflective
equilibrium may be simply too demanding for participants in law, or
for others who attempt to reason through difficult problems. Often
there are too many practical constraints to work out a fully general
theory. As compared with the search for reflective equilibrium,
analogical reasoning has the advantage, for ordinary lawyers and judges,
of humility and circumspection. To engage in analogical reasoning,
one need not take a stand on large, contested social issues, some of
which can be resolved only on a sectarian basis. A lawyer or judge
who claims to have reached reflective equilibrium may seem
immodest, insufficiently cautious, or even hubristic.</p>
        <p>Second, reasoning by analogy may have the significant advantage
of allowing people unable to reach anything like an accord on general
principles to agree on particular outcomes. Sometimes it is exceedingly
difficult to get people to agree on the general principles that account
for their judgments. But it may be possible for them to agree on
particular solutions or on low-level principles.134 An overlapping
consensus135 is often possible on the view that case A is relevantly
similar to case B - even if those who join the consensus could not
decide as between utilitarianism or Kantianism, or come to agreement
on the appropriate role of religion in society.</p>
        <p>Third, analogical reasoning may be especially desirable in contexts
in which we seek moral evolution over time.'36 If the legal culture
really did attain reflective equilibrium, it might become too rigid and
calcified; we would know what we thought about everything, whether
particular or general.137 By contrast, analogical reasoning has the
important advantage of allowing a large degree of openness to new
facts and perspectives. It enables disagreement and uncertainty to
turn into consensus.</p>
        <p>Fourth, analogical reasoning in law operates with precedents that
have the status of fixed points; this is so even for people who sharply
134See JONSON &amp; TOULMIN, supra note 3, at I6-20.</p>
        <p>135See John Rawls, The Idea of an Overlapping Consensus, 7 OXFORDJ. LEGALSTUD. I,
2-8 (I987).</p>
        <p>136I am grateful to Daniel Brudney for help with this point.</p>
        <p>137In searching for reflective equilibrium, avenues are of course open; new experiences and
new data make it necessary to reassess provisional fixed points.
disagree with the results embodied in those precedents. In searching
for reflective equilibrium, by contrast, everything is potentially
revisable. The fact that precedents are fixed points helps to bring about
an overlapping consensus as well, by constraining the areas of
reasonable disagreement. In this way, analogical reasoning introduces a
degree of stability and predictability. These are important virtues for
law, and they sharply reduce the costs of reaching particular decisions.</p>
        <p>In short, lawyers could not try to reach reflective equilibrium
without severely compromising the system of precedent. As noted, the
judgments at work in the search for reflective equilibrium are subject
to critical scrutiny, and any of them might be discarded.138 The point
helps explain Rawls's suggestion that "for the purposes of this book,
the views of the reader and the author are the only ones that count.
The opinions of others are used only to clear our own heads."'39</p>
        <p>Here we have a striking and illuminating contrast between the
search for reflective equilibrium and analogical reasoning. In a legal
system, precedents are far more than an effort "to clear our own
heads." If a judge or lawyer is to attempt to reach reflective
equilibrium, precedents will have at most the status of considered judgments
about particular cases, and these might be subject to revision if they
conflict with something else that he believes. In the legal system,
precedents have a much firmer status. To be sure, precedents are not
immune to revision; but the principle of stare decisis ensures that they
operate as relatively fixed points. The search for reflective equilibrium
is therefore a misleading description of law and in some ways an
unattractive prescription. Participants in a legal system that aspires
to stability should not be so immodest as to reject judgments reached
by others whenever those judgments cannot be made part of reflective
equilibrium for those particular participants. Of course, it is only a
mixed blessing to have fixed points that are wrong as a matter of
principle. Analogical reasoning may perpetuate confusion or injustice
where reflective equilibrium would not.</p>
        <p>2. Hercules, Harlan, and Integrity. - Ronald Dworkin has been
the most influential critic of legal positivism - the view that law is
a system of rules proceeding from authoritative sources.140 Dworkin
thinks that there is an inevitable evaluative or normative dimension
138 On revisability and the search for equilibrium, see T.M. Scanlon, The Aims and Authority
of Moral Theory, I2 OXFORDJ. LEGAL STUD. i, 8-12 (1992); and pp. 788-89 below.</p>
        <p>139 Rawls, supra note 6, at 50. I do not claim that the only function of this statement is to
point to revisability. In the relevant section, Rawls discusses the analogy between the sense of
grammar and the sense of justice, and suggests that a knowledge of one person's sense of either
would be a "good beginning toward a theory of justice." Id.</p>
        <p>140 For Dworkin's description of positivism, see DWORKIN, TAKING RIGHTS SERIOUSLY,
cited above in note i, at I7-22; and DWORKIN, LAw's EMPIRE, cited above in note I, at
3335. For influential positivist works, see HART, cited above in note i; and JOHN AUSTIN, THE
PROVINCEOF JURISPRUDENCEDETERMINED (I832).</p>
        <p>HARVARD LAWREVIEW
to statements "about what the law is." Often, at least, one cannot
say "what the law is" without also saying something about "what the
law should be." In other words, Dworkin believes that when lawyers
disagree about what the law is with respect to some hard question,
they are disagreeing about "the best constructive interpretation of the
community's legal practice."141 Thus, Dworkin argues that
interpretation in law consists of different efforts to make a governing text "as
good as it can be. "142 This is Dworkin's conception of law as integrity.</p>
        <p>Hercules, Dworkin's infinitely patient and resourceful judge,
approaches the law in this way. 143 Dworkin places a large emphasis on
"fit" as a criterion for correctness in legal outcomes. On Dworkin's
view, we do not look at moral theory until we have exhausted the
inquiry into "fitness"(although Dworkin is not entirely clear on this
point). The supreme lawyerly virtue of integrity is connected with
achievement of principled consistency among cases.</p>
        <p>These are illuminating suggestions. They do indeed help explain
what people disagreeing in law are disagreeing about. They also show
how the lawyer's task is different from that of the philosopher. Often
a statement describing the law is not a statement about some "plain
fact"; often there is a large evaluative dimension to positions about
what the law is. 144 Moreover, Dworkin's reliance on "fit" closely
connects with the analogical reasoner's own effort. Both Hercules and
the analogical judge are especially concerned to develop principles
that organize cases. Both of them are focused on coherence as a
criterion of truth in law.145</p>
        <p>But it is notable that Dworkin says little about the role of
analogical reasoning, which lies at the heart of how lawyers actually think. 146
His account does not give a proper place to this form of reasoning.
In his hands, theories are produced largely on the basis of abstract
141 DWORKIN, LAW'S EMPIRE, supra note I, at 225.
142 Id. at 239.
143 See id. at 240-50, 337-4I, 379-9I. I am compressing some complex issues here.
144 This issue is discussed in chapter five of CASS R. SUNSTEIN, THE PARTIALCONSTITUTION
(forthcoming I993).</p>
        <p>145 See SUSAN HURLEY, NATURAL REASONS II-I5, 36-39, I89-93, 3I8-22 (i989).
146 Joseph Raz takes Dworkin to have offered an argument for analogical reasoning and
suggests that "ProfessorDworkin has thus opted for the most conservative interpretation of the
judicial role: Judges are neither legally nor morally entitled to assume a reforming role. They
must rely only on analogical arguments which perpetuate and extend the existing legal ideology."
RAZ,supra note 3, at 205-06 n. I9. Raz suggests that Dworkin has provided in his early writings
"the most extreme case of total faith in analogical arguments." Id.</p>
        <p>The conflation of Dworkin's approach with analogical thinking is understandable in light of
the fact that, like analogizers, Dworkin places a large stress on "fit"and coherence, and little
weight on external challenges to current holdings. For reasons discussed in the text, however,
I do not wholly believe that Raz accurately describes Dworkin's view as expressed in either
DWORKIN, TAKING RIGHTS SERIOUSLY, cited above in note i, at Io6-I5; or DWORKIN, LAW'S
EMPIRE, cited above in note i, at 240-50.
moral theory. These theories are then brought to bear on particular
problems.147But this is not how lawyers proceed. In deciding whether
a restriction on cross-burning offends the First Amendment, lawyers
do not really ask which interpretation will make the Amendment the
best it can be. They do not begin with a high-level conception of the
value promoted by the Amendment. To develop such a conception,
they would have to ask questions that are too broad and abstract
too hard, large, and open-ended for legal actors to handle. Such
questions call for responses that are too deeply theorized.</p>
        <p>In thinking about free speech issues, lawyers instead ask what
particular sorts of practices seem clearly to violate the First
Amendment, or the principle of free expression, and then whether a
restriction on (for example) cross-burning is relevantly similar or relevantly
different. Of course the description of relevant similarities and
differences will have evaluative dimensions, and these should be made
explicit. But lawyers and judges will not engage in general moral
theorizing.'48 The resulting approach is the distinctive legal method.
As we have seen, that method has some important defects in
comparison with the search for reflective equilibrium, which Dworkin's
approach seems to resemble. But it has some advantages as well.</p>
        <p>From the standpoint of Dworkin's Hercules, we might respond in
the following way. A judge who operates from the "bottom up," rather
than from the "top down," might end up being Herculean too. At
least he had better have that aspiration in mind. When our modest
147 For examples of this approach, see the discussions of affirmative action in DWORKIN,
LAW'SEMPIRE, cited above in note i, at 393-97, and of free speech in Dworkin, The Coming
Battles Over Free Speech, cited above in note 22, at 55.</p>
        <p>At first glance it might seem as if statutory construction, at least, cannot involve analogical
reasoning. But this appearance is misleading. In hard statutory cases, the issue is sometimes
resolved by something like this: We know that the statute applies to case X. We do not know
if it applies to case Y. To resolve that issue, we have to decide whether case Y is relevantly
like, or relevantly unlike, case X. We have to think analogically.</p>
        <p>Something of this kind, I believe, underlies the dispute in United Steelworkers of America
v. Weber, 443 U.S. I93 (I979) in which the Court decided that private affirmative action is not
barred under the Civil Rights Act of I964. See id. at I97. Realistically speaking, the
disagreement among the Justices was not about anything Congress said or meant - the relevant
materials were indeterminate - but about whether affirmative action was relevantly different
from ordinary discrimination. Though I cannot prove the point here, I believe that the
dissenters' self-confidence about their view that the majority had distorted the law depended on
their own judgment that affirmative action was not relevantly different. See, e.g., id. at
22630 (Rehnquist, J., dissenting). That judgment may be correct, but it requires an argument, not
a mechanical reading of the statutory language. Analogical reasoning was therefore at least
implicitly at work.</p>
        <p>148 It is true, however, that some such theorizing may be implicit, in the sense that
particularistic case analysis may in some sense depend on it. But note that we can achieve an
overlapping consensus on particular outcomes among people who would disagree about general
theories, and also that general theories might be too hard to develop in advance, or to adapt
to the complexities of particular areas.
judge - Harlan, say, rather than Hercules - uses analogical
reasoning to say that case A is like case B, he must rely on a principle.
And if he is reasoning well, he will have before him a range of other
cases, C through Z, in which the principle is tested against other
principles and thereby refined. At least if he is a distinguished judge,
he will experience a kind of "conceptual ascent," in which the more
or less isolated and small low-level principle is finally made part of a
general theory, or of reflective equilibrium. In this way, we might
conclude that analogical reasoning is indeed part of Dworkin's
account, but only as an early step toward something both wider and
deeper.</p>
        <p>We have seen that there is a good deal of truth in this response.149
But the same points that were made earlier need to be reiterated.
Sometimes we can achieve an overlapping consensus on an analogy.
This is a real advantage over Hercules's approach, under which, if
we do well, we will arrive at a single general theory that could strike
others as sectarian. At least Harlan has this virtue - a partial and
ambiguous one - over Hercules. Sometimes participants in law do
not have the time or capacities to think everything fully through, and
hence analogical reasoning is the best that we can expect in the real
world of law. Sometimes it may be best to have analogical reasoning,
precisely because of the greater flexibility that it permits over time,
and because of its distinctive contribution to moral evolution in
society. Once in reflective equilibrium, Hercules's legal universe is frozen.
Finally, it may even be possible that considered judgments about
particulars count as truth in law, though I have suggested reasons to
be cautious about this claim. 150</p>
        <p>One additional note. Dworkin's conception of law as integrity
contains a theory of what it means for law to be legitimate. Hercules
149 See supra pp. 773-79.</p>
        <p>150 See supra p. 779. Arrow's Impossibility Theorem, see KENNETH ARROW, SOCIALCHOICE
AND INDIVIDUAL VALUES (2d ed. I963), raises important problems for coherence theories in
law, notably including Dworkin's account. I cannot discuss those problems here, but on a
multimember judicial body, there may be serious cycling problems, in which, paradoxically,
result A is favored over result B, which is favored over result C, which is (and here is the
paradox) favored over result A; or decisions may turn, arbitrarily, on the order in which issues
happen to arise ("path dependence"). See Frank H. Easterbrook, Ways of Criticizing the Court,
95 HARV. L. REv. 802, 8II-3I (I982). A strong theory of stare decisis, combined with a
commitment to analogical thinking, may alleviate some of the cycling problems and thus produce
greater stability in law, but it will simultaneously aggravate the problems of path dependence.
See id. at 8I7-23. The point suggests that it will be difficult to achieve real coherence through
decentralized, multimember courts, and that the Hercules metaphor will run into real difficulty.
A system built on analogical reasoning aspires to less and can diminish cycling; but the problem
of path dependence will result in a high degree of arbitrariness. See generally HURLEY, supra
note I45, at 225-53 (arguing that coherence theories can survive the Impossibility Theorem);
Lewis A. Kornhauser &amp; Lawrence G. Sager, Unpacking the Court, 96 YALEL.J. 82, I07-I7
(I986) (arguing that courts will not face severe problems under the Impossibility Theorem).
can produce vertical and horizontal consistency among judgments of
principle in law. Harlan can offer nothing so bold. A legal system
pervaded by analogy will not yield anything like full coherence.
Perhaps this is a decisive defect.</p>
        <p>A complete response would require more detail than I can offer
here, but a few remarks are in order. Full integrity, I suggest, consists
of much more than a legal system of numerous,
hierarchically-arranged courts can be expected to offer. Because of the need for
predictability and stability in law, judges must reason from cases with
which they disagree, and the resulting judgments are unlikely fully to
cohere. If this is so, a legal system may well be able to claim the
requisite legitimacy if it is democratic (broadly speaking) and if
individual judges seek to produce the limited but important sorts of
principled consistency that analogical thinking can yield. If this is
correct, a system in which judges reason by analogy, and do not seek
reflective equilibrium, might itself be justified as part of the reflective
equilibrium reached by informed observers who take institutional
issues into account.</p>
        <p>3. General Theories and Economic Analysis of Law. - We might
look, finally, at efforts to replace legal reasoning with general theories,
symbolized most dramatically by the effort to ask what sorts of legal
rules will promote economic efficiency.151 The advantage of economic
analysis of law is that it appears to distrust ordinary intuitions
altogether, showing that they are too crude to be a basis for law. Intuitions
about the effects of legal rules may be completely wrong. In a sharp
restatement of Bentham's attack on the common law, economic
analysts sometimes claim that traditional legal reasoning is not reasoning
at all, but instead is an encrusted system of unorganized and perhaps
barely processed intuitions. 152</p>
        <p>There can be no question that economic analysis of law has led to
major advances. Above all, perhaps, it has done so by helping to
untangle the social consequences of legal rules, many of which are
counterintuitive, and all of which are relevant to the proper evaluation
of law. There can be no question that instrumental rationality is highly
pertinent to those designing legal rules. Economic analysis is, for this
reason, exceptionally valuable for lawyers. Here it has a major
advantage over analogical reasoning, which is far less helpful on the
matter of consequences. One cannot discover consequences by
examining other judicial holdings.</p>
        <p>In its normative form, however, economic analysis depends on too
thin a repertoire for inquiry - that is, the notion that legal rules
151See, e.g., POSNER, supra note 33, ? I.2, at I2-I5.</p>
        <p>152 Compare3 BENTHAM, supra note 35, at 227-29 (discussing the irrationality of the common
law approach) with RICHARDA. POSNER, THE ECONOMICSOFJUSTICE 323-3 I (I98I) (discussing
privacy doctrine in this way).
should be designed so as to maximize wealth. This intuition can be
shown to be too crude and general to be right, and by making
reference to particular cases that appear to disprove it.153</p>
        <p>A special advantage of analogical reasoning over economic analysis
is that the former, unlike the latter, need not insist that plural and
diverse social goods should be assessed according to the same metric.
To make diverse goods commensurable in this way may do violence
to our considered judgments about how each good should be
characterized.154 Those considered judgments are far from embarrassing;
they are part of what it means to think well. Consider, for example,
the view that we should see all of the following as
"costs":unemployment, the loss of a species, higher prices for pencils, the adaptation
of workplaces to accommodate people on wheelchairs, sexual assault,
and chilling effects on speech. If we understand all these things as
"costs," to be assessed via the same metric, we will disable ourselves
from making important qualitative distinctions. It might be objected
that a more differentiated approach, one that insists on the plurality
and diversity of goods, is fatally unscientific. To this objection we
should respond that this conception of science is ill-suited to good
thinking about a certain range of legal problems. What is required is
not science, but practical reason.'55</p>
        <p>The hard question, not yet fully elaborated in the philosophical
literature, remains: How does one make choices in cases in which
incommensurable social goods are at stake, and in which some of
these goods must be sacrificed? An exploration of how analogical
reasoning actually works may well be helpful in this important
en153 Many illustrations of its weaknesses are contained in RICHARD A. POSNER, THE
PROBLEMS OF JURISPRUDENCE 353-92 (I990).</p>
        <p>154 See MICHAEL STOCKER, PLURAL AND CONFLICTING GOODS ch. 6 (I989); Elizabeth
Anderson, Values, Risks, and Market Norms, I7 PHIL. &amp; PUB. AFF. 54, 57-59 (I988); MARTHA
C. NUSSBAUM, Plato on Commensurability and Desire, in LOVE'SKNOWLEDGE, supra note 37,
at io6, IO6-24 (I990); Richard H. Pildes &amp; Elizabeth S. Anderson, Slinging Arrows at
Democracy, 90 COLUM. L. REv. 2I2I, 2I43-86 (I990); Charles Taylor, The Diversity of Goods, in
PHILOSOPHY AND THE HUMAN SCIENCES 230, 243(I985);Amaryta Sen, PluralUtility,8i PROC.
OF THE ARISTOTELIAN SOC'Y I93 (I981); cf. Margaret J. Radin, Market-Inalienability, ioo
HARV. L. REv. I849, I870-87 (I987) (critiquing universal commodification). A forthcoming
discussion is ANDERSON, cited above in note 39, at chs. I-4.</p>
        <p>155 This is of course an Aristotelian point. See ARISTOTLE, NICOMACHEAN ETHICS I49-53
(David Ross trans., I980) (I925); see also JONSEN &amp; TOULMIN, supra note 3, at 23-46; MARTHA
C. NUSSBAUM, THE FRAGILITY OF GOODNESS 290-3 I7 (I986). Consider also Holmes's
comment:</p>
        <p>After a sociological riot I read Aristotle's Ethics with some pleasure. The eternal,
universal, wise, good man. He is much in advance of ordinary Christian morality with its
slapdash universals (Never tell a lie. Sell all thou hast and give to the poor etc.) He has
the ideals of altruism, and yet understands that life is painting a picture not doing a
sum, that specific cases can't be decided by general rules, and that everything is a
question of degree . ...</p>
        <p>THE ESSENTIAL HOLMES 58 (Richard A. Posner ed., I992).
deavor. The analogical thinker is alert to the manifold dimensions of
social situations and to multiple relevant similarities and differences.
Unequipped with (or unburdened by) a unitary theory of the good or
the right, she is in a position to see clearly and for themselves the
diverse and plural goods that are at stake and to make choices among
them. 156 The very search for relevant similarities and differences
places a premium on this process of perceiving particulars.</p>
        <p>In any case, there is a large difference between using economics
to ascertain the social consequences of legal rules'57 and using
economics as a complete moral or political system. Racial discrimination
seems wealth-maximizing in some places; does this mean that we must
eliminate laws forbidding it? The comparative advantage of
analogical reasoning is that it provides a deep and broad resource for legal
thought.</p>
        <p>Economic analysis of law is an especially controversial top-down
approach; but the limitations of the economic approach may be
limitations of other such approaches as well. I cannot establish the point
here. But consider the distinguished efforts to approach the free speech
principle through the lens of a general theory of autonomy'58 or
democracy.'59 The autonomy principle has considerable appeal, but
it seems to run afoul of many considered judgments about particular
cases, and its most prominent defender has repudiated it as a complete
account. 160 A democratic approach to free speech runs into similar
difficulties.161 By itself, all this may prove little. But it suggests the
possibility that any top-down approach to certain areas of law will be
inadequate because ill-suited to the complexity and plurality of the
relevant values at stake. And if the theory is adjusted to take account
of this complexity and this plurality, it will cease to be a top-down
theory at all, at least as I have understood it here.</p>
        <p>156 See ANDERSON, supra note 39, at ch. 4. I think that something of this kind is at least
part of the import of Wittgenstein's remarks on categorization: "What is common to them all?
- Don't say: 'There must be something common, or they would not be called 'games"' - but
look and see whether there is anything common to all. - For if you look at them you will not
see something that is common to all, but similarities, relationships, and a whole series of them
at that. To repeat: don't think, but look!" WITTGENSTEIN, supra note I03, ? 66, at 3I.</p>
        <p>157Of course "social consequences" are not simply brute facts. Any effort to set them out
will be interpretive and to that extent evaluative.</p>
        <p>158 See Thomas Scanlon, A Theory of Freedom of Expression, I PHIL. &amp; PUB. AFF. 204,
215-22 (I972); David A. Strauss, Persuasion, Autonomy, and Freedom of Expression, 9I COLUM.
L. REV. 334, 336-37, 353-55 (I99I).</p>
        <p>159 See ALEXANDER MEIKLEJOHN, FREE SPEECH AND ITS RELATION TO SELF-GOVERNMENT
3-27 (I948); Robert H. Bork, Neutral Principles and Some First Amendment Problems, 47 IND.
L.J. I, 26-34 (I97I). I try to defend this view in Cass Sunstein, Free Speech Now (unpublished
manuscript) (developing some of the ideas in Cass R. Sunstein, Free Speech Now, 59 U. CHI.
L. REV. 255 (I992)).</p>
        <p>160 See Scanlon, supra note I20, at 528-37.</p>
        <p>161 See Martin H. Redish, The Value of Free Speech, I30 U. PA. L. REV. 59I, 596-6II
(I982).</p>
        <p>If the argument I have made is plausible, there may be much
more to be said in favor of the common law method than is now
popular. That method will have within it resources unlikely to be
available to anyone laying down rules in advance. It follows that a
large task for a legal system based on a general enthusiasm for rules
is to introduce the virtues of analogical reasoning. Debates in
contemporary administrative law are often about precisely this point.162
Many people have tried to obtain, in a rule-pervaded, statutory era,
some of the advantages of analogical thinking and of particular
examination of particular contexts.'63</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>IV. CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>Analogical reasoning is the conventional method of the lawyer; it
plays a large role in everyday thinking as well. Its distinctive
properties are a requirement of principled consistency, a focus on concrete
particulars, incompletely theorized judgments, and the creation and
testing of principles having a low or intermediate level of generality.
Because of its comparative lack of ambition, this form of reasoning
has some important disadvantages. Compared with the search for
reflective equilibrium, it is insufficiently theoretical; it does not account
for its own low-level principles in sufficient depth or detail. Compared
with economics and empirical social science, it is at best primitive on
the important issue of likely social consequences. Law should be more
attuned to facts, and on this score analogical thinking may be an
obstacle to progress.</p>
      <p>But in a world with limited time and capacities, and with sharp
disagreements on first principles, analogical reasoning has some
beneficial features as well. Most important, this form of reasoning does
162 Consicer the view that administrative agencies should be permitted large room for
discretion in statutory interpretation. See Chevron U.S.A. Inc. v. Natural Resources Defense
Council, Inc., 467 U.S. 837, 842-45 (I984). This view seems to contradict no less an authority
than Marbury v. Madison, 5 U.S. (i Cranch) I37, I77-80 (I803), and it has for that reason
been highly controversial. But the principle might be defended as a means of allowing
caseby-case adjustment of literal language in particular circumstances, some of them new and
unforeseen. The interpretive power of regulatory agencies will permit them to accommodate
apparent rules to the complexities of individual cases - and to do so, in significant part, through
analogical, case-by-case reasoning.</p>
      <p>163 See GuIDO CALABRESI, A COMMON LAW FOR THE AGE OF STATUTES 2-3 (I982) (calling
for courts to have the power to declare "obsolete"certain statutes). The rules-standards issue is
explored from different angles in Colin S. Diver, The Optimal Precision of Administrative Rules,
93 YALEL.J. 65, 66-8o (I983); Duncan Kennedy, Form and Substance in Private Law
Adjudication, 89 HARV. L. REv. I685, I687-I7I3 (I976); Louis Kaplow, RULES AND STANDARDS:
AN EcONOMIc APPROACH, 42 DUKE L.J. (forthcoming I993); and Kathleen Sullivan, The
Supreme Court, i991 Term - Foreword: The Justices of Rules and Standards, io6 HARV. L.
REV. 22, 95-I22 (I992).
not require people to develop full theories to account for their
convictions; it promotes moral evolution over time; it fits uniquely well with
a system based on principles of stare decisis; and it allows people who
diverge on abstract principles to converge on particular outcomes. In
any case it is unsurprising that analogical reasoning continues to have
enormous importance in legal and political discussion.</p>
      <p>A notable aspect of analogical thinking is that people engaged in
this type of reasoning are peculiarly alert to the inconsistent or
abhorrent result, and they take strong convictions about particular cases to
provide reasons for reevaluating their views about other cases or even
about apparently guiding general principles.'64 The emphasis on
particular cases and particular convictions need not be regarded as an
embarrassment, or as a violation of the lawyer's commitment to
principle.'65 On the contrary, it should be seen as a central part of the
exercise of practical reason in law (and elsewhere).</p>
      <p>In this light, it seems most unfortunate that analogical reasoning
has fallen into ill repute. To abandon this method of reasoning may
be to give up, far too quickly, on some of the most useful methods
we have for evaluating our practices, and for deciding whether to
change them through law.</p>
      <p>164 It may be tempting to conclude here that analogies can at most be persuasive, and never
demonstrative. If what I have said here is right, this response depends on a too-narrow
conception of what constitutes proof in law, and a too-sharp distinction between correctness and
persuasiveness.</p>
      <p>165 Consider in this regard William Blake's comment on the work of Sir Joshua Reynolds:
"To Generalize is to be an Idiot. I thank God I am not like Reynolds." WILLIAM BLAKE,
Blake's Marginalia, in BLAKE'S POETRY AND DESIGNS 429, 440 (Mary L. Johnson &amp; John E.
Grant eds., I979). Note, however, that the second sentence undermines the first, by relying
(implicitly) on a conception of relevant differences and similarities - and thus by generalizing.
The first sentence, itself a generalization, is undermined even more severely by Blake's
generalization in the same passage: "To Particularize is Alone the Distinction of True Merit." Id.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>104 I do not suggest that there is always such a consensus within law. Sometimes there are competing principles and competing analogies. But sometimes the analogies really do provide the requisite commonality; this is all I mean to claim</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>105 See generally John Rawls, The Idea of an Overlapping Consensus, 7 OXFORD J. LEGAL STUD. I</source>
          ,
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          )
          <article-title>(advocating a political conception of justice to gain the support of an overlapping consensus</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          106 BARRY, cited above in note 24, at 275-80 (
          <issue>I989</issue>
          ),
          <article-title>criticizes on similar grounds Ronald Dworkin's analogy between moral and legal reasoning in his article The Original Position</article-title>
          , cited above in note 22, at 28-29.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          107 See, e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mari</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Matsuda</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Public Response to Racist Speech: Considering the Victim's Story, 87 MICH</article-title>
          . L. REV.
          <volume>2320</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>2323</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          (
          <issue>I989</issue>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>108</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A large topic, which I cannot discuss here, involves the relationship between cognition and emotions in law. This is a very large gap in our understanding: how analogical reasoning, and other forms of thought, involve different cognitive and affective capacities. This relationship is highly relevant to the problem of analogy, which engages narratives, which prominently affect emotions. Some of these issues are discussed in RONALD DE SOUSA, THE RATIONALITY OF EMOTION21-46 (I990); GERALD GAUS, VALUE</article-title>
          AND JUSTIFICATION 26-
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ); Jon Elster,
          <source>Sadder but Wiser? Rationality and the Emotions, 3 Soc. SCI. INFO</source>
          .
          <volume>375</volume>
          (
          <issue>I985</issue>
          )
          <article-title>; and Martha Nussbaum, Emotions as Judgments of Value, 5 YALE J</article-title>
          . CRIT.
          <volume>201</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>210</lpage>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>109This was the federalist view, see supra note ioo</article-title>
          .
          <source>See also Frank I. Michelman</source>
          , The
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

