<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>See Ronald Coase, The Problem of Social Cost</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <email>unbound@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law", Coase-Sandor Institute for Law &amp; Economics Working Paper No.</institution>
          <addr-line>14, 1993</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1960</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1960</issue>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>JOHN M. OLIN LAW &amp; ECONOMICS WORKING PAPER NO. 14</p>
      <p>(2D SERIES)
ENDOGENOUS PREFERENCES, ENVIRONMENTAL LAW</p>
      <p>How can we explain the rise of environmental law? By what criteria should
we evaluate regulation of pollution? Why do some cities require recycling?
Should we tax waste disposal instead? Should we subsidize mass transit in order
to reduce automobile pollution, or should we regulate cars? Why do we do one
rather than another?</p>
      <p>In the last generation, considerable progress has been made on all of these
questions. Most of the progress results from the application of varieties or
offshoots of welfare economics—expected utility theory, social and public choice
theory, and game theory—to environmental problems. If we assume, for
example, that participants in the political process are trying to maximize their
utility, we can help explain many oddities of American environmental law. We
can see why some statutes seem to benefit regional interests.1 We can understand
why old pollution sources are regulated more severely than new ones.2 We can
see why Congress enacts measures that are expensive and only moderately
helpful to the environment, but that promise to deliver large benefits to
wellorganized groups.3 Perhaps most important, we can understand the
omnipresence of largely symbolic environmental legislation—measures that
appear on their face to promise vigorous and even draconian regulation, but that
in the enforcement process amount to little more than mere words. The pervasive
paradox of rigid but underenforced environmental legislation may well match
the electoral self-interest of legislators.4</p>
      <p>*Karl N. Llewellyn Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago, Law School and Department of
Political Science. I am grateful for very helpful comments from Douglas Baird, Gary Becker, William
Landes, Martha Nussbaum, Randall Picker, and Richard Posner, and from participants in a workshop at the
California Institute of Technology. Gabriel Gore provided excellent research assistance. For financial
support I am grateful to The Russell Baker Scholars Fund and The James H. Douglas, Jr. Fund for the Study
of Law and Government.</p>
      <p>2This approach is pervasive in environmental law. See, e.g., 42 U.S.C. 7475; 42 U.S.C. 7411; 33 U.S.C.
301.</p>
      <p>With similar tools, we can also think about how best to protect the
environment.5 Many people do want a cleaner environment—to protect life,
health, recreational opportunities, endangered species, and so forth. Many
people want other things as well, including lower prices, less poverty, and
greater employment. In light of the plurality of goods at stake, it is familiarly
suggested that we might try to achieve the optimal level of environmental
protection, understanding the notion of optimality by reference to people’s real
desires. This approach might claim a salutary neutrality among diverse goods
and among different conceptions of the good. It takes people and preferences
simply as they are.</p>
      <p>Approaches of this general sort have provided illuminating work on the
genesis of state and federal environmental law. No predictive tool has similar
power, and if we want to understand the structure of environmental regulation,
much progress remains to be made through use of the same analytic strategies.
On the normative side, things are more complex. But at least it seems fair to say
that we now lack an alternative framework for normative thinking in the
environmental area that can claim to combine the virtues of real-world
administrability and substantive plausibility. The extraordinary influence of
welfare economics in the regulatory sector of the federal government6 is
undoubtedly at least in part attributable to this fact.</p>
      <p>At the same time, the last decade has witnessed a number of intriguing
qualifications, refinements, or criticisms of rational actor models, coming mostly
from economists, but also from philosophers, political scientists, and
psychologists.7 Some of the work involves “anomalies” of various sorts. The
institutional implications of these qualifications and refinements are only
beginning to receive sustained elaboration.8 My principal goal in this essay is to
identify some of those implications in the distinctive context of environmental
regulation. Some of the apparently normative challenges to rational actor models
turn out to have important positive implications. The challenges point to facts
about human behavior and motivation that help explain some of American
environmental law, and indeed do so in a way that might add much to the
descriptive and predictive work of existing approaches. My particular interest is
in the endogeneity of preferences and the social “demand” for regulation, which
turns out to have peculiar dimensions.</p>
      <p>Throughout the paper, I will attempt to show how qualifications of rational
actor models generate testable hypotheses, and to explore whether such
qualifications offer plausible ways to understand the odd shape of current
environmental policies.9 In many cases, however, our current tools do not enable
us to sort out the role of plausible but competing explanations for regulatory
phenomena. An important task for the future, both conceptual and empirical, is
to develop better strategies for assessing causal explanations that although
strikingly different, would produce similar outcomes. Moreover, some
challenges to preference satisfaction as a normative ideal have unusual
characteristics in the environmental area. It is worth elaborating on those
characteristics.</p>
      <p>The paper is organized into four sections. The first suggests that there is
sometimes no such thing as a fully acontextual “preference” and that preferences
are endogenous to existing legal policy, including the setting of the legal
Economic Way of Looking at Life, University of Chicago, Law &amp; Economics Working Paper No. 12, pp.
1519 (1993). A helpful collection is Rationality in Action (Paul Moser ed. 1990), especially Part IB.</p>
      <p>8A leading essay is Roger Noll &amp; James Krier, Some Implications of Cognitive Psychology for Risk
Regulation, 19 J. Legal Stud. 747 (1990). See generally Herbert Hovenkamp, Legal Policy and the
Endowment Effect, 20 J. Legal Stud 225 (1991); Elizabeth Hoffman &amp; Matthew Spitzer, The Divergence
Between Willingness-to-Pay and Willingness-to-Accept Measures of Value, Wash. U. L. Q. (forthcoming);
Elizabeth Anderson, Some Problems in the Normative Theory of Rational Choice, With Consequences for
Empirical Research (Univ. of Mich., Dept. of Philosophy, unpublished manuscript). See also Gary Becker,
The Economic Way of Looking at Life, University of Chicago, Law &amp; Economics Working Paper No. 12, at
19 (1993): “An important step in extending the traditional analysis of individual rational choice is to
incorporate into the theory a much richer class of attitudes, preferences, and calculations.”
9I have discussed some of these issues elsewhere, but with a view to normative rather than positive
issues. See Cass R. Sunstein, Preferences and Politics, 20 Phil. &amp; Pub. AV. 3 (1991); Cass R. Sunstein, The
Partial Constitution ch. 6 (1993). In this essay, I stress positive issues, and in a number of places extend or
qualify some of my earlier normative claims. Except for a brief section of Part II, I do not discuss the
important distorting effect of various “heuristics” used to assess risk. See Noll &amp; Krier, supra note 8; W. Kip
Viscusi, Fatal Tradeoffs ch. 7 (1992). The use of these heuristics also has important positive and normative
implications.
entitlement. This point helps both to explain legislative outcomes and to unsettle
some common views about environmental protection on the predictive and
normative sides.10</p>
      <p>The second section claims that private preferences for environmental goods
may be adaptive to existing environmental options, and that this can sometimes
help explain the social demand for regulation and also “impeach” the
preferences that serve as inputs into environmental decisions. The second section
also briefly describes the role of the availability heuristic, intrapersonal collective
action problems, and the phenomenon of social cascades.</p>
      <p>The third section argues that there may be a disparity between private
consumption choices and collective judgments, as these are expressed in politics.
Partly because of some unusual free-rider problems, preferences may be
endogenous to the setting in which they are expressed, and in a way that casts
additional doubt on the assumption that preferences can be taken as acontextual.</p>
      <p>The fourth and most speculative section argues that people may not always
think that there is commensurability between environmental quality and the
things against which this good must be “traded off.” The social resistance to
commensurability helps explain some apparent oddities in the demand for
legislation and in public thinking about environmental problems. I also suggest
that despite its apparent oddity, the resistance to commensurability is plausible
as a normative matter. The assumption that environmental and other goods can
be assessed along the same metric does violence to some of our considered
judgments about how (not how much) to value pristine areas, species, and other
environmental amenities.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>1. The Endowment Effect, Status Quo Bias, and Others</title>
      <p>a. Prefatory note and overview.</p>
      <p>
        At the outset it will be useful to offer a catalogue of how law might deal, or
fail to deal, with environmental issues. (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
        ) It may fail to resolve collective action
problems, conventionally defined. This is a usual understanding of the state of
affairs under the common law. (2) It may actually solve collective action
problems, conventionally defined. This is a part of the optimistic, “public
interest” account of environmental legislation. (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">3</xref>
        ) It may reflect the political
power of well-organized private groups, redistributing wealth in their favor
10I do not discuss the normative issues associated with the criterion of private willingness to pay,
which is often said to be crudely correlated with utility. Despite its crudeness, it might be used because of
(a) the difficulty of finding other proxies that are realistically usable by policy makers and (b) the
wellknown (though in my view overstated) difficulty of making intrapersonal comparisons of utility. On the
latter issue, see Interpersonal Comparisons of Well-Being (Jon Elster and John Roemer eds. 1991).
while failing to improve and perhaps even impairing social welfare. This view is
prominent in public choice theory. (4) It may be relatively chaotic and arbitrary,
reflecting the order in which issues arise rather than aggregating preferences in
an accurate way or embodying any coherent social judgment about the public
good. This possibility, discussed in political science and economic writing
following Arrow’s impossibility theorem,11 has been infrequently explored in the
regulatory and environmental setting. (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">5</xref>
        ) It may be a product of a process of
deliberation among citizens and representatives in which private preferences for
environmental amenities are transformed and shaped through exposure to new
information and new perspectives.
      </p>
      <p>
        In practice, it may not be easy to distinguish among some of these different
possibilities. For example, (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">3</xref>
        ) and (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">5</xref>
        ) are especially hard to separate; we cannot
easily test whether some measure claimed to be (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">5</xref>
        ) is in fact (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">3</xref>
        ). But it is useful to
keep these possibilities in mind while thinking about both the positive and
normative issues.
      </p>
      <p>In this section, I argue that sometimes there are no acontextual preferences
with which to do normative or positive work. Preferences can be a function of the
initial allocation of the legal entitlement. valuation of environmental goods is
sometimes an artifact of law. When this is so, policy makers cannot simply
identify preferences and try to satisfy them, since the preferences are influenced
by law, and since there is no way to identify the preferences that would exist in
the absence of law.</p>
      <p>b. A conceptual problem.</p>
      <p>The initial problem is that it may be impossible to describe something as a
“preference” without undertaking some controversial normative tasks. Suppose
someone decides not to recycle all newspapers, or to vote against a law requiring
recycling. This preference might be understood as simply a choice, as in the idea
of the “revealed preference.” It is of course illuminating to catalogue and explain
choices. But if this is what we are doing, it is unnecessary and perhaps
misleading to use the notion of a “preference,” which seems to be intended to
explain or to back something called choices. If preferences are reducible to
choices, we can dispense with the idea entirely. But if we do this, much of the
explanatory value of expected utility and rational choice theory will be lost,12
since it will be necessary to give up on the notion of an underlying causal
relationship between choices and internal mental states. An important goal of
rational choice theory has been to help show how choices connect with
preferences, defined independently of choices. It would be unfortunate to have to
dispense with this goal.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, the notion of a “preference” is often meant to refer to not
to choices themselves, but to something that lies behind and accounts for
choices.13 But this idea introduces difficulties of its own, difficulties that the
“revealed preference” idea was intended to overcome. What is this thing called a
“preference"? Is it a steady mental state? A physical entity? How can it be
identified or even described? In light of the extraordinary complexity of internal
mental states—including whims, second-order preferences, aspirations,
judgments, drives of various kinds, and so forth—it is not simple to identity a
“preference” as something that stands behind choices and explains them. In the
environmental area, the problem is serious. For example, a decision not to recycle
is a choice, but the relationship between that choice and an independent entity
called a “preference” is often obscure. I will not belabor these complex matters
here,14 and will instead proceed as if it were possible to overcome the relevant
difficulties.</p>
      <p>c. The Coase theorem and the endowment effect.</p>
      <p>With respect to environmental issues, it is natural to begin with the Coase
theorem.15 Notably, the theorem was originally developed in the context of an
environmental problem arising in the law of tort. Coase’s conclusion was of
course that in the absence of transaction costs, the initial assignment of a legal
entitlement will be irrelevant to (a) the ultimate use of property or (b) the level of
the relevant activities. The theorem suggests, for example, that where transaction
costs are zero, it does not matter whether an entitlement is given to breathers or
to polluters, to railroads or to farmers. The two will in any case bargain to a
result which is both efficient and (more striking) the same.</p>
      <p>It should be plain that the Coase theorem (like most illuminating work in
economics) takes preferences as both static and given. This is a key feature of the
claim that the ultimate use of property, and ultimate activity levels, are
unaffected by the allocation of the entitlement.</p>
      <p>13See George Stigler &amp; Gary Becker, De Gustibus Non Est Disputandum, 67 Am. Econ. Rev. 76 (1977).
14Some of these issues are discussed in Amartya Sen, supra, note 12; Elizabeth Anderson, Some
Problems in the Normative Theory of Rational Choice (University of Michigan, Department of Philosophy,
unpublished manuscript 1991); Jean Hampton, The Failure of Expected Utility Theory as a Theory of Reason
(University of Arizona, Department of Philosophy, unpublished manuscript 1992).</p>
      <p>But insofar as the theorem says that the result will be the same independently
of the legal rule, it rests on an intriguingly false assumption, one that suggest that
it may sometimes be impossible for government to take preferences “as they
are.” The problem is that whether people have a preference for a good, a right, or
anything else is often in part a function of whether the government, or the law,
has allocated it to them in the first instance. There is simply no way to avoid the
task of initially allocating a legal entitlement,16 at least short of anarchy (the only
system without initial allocations). What people “have” is partly a product of
what the law protects. And with respect to environmental amenities, what
people have is, simply as a matter of fact, a creation of legally-conferred rights.17</p>
      <p>The key point is that the decision to grant an entitlement to A rather than B
can affect the valuations of that entitlement by both A and B. More specifically,
the initial grant of the entitlement to A frequently makes A value that entitlement
more than he would if the right had been allocated to B. (It also makes B value it
less than he otherwise would.18) The initial allocation—the legal rule saying who
owns what, before people begin to contract with one another—serves to create,
to legitimate, and to reinforce social understandings about presumptive rights of
ownership. That allocation can help produce individual perceptions about the
entitlement in question.19 It should be clear that if this is so, the demand for
environmental regulation will be importantly affected by the initial allocation.</p>
      <p>16“When a loss is left where it falls in an auto accident, it is not because God so ordained it. Rather it is
because the state has granted the injurer an entitlement to be free of liability and will intervene to prevent
the victim’s friends, if they are stronger, from taking compensation from the injurer. . . . [A]n entitlement to
a good or to its converse is essentially inevitable. We either are entitled to have silence or entitled to make
noise in a given set of circumstances. We either have the right to our own property or body or the right to
share others’ property or bodies. We may buy or sell ourselves into the opposite position, but we must start
somewhere.” Guido Calabresi &amp; A. Douglas Melamed, Property Rules, Liability Rules, and Inalienability:
One View of the Cathedral, 85 Harv. L. Rev. 1089, 1091, 1100-1101 (1972).</p>
      <p>17I am not speaking here of wealth effects, to which Coase does refer. See Ronald Coase, The Firm, the
Market, and the Law 170-74 (1988). Wealth effects consist of the consequences for social demand of shifts in
wealth brought about by the allocation of the entitlement. In most real-world cases, it has been persuasively
argued that wealth effects are likely to be small. See R.D. Willig, Consumer’s Surplus Without Apology, 66
Am. Econ. Rev. 589 (1976), though the point is controversial, see note 36 infra. The empirical work on
endowment effects has shown consequences for willingness to pay that do not depend on material changes
in wealth. See citations in notes 20 &amp; 26 infra. There is thus an important difference between wealth effects
and endowment effects. They are not equivalent phenomena.</p>
      <p>18The popular notion that “the grass is always greener” suggests that preferences may be strongest for
things to which people do not have entitlements; but there is apparently no empirical support for this
intuitively plausible view.</p>
      <p>19I do not claim that private preferences are always an artifact of law. In some cases, people order their
affairs on the basis of social norms that operate independently of law, and the preferences that undergird
those norms are not legally constructed. See Robert Ellickson, Order Without Law (1991).</p>
      <p>The effect on preferences of the initial allocation of a commodity or an
entitlement is commonly described as the “endowment effect.”20 The endowment
effect suggests that any initial allocation of an entitlement—and government
cannot refuse to make an initial allocation—may well have effects on preferences.</p>
      <p>1. Survey evidence and experimental results. This point has received
considerable empirical confirmation, often in the context of environmental
amenities. Studies based on survey research have found endowment effects in
many settings. One such study found that people would demand about five
times as much to allow destruction of trees in a park as they would pay to
prevent the destruction of those same trees.21 When hunters were questioned
about the potential destruction of a duck habitat, they said that they would be
willing to pay an average of $247 to prevent the loss—but would demand no less
than $1044 to accept it.22 In another study, participants required payments to
accept degradation of visibility ranging from 5 to more than 16 times higher than
their valuations based on how much they were willing to pay to prevent the
same degradation23 According to yet another study, the compensation demanded
for accepting a new risk of immediate death of .001% was one or two orders of
magnitude higher than the amount of willingness to pay to eliminate an existing
risk of the same magnitude.</p>
      <p>A related survey showed similarly large status quo biases in willingness to
pay for changes in risks. Thus only 39% of respondents would accept $700 to
have their chance of a serious accident increased by 0.5% (from 0.5% to 1.0%); the
substantial majority of 61% would refuse the trade. By contrast, only 27% would
trade an identical decrease in accident risk (from 1% to 0.5%) for $700; here an
even larger majority of 73% would refuse to do. In another study, people were
willing to pay $3.78 on average to decrease the risk from an insecticide, but 77%
refused to buy the product at any price, however reduced, if the risk level would
increase by an equivalent amount.24 In short: A powerful status quo bias affects
reactions to environmental risks or losses.25</p>
      <p>There are of course notorious problems with survey evidence, which is hardly
a reliable guide to real-world behavior. But experimental studies reveal similar
effects. For example, a recent study showed that people who were given certain
objects—pens, coffee mugs, and binoculars—placed a much higher valuation on
those objects than did those who were required to purchase them. People initially
given such things required a relatively high price from would-be purchasers;
people not initially given such things would over a relatively low price to
wouldbe sellers.26 No such effects were observed for money tokens in otherwise
identical experiments.</p>
      <p>A similar study gave some participants a mug and others a chocolate bar, and
told members of both groups they could exchange one for the other. Participants
in a third group, not given either, were told that they could select one or the
other; 56% of these selected the candy bar. By contrast, 89% of those initially
given the mug refused to trade it for the candy bar, and only 10% of those
initially given the candy were willing to trade it for the mug.27 The different
evaluations apparently could not be explained by reference to anything other
than the initial endowment.</p>
      <p>Another experiment found a significant disparity between willingness to
accept (WTA) and willingness to pay (WTP) in the especially interesting context
of irreversible choices about preserving species and other environmental
amenities. In one experiment, the authors tried to ascertain the “existence value”
of a houseplant that grows like a pine tree. The subjects were told that any trees
not sold or kept would be killed at the end of the experiment. The mean
willingness to pay to avoid the “kill” option was $7.81. The mean willingness to
accept payment to allow a tree to be killed was $18.43.28</p>
      <p>27Knetch, supra note 26.</p>
      <p>In some studies, the disparity between WTA and WTP—the extent of the
endowment effect—appears to diminish with repeated participation in a market.
But it rarely disappears entirely, and many studies show that the disparity
persists.29 The range of the disparity appears to vary from slight disparities to a
ratio of more than four to one, with WTA usually doubling WTP. In field studies,
environmental goods tend to reflect a disparity of factors from two to over ten.30
In some environmental experiments involving trees, the WTA/WTP ratio is
extraordinarily high, ranging between 60/1 and 90/1.31</p>
      <p>2. Explanations. In many settings, then, it has been shown that people place a
higher value on rights or goods that they currently hold than they place on the
same goods when in the hands of others. The disparity is puzzling; but there are
many possible explanations.</p>
      <p>Some studies suggest that that assignment creates the basic “reference state”
from which judgments of fairness are subsequently made, and those judgments
affect preferences and private willingness to pay.32 On this account, people
perceive things as fair if they stay close to the status quo, and judgments of
fairness connect to preferences. An especially influential approach to the
endowment effect stresses “loss aversion,” which refers to the fact that a negative
change from the status quo is usually seen as more harmful than a positive
change is seen as beneficial. Here too there is a status quo bias.33</p>
      <p>Perhaps, too, people prefer what they have to what they might have because
of psychological attachments to existing allocations. Endowment effects may thus
reflect an effort to reduce cognitive dissonance. High valuation of what one
owns, and low valuation or what one does not, is a means of reducing
dissonance, and in some respects it is highly adaptive. It may well be
welfarepromoting.34 Perhaps the initial allocation has an important legitimating effect.35
29See the overview in Hoffman &amp; Spitzer, supra note 39.
30See Boyce et al., supra note 28, at 1366.</p>
      <p>35See Edward Zajac, supra, note 92.
It may suggest that the entitlement “naturally” belongs where it has been placed,
and therefore put a social burden on even voluntary changes. In some cases the
divergence between willingness to pay and willingness to accept is probably a
product of the change in social attitudes brought about by the change in the
allocation of the entitlement. With respect to sexual harassment, for example, the
mere shift in the entitlement appears to have had significant attitudinal effects.
The example may be generalizable.</p>
      <p>There are other possibilities. Endowment effects may come from experience;
people who use a product or have an entitlement may learn to appreciate its
value. They may be a product of strategic considerations. Someone may be
unwilling to give up a right because the concession would reveal weakness in
bargaining. Sometimes apparent endowment effects might be produced by the
wealth effect of the initial allocation of the entitlement. Different allocations
produce differences in wealth—someone with more entitlements is to that extent
richer—and perhaps some allocations have wealth effects sufficiently large to
affect the point to which people will bargain.36</p>
      <p>Alternately, such effects might derive from what we might call “anticipated
ex post regret.”37 People who trade one good for another may fear that in the
event of disappointment, they will be left not only with a good of uncertain
value, but also with a feeling of personal responsibility and thus intense regret
for having brought about that very fact. In the environmental context, the
explanation may be connected with the fact that substitutes do not exist for some
public goods.38 Recently it has been suggested that the disparity is connected
with intrinsic moral values involving the assignment of moral responsibility for
the destruction of environmental assets. The WTA measure assigns responsibility
to the individual. The WTP measure does so more ambiguously.39 Perhaps some
of the disparity can be attributed to the desire to avoid or to minimize the feeling</p>
      <p>39This is an apparently pervasive social judgment about responsibility, but it must of course be
defended; it is not self-evident.
that one has been morally culpable for producing the loss of an environmental
amenity.40</p>
      <p>Notably, some of these explanations do not depend on real preference change
at all. They account for endowment effects while holding preferences constant.
But these sorts of explanations do not appear sufficient.</p>
      <p>For present purposes, it is enough to say that the initial allocation often
shapes preferences, and that no legal system can operate without an initial
allocation. When this is so, there is no acontextual “preference” with which to do
legal or political work. A government deciding on environmental issues cannot
be neutral among preferences when—and this is the key point—it does not know
what preferences are until it has acted, and when there is no sense in which it can
refuse to act (again, short of anarchy).</p>
      <p>It is tempting to respond that government might indeed refuse to act—as, for
example, by failing to create liability at all. A railroad might be freely permitted
to emit air pollution, for example. Is this not a case of inaction? Might not a
system of this sort turn out to be neutral, in the sense that it simply allows people
to do what they want in light of their (pre-legal) preferences?</p>
      <p>The answer is that such a system would not be neutral, that it would not
involve inaction, and that it would not simply allow people to do what they
want. A decision to permit railroads to emit pollution is a grant, by law, of a legal
entitlement. It allocates the relevant right to the railroads. It is not helpful to
point to what would happen in anarchy, or in the state of nature. In anarchy or
nature, the state does not enforce entitlements at all. In anarchy or nature, the
state does not prohibit people from taking corrective action (of whatever sort)
when they perceive themselves to be injured. In any legal system, however, a
right to pollute is indeed backed by the force of law. It is accompanied by
stateenforced prohibitions on certain sorts of corrective action by victims, including
physical violence, or the attempted taking, by victims, of relevant property
interests. It is in this sense that the state, so long as it exists, inevitably allocates
entitlements.</p>
      <p>Now let us return to the Coase theorem. In light of the endowment effect, the
theorem appears at least sometimes to be inaccurate insofar as it predicts that the
allocation of the entitlement will not affect ultimate outcomes. (The theorem
remains true insofar as it shows that the result will be efficient regardless of the
initial allocation. There is no problem with the theorem to the extent that it says
that under ideal conditions, private and social costs are equal.) The difficulty for
40See Rebecca Boyce et al., An Experimental Examination of Intrinsic Values as a Source of the
WTAWTP Disparity, 82 Am. Econ. Rev. 1366 (1992).
this prediction is that it overlooks the effects of the initial allocation on
preferences. The endowment effect means that contrary to the Coase theorem,
the entitlement will tend to stay where it has been initially allocated. People to
whom the entitlement has been initially allocated will value it most, and
precisely because of the initial allocation. For example, a grant of the initial
entitlement to breathers will probably make them value clean air more than they
otherwise would.</p>
      <p>d. Status Quo Bias.</p>
      <p>The endowment effect can be understood as a special instance of a much
more general phenomenon: status quo bias. In many settings, people appear to
give more weight to the status quo than would be predicted by conventional
models of rational choice. The phenomenon appears to occur in many places.</p>
      <p>Samuelson and Zeckhauser have shown that the affinity for the status quo
appears to affect such diverse forms of behavior as brand allegiance, choice of
insurance plans, changing public policies, marketing techniques, and investment
decisions.41 This affinity may be fully rational. It may well reflect the high costs of
any transition. It may be that the goods people own become integrated into daily
life, so that a form of relocation cost is incurred whenever currently owned goods
are lost. Or status quo bias may reflect search costs. Whether or not rational, the
phenomenon of status quo bias probably has some of the same roots as the
narrower phenomenon of endowment effects. Loss aversion is plausibly at work
here; so too with the effort to reduce cognition dissonance, the desire to avoid
anticipated ex post regret, and the concern about one’s moral responsibility for
introducing changes in the status quo. In any case, there is evidence that people
are more strongly biased toward the status quo than would be predicted by
usual theory about decision-making under uncertainty.</p>
      <p>e. Positive implications.</p>
      <p>If all this is correct, large consequences follow. We can predict that much
governmental behavior in the environmental context will be a product of
endowment effects. Private and public reactions to risks should reflect a status
quo bias. Both supply and demand will be affected. Government regulation of
new risks will predictably be more stringent than government regulation of
(equivalent) old risks. This is so precisely because the public demand for
regulation will be a product of status quo bias.</p>
      <p>41William Samuelson and Richard Zeckhauser, Status Quo Bias in Decision Making, 1 Journal of Risk
and Uncertainty 7 (1988)</p>
      <p>This is in fact what we observe. It is a defining characteristic of the current
system of environmental controls.42 New risks are regulated far more stringently
than old ones, even though this strategy sometimes creates extremely perverse
results, by perpetuating the life of the especially severe old risks and thus
damaging public health and safety. New stationary sources of air pollution must
meet technological requirements not imposed on old sources; new cars are
regulated far more heavily than old ones.43</p>
      <p>The disparity is sometimes explained on the ground that old industries seek
to use regulation to stop new entry.44 This is a plausible explanation. But without
more evidence, we cannot be sure that it is true. The disparity may well result in
part from status quo bias. It would be useful to attempt to test the competing
hypotheses, perhaps by seeing whether more stringent controls on new sources
result when the producers of old sources are better organized.</p>
      <p>More generally, political participants should be able to exploit endowment
effects by attempting to describe the regulatory status quo in a way that takes
advantage of the phenomenon of loss aversion. Politicians are frequently
successful when they are able to identify and control the perception of the status
quo. One example is provided by constant political efforts to lower expectations
by describing the status quo as systemically worse than in fact it is, so that the
citizenry will rarely perceive deviations as losses but instead only as gains.</p>
      <p>There are many examples in the area of environmental regulation. Consider,
for example, the controversial and probably irrational Prevention of Significant
Deterioration (PSD) program.45 The PSD program says roughly that states that
met national ambient air quality standards in 1977 cannot suffer a deterioration
in air quality, even if the air would remain very clean, and even if there are good
reasons for allowing new development. The use of the 1977 benchmark seems
puzzling and even senseless. There is no clear reason to conclude that the air
cannot become dirtier than it happened to be in 1977, so long as it is consistent
with the other national benchmark standards in the Clean Air Act.</p>
      <p>How, then, can we explain the existence of the PSD program, which seems
hard to justify on public interest grounds? Certainly part of the explanation
comes from public choice theory. Representatives in “clear air” states
disproportionately opposed the program, and those in “dirty air” states
disproportionately supported it, no doubt in order to prevent the exodus of
42See Peter Huber, The Old/New Division in Risk Regulation, 64 Va. L. Rev. 613 (1984).
43See Cass R. Sunstein, After the Rights Revolution (1990).
44See Chicago Studies in Political Economy (G. Stigler ed. 1987).</p>
      <p>4542 U.S.C. 7470 et seq.
revenue-producing, polluting companies to “clean air” states.46 But the
apparently broad appeal of the PSD program may owe a good deal as well to the
endowment effect. The perception that air quality ought at least to stay where it
is—that the government should prevent deterioration from the status quo—
seems to have widespread appeal. This is so despite the fact that other things
being equal, regulatory efforts to make the air cleaner than it now is often face
strong political roadblocks. The asymmetry cannot be fully explained on public
interest grounds, for prevention of deterioration can be far worse than actual
improvements. It probably has a good deal to do with status quo bias and with
the initial endowment reflected in air quality at the time the legislation was
under consideration.</p>
      <p>Or consider one of the most-criticized features of the Clean Air and Clean
Water Acts, the persuasive requirement that companies adopt the “best available
technology” (BAT).47 This strategy has been challenged on the ground that there
is at best an incidental relationship between cost-effective environmental policy
and adoption of BAT.48 In principle, it seems unreasonable to require everyone to
adopt the best available technology. Instead government should allow
companies a high degree of flexibility in achieving air quality goals. Some
companies should switch to clean energy sources, rather than put expensive
technology on dirty energy sources; some companies should go out of business
because once they pay the environmental costs, their activity is not worthwhile;
some companies should not use BAT at all, since they do business in regions in
which adoption of expensive technology is not sensible in light of the variables at
stake.</p>
      <p>An interest-group explanation is not entirely implausible for BAT
requirements.49 But perhaps the requirements can also be understood as an
outgrowth of the status quo bias. If the technological status quo is thought to be
an appropriate benchmark for legal requirements, its use in environmental law
may not be so puzzling. There may be general agreement that the technological
46Pashigian, supra note 1.
4742 U.S.C. 7475; 42 U.S.C. 7411; 33 U.S.C. 301.</p>
      <p>49There are two possibilities here. (a) Industries may Wnd BAT the best of their various options.
Predictably, there will be a great deal of pre-enforcement administrative and litigative activity before
adoption of BAT; hence the BAT approach will produce comparatively less regulation than (for example) a
fee imposed on polluting activity. (b) BAT may be linked with the electoral self-interest of legislators. When
statutes requiring BAT are enacted, legislators can claim credit before their constituents, and blame the
relevant agencies for the (predictably) low level of enforcement activity.
status quo is the best and fairest foundation for environmental law, even if this
view will not survive critical scrutiny.50</p>
      <p>It is notable too that it appears very difficult (though not impossible) to bring
about even rational environmental regulation through tax increases—on, for
example, polluting vehicles or gasoline. “Green taxes” are supported by strong
justifications; but they are an almost invisible part of national environmental
policy.51 Perhaps the difficulty can be attributed to the influence of the
automobile industry; but some of the spokesmen for the industry have actually
favored gasoline taxes. The difficulty may well be understood in terms of the
endowment effect, as that effect operates to define the public demand for
regulation. The existing price of gasoline marks the status quo from which
departures are measured. Government efforts to raise the price therefore meet
strong resistance. Hence the public is generally quite hostile to any effort to
increase the price of gasoline.52</p>
      <p>By contrast, there are many popular regulatory requirements that ultimately
raise the cost of energy and automobiles, but that do so mostly by affecting new
sources. By almost any measure of social welfare, the direct tax approach would
be preferable to the regulatory approach.53 I do not deny that there are many
possible explanations for currently dysfunctional environmental policy. But a
contributing factor may be that a tax or fee imposes highly visible losses as
compared with the status quo, whereas the regulatory approach does no such
thing.</p>
      <p>Or consider the fact that subsidies to mass transit might well be an especially
sensible and inexpensive environmental strategy. If automobiles are a major
contributor to air pollution, an important goal is to reduce vehicle miles traveled,
as well as (or instead of) improving pollution control devices on cars. This much
seems clear from the fact that regulatory requirements have not succeeded in
50See the discussion of fairness in Daniel Kahneman, Jack Knetch, and Richard Thaler, Fairness and the
Assumptions of Economics, supra note 32.</p>
      <p>51There is a partial exception in the most recent amendments to the Clean Air Act. The new provisions
governing acid deposition create a process by which polluters may purchase the right to emit sulfur dioxide
in excess of allowed levels. The purchase will occur both through direct sales and through an innovative
auction system. See 42 U.S.C. 7651o. For a good general discussion of green taxes, see W. Kip Viscusi,
Wesley Magat, Alan Carlkin, and Mark Dreyfus, Environmentally Responsible Energy Pricing (Duke
University, Department of Economics. unpublished manuscript, 1993). Of course President Clinton’s
proposed energy taxes, defended in part on environmental grounds, may make “green taxes” an important
part of national policy.</p>
      <p>52Cf. the discussion of price increases in Thaler, supra note 20.
reducing aggregate automobile pollution levels, because the decrease in air
pollution per mile traveled has been more than offset by increases in total car
use.54 It follows that an imperative for environmental policy is to create
incentives that will decrease the use of the underlying polluting activity. But this
idea has played little role in policy, especially in the area in which it makes most
sense: government expenditures devoted to mass transit and highways.</p>
      <p>Here too the political influence of the automobile industry is a plausible
contributing factor. But status quo bias may play a large role as well. Because
Americans have adapted their behavior to frequent use of the automobile, it is
especially difficult to change their behavior in the direction of mass transit. This
explanation helps to account for the remarkable comparative popularity in
Europe of environmental strategies that do deter automobile use and promote
mass transit.55 In Europe, people have not so deeply adapted their practices and
preferences to automobile use.</p>
      <p>The point is very general. Public policy often takes the status quo—including,
very prominently, the existence of particular firms—as if it were a given. Laws
that endanger current institutions are subject to special social scrutiny. To some
extent this is fully rational in light of the real costs of transition. But I hypothesize
that a large part of the phenomenon is attributable to a bias in favor of the status
quo that is far stronger than traditional theory would predict.</p>
      <p>f. Normative implications.</p>
      <p>Thus far we have seen that many puzzles in current environmental policy
might be an outgrowth of the endowment effect and status quo bias. What about
on the normative side?</p>
      <p>The most general point is that the preference-shaping effects of legal rules
cast doubt on the idea that environmental regulation should attempt to satisfy or
follow some aggregation of private preferences. If legal rules have inevitable
effects on preferences, it is hard to see how a government might even attempt to
take preferences “as given” in any global sense.56 When preferences are a
function of legal rules, the rules cannot be justified by reference to the
preferences.57 Social rules and practices cannot be justified by practices that they
54Roger Crandall, Regulating the Automobile (1986).
55See Marcia Lowe, Shaping Cities, in State of the World 1992, at 119 (Lester Brown ed. 1992).
56A qualification is necessary here. The words “in any global sense” are crucial. Usually the
incremental work of law and economics makes perfect sense, because the particular issue does not affect
preferences. “Local” neutrality among preferences is therefore fully possible.
have produced. Sometimes there is no such thing as a prelegal or prepolitical
“preference” that can be used as the basis for decision.</p>
      <p>The point has normative implications for environmental policy. One would
expect that a decision to farmers a right to be free from water pollution will have
an impact on social attitudes toward clean water. The allocation will affect the
valuation of the rights by both current owners and would-be purchasers. In this
sense—again speaking globally—neutrality as among preferences cannot be
achieved through legal rules, because the preferences will sometimes be a
function, or a creation, of legal rules. In setting policy, it may therefore be
important to make some choice about the sorts of preferences that ought to be
encouraged, rather than to act as if preferences can be kept constant.58</p>
      <p>None of this suggests that it is generally impossible for those interested in
environmental law to work from existing preferences. Sometimes the
endowment effect is small, and in any case we can generate a relatively narrow
range of prices from which to make policy choices. But in valuation of natural
resources, the endowment effect can create a significant problem, one that is
impairing efforts to make contingent valuation of resources not traded on
markets.59 It follows that some ground should ultimately be identified for
choosing between the different outcomes that would be produced by
preferenceshaping legal rules.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>2. Adaptive Preferences, Intrapersonal Collective Action Problems, Cascades, and</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>Heuristics</title>
      <p>Private preferences are endogenous to current practices, current
opportunities, and past consumption. This conclusion follows from the
endowment effect. In this section, I generalize the point.</p>
      <p>a. Adaptive Preferences.</p>
      <p>People may well adapt their conduct and even their desires to what has been
available. Consider here the story of the fox and the sour grapes. The fox does
not want the grapes because he considers them to be sour; but his belief to this
effect is based on the fact that the grapes are unavailable. It is therefore hard to
58It is highly notable in this regard that the institutions of the market and democracy—now often
defended as neutral among preferences—were originally justified as producing good preferences. On
democracy, see J.S. Mill, Considerations on Representative Government (1991; originally published 1861);
on the market, see especially the discussion of “doux commerce” in Albert Hirschmann, The Passions and
the Interests (1983).
justify their unavailability by reference to his preferences.60 In the environmental
context, it might be hypothesized that the preference for environmental quality
will be especially weak among people who have not been exposed to pristine
areas, clean water, and clean air. If the point is right, it will have important
implications for positive and normative work.61</p>
      <p>To be sure, it will be hard to test this hypothesis in any authoritative way.
There is an overlap between a lack of information on the one hand and an
adaptation of preferences to what is available on the other. People unexposed to
beautiful areas may be uninterested in them not because of an adaptation, but
because they lack relevant information. Moreover, people whose preferences are
said to have adapted to the absence of environmental quality are likely to be
deprived in a general way. If so, it may be best to say not that their preferences
have adapted, but that they are choosing rationally and as best they can among a
limited set of opportunities. Both of these phenomena—lack of environmental
information and apparent devaluation of environmental quality under
conditions of deprivation, because of the need to trade it off against other
goods—undoubtedly explain a good deal of private and public behavior. They
help account for the fact that poor people seem comparatively uninterested in
many forms of environmental protection. There is, however, a third possibility,
sometimes realized in the world, in which people’s preference for environmental
quality is low because of an adaptation to what is available.</p>
      <p>If this is so, we should be able to explain both private and public behavior
accordingly. Akerlof and Dickens have argued, with some modest evidence, that
workers may be unwilling to confront the real magnitude of environmental risks
faced in the workplace, because it is too distressing for them to do so.62 On this
view, workers, having adapted their preferences and beliefs to a relatively risky
status quo, attempt to reduce cognitive dissonance by concluding that the
dangers are trivial. The claim is speculative and the relevant evidence is largely
anecdotal. But there is some empirical support for the general view. Consider the
fact that after the Three Mile Island nuclear power plant accident, it was the
people who lived on Three Mile Island who, of all those polled, believed that the
relevant risks were lowest.63
60Jon Elster, supra note 57.</p>
      <p>If the general claim is right, it would follow that the demand for
environmental legislation might be relatively low among people deprived of
exposure to environmental quality, and the phenomenon would be attributable
to adaptation of preferences to what is available. It is extremely difficult to test
this hypothesis against more conventional alternatives stressing learning and
rational choice under conditions of deprivation. We might, however, begin to
investigate the demand for environmental protection across regions and across
nations. It would be especially valuable to see how the demand for
environmental quality changes over time, perhaps with exposure to pristine
areas, perhaps with a social belief that the degradation of environmental
amenities is not inevitable, perhaps with the rise of organizations solving
collective action problems of various sorts (see below).</p>
      <p>As a normative matter, it might also follow that existing preferences are an
uncertain basis for environmental policy, since we cannot without circularity
justify environmental outcomes by reference to preferences that those outcomes
have generated. Of course there is a risk of totalitarianism here. Of course it is
right to insist that government should respect private preferences, partly because
of the frustration and resentment that are produced by efforts to bring about
change, partly because of the constant risk of ignorance and bias on
government’s part. But if what I have said here is true, it will be necessary to
rethink the underanalyzed and vexing issue of paternalism, in environmental
law and elsewhere.64
b. Intrapersonal collective action problems.</p>
      <p>A closely related problem arises when environmental preferences are a
function of past acts of consumption and when such acts alter people’s desires or
beliefs in such a way as to cause long-term (subjective) harm to them. In such
cases, the two key facts are (a) that preferences are endogenous to past
consumption decisions and (b) that the effect of those decisions on current
preferences is pernicious. The effect is pernicious when the aggregate costs of
consumption, over time, exceed the aggregate benefits. The phenomenon is a
general one, but it is especially important in the context of environmental
protection, where it is often said that it is necessary to alter social or individual
habits by inducing people to engage in a different kind of behavior. A pervasive
and difficult question involves the cost, especially the transition cost, of the
attempted alteration. If preferences are endogenous to past consumption
64Cf. Amartya Sen, Inequality Reexamined (1992); Hilary Putnam, Renewing Philosophy 183-85 (1992).
For a defense of a form of liberal perfectionism—a belief in a principle of autonomy not necessarily tied to
existing preferences—see Joseph Raz, The Morality of Freedom (1986).
behavior, we might hypothesize that the cost will often be lower than
anticipated, and precisely because of the change in preference that is brought
about by new behavior.</p>
      <p>Consider the extreme case of an addiction. Here the problem (if there is one65)
is that the costs of not consuming the addictive substance increase dramatically
over time, as the benefits of consumption remain constant or fall sharply.66 A
possible result is that the aggregate costs, over time or over a life, of consumption
exceed the aggregate benefits, even though the initial consumption choice
provides benefits that exceed costs. As a result, people can be made much worse
of even by their own lights. In such cases, people, if fully informed, might well
not want to become involved with the good in the first place.67</p>
      <p>This situation might be described as involving an intrapersonal collective
action problem,68 in which the costs and benefits, within a particular person, of
engaging in the same activity change dramatically over time. The key point is
that consumption patterns bring about a significant change in preferences and in
a way that makes people worse off in the long-run.69</p>
      <p>While addiction is the most obvious case,70 it is part of a broad category, and
the broader category includes a wide range of environmental examples.
Consider, for example, myopic behavior, defined as a refusal—because the
short65It is certainly possible to imagine a case in which people rationally choose to become addicted—that
it, they might do so with full information about costs and benefits over time. The subjective benefits may
dwarf the subjective costs, even if the benefits diminish and the costs increase. I am suggesting only that this
is not always the case. See also note 70 infra.</p>
      <p>69Of course all consumption has an effect on preferences. For example, exposure to classical music
usually increases appreciation. But the pattern under discussion is a rare one; it is that pattern, producing
miserable lives, to which a democracy might respond. To be sure, in practice the response might make
things worse rather than better.</p>
      <p>70There is a growing literature on the issue of rational addiction, a literature with interesting
applications for environmental protection. See K.M. Murphy and Gary Becker, A Theory of Rational
Addiction, 96 J. Pol. Econ. 675 (1988). I do not believe that there is a substantial difference between the
account offered in the text and that offered by Becker and his followers. It does not much matter whether we
say that preferences stay constant, and choices change, or that preferences change as a result of choices. (See
the discussion supra of the problematic character of the notion of a “preference.”) It is possible to say on
either account that an addiction is rational; and an intrapersonal collective action can also arise on either
account.
term costs exceed the short-term benefits—to engage in activity having long-term
benefits that dwarf long-term costs. We can see this at both the social and
individual levels. Akrasia, or weakness of the will, has a related structure
(though it may also reflect a problem of incommensurability71). Another kind of
intrapersonal collective action problem is produced by habits, in which people
engage in behavior because of the subjectively high short-term costs of change,
notwithstanding the fact that the long-term benefits exceed the short-term
benefits.</p>
      <p>Habits that pose intrapersonal collective action problems are a prominent
target of environmental regulation. Consider, for example, the issue of
compulsory recycling. It may be that the costs of recycling are initially quite high,
simply because the change of behavior is unsettling. The costs may include
transition costs and the costs produced by private annoyance and irritation. But
once people are in the habit of recycling, some of these costs decrease (perhaps
because of learning, perhaps because of preference change), and for many people
these costs may even turn into benefits. As a possible analogy, consider the habit
of brushing one’s teeth in the morning. Even for those who dislike brushing
most, a failure to brush may be still more costly than brushing, simply because
one is in the habit, and because the habit brings about internalized norms.</p>
      <p>It may even be that people in the habit of recycling develop certain social
norms72 that help turn the hedonic costs of environmental protection into
hedonic benefits and thus help solve the collective action problems pervasively at
stake in environmental regulation.73 If so, there is much more to be said on behalf
of recycling, as a policy alternative to a disposal tax, than at first appears.74 The
legally-induced change of preferences may well have salutary long-term
consequences, though before proceeding, it is important for government to be
certain of this fact.</p>
      <p>The same considerations bear on the creation of incentives to use mass transit
rather than automobiles. It may be that expenditures on mass transit will be
71See Martha Nussbaum, Plato on Commensurability and Desire, in Love’s Knowledge 106 (1990).
72See Gary Becker, The Economic Way of Looking at Life, University of Chicago, Law &amp; Economics
Working Paper No. 12 (1993), at 17: “Economists have too narrow a perspective on commitments.
‘Manipulating’ the experiences of others to influence their preferences may appear to be inefficient and
fraught with uncertainty, but it can be the most effective way available to obtain commitment. Economic
theory, especially game theory, needs to incorporate guilt, affection, and related attitudes into preferences in
order to have a deeper understanding of when commitments are ‘credible.’”
73Cf. Jon Elster, The Cement of Society (1990).</p>
      <p>74An excellent argument against compulsory recycling is Peter Mennell, Beyond the Throwaway
Society, 17 Ecology L.Q. 655 (1990); but Mennell’s treatment does not take adequate account of the
endogeneity of preferences.
firmly resisted at first. Indeed, the relevant incentives will have to be very strong
in order to encourage people to change their behavior, adaptive as this has been
to the cheap automobile transportation. Here is a case in which preferences are
highly adaptive to past consumption choices, a fact that helps account for the
high premium placed on automobile transportation in the United States as
compared to (for example) Germany and Sweden. But once behavior has
changed, preferences may change as well, and the subjective costs of using mass
transit may well decrease.</p>
      <p>This is a speculative hypothesis, and it would be good to test it. Some
evidence could be produced from examining experience with compulsory seat
belt usage. I hypothesize that after seat belt use has been compelled, the costs of
buckling up decrease, and may even turn into benefits, in the sense that an
unbuckled belt will produce discomfort and annoyance. It would follow that
states that have enacted and then repealed seatbelt laws should see a large
shortterm increase in seatbelt use even after a highly publicized repeal.
c. Cascades.</p>
      <p>Habits and customs can be vulnerable to large-scale shifts on the basis of
relatively mild government interventions. Sometimes the practice of many
people is dependent on what other people do. Once some people change their
practices, a wide range of others change as well. Thus it has been shown that
“mass behavior is often fragile in the sense that small shocks can frequently lead
to large shifts in behavior.”75</p>
      <p>This is so especially in view of the fact that the modest changes sometimes
have a large signaling effect for other people. The point has implications for the
positive and normative theory of environmental protection. Compulsory
behavior—or disclosure of information—may produce a large-scale cascade in a
certain direction as a result of new social norms. Something of this kind may
have happened with respect to recycling and “green marketing.” As a result, the
effects of government policy may be quite different from what would be
expected if it were assumed that preferences were rigid and fixed. The costs of
regulatory change may therefore turn out to be lower than expected.</p>
      <p>If this idea is to be used for policy purposes, it would be valuable to come up
with precise predictions about the circumstances in which such cascades will
occur. But we already have sufficient reason to believe that current tastes and
habits are sometimes vulnerable to large-scale shifts.
d. The availability heuristic.</p>
      <p>A final problem is that perceptions of the world are endogenous to what
events are psychologically “available,” in the sense that they come readily to
mind.76 This problem should be grouped with the others in this section, for here
too, we are dealing with preferences and beliefs that are adaptive to context, and
in a way that might have positive implications and also impeach their reliability
for policy purposes.</p>
      <p>If pervasive, the availability heuristic will produce systematic errors.
Assessments of risk will be pervasively biased, in the sense that people will think
that some risks (of a nuclear accident, for example) are high, whereas others (of a
stroke, for example) are relatively low. One would predict that the availability
heuristic would create a kind of crazy-quilt pattern in regulation, with some
events calling for stringent regulation and others calling for little or no regulation
at all. The regulation would not be closely associated with actual risk levels. This
is the pattern we observe.77 Studies of American government show extraordinary
disparities in expenditures per life saved.78</p>
      <p>The disparities are plausibly attributed at least in part to the availability
heuristic. The dramatic difference between expert and public assessments of risk
levels79 is very likely an outgrowth of this heuristic, and the difference maps
closely onto actual differences in expenditures per life saved. The public demand
for regulation therefore appears to be a product of the availability heuristic,
which is itself endogenous to the nature and levels of public and private
publicity.</p>
      <p>Thus, for example, there are enormous expenditures designed to counteract
cancers in the workplace, and relatively low expenditures designed to prevent
injuries in automobile accidents. The comparative overregulation of certain
environmental risks may well be a product of the fact that those risks, when they
come to fruition, are highly publicized. Through this route too we might be able
to explain the other inexplicably severe controls on nuclear power. We might
also be able to explain the extraordinary safety of air travel as compared with
other means of transportation.80</p>
      <p>76See Noll &amp; Krier, supra note 8; Kahneman &amp; Tversky, supra note 7; W. Kip Viscusi, Fatal Tradeoffs
(1992).</p>
      <p>77See appendix B in C. Sunstein, After the Rights Revolution (1990); Stephen Breyer, Breaking the
Vicious Circle (1993)..</p>
      <p>78Id.
79See Breyer, supra note 77.</p>
      <p>The availability heuristic also has normative implications. It produces serious
biases, and it is important to ensure that these are reduced or eliminated. A
comprehensive system of uniform warnings about risk levels81 might well make
public assessments less dependent on sensationalistic anecdotes, which very
much affect the operation of the availability heuristic. Government information
policies might bring public and expert judgments more closely into line. If this
proves difficult, institutional changes might be introduced so as to introduce the
distorting features of the public demand for regulation.82</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>3. Collective Judgments and Some Unusual Free-Rider Problems</title>
      <p>Environmental measures might reflect the use of law to embody not the
preferences that people hold as private consumers, but instead what might be
described as collective judgments, which sometimes solve collective action
problems with unusual characteristics. In political processes, people’s
“preferences”—or what backs their choices—are quite different from what they
are in market arrangements. They are subject to different norms and different
constraints. They are endogenous to the setting in which they appear. It should
hardly be surprising that they yield different outcomes.83</p>
      <p>Consider the fact that some people seek stringent laws protecting the
environment or endangered species even though they do not use the public
parks or derive material benefits from protection of species—and even though in
their private behavior, they are unwilling to do much to protect environmental
amenities. The mere existence of certain environmental goods seems to be highly
valued by political participants, even if they are not willing to back up the
valuation with dollars in private markets. Of course many people are so willing,
and many people give to organizations that will do so. But it seems clear that the
choices people make as political participants are different from those they make
as consumers. It is in part for this reason that democratic outcomes are distinct
from those that emerge from markets.</p>
      <p>a. The disparity.</p>
      <p>The widespread disjunction between political and consumption choices
presents something of a puzzle. There are many plausible explanations for the
disjunction. It would be possible to suggest that markets reflect individual choice
more reliably than politics; that democratic choices differ from market outcomes
81Cf. Viscusi, supra note 76.
82This is suggested in Breyer, supra note 77.</p>
      <p>83Cf. the discussion of “dual utility functions” in Howard Margolis, Selfishness, Altruism, and
Rationality: A Theory of Social Choice (1982); see also Mark Sagoff, The Economy of the Earth (1987).
largely because of confusion, as voters fail to realize that they must ultimately
bear the costs of the programs they favor; that voting patterns reveal a free-rider
problem, reflected in a general willingness to support governmental provision of
certain goods so long as it is mostly other people who are footing the bill; and
that the disparity stems from rational ignorance, as voters, often uninformed
about public policy issues, produce political outcomes that are especially
unreliable.</p>
      <p>Undoubtedly there is something true about each of these claims. Consumer
behavior is sometimes a better or more realistic reflection of actual preferences
than is political behavior. Moreover, there are distinctive problems in collective
behavior—not only because of the foregoing considerations, but also because of
the risks of government manipulation of both preferences and choices, and
because of the sheer power of collectivities, especially when backed by the force
of law. But in light of the fact that preferences—taken either as a motivation for
behavior or as behavior itself—depend on context, the very notion of a “better
reflection” of “actual” preferences is a confusing one. There is no such thing as an
actual (in the sense of unitary or context-free) preference in these settings.
Moreover, the difference between market choice and political choice might be
explained by the fact that in the environmental arena, political behavior can
reflect a variety of influences that are distinct to the context of political
deliberation, and that may even justify giving special weight to what emerges
through the political setting. These include four possible phenomena.</p>
      <p>First, citizens may seek to implement their aspirations in political behavior,
but not in private consumption. As citizens, people may seek the aid of the law to
bring about a system that they consider to be in some sense higher than what
emerges from market ordering. In the environmental arena, this idea may
include, for example, protection of the interests of future generations or of
nonhuman life.</p>
      <p>Second, some people may, in their capacity as political agents, attempt to
satisfy altruistic, justice-related, or other-regarding desires. These can diverge
from the self-interested preferences sometimes characteristic of markets.84
Discussion among political participants may affect the development and
expression of preferences. There is a body of empirical work to this effect.85 The
narrowest explanation is that implicit contracts, arrived at and understood as
84See Howard Margolis, SelWshness, Altruism, and Rationality: A Theory of Social Choice (1982).
85See, e.g., Norman Frohlich &amp; Joseph Oppenheimer, Choosing Justice (1992).
such through discussion, can help solve collective action problems; but the
phenomenon is almost certainly broader than this.86</p>
      <p>Third, political decisions might vindicate what might be called
metapreferences or second-order preferences. People have wishes about their wishes.
Sometimes they try to vindicate those second-order wishes, including considered
judgments about what is best, through law. Here environmental law may not
only protect against collective action problems, but also vindicate second-order
judgments about (for example) the importance of aesthetic and recreational
values.</p>
      <p>Fourth, people may precommit themselves, in democratic processes, to a
course of action that they consider to be in the general interest. They may do so
in order to protect themselves against what they know to be their own
selfishness, myopia, or impulsiveness. The story of Ulysses and the Sirens is the
model. The point may well help explain certain aspects of environmental policy,
including compulsory recycling statutes.87</p>
      <p>I emphasize that these are only possible accounts of some of what can be
observed in the environmental arena. It is undoubtedly true that much of
environmental behavior reflects the self-interest of powerful private groups
seeking to bring about or to prevent environmental regulation, or to ensure that
any such regulation serves their parochial interests. I suggest only that a full
explanation of public behavior will have to take account of the phenomena I am
describing.</p>
      <p>86Robin Dawes et al., Explaining Discussion-Induced Cooperation, 54 J. of Personality and Social
Psych. 811 (1988).</p>
      <p>87Some qualifications are necessary here. First, these claims might be proved false in any particular
case. It might well be that a law justified as reflecting altruistic desires in fact results from the pressures of
well-organized private groups, and has nothing to do with altruism at all. This phenomenon is of course a
common one. A detailed study of the forces that produce particular legislation, and of divergences between
public and private choices, is necessary to evaluate the claims made here. There is thus a rich source for
empirical work.</p>
      <p>Second, to point to these various possibilities is not at all to deny that market and private behavior
frequently reflects considered judgments, altruism, aspirations, or far more complex attitudes toward
diverse social goods than is captured in conventional economic accounts about self-interested preferences.
There are numerous counterexamples to any such claim. All I mean to suggest is that divergences between
market and political behavior will sometimes be attributable to phenomena of this sort.</p>
      <p>Third, a democratic system must be built on various safeguards to ensure that its results are in fact a
reflection of deliberative processes of the sort described here. Often such processes are distorted by the fact
that some groups are more organized than others, by disparities in wealth and influence, and by public and
private coercion of various kinds.
b. Explanations.</p>
      <p>Thus far I have suggested that people may seek, through law, to implement
collective desires that diverge from market choices. Might we come up with more
concrete explanations for the differences? There are a number of possibilities.</p>
      <p>First, the collective character of politics, permitting a response to collective
action problems, may be relevant. People may not want to implement their
considered judgments about environmental protection, or to be altruistic toward
future generations, unless there is legal assurance that others will do so as well.
More simply, people may prefer not to contribute to a collective benefit if
donations are made individually, with no guarantee that others will participate;
but their favored system, obtainable only or best through democratic forms,
might be one in which they contribute if (but only if) there is assurance that
others will do so. Perhaps people feel ashamed if others are contributing and
they are not. Perhaps they feel victimized if they are contributing and others are
not. Social norms thus help explain the disparity between public and private
behavior.</p>
      <p>In any case, and most fundamentally, the satisfaction of environmental
aspirations or altruistic goals will sometimes have the characteristics of the more
conventional provision of public goods or the solution of prisoners’ dilemmas.
Both altruism and aspirations have some of the features of a public good.
Aspirations are not conventional public goods, because the market does not fail
according to ordinary understandings of market failure. But if the most preferred
option is to reflect and carry out aspirational or altruistic goals, political action
may be the best alternative. Market behavior, even when working well, may fail
to do the job.</p>
      <p>Second, the collective character of politics might overcome the problem,
discussed above, of preferences and beliefs that have adapted, or to some extent
adapted, to an environmentally unsatisfactory status quo or to limits in
environmental opportunities. Without the possibility of collective action, the
status quo may seem intractable, and private behavior and even beliefs will
adapt accordingly. But if people can act in concert, preferences might take on a
quite different form. Social movements for environmental protection are
plausible examples.</p>
      <p>Third, social and cultural norms might incline people to express aspirational
or altruistic goals more often in political behavior than in markets. Such norms
may press people, in their capacity as citizens, in the direction of a concern for
others, for justice, or for the public interest.</p>
      <p>Fourth, the deliberative aspects of politics, bringing additional information
and perspectives to bear, may affect preferences as expressed through
governmental processes. A principal function of a democratic system is to ensure
that through representative processes, new voices, or novel depictions of where
interests lie and what they in fact are, can be heard and understood. It should
hardly be surprising if preferences, values, and perceptions of environmental
welfare are changed as a result of that process.</p>
      <p>Fifth, and finally, consumption decisions are a product of the criterion of
private willingness to pay. Willingness to pay is a function of ability to pay, and
it is only a proxy for utility or welfare.88 Poor people may be unwilling to pay
much for an environmental good, like clean air, that they very much want; rich
people may be willing to pay a good deal for things toward which they feel
relatively indifferent. Because of the one-person one-vote rule, political behavior
helps remove this distortion (which is emphatically not to deny that it introduces
many distortions of its own).</p>
      <p>c. Qualifications.</p>
      <p>The argument for respecting collective desires seems irresistible if the
measure at issue is adopted unanimously. But more serious difficulties are
produced if (as is usual) the law imposes on a minority what it regards as a
burden rather than a benefit. Suppose, for example, that a majority wants to
require recycling, but that a significant minority hates the idea. It might be
thought that those who perceive a need to express an aspiration should not be
permitted to do so if the consequence is to deprive others of an opportunity to
satisfy their preferences.</p>
      <p>The foreclosure of the preferences of the minority is unfortunate, but in
general it is hard to see what argument there might be for an across-the-board
rule against collective action of this sort. If the majority is prohibited from
vindicating its considered judgments through legislation, an important
democratic arena will be eliminated. The choice is between the considered
judgments of the majority and the preferences (and perhaps considered
judgments as well) of the minority. On the other hand, the foreclosure of the
minority should probably be permitted only when less restrictive alternatives,
including private arrangements, are unavailable to serve the same end. In the
environmental context, often such alternatives are indeed available.</p>
      <p>If what I have said in this section is correct, some environmental measures
will result from desires and aspirations that have a distinctive character precisely
because they emerge in the political context. It is not right to think that the
consumption choice reflects a “true” or “accurate” picture of preferences, and
that politics reveals a blunder. Nor is it right to say that the political choice
88See note supra 10, on intrapersonal comparisons of utility and willingness to pay.
reflects the true picture. The preference and the choice are endogenous to the
setting in which they are expressed. There is no unitary “preference” that can be
described as accurately reflected individual choice.</p>
      <p>I emphasize that I have offered a portrait of what politics might sometimes
be, not what it actually, always, or usually is. To know whether the various
phenomena are truly at work, it is necessary to investigate the details. But it
would be surprising if we could not explain at least some of the disparities
between market and political choice on this general ground. At the same time,
the disparities provide a reason to value political over market choices, at least
under ideal or very favorable conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>4. Diverse Goods, Context, and Commensurability.</title>
      <p>The last point is the most speculative and complex, and its implications for
positive and normative work are far from clear. The point starts with the fact that
most positive theories assess environmental issues by reference to “preferences”
for environmental quality viewed abstractly, through a unitary scale, along the
same metric—that of utility or of willingness to pay. This approach is perfectly
reasonable in light of the fact that people must make choices under conditions of
scarcity, and it therefore seems sensible to say that people behave as if they make
things commensurable even if they do not do so knowingly or willingly.</p>
      <p>The puzzle stems from the fact that ordinary people appear to resist the use of
a unitary scale and the claim of commensurability along a single metric.89 I claim
that two goods are incommensurable if they are not valued in the same way and
if their assessment along a single metric therefore does violence to our
considered judgments about how (not how much) these goods should be valued.
This section attempts to see if it is possible to use this fact to make sense out of
89The philosopher Joseph Raz understands incommensurability in terms of a failure of transitivity:
“Two valuable options are incommensurable if (I) neither is better than the other, and (2) there is (or could
be) another option which is better than one but is not better than another.” Joseph Raz, The Morality of
Freedom 325 (1986) (emphasis in original). On this view, A may not be better than B, or vice-versa, but C
may be better than A but not better than B.</p>
      <p>This statement seems to point to a puzzling or even incomprehensible state of affairs, but Raz shows
that it sometimes obtains. I may be indifferent between lunch with a friend and a $50 gift. At the same time,
I would prefer a $60 gift to a $50 gift. But I am still indifferent between lunch with a friend and a $60 gift.
Or: There are two political initiatives that seem to me equally good: Saving two endangered species, or
cutting the budget deficit by $1 billion. I would prefer a $1.5 billion reduction in the budget to a $1 billion
reduction. But I am indifferent as between a $1.5 billion reduction and saving two endangered species.
When incommensurability occurs, there is a failure of transitivity. I put to one side two complex questions:
(a) whether a failure of transitivity is irrational and (b) whether incommensurability of this sort is frequent.
Raz’s conception of incommensurability is closely related to that in the text. The failure of transitivity stems
from the absence of a single metric from which the three alternatives can be evaluated. Two may be ranked
along the same metric, but a third may not.
some otherwise puzzling phenomena relating to the public’s environmental
judgments. Through this route it may be possible to understand some features of
the apparent demand for regulation, and this is so even if we ultimately conclude
that the demand is built on confusion or irrationality. Consider a few examples.</p>
      <p>a. Some people feel extremely insulted when asked how much they would
accept for a specified level of environmental deterioration, treating the question
as outrageous or a form of bribery, rather as if they had been asked to sell a child,
or a friendship, or a part of their body. “Studies using WTA questions have
consistently received a large number of protest answers, such as ‘I refuse to sell’
or ‘I want an extremely large or infinite amount of compensation for agreeing to
this,’ and have frequently experienced protest rates of 50 percent or more.”90
b. Some people say that environmental goods have infinite value or that the
effort to achieve a clean environment should not be “traded off” against other
important values. In opinion polls, people sometimes say that we should achieve
a clean environmental “regardless of cost.”</p>
      <p>c. Some apparently popular statutes reflect a kind of environmental
absolutism. The Endangered Species Act91 forbids balancing except in the rarest
of circumstances. Some statutes, including the Delaney Clause,92 forbid any entry
of carcinogenic substances onto the market, banning tradeoffs of any kind.</p>
      <p>d. As noted, there are extraordinary disparities in federal expenditures per
life saved. In some environmental programs, risks are prevented at enormous
cost; the government is willing to spend relatively little to stop other risks. All
current efforts to produce uniformity in expenditures have failed.</p>
      <p>Phenomena of these sorts may in the end reflect irrationality, confusion,
interest-group power, or sheer chance. But it would be useful to explore whether
there might not be some other kind of explanation. When people are thinking in
these various ways, exactly what are they doing?</p>
      <p>We might hypothesize that people’s apparently irrational valuation of
environmental goods comes partly from an insistence that diverse social goods
should not be assessed according to the same metric. Some people think that
these diverse goods should be valued in qualitatively different ways. This is not
to deny that people make trade-offs among incommensurable goods. But with
90E.M. Mitchell and K.S. Carson, Using Surveys to Value Public Goods 34 (1989). “These extreme
responses reflect the feelings of outrage often seen when communities are faced with the prospect of
accepting a new risk such as a nuclear power plant or waste disposal facility.” Daniel Kahneman, Jack
Knetch, and Richard Thaler, The Endowment Effect, Loss Aversion, and Status Quo Bias, 5 J. Econ. Persp.
193, 203 (1991).</p>
      <p>9116 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.
this hypothesis, some apparent anomalies dissolve or become more readily
explicable. Some people, for example, rebel against the idea that we should see
all of the following, environmentally related consequences as “costs”:
unemployment, higher prices, greater poverty, dirtier air, more cancer,
respiratory problems, the loss of species. It is tempting to say that this is simply
an irrational thought. In a way, of course, all of these things are indeed costs;
they are harmful things that society should, other things being equal, attempt to
reduce. Moreover, the effort to render them commensurable by assimilating
them to a unitary category—“costs”—is more than plausible. That effort is
motivated by the view that through such assimilation, we will render tractable
certain social decisions that otherwise become amorphous and unmanageable.93
If we have six, seven, or a thousand desiderata—if we have plural utility
functions—and we assume that these are qualitatively distinct, we may not know
what to say or do. A choice among them will be rendered too chaotic. Predictions
will become impossible.</p>
      <p>But it is also possible to understand the resistance to commensurability,
captured in the insistence on qualitative distinctions, on diverse modes of
valuation, and on the plurality of social goods. The resistance, with roots in John
Stuart Mill,94 stems from the view that if we make diverse goods commensurable
in this way, we will do violence to our considered judgments about how all these
should be characterized, experienced, and understood.95 Some people think that
those considered judgments are not embarrassing, but instead are part of what it
means to think well. If all these things are understood as “costs,” to be assessed
via the same metric, important qualitative distinctions may become lost. Simply
as a positive matter, it might be hypothesized when people refuse to trade off
environmental quality and other goods, they are making a claim about the
diversity of goods and about incommensurability. They are claiming that one set
of goods is superior to another not in the sense that it is infinitely valuable, or in
the sense that a small amount of it is more valuable than a large amount of
93For remarks on the origins of this idea, see Martha Nussbaum, Plato on Commensurability and
Desire, in Love’s Knowledge 106 (1990).</p>
      <p>94See J.S. Mill, Utilitarianism (1991; originally published 1861), especially the discussion of higher and
lower pleasures. A more detailed normative discussion of incommensurability can be found in Cass R.
Sunstein, Incommensurability in Law (University of Chicago Law School, unpublished manuscript 1993).</p>
      <p>95See Amartya Sen, Plural Utility, 80 Proceedings of the Aristotelian Society (1980-81); see also Joseph
Raz, The Morality of Freedom (1986); Charles Taylor, The Diversity of Goods, in C. Taylor, Philosophy and
the Human Sciences 230, 243 (1985); Anderson, Values, Risks, and Market Norms, 17 Phil. &amp; Pub. AV. 54,
57-59 (1987); Pildes &amp; Anderson, Slinging Arrows at Democracy: Social Choice Theory, Value Pluralism,
and Democratic Politics, 90 Colum. L. Rev. 2121 (1990); Anderson, Value in Ethics and Economics
(forthcoming 1993); Nussbaum, Plato on Commensurability and Desire, in Love’s Knowledge (1991).
something else, but in the sense that it is important to see that it is to be valued in
a distinctive way and that is therefore stands higher in a hierarchy.96</p>
      <p>This point leaves many ambiguities, and I will not be able to address them all
here. But let us consider, for example, the issue of environmental risks in the
workplace. It is clear that people take jobs that expose them to certain risks to
health and safety. From this it is tempting to say that a risk of level A is really
worth a dollar amount X, or that people value their lives at a certain dollar
amount.97 In a way this makes obvious sense. But suppose that people firmly
resist (as is predictable) the conclusion that the view that to them, risk A, or their
life, is really worth X. Suppose they claim that this is not in fact their view. To the
evidence of their behavior, suppose they respond that they did indeed take the
job, but they adamantly resist any broader inference about their tradeoffs
between risk and dollars. Is it clear that they are not making sense?</p>
      <p>Even if they are indeed not making sense, we might be able to use their
responses to understand some otherwise peculiar features of the social demand
for environmental regulation. And it is even possible that they are making
sense.98 If so, it is because their valuation is not an acontextual one or a global
judgment about optimization, but instead highly dependent on and geared only
to the particular setting in which the choice is made. When a worker accepts a
risky job for cash, it may be wrong to say that he “really” thinks that the risk is
equivalent to that amount of cash—if the word “really” is intended to capture an
abstract, acontextual judgment. Instead he has simply taken the job, and this
decision, in its context, may mean nothing more general. Of course it remains
possible that the valuation that is expressed through the occupational choice
should be the relevant one for those who make policy.</p>
      <p>Through this route, it might be possible to help account for phenomena (a)
through (d) above. For example, the risk charts might reflect qualitative
distinctions among different sorts of hazards. People might not be interested only
in cost per life saved, but also in whether the risk was voluntarily assumed;
whether the exposed person, the employer, or the employee knows the facts;
whether the underlying activity produces valuable goods; whether the hazard is
common; whether the exposure is essential to productive activity; whether the
96See the discussion of hierarchical incommensurability in Pildes &amp; Anderson, supra note 95. One
should not make too much of this claim even if it is descriptively accurate and normatively plausible. It may
still be most parsimonious to study behavior as if people believed in commensurability even if they do not,
or believe that they do not. Moreover, the fact that people make choices among diverse goods may be all we
need to engage the assumption of commensurability.</p>
      <p>97See W. Kip Viscusi, Risk by Choice (1984); W. Kip Viscusi, Fatal Tradeoffs (1992).</p>
      <p>98See Pildes &amp; Anderson, supra note 95; Anderson, supra note 95.
risk is encountered occupationally or elsewhere; whether the people subjected to
risk were able to participate in making relevant decisions.99 With such questions,
it may emerge that people’s valuations of different risks will vary a good deal
with context. Hence the varying valuations may reflect not irrationality or
interest-group pressure, but diverse judgments about qualitatively diverse risks.</p>
      <p>I do not claim that the actual disparities can be justified in this way. In view of
their obvious irrationality, that conclusion would be extravagant. But it may well
be rational to allow widely varying expenditures in light of the diverse factors
outlined above, and at least some of the current variations might have some such
foundation.</p>
      <p>It might also be possible to understand some of the reactions to opinion polls
and perhaps environmental legislation as well. Begin with an exotic example. If a
pet owner were asked how much he would accept to allow his pet cat or dog to
be used for laboratory experiments, he could be insulted and might well respond
very much like the people in (a)100 This is so even though economic valuation of
pets, in terms of purchase price, sale price, and medical expenditures, is perfectly
common. This response stems from the fact that the pet owner’s ordinary
attitude toward his pet is incompatible with the idea that that pet is solely for
human experimentation—though that attitude is not incompatible with imposing
budgetary limits on sale price and on medical expenditures. In these
circumstances the problem is not that the offered price is too low, or that the pet
is infinitely valuable, but that the very idea of sale for the purpose of
experimentation seems inappropriate. Some people think of freedom from
certain environmental risks, and the protection of pristine areas, in just this way.
They value the relevant goods not for their use but for their beauty. The
emphasis on “use value” inadequately captures the way they value the relevant
goods. We might conclude that much of public discussion about the environment
is about the appropriate mode (not only the appropriate level) of valuation for
diverse human goods.</p>
      <p>If something of this kind is right, it may be that people think that the loss
through human action of an endangered species is incommensurably (not
infinitely) bad, and that this thought should be expressed through regulatory
99Some of these factors are discussed in William Lowrence, Of Acceptable Risk (1976).</p>
      <p>100Cf. Anderson, supra note 95. Note some related puzzles: people do not ask their neighbors to mow
their laws, or clean up their house, even for a high price; people do not ask other people to exchange their
place in queues for cash; people offer to drive each other home, but they rarely offer to pay for taxis. Some of
this is discussed in terms of “social norms” in Jon Elster, The Cement of Society (1989), but I think that an
approach that investigates issues of commensurability will be more helpful.
proscriptions. To say the least, this view raises many complexities. All I mean to
suggest is that it is a common idea.101</p>
      <p>In some cases, the claim of incommensurability is understandably but
wrongly converted into a claim of infinite value. It is wrongly so converted
because people do and must make choices under conditions of scarcity. We
might think that (say) a loss of a species cannot really be made commensurable
with the loss of jobs, but that neither of these is of infinite value, and that it is
appropriate even if tragic to sacrifice one incommensurable good for another.
The hard questions, not yet fully elaborated in the philosophical literature,
remain: How does one make choices when noncommensurable social goods are
at stake, and when some of these must be sacrificed? When noncommensurable
goods are at stake, how can choices be assessed as reasonable or not? I cannot
attempt to answer these questions here. But attention to valuation of the diverse
goods at stake in environmental regulation may well provide relevant
information on this subject.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Recent refinements and qualifications of rational choice theory have
important implications for the study of government regulation. Above all, the
endogeneity of preferences offers a large area for positive work. Some
environmental outcomes can probably be explained by status quo bias and the
endowment effect. In particular, these phenomena help account for the
asymmetry between old and new risks and the public antipathy toward
strategies that create incentives to decrease use of automobiles.</p>
      <p>Both private and public behavior in the environmental context are an
outgrowth of the fact that environmental preferences are endogenous to
available opportunities, to shifting social norms, and to past acts of consumption.
Some environmental outcomes may well be a reflection of the asymmetry
between political and consumption choices, an asymmetry sometimes
attributable to the peculiar features of political deliberation. It is incorrect to say
that the consumption choice accurately reflects a preference, whereas a political
choice does not. The preference is itself endogenous to the setting in which it is
expressed.</p>
      <p>Finally, and most tentatively, I suggest that environmental absolutism may
sometimes result from a resistance to claims of commensurability between
environmental and other goods. From these admittedly speculative claims, there
101An especially good discussion can be found in Elizabeth Anderson, supra note 95, chapters 1, 2, and
is obviously large room for empirical testing, though we do not yet have the tools
to find all that is required.</p>
      <p>I have made some normative suggestions as well. Private preferences are an
inadequate basis for environmental policy insofar as these are adaptive to an
environmentally inadequate status quo. At least under ideal conditions (met
rarely in the real world), democratic choices about the environment are probably
to be preferred over private consumption choices, even if free-rider and
informational problems could be solved. Finally, claims of incommensurability
among diverse environmental goods are at least plausible so long as they are not
confused with claims of infinite valuation. Much remains to be done on this
important and difficult subject.</p>
      <p>In the end, I believe, these sorts of suggestions will point to the need to
question whether private preferences should be the exclusive touchstone of
environmental policy. We might venture as well an account of what human
beings need for good lives102 and try to set up conditions under which democratic
decisions about environmental matters can be most fully informed, so as to
ensure appropriate valuation of diverse environmental assets.103 To undertake
such endeavors would be to recover important aspects of the old discipline of
political economy But an account of these abstract and complex claims would
take me well beyond the present discussion.</p>
      <p>102This is the direction suggested in Amartya Sen, Inequality Reexamined (1992); Amartya Sen,
Commodities and Capabilities (1985).</p>
      <p>103This is the direction suggested in Elizabeth Anderson, supra note 95.</p>
      <p>This Working Paper is a preliminary version of an article that will be
published in The Journal of Legal Studies. Readers with comments should address
them to:
1. William M. Landes, Copyright Protection of Letters, Diaries and Other</p>
      <p>Unpublished Works: An Economic Approach (July 1991).
2. Richard A. Epstein, The Path to The T. J. Hooper: The Theory and History of</p>
      <p>Custom in the Law of Tort (August 1991).
3. Cass R. Sunstein, On Property and Constitutionalism (September 1991).
4. Richard A. Posner, Blackmail, Privacy, and Freedom of Contract (February
1992).
5. Randal C. Picker, Security Interests, Misbehavior, and Common Pools
(February 1992).
6. Tomas J. Philipson &amp; Richard A. Posner, Optimal Regulation of AIDS (April
1992).
7. Douglas G. Baird, Revisiting Auctions in Chapter 11 (April 1992).
8. William M. Landes, Sequential versus Unitary Trials: An Economic Analysis
(July 1992).
9. William M. Landes &amp; Richard A. Posner, The Influence of Economics on</p>
      <p>Law: A Quantitative Study (August 1992).
10. Alan O. Sykes, The Welfare Economics of Immigration Law: A Theoretical</p>
      <p>Survey With An Analysis of U.S. Policy (September 1992).
11. Douglas G. Baird, 1992 Katz Lecture: Reconstructing Contracts (November
1992).
12. Gary S. Becker, The Economic Way of Looking at Life (January 1993).
13. J. Mark Ramseyer, Credibly Committing to Efficiency Wages: Cotton</p>
      <p>Spinning Cartels in Imperial Japan (March 1993).
14. Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law (April 1993).</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>1The Prevention of Significant Deterioration program is a conspicuous example</article-title>
          . See 42 U.S.C.
          <article-title>7470 et seq</article-title>
          . See Peter Pashigian, Environmental Regulation:
          <article-title>Whose Self-Interests Are Being Protected?</article-title>
          ,
          <source>in Chicago Studies in Political Economy</source>
          <volume>498</volume>
          (George Stigler ed.
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>3Examples include the emphasis on “scrubbing” coal, see Bruce Ackerman</article-title>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <given-names>William</given-names>
            <surname>Hassler</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Clean Coal/Dirty Air (
          <year>1981</year>
          ),
          <article-title>and more recently the clean fuels provisions of the 1990 Clean Air Act, see Jonathan Adler, Clean Fuels, Dirty Air</article-title>
          , in Michael Greve &amp; Fred
          <string-name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Environmental Politics</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ). 4See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Paradoxes of the Regulatory State</source>
          , 57
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
            <surname>Chi</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. Rev.
          <volume>407</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          5See, e.g.,
          <source>William Baumol and Wallace Oates</source>
          ,
          <source>The Theory of Environmental</source>
          Policy (2d ed.
          <year>1988</year>
          ); William Baxter, People Not Penguins (
          <year>1975</year>
          ); Richard Epstein, Nuisance Law:
          <article-title>Corrective Justice and Its Utilitarian Constraints, 8</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J. Legal</given-names>
            <surname>Stud</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>49</volume>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          ); Richard Epstein,
          <source>The Principles of Environmental Protection: The Case of Superfund, 2 Cato Journal</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>6The influence is clear especially with the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs (OIRA) in the Office of Management and Budget, the regulatory “czar” that oversees regulatory decisions, including those of the Environmental Protection Agency</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>OIRA has undertaken cost-benefit analysis, and applied many principles recommended by economists</article-title>
          ,
          <source>in the implementation of Exec. Ord</source>
          .
          <volume>12291</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>3</surname>
            <given-names>CFR</given-names>
          </string-name>
          127, reprinted in 5 U.S.C. 601 note (
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>and Exec</article-title>
          . Ord.
          <volume>12498</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>3</surname>
            <given-names>CFR</given-names>
          </string-name>
          323, reprinted in 5 U.S.C. 601 note (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The status of these executive orders is now under review by the Clinton Administration</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>7The relevant work is extremely diverse</article-title>
          . See, e.g., Richard Thaler, Quasi-Rational
          <string-name>
            <surname>Economics</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ); Richard Thaler,
          <source>The Winner's Curse</source>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          );
          <article-title>Thomas Schelling, Choice and Consequence (</article-title>
          <year>1986</year>
          ); George Ainslie,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picoeconomics</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ); Jon Elster, Sour
          <string-name>
            <surname>Grapes</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Gary Becker</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
            <surname>Murphy</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Theory of Rational Addiction</source>
          , 94
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Pol</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Econ.
          <volume>675</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ); Amartya Sen, Inequality
          <string-name>
            <surname>Reexamined</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ); W. Kip Viscusi,
          <source>Fatal Tradeoffs, chapters 6</source>
          ,
          <issue>7</issue>
          , and 8 (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Jon Elster, Ulysses and</article-title>
          the
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sirens</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          );
          <article-title>Daniel Kahneman and Aaron Tversky, Prospect Theory: An Analysis of Decision under Risk, 47 Econometrica 263 (</article-title>
          <year>1979</year>
          ); C.C. von Weiszacker,
          <source>Notes on Endogenous Change of Tastes</source>
          , 3
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Theory</source>
          <volume>345</volume>
          (
          <year>1971</year>
          ); Gary Becker, The
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          11See
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
            <surname>Arrow</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Social Choice and Individual
          <string-name>
            <surname>Values</surname>
          </string-name>
          (2d ed.
          <year>1963</year>
          ).
          <article-title>For a critique</article-title>
          , see Richard Pildes &amp; Elizabeth
          <string-name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            , Slinging Arrows at Democracy: Social Choice Theory,
            <given-names>Value</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pluralism</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and Democratic Politics,
          <volume>90</volume>
          Colum. L. Rev.
          <volume>2121</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          )
          <article-title>12See Amartya Sen, Behavior and the Concept of a Preference, 40 Economica 241 (</article-title>
          <year>1973</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>20It was first so-called in Richard Thaler, Toward a Positive Theory of Consumer Choice, 1</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Behavior and Org</source>
          .
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
          <article-title>This essay, along with others of similar interest, can be</article-title>
          found in Richard Thaler, Quasi-Rational
          <string-name>
            <surname>Economics</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>21Dan Brookshire and Don Coursey, Measuring the Value of a Public Good: An Empirical Comparison of Elictation Procedures, 77 Am</article-title>
          . Ec. Rev.
          <volume>554</volume>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>22Judd</given-names>
            <surname>Hammock and G. M. Brown</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Waterfowl and Wetlands:
          <string-name>
            <surname>Toward Bioeconomic Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Robert Rowe et al</article-title>
          .,
          <source>, An Experiment on the Economic Value of Visibility</source>
          , 7
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Env</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Ec. and Management</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          23Richard Thaler,
          <article-title>Toward a Positive Theory of Consumer Choice, 1</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Behavior and Org</source>
          .
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
          <article-title>A good overview is Elizabeth Hoffman and Matthew L. Spitzer, The Divergence Between Willingness-to-Pay and Willingness-to-Accept Measures of Value, Wash</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>U. L. Q.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (forthcoming
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>24W. Kip</given-names>
            <surname>Viscusi</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Wesley Magat, and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            <surname>Huber</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>An Investigation of the Rationality of Consumer Valuations of Multiple Health Risks, 18</article-title>
          <source>RAND Journal of Economics</source>
          <volume>465</volume>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>25See generally William Samuelson</article-title>
          and Richard Zeckhauser,
          <source>Status Quo Bias in Decision Making, 1 Journal of Risk and Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          26Daniel Kahneman,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Jack</given-names>
            <surname>Knetsch</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and Richard Thaler,
          <article-title>Experimental Tests of the Endowment Effect and the Coase Theorem, 98</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Pol</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Econ.
          <volume>1325</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ). See also Jack Knetch,
          <source>The Endowment Effect and Evidence of Nonreversible Indifference Curves, 79 Am. Econ. Rev</source>
          .
          <volume>1277</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Jack Knetch and Sinden, Willingness to Pay and Compensation Demanded: Experimental Evidence of an Unexpected Disparity in Measures of Value, Q</article-title>
          . J. Econ.
          <volume>507</volume>
          (
          <year>1984</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>28See Rebecca Boyce</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <article-title>An Experimental Examination of Intrinsic Values as a Source of the WTAWTP Disparity, 82 Am</article-title>
          . Econ. Rev.
          <volume>1366</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          31David
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Brookshire and Don L. Coursey</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Measuring the Value of a Public Good: An Empirical Comparison of Elicitation Procedures, 77 Am</article-title>
          . Econ. Rev.
          <volume>554</volume>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          32See
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            <surname>Kahneman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jack Knetsch, and Richard Thaler,
          <article-title>Fairness and the Assumptions of Economics</article-title>
          ,
          <source>in Rational Choice: The Contrast Between Economics and Psychology</source>
          <volume>101</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
          <article-title>See also Edward Zajac, Perceived Economic Justice: The Example of Public Utility Regulation</article-title>
          , in Cost Allocation: Methods, Principles,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Applications (H. Peyton</surname>
          </string-name>
          Young ed.
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          33See, e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Roger</surname>
            <given-names>Noll</given-names>
          </string-name>
          &amp; James
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krier</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Some Implications of Cognitive Psychology for Risk Regulation</source>
          ,
          <volume>19</volume>
          J. Legal Stud.
          <volume>747</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
          <article-title>This argument was originally offered in Richard Thaler, Toward a Positive Theory of Consumer Choice, 1</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ). 34See Shelley Taylor, Positive
          <string-name>
            <surname>Illusions</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>36An interesting argument to this effect appears in Michael Hanemann, Willingness to Pay and Willingness to Accept: How Much Can They Differ?, 81 Am</article-title>
          . Econ. Rev.
          <volume>635</volume>
          ((
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>37Cf. Graham</given-names>
            <surname>Loomes</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Robert</given-names>
            <surname>Sugden</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Regret Theory: An Alternative Theory of Rational Choice Under Uncertainty, 92 Economic Journal</source>
          <volume>805</volume>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Graham Loomes and Robert Sugden, Disappointment and Dynamic Consistency in Choice Under Uncertainty, 53 Rev</article-title>
          . of
          <source>Economic Studies</source>
          <volume>271</volume>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          ); David Harless,
          <source>Actions Versus Prospects: The Effect of Problem Representation on Regret, 82 Am. Econ. Rev</source>
          .
          <volume>634</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Chris Starmer and Robert Sugden, Probability and Juxtaposition Effects: An Experimental Investigation of the Common Ratio Effect, 2</article-title>
          <source>J. Risk and Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>159</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Graham Loomes, Further Evidence of the Impact of Regret and Disappointment in Choice Under Uncertainty</article-title>
          ,
          <volume>55</volume>
          Economica 47 (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          38See
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            <surname>Hanemann</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Willingness to Pay and Willingness to Accept: How Much Can They Differ?,
          <source>81 Am. Econ. Rev</source>
          .
          <volume>635</volume>
          ((
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>48The best discussion is Bruce Ackerman</article-title>
          &amp; Richard Stewart, Reforming Environmental Law,
          <volume>13</volume>
          Colum.
          <source>J. Env. Law</source>
          <volume>171</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>53See Roger</surname>
            <given-names>Crandall</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Policy Watch: Corporate Average Fuel Economy Standards, 6 J. of Econ. Persp</source>
          .
          <volume>171</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          59See, e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>R.G.</given-names>
            <surname>Cummings</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
            <surname>Brookshire</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>W.D.</given-names>
            <surname>Schulze</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Valuing Environmental Goods;
          <article-title>An Assessment of the Contingent Valuation Method(</article-title>
          <year>1986</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Paul Carlin and Robert Sandy, Estimating the Implicit Value of a Young Child's Life, 58</article-title>
          <source>Southern Economic Journal</source>
          <volume>186</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>61Amartya Sen has insisted on this general point in many places</article-title>
          .
          <source>See Amartya Sen, Commodities and Capabilities</source>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ); Amartya Sen, Inequality
          <string-name>
            <surname>Reexamined</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          62See
          <string-name>
            <given-names>George</given-names>
            <surname>Akerlof</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Robert
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dickens</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Economic Consequences of Cognitive Dissonance, 72 Am. Econ. Rev</source>
          .
          <volume>307</volume>
          -
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>63See Elliott</surname>
            <given-names>Aronson</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , The Social Animal (4th ed.
          <year>1984</year>
          ).
          <article-title>It is possible, of course, that the people who lived in this area were better informed</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>66But see Alan Schwartz, Views of Addiction and the Duty to Warn, 75</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Va. L.</given-names>
            <surname>Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>509</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ); W. Kip Viscusi,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Smoking</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          67Menachem Yaari,
          <article-title>Endogenous Changes in Tastes: A Philosophical Discussion, in Decision Theory and Social Ethics: Issues in Social Choice 59 (</article-title>
          <year>1978</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          68Thomas Schelling,
          <article-title>Egonomics, or the Art of Self-Management, 68 American Economic Review 290 (Papers</article-title>
          and Proceedings) (
          <year>1978</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Jon Elster, Weakness of Will and the Free-Rider Problem, 1</article-title>
          <source>Economics &amp; Philosophy</source>
          <volume>231</volume>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ). See also George Ainslie,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picoeconomics</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          );
          <article-title>The Multiple Self (Jon Elster ed</article-title>
          .
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>75See Sushil Bikhchandani</surname>
            , David Hirshleifer,
            <given-names>and Ivo</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Welch</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Theory of Fads</source>
          , Fashion, Custom, and Cultural Change as Informational Cascades, 100
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Polit</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Econ.
          <volume>992</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
          <article-title>See also Douglas Baird, Robert Gertner, and Randall Picker, Strategic Behavior and the Law ch. 6 (forthcoming</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

