<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Anticaste Principle
Author(s): Cass R. Sunstein
Source: Michigan Law Review</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>92</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <fpage>2410</fpage>
      <lpage>2455</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at . http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp . JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org. http://www.jstor.org</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>The Michigan Law Review Association is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to
Michigan Law Review.</p>
      <p>This content downloaded from 62.122.78.43 on Sat, 21 Jun 2014 19:14:40 PM</p>
      <p>All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein*</p>
      <p>It is sometimes suggested that there is a sharp opposition
between "liberty" and "equality."' If the law forbids racial
discrimination in employment, it may promote equality, but perhaps it will
simultaneously interfere with liberty. If the law requires wealthy
people to transfer some of their income to poor people, it may
promote equality, but it may also undermine liberty. If a health care
program ensures universal access to health care, it may promote
equality, but it could also raise serious doubts from the standpoint
of liberty. The tension between liberty and equality often appears
deep, and it plays a large role in American political and legal
thought.</p>
      <p>But before accepting the alleged opposition between liberty and
equality, we should observe that there are many possible
understandings of liberty and equality. These understandings reveal not
disputes about dictionary definitions but diverse substantive
judgments that need to be identified and assessed. Different
conceptions of the two values will lead to different views about their
relationship. For example, the term equality could refer to freedom
from desperate conditions, in the form of minimum welfare
guarantees; to a ban on discrimination on certain specified grounds; to the
idea that every citizen should have the same power over political
outcomes, as in the one-person, one-vote rule; to similar starting
points or basic opportunities for every citizen; to similar incomes or
wealth; to similar incomes unless disparities can be justified as
beneficial for all; or to much more.</p>
      <p>The same is true for liberty. That capacious term could refer to
the basic political rights of free speech and free elections. It could
include the guarantees of a fair system of criminal justice, in which
rules are laid down in advance and a defendant has a right to a fair</p>
      <p>* Karl N. Llewellyn Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago. - Ed. This
essay develops some ideas contained elsewhere. See CASSR.
SUNSTEINT,HEPARTIALCONSTITUTION338-46 (1993). The essay greatly benefited from comments by Akhil Amar, Martha
Minow, and others at a conference on equal citizenship held at Brown University in March
1994. I am also grateful for very helpful suggestions from Richard Epstein, Jane Mansbridge,
and Susan Moller Okin.</p>
      <p>1. See the helpful discussion in AMARTYA SEN, INEQUALITRYEEXAMINED12-30 (1992),
upon which I draw here.</p>
      <p>2410
trial before an independent judge. It could entail social respect for
the outcomes of processes in which citizens pursue their various
conceptions of the good, given market forces, existing common law
rules, existing preferences, and existing distributions of wealth. The
term liberty could refer to a system that ensures autonomy in the
formation of preferences and beliefs by providing a decent
education for all and by counteracting unjust background conditions. It
could refer to much more.</p>
      <p>We can readily see that some conceptions of equality are quite
compatible with - indeed identical to - some conceptions of
liberty. For example, libertarians, who may appear to oppose
equality, insist on equality of an important kind; they want to ensure that
all citizens have an equal right to pursue their own ends.2 An
understanding of equality lies at the heart of the libertarian creed.</p>
      <p>Freedom from desperate conditions, often treated as an egalitarian
idea, is an understanding of liberty as well. Those who emphasize
autonomy in the formation of preferences are speaking of both
equality and liberty; they want to ensure that unjustified
inequalities - inequalities based upon wealth, race, or sex, for example
do not limit the free development of individual personality.</p>
      <p>In these circumstances, it is important to be quite careful before
seeing any tension between equality and liberty. Tension exists
only when we specify conceptions of these broad terms that cannot
peacefully coexist. Perhaps such incompatible conceptions cannot
be defended. Perhaps the best conceptions of equality are entirely
compatible with the best understandings of liberty.</p>
      <p>In this essay, I seek to defend a particular understanding of
equality, one that is an understanding of liberty as well. I call this
conception "the anticaste principle."3 Put too briefly, the anticaste
principle forbids social and legal practices from translating highly
visible and morally irrelevant differences into systemic social
disadvantage, unless there is a very good reason for society to do so. On
this view, a special problem of inequality arises when members of a
group suffer from a range of disadvantages because of a
groupbased characteristic that is both visible for all to see and irrelevant</p>
      <p>2. See id. at 22 (arguing that libertarians "insist[ ] on equal immunity from interference by
others").</p>
      <p>3. Related ideas can be found in LAURENCEH. TRIBE, AMERICANCONSTITUTIONAL
LAW? 16-21 (2d ed. 1988), and Owen M. Fiss, Groups and the Equal Protection Clause, 5
PHIL.&amp; PUB. AFF. 107. 147-70 (1976). There are, however, important differences between
these approaches and what I defend here, partly because of my understanding of the equality
principle, and partly because I suggest that the principle is for legislative rather than judicial
enforcement. Many such differences will emerge in the course of the discussion.
from a moralpoint of view. This form of inequalityis likely to be
unusuallypersistentand to extend into multiplesocial
spheres,indeed into the intersticesof everydaylife.</p>
      <p>I do not claimthat this is the only validunderstandingof
equality. On the contrary,there are many such understandings.Our
Constitution'sequality principleis plural rather than singular. It
has numerous manifestations;4a unitary conception of equality
would not exhaust the term as it operates in American legal and
politicaldiscussion. Considerpoliticalequalityand
principlesdisallowing discriminationon the basis of religiousconvictionor
prejudice. These conceptionsof equalitywarrantsupport,andthey have
considerablegroundingin our constitutionaltraditions.5</p>
      <p>I emphasizethe anticasteprinciple,not because it exhauststhe
concept of equality,but because it capturesan understandingthat
has strong roots in Americanlegal traditions,has
considerableindependentappeal,is violatedin manyimportantpartsof American
life, and fits well with the best understandingsof liberty. In other
words, the anticasteprincipleis an importantand
perhapsinsufficiently appreciated part of the lawyer's conception of equality
underthe AmericanConstitution.6</p>
      <p>In describingthe anticasteprinciple,I also offer some
information about racialand gender disparitiesin the United States. I do
so because it is hardto have a sense of the worldof discrimination
without having a good sense of the data. Legal discussionsabout
equalityare too often and too exclusivelyconceptual,attemptingto
offer perspicuousdescriptionsof discriminationor
inequalitywithout a sufficientdiscussionof the factsthat underlieeither the
problem or the solutions.7 I will not offer much detail about solutions
here, but I do hope that my presentationof informationabout
existing inequalitieswill help to illuminatethe problem.</p>
      <p>I emphasizeas well thatenforcementof the anticasteprincipleis
mostlyfor legislativeandexecutiveofficersandonly secondarilyfor
courts. Sometimein the late nineteenthand
earlytwentiethcenturies, there was a large-scaletransformationin the substanceof the
constitutionalequality principle. This is a long and as-yet-untold
4. In this way it is similar to most constitutional rights, which serve a number of functions.
5. Some are discussed in SUNSTEINs,upra note *, at 123-61.</p>
      <p>6. Although this is a lawyer's conception, it is mostly for nonjudicial enforcement. See
infra section II.B.2.</p>
      <p>7. See Stephen J. Schulhofer, The Feminist Challenge in Criminal Law, (Feb. 28, 1994)
(unpublished manuscript, on file with author) (discussing the need for data and midlevel
solutions in feminist reform of criminal law).
story. A set of amendmentsoriginallydesigned at least in part to
eliminatesocial caste eventuallybecame a requirementthat
legislation be reasonablyrelatedto legitimatestate interests- a
requirement whose original home was the Due Process Clause.8 The
transformationmakes some sense if we think about the limited
capacities of the judiciary. Taken seriously, a full-blown anticaste
principle is beyond judicial competence. But if the Constitution
speaks to nonjudicialactorsas well, the broadcommitmentsof the
Fourteenth Amendment have a different meaning outside the
courtroom. It is possible, in short, to insist on the
continuingimportanceof one of the great unusedprovisionsof the Constitution,
Section5 of the FourteenthAmendment: "TheCongressshallhave
power to enforce, by appropriatelegislation,the provisionsof this
article."9</p>
      <p>I. FALSE STARTS</p>
      <p>In this Part,I discussthree understandingsof the
equalityprinciple. All three have played a majorrole in public and sometimes
legal debate. The firststressesthe advantagesof free markets. The
second relies on respect for existing preferences. The third and
most importantsees the equalityprincipleas a ban on unreasonable
distinctionsbetween social groups. As we will see, the difficulties
with each of these understandingshelp lay the foundationfor the
anticasteprinciple.</p>
      <p>A.</p>
      <p>Markets?</p>
      <p>In light of the extraordinaryrecentoutburstof
internationalenthusiasmfor free markets,it should not be surprisingto find a
resurgenceof the view thatall invidiousdiscriminationon the basisof
race and sex will be eliminatedby laissez faire.10On this view, the
appropriateapproachfor law would be to eliminateconstraintson
marketorderingand to rely solely on
propertyrights,voluntaryarrangements,and freedom of contractto produceequality.</p>
      <p>8. U.S. CONST.amends. V, XIV; see, e.g., Allgeyer v. Louisiana, 165 U.S. 578, 589-90
(1897) (striking down a Louisiana law limiting the right of out-of-state insurance companies
to do business in Louisiana as an infringement on liberty of contract not justified by the law's
purpose).</p>
      <p>9. U.S. CONST.amend. XIV, ? 5.</p>
      <p>10. See, e.g., RICHARDA. EPSTEINF,ORBIDDENGROUNDS59-78 (1992). But see id. at 76
(conceding that discrimination of some sort will persist in markets because such
discrimination is "rational"). I focus on race and gender equality, with occasional reference to
disability. Other forms of inequality raise additional issues that I cannot take up here. See infra
section II.B.4.</p>
      <p>In many ways, free markets are indeed connected with equality
on the basis of race and sex. Legal barriers to female and black
employment are a form of government intervention in the market,
and they have often been an effective and severe hindrance to
equality. Antifemale and antiblack cartels, especially when
government-sponsored, can drive down both wages and employment for
women and blacks. In a free market, by contrast, all people should
succeed to the extent that they are able to perform their respective
functions - as employers, employees, co-workers, and customers.</p>
      <p>It is unnecessary to stress that women and blacks often perform as
well as or better than men and whites. Once discriminatory laws
are eliminated, free markets may therefore accomplish a great deal
in breaking down a system of inequality. In South Africa, for
example, it is most doubtful that the system of apartheid could have
survived under free markets. Too many employers would have found
it desirable to hire blacks; too many companies would have found it
in their economic interest to serve people on a nondiscriminatory
basis.</p>
      <p>The point can be made through a simple example. Suppose that
an employer prefers to hire only men; suppose he believes that
women belong in the home. This employer should face severe
obstacles to continued profitability and, in the end, might even be
driven out of the market. An employer who restricts himself to one
social group will be placed at a serious disadvantage; it would be as
if he refuses to hire people whose last names begin with a particular
letter. If the employer is sexist or racist, his "taste" for
discrimination operates as an implicit tax on the operation of his business. To
say the least, self-imposed implicit taxes are self-defeating in a
competitive market.</p>
      <p>Much the same can be said for a company that prefers to serve
only whites or men. Such a company will artificiallyrestrict its
business to one social group, and it will thus impair its own economic
interests by reducing its market and the corresponding demand for
its product. An employer who hires and serves women as well as
men should do much better in market competition.</p>
      <p>As a complete solution, however, free markets will be
inadequate if used to remedy sex and race discrimination. There are
several reasons.11 First, a market system allows discriminatorily
motivated third parties to impose costs on people who agree to
treat men and women, or blacksand whites,equally.12Customers,
co-workers,and otherssometimeswithdrawpatronageand services
from nondiscriminatoryemployers. For example, a law firm that
hires female lawyersmightfind itself punishedin the marketplace.</p>
      <p>A grocerystore that hiresblacksmightfindit harderto
attractcustomers. Under these circumstancesm,arketpressuresdo not check
discriminationbut instead increase the likelihood that it will
continue. Ironically,the failureto discriminateoperatesas a tax on the
employer's business, rather than vice versa. A nondiscriminator
could face the equivalent of a self-imposed tax by virtue of
coworker or customerreactions.</p>
      <p>The phenomenon is hardlyunusual. Consider,for example, a
shopkeeper whose customers do not like dealing with blacks or
women; a commercialairline whose patrons react unfavorablyto
female pilots;a universitywhose studentsand alumniprefer a
primarilywhite faculty;a hospital whose patients are uncomfortable
with female doctorsor blacknurses. The persistenceof
privatesegregationin majorleague baseballis a familiarexample. The latter
finds a modern analoguein studies of the prices of baseballcards,
which show a race-basedpremiumfor white players.13We may
speculatethat in some athleticcompetitionscustomerspreferwhite
athletes, and these preferencesplay a role in some market
decisions. In cases of
thiskind,marketpressurescreateratherthanprevent discrimination.14</p>
      <p>Of course,thirdpartiesdo not have uniformpreferences. Many
and perhapsmost whites and men are not discriminators.In any
case third-partypreferencesare sharplydivided,andfor this reason
we should expect a wide rangeof diverseviews and practices,each
gaining and losing influence in different times and places.15 My
point is only that in some importantsectors, and for important
lengths of time, the existence of third-partydiscriminationcan
en</p>
      <p>12. See GEORGEA. AKERLOFT,he economics of the caste and of the rat race and other
woeful tales, in AN ECONOMIST'SBOOKOFTALES23, 31-43 (1984).</p>
      <p>13. See Clark Nardinelli &amp; Curtis Simon, Customer Racial Discrimination in the Market
for Memorabilia: The Case of Baseball, 105 Q.J. ECON.575 (1990).</p>
      <p>14. On this account it remains necessary to explain why third parties are not themselves
hurt by their taste. Sometimes they will be; an employee who prefers not to work with
women may find himself with a worse job. But sometimes the third parties will not suffer
competitive injuries in markets because they are not competing in markets - consider
people who prefer not to fly in airplanes piloted by blacks - and sometimes the harm inflicted
by a discriminatory taste will operate like any other harm inflicted by a taste, for example,
the taste for color television or high-quality ice cream. Prices will go up, but the relevant
goods will not be driven from the market.</p>
      <p>15. The point is emphasized in EPSTEIN, supra note 10, at 30-31, 44-46.
sure that inequality persists even in free markets. The extent of the
effect is of course an empirical question.</p>
      <p>Thus far, then, we have seen that co-worker and customer
discrimination may lead markets to perpetuate discrimination. A
second problem with relying on markets to produce equality is that
race and sex discrimination can be a successful and indeed ordinary
market response to generalizations or stereotypes that, although
overbroad and perhaps in one sense even invidious, provide an
economically rational basis for market decisions.16 If stereotypes are
economically rational, the market will not operate against them.</p>
      <p>Stereotypes and generalizations are of course a common ingredient
in market decisions. There are information costs in making
distinctions within categories, and people sometimes make the category
do the work of a more individualized and perhaps more costly
examination into the merits of the particular employee.</p>
      <p>Many categorical judgments are not only pervasive but also
legitimate. We all rely on them every day. Employers rely on proxies
of various kinds, even though the proxies are overbroad
generalizations and far from entirely accurate. Test scores, level of education,
and prestige of college attended are all part of rational employment
decisions. Despite their imprecision, such categorical judgments
might well be efficient as a cost-saving device and thus persist in
free markets; but they might also disserve the cause of equality on
the basis of race and gender.</p>
      <p>This is so especially in light of the fact that race and gender are
so highly visible and thus so cheaply used as a proxy for other
things.17 Different characteristics - for example, educational
attainment - might be more accurate as proxies but less efficient to
use because the cost of gaining accurate information is higher.</p>
      <p>We might compare statistical generalizations of the sort I am
describing with the category of prejudice. Perhaps we can
understand that controversial term to include a continuum of unnecessary
or inefficient categorical judgments, including, for example, (i) a
belief that members of a group have certain characteristics when in
fact they do not, (ii) a belief that many or most members of a group
have certain characteristics when in fact only some or a few do, and
(iii) a reliance on fairly accurate group-based generalizations when</p>
      <p>16. See Edmund S. Phelps, The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism, 62 AM. ECON.</p>
      <p>REV. 659 (1972).</p>
      <p>17. The point is, of course, related to the discussion of why a morally irrelevant
characteristic should be highly visible in order to be part of a caste system. See infra text
accompanying notes 70-75.
more accurateand reasonablycheap classifyingdevices are
available, or, in other words, when there is a more efficientclassifying
device. Statisticaldiscriminationis quite different. It occurswhen
the generalization,thoughinaccurate,is less costly to use than any
subclassifyingdevice, even thoughsubclassificationwsouldbe more
accuratein particularcases. Underplausibleassumptionsaboutthe
cost of acquiringinformation,statisticaldiscriminationmight well
be efficient.</p>
      <p>Relianceon race-or sex-basedgeneralizationsmaybe a product
of prejudice,but this need not be the case. Generalizationsabout
race and gendermaywell be overbroad,but no more so
thangeneralizations that are typically and unproblematicallyused in many
areas of decision. Note that "collegeattended"mightwell be used
in the employmentmarket,despiteits considerableimprecisionas a
classifyingdevice. Moreover,in the area of sex discrimination,an
employermight discriminateagainstwomen, not because he hates
or devalues them, but because he has found from experiencethat
women devote more time to childcarethando men, or thatwomen
are more likely to take leave for domestic duties. For this reason
sex discriminationmight be based on genuine facts, not irrational
prejudice- althoughthose facts may themselvesbe a productof
discriminationelsewhere, particularlywithin the family.18 This
formof statisticaldiscrimination- judgmentsbasedon statistically
reasonablestereotyping- need not be a form of prejudice.</p>
      <p>My point here is not to celebrateor to
condemnstatisticaldiscriminationbut insteadto say that economicallyrationaldecisions
can ensurethat inequalitywill persistfor women or blacks,even or
perhaps especially in free markets. In variousways, blacks differ
from whites and women differ from men. In light of these
differences, it is fully possible that in certainsettings,race- or sex-based
generalizationsare sufficientlyaccurateas proxiesfor
certaincharacteristics. The conclusionis that free marketswill not drive out
discriminationto the extent that discriminationis an efficientuse of
generalizationsthat, while inaccuratein some ways,have sufficient
accuracyto persistas classificatorydevices.</p>
      <p>This point suggeststhat there is no sharpdiscontinuitybetween
laws callingfor affirmativeaction and laws embodyingthe
antidiscriminationprinciple,at least if the outlawed discriminationis a
form of statisticaldiscrimination.The ban on
statisticaldiscrimina</p>
      <p>18. See SUSANM. OKIN,JUSTICEG,ENDERA,NDTHEFAMILY110-33 (1989) (arguing that
the family as currently constituted "raises psychological as well as practical barriers against
women in all other spheres").
tion shows that the law does not just forbid irrational bigotry or
prejudice. Instead, the most elementary antidiscrimination
principle singles out one kind of economically rational stereotyping and
condemns it, on the theory that such stereotyping has the harmful
long-term consequence of perpetuating group-based inequalities.</p>
      <p>Along this dimension, the distinction between affirmative action
and antidiscrimination is thin in principle.19 It is thin because the
law does not only ban discrimination rooted in prejudice or
hostility; it also bans discrimination in the form of statistical
generalizations of the sort that employers, customers, and others rely on all
the time. The ban on statistical discrimination is based on many of
the reasons that support affirmative action. I do not contend that
the two are the same thing.</p>
      <p>Thus far, then, we have seen that markets are unlikely to bring
about equality on the basis of race and sex when third parties are in
a position to impose costs on nondiscriminators and when statistical
discrimination is rational. The third problem with relying on laissez
faire to eliminate discrimination is that in free markets, people who
are subject to discrimination may fail to attempt to overcome their
unequal status because they will fail to invest in "human capital"
the time and effort, in terms of education and experience, needed to
produce economically valued characteristics. They may fail to do so
simply because of current social practices and a discriminatory
status quo. Suppose, for example, that there is current sex
discrimination in a certain field for any number of reasons - employers
themselves prefer to hire male employees, or third parties impose
pressures in discriminatory directions, or employers engage in
statistical discrimination. These discriminatory phenomena will affect
the decisions of women with regard to education or training in the
relevant field and indeed may affect their aspirations in general. As
market participants, women might well invest less than men in
training to be, for example, doctors or technicians, if these
professions discriminate against women and thus reward their investments
less than those of men. The decision to invest less would be fully
rational as a response to the practices of employers.20</p>
      <p>19. See David A. Strauss, The Myth of Colorblindness, 1986 SUP. CT. REV. 99 (arguing
that insistence on nondiscrimination in fact amounts to affirmative action when racial
classifications are accurate).</p>
      <p>20. Notably, this is a form of market failure, unlike the first two problems. The lower
investments in human capital will produce externalities. See Shelly J. Lundberg &amp; Richard
Startz, Private Discrimination and Social Intervention in Competitive Labor Markets, 73 AM.</p>
      <p>ECON.REV.340 (1983) (producing a model in which workers with similar initial capabilities
end up with different amounts of human capital according to how much employers are willing
to pay different groups of workers).</p>
      <p>Of course the same would be true in the racial context. If law
firms are less likely to hire blacks than whites, blacks will, other
things being equal, be less inclined than whites to go to law school.</p>
      <p>If shops are less likely to hire blacks than whites, blacks will be less
likely than whites to acquire the skills necessary to work in shops.</p>
      <p>In every sector of the market that contains discrimination, the
behavior of prospective black employees will be affected, in the sense
that blacks will scale back their investments in acquiring the
requisite training and skills.</p>
      <p>The result of these various factors can be a vicious circle or even
a spiral. Because of existing discrimination, members of the
relevant groups will invest less in human capital. Because of this lower
investment, the discrimination may persist or even increase,
because its statistical rationality increases. Because of this effect, the
discriminatory tastes of employers and customers may well
increase. Because of this effect, investments in human capital will
decrease still further, and so on.</p>
      <p>These considerations suggest that although free markets can
often help further the cause of race and gender equality, they are
not a panacea. Discrimination can persist because of the effects of
third-party discriminators, because of statistical discrimination, and
because of adverse effects on investment in human capital.21 If
discrimination is to be reduced,22markets are not enough;
supplemental legal controls will be necessary. Empirical questions are very
important here, and we cannot get a full handle on the subject
without knowing a great deal about the facts. For example, in some
imaginable contexts, third-party prejudice will be too weak to
promote much discrimination, and in some imaginable contexts,
prejudice will be a spur to further investments in human capital. What I
am suggesting here, based on highly plausible assumptions and
supported by recognizable phenomena in the United States, is that free
markets can fail to undermine race and sex inequality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>B. Preferences?</title>
      <p>I turn now to an influential claim about the relationship
between discrimination and law. The claim is that the legal system
should take preferences as a given rather than attempt to alter
21. Of course women and blacks have sometimes invested a large amount to overcome
discrimination, and of course I am describing possibilities, not certainties. To see the effects
of free markets on race and sex equality, a good deal of empirical data is necessary.</p>
      <p>22. The question whether discrimination should be reduced requires a theory of equality,
which reliance on free markets does not itself provide.
them. This claim seems especially important for sex equality,
thoughit bearson race equalityas well. In manydifferentnations,
and in some placesin the United States,womenfrequentlysay that
they are content with the sexual status quo. Legal efforts might
therefore be thought to representan unacceptableform of
paternalism. If women themselves are content, on what basis can the
legal systemintervene? Is not legal interventionan
illegitimateinterferencewiththe rightto libertyor autonomy?Thussome people
suggest,for example,that abortioncannot possiblyraise problems
of sex equalitybecause many women are opposed to abortion.23</p>
      <p>These questions raise some complex issues; I deal with them
only brieflyhere.24The basic responseis that a social or legal
system that has producedpreferences,andhas done so by
limitingopportunitiesunjustly,can hardlyjustifyitself by referenceto existing
preferences. The satisfactionof privatepreferences,whatevertheir
content and origins,does not respondto a persuasiveconceptionof
liberty,welfare,or autonomy. The notionof autonomyshouldrefer
insteadto decisionsreachedwitha full andvividawarenessof
available opportunities,with relevantinformation,and without
illegitimate or excessive constraints on the process of preference
formation. When there is inadequateinformationor opportunity,
decisions and even preferencesshould be describedas unfree or
nonautonomous.</p>
      <p>Private preferences often do adjust to limitations in current
practicesand opportunities.Considerhere the storyof the fox and
the sour grapes.25The fox does not want the grapes because he
considersthem to be sour,but his belief that the grapesare sour is
based on the fact that they are unavailable. One cannot therefore
justify the cessation of the fox's efforts to get the grapesby
reference to the fox's preferences. MaryWollstonecraft'As Vindication
of the Rights of Women26applies this basic idea to the area of
discriminationon the basis of sex. Wollstonecraftwrites,"I will
venture to affirm,that a girl, whose spiritshave not been dampedby
inactivity,or innocence tainted by false shame, will always be a
romp, and the doll will never excite attention unless confinement</p>
      <p>24. For further discussion, see
ELIZABETHANDERSONV,ALUEINETHICSANDECONOMICS(1993); JONELSTERS,OURGRAPES(1983); SEN,supra note 1, at 53-55.
25. See ELSTERs,upra note 24, at 109-40 (including an extended argument on the point).
26. MARYWOLLSTONECRAFAT,VINDICATIONOFTHERIGHTSOF WOMEN(Carol H.
Poston ed., Norton &amp; Co. 1975) (2d ed. 1792).
allows her no alternative."27Mill makes the same points in his
work on sex equality.28</p>
      <p>AmartyaSen offersan especiallyvividreal-worldexamplefrom
India. In 1944,the All-IndiaInstituteof HygieneandPublicHealth
surveyedwidowsandwidowersabouttheirhealth. About 48.5%of
the widowers said that they were "ill" or in "indifferent"health,
while only 2.5% of widowsgave the same response.29In these
circumstancesit would seem odd to base healthpolicyon subjectively
held views about health conditions. Such an approachwould
ensure that existing discriminationwould be severely aggravated.</p>
      <p>One goal of a legal system is, in short,to ensure autonomynot
merely in the satisfactionof preferencesbut also and more
fundamentally in the processes of preferenceformation. The view that
freedomrequiresan opportunityto choose amongalternativesfinds
a naturalsupplementin the view thatpeople shouldnot face
unjustifiable constraintson the free development of their preferences
and beliefs.</p>
      <p>Thisdiscussiondoes not at all meanthatgovernmentshouldfeel
free to reject existingviews of the citizenry,or that such views are
irrelevantto antidiscriminationpolicy. For purely
prudentialreasons, it is importantfor governmentto be cautiousabout intruding
on widespreadcurrentviews even if it seems clear that they are
wrong. A system of governmentalreformsthat does not connect
with publicconvictionsis likelyto be futile or self-defeating.
Moreover, governmentis itself vulnerableto the same distortionsthat
affect private preferences.30There is no reason to think that the
judgmentsthat underliegovernmentaction are systematicallyless
susceptible to distortionthan the judgmentsthat underlie private
action. In addition,there is certainlysome relationbetweenprivate
desiresandindividualandsocialwelfare,andfor this reasonprivate
desires should generallycount in decidingon appropriatepolicy.</p>
      <p>For all these reasons governmentshould be modest in its
willingness to revisit privatedesires and beliefs;certainlyit should be
cautious before proceeding against apparentlywidespreadpublic
judgments. All I suggesthere is thatprivatepreferencesare an
un27. Id. at 43.</p>
      <p>28. See JOHNSTUARTMILL,THESUBJECTIOONFWOMEN15-16 (MIT Press 1970) (1869)
(writing against the claim that the existing desires of women are a product of consent).</p>
      <p>29. AMARTYASEN, COMMODITIEASND CAPABILITIE8S2 (1985); see generally JOSEPH
RAZ, ETHICS IN THE PUBLIC DOMAIN 169-72 (1994).</p>
      <p>30. See W. KIPVISCUSIF,ATALTRADEOFF2S1-23 (1992) (illustrating this point for risk
perceptions).
promising foundation for antidiscrimination policy to the extent
that such preferences can be shown to be a product of unjust
background conditions.</p>
      <p>C. Irrational or Unreasonable Distinctions?</p>
      <p>Much of equality law has proceeded by asking whether similarly
situated people have been treated differently. On this view, blacks
can be treated differently from whites only when they are different
from whites; the same is true of differential treatment between
women and men. At least implicitly, legal doctrines in the area of
discrimination allow differences in treatment when people really
are different and ban differences in treatment when people really
are the same.31</p>
      <p>It will readily appear that the notion that the similarly situated
must be treated similarly is purely formal. To become workable,
that notion requires a substantive theory explaining what sorts of
similarities and differences are relevant. Blacks and whites, for
example, are differently situated along many dimensions; so too are
women and men. The government could not justify a racially
discriminatory law enforcement policy on the ground that blacks are
disproportionately involved in crime, even if such a policy could be
justified by reference to actual racial differences with respect to
participation in crime. What is necessary is a theory to explain
when differences will be treated as relevant. By itself the "similarly
situated" test cannot supply that theory. From this we might
conclude that the problem with the theory is that it is empty, not that it
is wrong.32</p>
      <p>As a reaction to the "similarly situated" test in the abstract, this
conclusion seems right. But from Supreme Court jurisprudence
over the last few decades, we can construct a general understanding
31. See, e.g., Rostker v. Goldberg, 453 U.S. 57, 78 (1981) (upholding men-only draft
registration on the grounds that "[m]en and women, because of the combat restrictions on
women, are simply not similarly situated for purposes of a draft"); Michael M. v. Superior
Court, 450 U.S. 464, 476 (1981) (plurality opinion) (upholding a statutory rape law applying
only to underage females because "the statute ... reasonably reflects the fact that the
consequences of sexual intercourse and pregnancy fall more heavily on the female than the male");
Califano v. Webster, 430 U.S. 313, 317-18 (1977) (upholding a statute that treated men and
women differently with respect to social security benefits because Congress acted to
compensate women for past employment discrimination); Califano v. Goldfarb, 430 U.S. 199, 216-17
(1977) (plurality opinion) (striking down a statute that treated men and women differently
with respect to social security benefits in part because Congress did not enact the scheme "to
remedy the arguably greater needs of women").</p>
      <p>32. See Peter Westen, The Empty Idea of Equality, 95 HARV.L. REV.537, 543-48 (1982)
(arguing that equality is meaningless without a separate standard for judging whether people
are the same or different).
of what the test means, and this understanding is not merely formal.
On that understanding, blacks must be treated the same as whites
to the extent that they are the same as whites; women must be
treated the same as men to the extent that they are the same as
men. But these ideas also seem unhelpful. To what extent are
blacks the same as whites, and to what extent are women the same
as men? The law has answered this question largely by saying that
blacks and whites should almost always be taken to be the same,
and that women should be taken to be the same as men unless there
is (i) a physical difference associated with reproduction,33 (ii) a
legally constructed difference not itself in dispute,34 or (iii) a
difference closely associated with past discrimination for which the law in
dispute operates as a remedy or compensation.35 In all other cases,
distinctions based on race and gender should be struck down as
irrational, as stereotypical, or as based on hostility and prejudice.36 It
follows that the law operates as a ban on formal inequality of the
sort that prohibits most explicit distinctions between men and
women or blacks and whites.</p>
      <p>There is much to be said on behalf of invalidating formal
distinctions on the basis of race and gender. Wholesale disparagement of
the pursuit of formal equality makes little sense. In the racial
context, formal inequality is often associated with second-class
citizenship for blacks. Sometimes the same has been true for gender as
well, as in the exclusion of women from the jury and from the
practice of law. Many formal distinctions do help produce inequality in
the form of second-class status, and many of them are based on
prejudice. Even if some formal distinctions between blacks and
whites or men and women can be justified, a strong presumption
against such distinctions might be defended as being well adapted
to the limited capacities of courts. Individualized inquiry into the
legitimacy of formal distinctions might produce too many errors in
particular cases. Perhaps a flat ban on race and sex distinctions
could be justified as a way of producing results that make sense in
the aggregate and that allow errors that are few enough in number
to be acceptable in light of the risks that would be produced by
more individualized inquiry. In addition, formal inequalities tend
33. Michael M., 450 U.S. at 471-73.
34. Rostker, 453 U.S. at 78.
35. Webster,430 U.S. at 318.</p>
      <p>36. See, e.g., Craig v. Boren, 429 U.S. 190 (1976) (striking down a statute that permitted
women but not men between the ages of 18 and 20 to purchase 3.2% beer); see also cases
cited supra note 31.
to encourage people to think in terms of race and gender, and a
broad prohibition on laws containing such inequalities therefore has
a desirable educative or expressive effect.</p>
      <p>Similar ideas could help justify a judicial refusal to test carefully
laws that discriminate in fact but that do not embody formal
inequality.37 Careful scrutiny of laws that discriminate in fact but not
on their face might lead courts to face issues that are beyond their
competence and best assessed legislatively. Consider the
extraordinary difficulties that would be raised by asking whether a veteran's
preference law would be adopted in a world of sex equality, or
whether it could be adequately justified in light of its discriminatory
effects.38</p>
      <p>These considerations might form the basis for a justification of
the Supreme Court's current equality jurisprudence, casting it as
reasonable in principle and sensibly adapted to the courts' modest
role. But there is a problem with this project. It is not at all simple
to come up with a sensible theory of equality that would map onto,
or adequately account for, the existing approach. On what possible
theory would the Constitution ban all explicit race and sex
distinctions and allow all other laws to stand? There are two problems
here.</p>
      <p>First, some deviations from formal equality might well promote
equality as that term is often or best understood. Consider, for
example, a decision of a local police department to furnish special
police protection for women who are traveling alone at night, and
suppose that the decision was based on a recent outbreak of sexual
violence in the area. It is at least unclear that this decision is
inconsistent with equality as it is best understood. Perhaps it promotes
equality by counteracting social conditions that subject women to
disproportionate risks.39 From this example it may follow that
some laws that treat women differently from men are acceptable
and indeed promote the goal of equality, rightly understood.
Califano v. Webster,40 upholding formal sex discrimination in the
benefit formula under social security law, is an explicit and unusual
reflection of this point. Perhaps a maternal deference rule could be
37. See Washington v. Davis, 426 U.S. 229, 246-48 (1976).</p>
      <p>38. See David A. Strauss, Discriminatory Intent and the Tamingof Brown, 56 U. CHI.L.
REV. 935, 1000-03 (1989).</p>
      <p>39. Cf Michael M. v. Superior Court, 450 U.S. 464 (1981) (plurality opinion) (upholding
a sex discriminatory statutory rape law on the ground that nature already deters women from
engaging in sexual intercourse by imposing the penalty of pregnancy, something to which
men are not subject).</p>
      <p>40. 430 U.S. 313 (1977).
justified duringchild custody proceedings;perhapsalimony
determinationsshould be requiredto considerdomestic work, which is
closely correlatedwith gender.41</p>
      <p>Alternatively,some laws raise equalityconcernseven if they do
not violate formal equality. Considera law that forbids pregnant
women from appearingin public. Perhapsno man can be similarly
situated to a pregnantwoman, and perhaps there is no problem,
from the standpointof formalequality,in these circumstances.But
from the standpoint of sex equality, does this make any sense?
Surely problemsof inequalityare raised by a law that penalizes a
physicalcapacitylimitedto one gender.42Or suppose that the law
forbids women from having an abortion, or excludes pregnancy
from a disabilityprogram. Under currentconstitutionallaw, there
is apparentlyno issue of sex discrimination.43Men cannotget
pregnant;women and men are to that extent not similarlysituated. A
law that restrictsabortionor excludespregnancythereforeraisesno
equalityproblem. But this is an odd way to thinkaboutequality. If
the law takes a characteristiclimited to one group of citizens and
turnsthat characteristicinto a source of social disadvantage,it may
well violate the equalityprinciple,best conceived.44</p>
      <p>Let us push this argumentfurther. Sometimesequalityrequires
the similarlysituatedto be treatedsimilarly.But sometimespeople
who are differently situated ought to be treated
differently,precisely in the interest of equality.45In the area of disabilities,for
example,the use of stairsdenies equalityto people who are bound
to wheelchairs,and the use of oral communicationcreates a
problem for people who cannot hear. Legislativechanges have often
been based on an understandingthatpeople who are differentmust
41. The point is made nicely in Mary E. Becker, Maternal Feelings: Myth, Taboo, and
Child Custody, 1 S. CAL.REV.L. &amp; WOMEN'STUD.133,203-23 (1993), and Mary E. Becker,
Prince Charming: Abstract Equality, 1987 Sup. CT. REV. 201, 219-22.</p>
      <p>42. But cf. Bray v. AlexandriaWomen'sHealth Clinic,113 S. Ct. 753, 760-62 (1993)
(holdingthat"thedisfavoringof abortion... is not ipsofactosex discrimination"G); eduldig
v. Aiello, 417 U.S. 484, 494-96 &amp; n.20 (1974) (holdingthat excludingpregnancycoverage
froma statedisabilityprogramdoes not violatethe EqualProtectionClauseabsentan intent
to discriminatee,ven though"it is truethat only womencan becomepregnant").</p>
      <p>43. SeeBray,113S. Ct. at 760-62;Geduldig,417 U.S. at 494-98&amp; n.20. But note too the
strikingappearanceof argumentsinvolvingsex discriminationin PlannedParenthoodv.
Casey,112 S. Ct. 2791,2807,2809,2830-31(1992)(jointopinionof O'Connor,Kennedy,&amp;
Souter,JJ.);112S. Ct. at 2842(Stevens,J., concurringin partand dissentingin part);112S.
Ct. at 2846-47(Blackmun,J., concurringin partand dissentingin part).</p>
      <p>44. See the discussion of differences in CATHARINEMACKINNON, Difference and
Dominance: On Sex Discrimination, in FEMINISMUNMODIFIED32 (1987).</p>
      <p>45. See SEN,supranote 1, at 16-19(arguingthat achievingequalityin one
areamaynecessitateinequalityin anotherarea).
be treated differently if they are to be treated equally.46 Of course,
the expense of the adaptation is relevant to the question of what,
exactly, ought to be done. But constitutional doctrine has rarely
recognized that differences in people's situations might justify a
claim for differential treatment in the interest of equality.</p>
      <p>We can connect this issue to the broader failure of American
law to do as much as it might have about existing inequalities on the
basis of both sex and race. In many areas there has been much
progress; women cannot be excluded from professions, and most
laws that build on or ratify sex-based stereotypes are forbidden.47
But if we look at the basic indicators of social welfare, it is not clear
how much difference the law has made.48 The relative
labormarket status of women has not changed much in the aftermath of
judicial decisions.49 The difference between the earnings of women
and of men was greater in 1980 than it was in 1955, even though the
key Supreme Court decisions were in the 1970s.50 Women continue
to face occupational segregation in the workforce, and the result is
that women disproportionately occupy low-paying positions
traditionally identified as female.51 Thus Gerald Rosenberg's influential
study concludes that "[c]ourt action contributed little to eliminating
discrimination against women. Cases were argued and won but,
litigants aside, little was accomplished."52</p>
      <p>This conclusion is probably too blunt. It is hard to measure the
real-world effects of Supreme Court decisions, and the ban on
unequal treatment by government may well have made an important
difference for many women, even if it is hard for social scientists to
tie real-world changes to judicial decisions. A degree of
agnosticism makes good sense here. But it is highly revealing that the
requirement of formal equality cannot be easily associated with
largescale changes in the social welfare of women.</p>
      <p>46. The most important example is the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, Pub. L.
No. 101-336, 104 Stat. 328 (codified as amended at 42 U.S.C. ?? 12101-12213) (Supp. IV
1992).</p>
      <p>47. See cases cited supra note 31.</p>
      <p>48. See infra text accompanying notes 122-27; see also GERALDN. ROSENBERGT, HE
HOLLOW HOPE 207-12 (1991) (concluding that "[l]itigation has failed to end [sex]
discrimination"); Mary E. Becker, Politics, Differences, and Economic Rights, 1989 U. Cmii.LEGALF.
169, 172-74 (arguing that while antidiscrimination laws have produced progress for women,
they have not made women economically equal to men).</p>
      <p>49. ROSENBERGs,upra note 48, at 207.
50. Id. at 207, 209 tbl. 7.1.
51. Id. at 209-10.
52. Id. at 212.</p>
      <p>Ironically,some existinginequalitiesmay be partlya productof
contemporaryequalitylaw. After
divorce,women'seconomicwelfare goes sharplydown, whereas men's goes sharplyup.53 Legal
rules,not nature,assurethis resultby generallyrefusingto take
account of domesticcontributionsand by refusingto regardthe
husband's success in the employment market as a joint asset. The
relevantrules mightwell be subjectto legal attack.</p>
      <p>Certainlysome existinginequalitiesstem from laws that do not
violate formal equality. Considerveterans' preference laws,
sexbased in effect if not in intent. Such laws are immunefrom attack
under the formal equality standard,but they can have enormous
effects on state employment.54Perhapsmoreimportantis the
existence of a socialsecuritysystemthatwas designedfor
andthatbenefits male breadwinners,while helping women much less because
women do not follow conventionalmale careerpaths.55The failure
to provide adequate protection against rape, sexual harassment,
and other formsof sexual assaultand abusemightalso
raiseequality issues;these failuresraiseno problemsunderthe formalequality
approach.</p>
      <p>Now we are in a position to make some general observations
about the question of race and sex differences. The question for
decisionis not whetherthereis a difference- often there certainly
is - but whetherthe legal and social treatmentof that difference
can be adequatelyjustified. Differencesneed not implyinequality,
and only some differenceshave that implication.Whendifferences
do have that implication,the implicationis a resultof legal and
social practices,not the resultof differencesalone. Because they are
legal and social, these practicesmightbe alteredeven if the
differences remain.56Existinglaw recognizesthis point insofaras formal
discriminationon the basis of race and sex is prohibitedeven if
based on differencesthat are "real"in the sense that as a matterof
simple fact, blacks are not similarlysituatedto whites and women
53. See OKIN,supra note 18, at 160-67, 337; LENOREJ. WEITZMANT,HE DIVORCE
REVOLUTION337-40 (1985).</p>
      <p>54. See Personnel Admr. v. Feeney, 442 U.S. 256, 259 (1979) (holding that a
Massachusetts law giving absolute lifetime preferences to veterans for civil service positions does not
violate the Equal Protection Clause even though the law "operates overwhelmingly to the
advantage of males").</p>
      <p>55. See Becker, supra note 48, at 176-78 (citing statistics to show the adverse
consequences of structural discrimination in the social security system).</p>
      <p>56. See MACKINNONs,upra note 44, at 32-45 (arguing for an equality principle focusing
on gender dominance, not gender difference); see also JOHNRAWLSA, THEORYOFJUSTICE
107-08 (1971) (stressing how the social structure affects the naturally unequal distribution of
talents and privileges).
are not similarlysituatedto men.57But existinglaw stops
shortinsofaras it does not allowattackson discriminatorybut
faciallyneutral practicesbased on an unequalstatusquo.58</p>
      <p>An analogy may be helpful here. The problemsfaced by
disabled people are not a functionof disability"alone"(an
almostimpenetrableidea - what would currentdisabilitieseven mean in a
different world?) but are instead the result of the
interactionbetween physicaland mentalcapacitieson the one hand and a set of
humanobstaclesmade by and for the able-bodiedon the other. It
is those humanobstacles,ratherthan the capacitiestaken as brute
facts, that create a largepartof whatit meansto be disabled. One
could not defend, for example,the constructionof a buildingwith
stairsand withoutmeans of accessfor those on wheelchairson the
ground that those who need wheelchairsare different. The
question is whetherit is acceptable,or just, to constructa buildingthat
excludes people who need an unusualmeans of entry. That
question may not be a simpleone, but it cannotbe answeredsimplyby
pointingto a difference.</p>
      <p>We might conclude that there are two fundamentalproblems
with the "similarlysituated"idea. The firstis that the idea cannot
be made operationalwithouta theoryof some kind. The second is
that the implicittheorybehindthe currentapproachseems hardto
justifyor even to describe. The best defensewouldsuggestthat the
approachis adaptedto a reasonableunderstandingof equality,or
several reasonable understandingsw,hile at the same time being
uniquelywell suited to judicialadministration.This defense is far
from implausible,but it suggeststhat a fulljustificationof the
constitutionalequalityprincipleremainsto be offered.</p>
      <p>II. THE ANTICASTEPRINCIPLE</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>A. Definition</title>
      <p>I suggest that in American constitutionallaw, an important
equality principlestems from opposition to caste. This principle
grows out of the originalrejectionof the monarchicallegacy59and
57. See, e.g., Califano v. Goldfarb, 430 U.S. 199 (1977) (plurality opinion) (forbidding
discrimination in social security even though men are less frequently dependent on their
spouses than are women); see also J.E.B. v. Alabama ex rel. T.B., 114 S. Ct. 1419, 1427 n.l1
(1994) (stating that peremptory challenges are forbidden even if women's perceptions really
are different from men's); 114 S. Ct. at 1432 (O'Connor, J., concurring) (emphasizing that law
does not always take real differences into account).</p>
      <p>58. See, e.g., Feeney, 442 U.S. at 260.</p>
      <p>59. See GORDONS. WOOD,THE RADICALISMOFTHEAMERICANREVOLUTION95-109
(1992) (discussing consequences of the attack on monarchical heritage).
private choices, as in the selection of dancing partners. When I
speak of the impermissibility of turning morally irrelevant factors
into a systematic source of social disadvantage, I do not mean to
deny that in many settings morally irrelevant factors may well be
used. But even this point leaves numerous open questions. We do
not have anything like a full account of what sorts of differences are
relevant to legitimate official judgments. Can such an account be
provided here?</p>
      <p>For lawyers, at least, many of the political and moral
complexities can be bracketed. Perhaps those involved in the legal system
can build on the general understanding that race and gender are
irrelevant from the moral point of view without making complex
and perhaps sectarian claims about moral relevance in general.
Indeed, one happy feature of legal thinking is that participants in legal
disputes can often bracket large-scale claims about the right and the
good and build incompletely theorized agreements about particular
issues.78 There is general public or judicial agreement that race and
sex are morally irrelevant in the sense that the distribution of social
benefits and burdens ought not to depend on skin color or gender.
This agreement is founded on good reasons, because both of these
are accidents of birth, because accidents of birth should not
produce second-class citizenship, and because it is hard to imagine an
account that would justify lesser benefits or greater burdens by
reference to these particular accidents.79 To say this is not to say that
social roles must have nothing to do with gender; many people
think that roles and gender cannot be entirely separated. But it is
to say that social disadvantage cannot be justified by reference to
race or sex alone, and that point is sufficient for my purposes here.</p>
      <p>Nor, for lawyers, is the notion of moral irrelevance a new one.
The anticaste principle has distinctive historical roots. Recall that
the Constitution forbids titles of nobility and that an important part
of the founding creed involved the rejection of the monarchical
heritage, largely on the ground that monarchy made caste distinctions
78. This idea is discussed in Cass R. Sunstein, Rules and Analogies, 17 THE TANNER
LECTURES ON HUMAN VALUES (forthcoming 1995); it has an obvious resemblance to the
idea of "overlapping consensus" as found in RAWLSP,OLITICALLIBERALISMsu,pra note 67,
at 133-72.</p>
      <p>79. Compare on this score such accidents of birth as great strength or intelligence or
ability to produce products that the market rewards. These accidents may be entangled with
nonaccidental factors; promoting them brings about desirable incentives and also is
associated with a range of valuable social goals, like increased productivity. Of course it would be
possible to say that when people do not like people of certain races, there is a productivity
loss from forbidding them to indulge their "taste" - sometimes this may even be true - but
this productivity loss seems inadequate to overcome the basic case offered in the text.
among fundamentally equal human beings.80 The Civil War
Amendments were rooted in a judgment about the moral
irrelevance of race, formerlytaken to be relevantbecause of nature. In
the aftermathof the AmericanCivilWara high U.S. officialstated,
"God himself has set His seal of distinctivedifferencebetween the
two races, and no human legislation can overrule the Divine
decree."81In the same period, antidiscriminatio nlaw was challenged
squarelyon the groundthat it put the two racesin
"unnaturarlelation" to each other.82</p>
      <p>The Civil War Amendmentswere based on a wholesale
rejection of the supposednaturalnessof racialhierarchy.The hierarchy
was thought to be a functionnot of naturaldifferencebut of law,
most notablythe law of slaveryand the variousmeasuresthat grew
up in the aftermathof abolition. An importantpurposeof the Civil
War Amendmentswas the attack on racial caste.83Thus Senator
Howardexplainedthat the purposeof the FourteenthAmendment
was to "abolish[] all class legislationin the States and [do] away
with the injusticeof subjectingone caste of persons to a code not
applicable to another."84The defining case of the Black Codes,
placingspecialdisabilitieson the freedmen'slegal
capacities,exemplified the concern with caste legislation.85Thus Justice Harlan,
dissenting in Plessy v. Perguson,86wrote one of the greatest
sentencesin Americanlaw: "Thereis no caste
here."87Contemporaryunderstandingsof sex inequalitybuild on this basic idea.88</p>
      <p>I do not contend that the anticaste principle,as I describe it
here, can be understoodas a mechanicalreflectionof pre- and
postCivil War aspirations. The ratifiersdid believe that caste or class
legislation was forbidden;but they did not fully unpackthe
category. They understood that legislation always made distinctions
80. See WOOD,supra note 59, at 254-61 (arguing that although the Federalists and the
anti-Federalists disagreed as to how privileged the government leaders needed to be, both
opposed monarchical hierarchy based on heredity alone).</p>
      <p>81. 2 CONG.REC. app. at 3 (1874) (speech of Rep. Southard).
82. 3 CONG.REC.983 (1875) (statement of Rep. Eldredge).</p>
      <p>83. See Charles Fairman,Does the FourteenthAmendment Incorporate the Bill of Rights?,
2 STAN.L. REV.5 (1949) (arguing that the framers of the Fourteenth Amendment intended
to forbid discrimination against blacks at the state level).</p>
      <p>84. CONG.GLOBE,39th Cong., 1st Sess. 2766 (1866).</p>
      <p>85. See John Harrison, Reconstructing the Privileges or Immunities Clause, 101 YALEL.J.
1385, 1413 (1992) (explaining how Black Codes were used to prevent blacks from enjoying a
wide variety of social and legal privileges available to whites, including testifying in court and
owning property).</p>
      <p>86. 163 U.S. 537 (1896).
87. 163 U.S. at 559.
88. See Okin, supra note 77.
amongpersons,and they thoughtthe categoryof caste or class
legislation was a small subset of legislation, involving illegitimate
groundsfor differentialtreatment. In seeing what counted as
illegitimategrounds,they looked not to theorybut to slaveryand the
Black Codes as definingillustrations.So far there is considerable
overlap between an importantstrandin the Civil Warperiod and
what I am urging here. But the Civil War Amendments were
targeted at caste legislation,that is, at specificlaws that embodied
discriminationand in this way helped to create caste. This is what
JusticeHarlanhad in mindin Plessy. Therewas no
generalunderstandingthat these amendmentsimposedon governmenta general
duty to remove caste statusor bannednondiscriminatorylaws that
contributedto caste status - even if it was understoodthat
Congresswouldhave the powerto counteractthe legacyof slaverywith
affirmativelegislation.89</p>
      <p>The anticaste principleas I understandit here is more
ambitious. It is not directedmerelyat caste legislationbut more
generally at a social status quo that, through historical and current
practices,createssecond-classstatus. We can understandthis
principle as emphasizinglegislativeratherthan judicial duties and as
reading the Civil WarAmendmentsthroughthe lens of the New
Deal, which reflected an understandingthat social practices are
often a creationof law,at leastin part,andthatgovernmentis
legitimatelymade responsiblefor practicesthat producesocial evils,
including pervasive deprivation.90 Reading the Civil War
Amendmentsthroughthe lens of the New Deal,91we might see a
constitutionalproblemnot only withparticularcaste legislationbut
with lower-castestatusin general.</p>
      <p>Thus far I have emphasizedsocial consensusand history.
Perhapslawyerscanbuildon these sources,but an adequateaccountof
the subject of caste and moral irrelevancecould not rest content
withsocialagreementandwiththe past. I cannotofferthataccount
here, but a few observationsmaybe helpful. If the notion of moral
89. See generally Eric Schnapper, Affirmative Action and the Legislative History of the
FourteenthAmendment, 71 VA. L. REV.753, 796-97 (1985).</p>
      <p>90. See BRUCEACKERMAN, WE THEPEOPLE:FOUNDATION1S00-04 (1991) (seeing both
the Lochner Court and the New Deal as attempts to synthesize a coherent framework of
rights out of existing sources of legal doctrine, including the Civil War Amendments);
SUNSTEIN,supra note *, at 40-67 (arguing that New Deal jurisprudence recognized that social
practices determining ownership rights, labor rights, and civil rights were themselves
products of the legal regime).</p>
      <p>91. See the discussion of "synthesis" in ACKERMANs,upra note 90, at 140-50 (arguing
that Brown v. Board of Education, 347 U.S. 483 (1954), reinterpreted Fourteenth
Amendment equal protection requirements in light of post-Plessy social developments).
irrelevance involves a lack of connection to either entitlement or
desert, we might think that a wide range of differences among
people are indeed morally arbitrary, in the sense that such differences
do not by themselves justify more resources or greater welfare. In a
market economy, those morally irrelevant differences are quite
frequently translated into social disadvantages. Consider educational
background, intelligence, physical strength, and existing supply and
demand curves for various products and services. Certainly
someone does not deserve more goods and services merely by virtue of
the fact that many people want what he is able to provide.
Consider an especially fast run from one side of a tennis court to
another, or a book about a murder that is especially entertaining to
read. For good instrumental reasons, including the production of
desired commodities, we may well want to reward people who can
provide widely valued goods; but the relationship between that
talent and desert or entitlement is obscure.</p>
      <p>In a market economy, many factors - strength, intelligence,
and educational background - affect resources and welfare, and
most of these factors are arbitraryfrom the moral point of view. Is
someone really entitled to more money because he was born into a
family that stressed education, or because of his intelligence, or
because he happened to produce a commodity that many people like?
Markets do reward qualities that are irrelevant from a moral point
of view. But it would be difficult indeed to justify a principle that
would attempt, through law, to counteract all or most of the factors
that markets make relevant. The reason is that in general, the
recognition of such factors is inseparable from the operation of a
market economy, and by and large, a market economy is a source of
many important human goods, including individual freedom,
economic growth and prosperity, and respect for different conceptions
of the good. Any legal solutions that call for major intrusions on
markets must be evaluated in light of the effects on various possible
human goods that those alleged solutions will compromise. If legal
remedies produce more unemployment, greater poverty, and higher
prices for food and other basic necessities, they are, to that extent, a
bad idea.</p>
      <p>The implementation and reach of any anticaste principle should
depend on considerations of this kind. The point is not that human
equality should be "traded off" against the seemingly sterile and
abstract notion of market efficiency. I do not claim that otherwise
unjustified inequality can be supported by some intrinsic good
called "efficiency." Efficiency is an instrumental good, though no
less important for that. I argue only that intrusions on markets may
defeat valuable human goals and that this is important to keep in
mind.</p>
      <p>To be more precise: The use of the factors that ordinarily
underlie markets is at least sometimes, though of course not always, in
the interest of the most disadvantaged, certainly in the sense that
lower prices and higher employment are especially valuable to the
poor. When this is so, any government initiative that would bar use
of those factors - intelligence, production of socially valued goods,
and so forth - seems perverse.92 Moreover, a principle that would
override all morally irrelevant factors would impose extraordinary
costs on society, both in its implementation and administrative
expense and in its infliction of losses on a wide range of people. The
anticaste principle seems to have greatest appeal in discrete
contexts in which gains from current practice to the least well-off are
hard to imagine; in which second-class citizenship is systemic and
occurs in multiple spheres and along easily identifiable and sharply
defined lines; in which the morally irrelevant characteristic is highly
visible; in which there will be no major threat to a market economy;
and in which the costs of implementation are most unlikely to be
terribly high.</p>
      <p>Ideas of this sort do not justify a judgment that poor people
constitute a lower caste. For one thing, poor people represent a
broad, amorphous, not easily identified, and to some degree shifting
group. When people are poor, we cannot say that social and legal
practices turn a highly visible and morally irrelevant characteristic
into a systemic source of social disadvantage. Of course human
deprivation creates a significant problem of justice, and a
recognizable constitutional understanding tries to provide all people with
freedom from desperate conditions.93 I mean here to identify a
separate understanding - one that supports a legal assault on the
castelike features of the status quo with respect to race, sex, and
disability. It is relevant here that the benefits of antidiscrimination
92. Rawls's difference principle, see RAWLSs,upra note 56, at 60, would almost certainly
fail to justify many of the inequalities that markets introduce, since many of those
inequalities do not benefit the least well-off. But a less rigid set of understandings, allowing
inequalities that benefit most people, including many of the disadvantaged, would justify reliance on
markets, especially in light of the government's ability to use greater aggregate wealth to help
disadvantaged people and to provide a basic floor. See the intriguing finding in NORMAN
FROHLICH&amp; JOE A. OPPENHEIMER, CHOOSINGJUSTICE58-60 (1992), suggesting that in
experimental studies most people choose average utility with a welfare floor, rather than the
difference principle.</p>
      <p>93. See supra note 69.
law do seem substantial,and the negative effects on the economy</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>Judges and Legislators</title>
      <p>Originallythe FourteenthAmendmentto the Constitutionwas
understoodas an effort to eliminateracialcaste
emphaticallynot
as a ban on distinctionson the basis of race.95 A prohibitionon
racial caste is of course differentfrom a prohibitionon racial
distinctions. A ban on racialdistinctionswouldexcise all use of race in
decisionmaking.By contrast,a ban on caste mightwell drawsome
measureshaving discriminatoryeffects into question, and it would
certainlyallow affirmativeaction programs.96</p>
      <p>Originally,Congress,not the courts,was to be the
principalinstitution for implementingthe FourteenthAmendment. The basic
idea was that Congress would transformthe status of the newly
freed slaves by engagingin a wide rangeof remedialmeasures.97It
was not at all anticipatedthat federaljudges
responsiblefor the
which establishedslaveryas a constitutionalright
then-recent and highly visible Dred Scott v. Sanford98 decision,
would be
enforcingthe Amendment. Indeed,the notion thatjudgeswould play
a major role in helping to bring about equality under law was
entirely foreign to the drafters and ratifiers of the Civil War
Amendments.</p>
      <p>At some stage in the twentieth century, there was a dramatic
changein the legal culture'sunderstandingof the notion of equality
under the Constitution. The anticaste principle was transformed
94. See John J. Donohue III, Employment Discrimination Law in Perspective: Three
Concepts of Equality, 92 MICH.L. REV. 2583, 2600-01 (1994) (this issue) (describing
antidiscrimination laws as correcting market imperfections to some extent); James J. Heckman &amp;
Brook S. Payner, Determining the Impact of Antidiscrimination Policy on the Economic
Status of Blacks: A Study of South Carolina, 79 AM. ECON.REV. 138 (1989) (concluding that
federal antidiscrimination law may account for increased wages and employment among
blacks in the South Carolina textile manufacturing industry).</p>
      <p>95. This idea is supported by Justice Harlan's statement "There is no caste here," which
appears in his dissenting opinion in Plessy v. Ferguson, 163 U.S. 537, 559 (1896), in the
sentence immediately preceding his famous assertion that "[o]ur Constitution is color-blind."
163 U.S. at 559. See the excellent discussion in T. Alexander Aleinikoff, Re-Reading Justice
Harlan's Dissent in Plessy v. Ferguson: Freedom, Antiracism, and Citizenship, 1992 U. ILL.L.
REV. 961 (maintaining that Justice Harlan's dissent in Plessy can be read to support
raceconscious programs that combat subordination).</p>
      <p>96. See Schnapper, supra note 89, at 789-98 (arguing that history does not support the
attack on affirmative action).</p>
      <p>97. See id. at 784-88 (arguing that Congress intended the Fourteenth Amendment to
provide a constitutional basis for An Act To Establish a Bureau for the Relief of Freedmen and
Refugees, ch. 90, 13 Stat. 507 (1865) [hereinafter Freedmen's Bureau Act]).
into an antidifferentiation principle.99 No longer was the issue the
elimination of second-class citizenship. The focus shifted instead to
the entirely different question whether people who were similarly
situated had been treated similarly - a fundamental change. This
shift in focus remains one of the great untold stories of American
constitutional history.</p>
      <p>So long as the courts were to be the institution entrusted with
enforcing the Equal Protection Clause, the shift was fully
intelligible, notwithstanding its problematic relationship with the original
understanding of the Fourteenth Amendment and with the best
understanding of what race and sex inequality really are. The
judiciary simply lacks the necessary tools to implement the anticaste
principle. The transformation in the conception of equality is
therefore understandable in light of what came to be, under the
Fourteenth Amendment, the astonishing institutional importance of
courts and the equally astonishing institutional insignificance of
Congress. But the transformation of an anticaste principle into a
prohibition on racial differentiation has inadequately served the
constitutional commitment to equal protection of the laws.100It has
meant that too little will be done about the second-class citizenship
of blacks, women, and the disabled.</p>
      <p>If the legal culture is to return to the roots of the constitutional
commitment and to a better understanding of equality, the
legislative branch should take the lead. The anticaste principle, if taken
seriously, calls for significant restructuring of social practices. For
this reason legislative and administrative bodies, with their superior
democratic pedigree and fact-finding capacities, can better
implement the principle than can the courts.101</p>
      <p>Of course there are difficult issues of strategy, timing, and
implementation. Some legal interventions may not be fruitful; they
may even be counterproductive. Some may breed confusion and
resentment. Others may be unintelligible. Still others may disrupt
a society's basic organizing frameworks in a way that does great
harm and little good. Outsiders - and insiders too - will often
know too little, and both must be careful about introducing legal
99. The high-water mark of the anticaste understanding was probably Loving v. Virginia,
388 U.S. 1 (1967), with its reference to "White Supremacy." 388 U.S. at 11. The triumph of
the antidifferentiation idea can be found in Washington v. Davis, 426 U.S. 229 (1976), and
City of Richmond v. J.A. Croson Co., 488 U.S. 469 (1989).</p>
      <p>100. For present purposes I do not discuss the possibility that the Privileges or
Immunities Clause would be a better source of the equality principle of the Fourteenth Amendment.</p>
      <p>101. See ROSENBERG, supra note 48, at 336-43 (arguing that courts alone can do little in
the way of social reform).
principles that do not cohere with cultural norms. Context will
thereforemattera greatdeal. But these issuesconcernquite
different mattersfrom the issue of principlethat I am now discussing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>3. SuspectClasses</title>
      <p>Whatis the relationshipbetween the anticasteprincipleand the
familiaridea that some classificationsare "suspect,"in the sense
that the courts will be hostile to discriminationagainst certain
groups? We can start by observing that the Supreme Court has
granted heightened scrutinyto laws that discriminateagainst
certain identifiablegroupsthoughtlikely to be at particularrisk in the
ordinarypolitical process.102When the Court grants heightened
scrutiny,it is highlyskepticalof legislation,and the burdenof every
doubt operateson behalfof groupschallengingthe relevantlaws.103</p>
      <p>The difference between the two ideas can be describedin the
following way: The notion of suspect classificationsis based on a
fear that illegitimateconsiderationsare likely to lie behind
legislation, whereas the anticasteprincipleis designed to ensure against
second-classstatusfor certainsocialgroups. The two ideas overlap,
because lowercastes maywell be subjectto legislationgroundedon
illegitimateconsiderations. But the two ideas are nonetheless
distinct, because illegitimateconsiderationsmay lie behindlegislation
discriminatingagainstgroupsthat do not count as lower castes, and
because the anticasteprincipleimposes duties on governmentthat
go well beyond a ban on illegitimatelymotivatedlegislation.</p>
      <p>In decidingwhetherto grantheightenedscrutiny,the Courthas
not been altogetherclear aboutits underlyingrationale. The Court
appears to have examined a set of factors - above all, the
relevance of the group characteristicto legitimategovernmentalends,
the likelihood that the group in question will be subjectto
prejudice, the immutabilityof the characteristict,he existenceof past and
102. See Croson,488 U.S. at 470-72(applyingstrictscrutinyto legislationusing racial
distinctions)C;leburnev. CleburneLivingCtr.,473U.S.432,440-42(1985)(refusingto apply
strictscrutinyto legislationdistinguishingthe mentallyretardedbecauseof the lackof a legal
traditiondisadvantagingthis group);Craigv. Boren, 429 U.S. 190, 204 (1976) (applying
heightenedscrutinyto legislationusinggenderdistinctions).</p>
      <p>103. I am puttingto one side the distinctionbetween"strictscrutiny,"usedin the racial
context,and "intermediatescrutiny,"usedin the contextof sex discriminationA.n
interesting developmentis the Court'srecent suggestionthat it has failed to determinewhether
genderclassificationsare inherentlysuspectandthuswhetherintermediatescrutinyor strict
scrutinyshouldapplyin gendercases,seeJ.E.B.v. Alabamaex rel.T.B., 114S. Ct. 1419,1425
n.6 (1994)(decidinga genderdiscriminationcasewithoutmentioningthe differencebetween
intermediateandstrictscrutiny),thoughit is not clearthatthereis muchdifferencebetween
the two standards.
present discrimination, and the group's lack of political power.104
In this way, it has moved well beyond the defining case of
discrimination against blacks to include discrimination against women,
illegitimate children, and sometimes aliens.105</p>
      <p>Most of these factors have yet to be fully analyzed. They
purport to involve a quasi-factual investigation into real data, but they
actually depend on controversial and usually unidentified
normative judgments. For example, we cannot know whether a
characteristic is "relevant" just by looking at facts. Often race and sex are
relevant to employment decisions, in the sense that profits depend
on them. We cannot know whether a group has historically been
subject to "discrimination" without knowing whether the unequal
treatment was justified; discrimination is of course a value-laden
category.</p>
      <p>Similarly, a major problem with the key issue of political
powerlessness is that relevant judgments are based not simply on
facts about political influence. They also depend on some
controversial and usually unarticulated claims about how much political
power is appropriate for the group in question and about the
legitimacy of the bases for legislative judgments on matters affecting the
group. The claim that a group is politically weak in the
constitutional test is thus a product of controversial and rarely articulated
claims.</p>
      <p>For example, blacks may have a good deal of political power;
they can influence elections, even elections of the President. The
same is true of women, who of course can affect elections a great
deal. The potentially large electoral influence of both groups does
not exclude them from the category of groups entitled to particular
protection against discrimination. The reason is that even if they
can wield political influence, prejudice in the constitutionally
relevant sense is likely to operate against both blacks and women in the
political process. Blacks may be subject to hatred or devaluation;
women may be subject to stereotypes about their appropriate role
that affect their political power and even their own aspirations. The
conclusion is that the category of political powerlessness looks like
an inquiry into political science, but it really depends on some
judgments about the legitimacy of the usual grounds for government
action classifying on the basis of race and sex. The real question is
whether legislation disadvantaging the relevant group is peculiarly
104. See J.E.B., 114 S. Ct. at 1424-26.</p>
      <p>105. See, e.g., Craig v. Boren, 429 U.S. 190 (1978) (women); Graham v. Richardson, 403
U.S. 365 (1971) (illegitimate children); Trimble v. Gordon, 430 U.S. 762 (1977) (aliens).
likely to rest on illegitimategrounds. Heightenedscrutinyis a way
of testing whetherit does.</p>
      <p>This discussion should show that the basic features of the
Court's analysis - the history of discrimination,the category of
prejudice,the inquiryinto whetherthe relevantcharacteristicis
immutable - can be analyzed in the same way. These ideas are
designed to help determine if illegitimateconsiderationstypically
underlie legislation classified on the relevant basis. As noted, a
judgmentthat there has been a history of discriminationdepends
on a theory of appropriatedistribution,at least of a general sort.
We rarelysay that criminalshave suffereda historyof
discrimination, and if we do say so, it is not because they are punishedfor
criminalconduct. To say thatthere has been prejudiceis to say that
the usual grounds for discriminationare impermissible, even
though those groundsmay representgood-faithmoralconvictions.
Consider,for example,the widely held view that women and men
shouldoccupydifferentsocialroles - a view that,despiteits
popularity,may not be used to supportlegislation.
Moreover,immutability is neither a necessarynor a sufficientcondition for suspect
class status. Blind people are not entitled to the
heightenedscrutiny accordedlegislationtargetingsuspectclasses,even though the
conditionof being blindis usuallyimmutable. And if new drugsor
technology allowed blacks to become whites, or vice versa, and
made sex-changeoperationsfeasibleand
cheap,wouldcourtsabandon their careful scrutinyof race and sex discrimination?Surely
not.</p>
      <p>My majorpoint here is that the anticasteprincipleis quite
different from the antidiscriminationprinciple. We might therefore
think that undercurrentdoctrine,discriminationagainst,for
example, Asian Americansand Jews should be
presumedinvalid,without also thinking that Asian Americansand Jews count as lower
castes. The inquiryinto suspectclassificationis thereforequite
different from the inquiryinto caste, thoughthe two ideas do overlap.
4. Discrimination Without Caste? Caste Without Discrimination?</p>
      <p>The above discussionillustratesthat many groupsthat are
frequently subjectto discriminationdo not qualifyas lower castes in
the way I have understoodthat term. It seems reasonableto think
that Asian Americanssufferfromdiscriminationand prejudice,but
it is doubtfulthat they qualifyas a lower caste, becausethey do not
appearto be systematicallybelow othergroupsin termsof the basic
indicatorsof social well-being. The same is true for many other
groupssubjectto discriminationi,ncluding,for
example,homosexuals and Jews. Homosexualsare not a lower caste in the sense that
they are not worse off than heterosexualsin terms of many of the
usual indicatorsof social welfare;they cannot show second-class
citizenshipin this sense. But they are also subjectto
pervasivediscriminationand prejudice,with possibly corrosiveeffects on
selfrespect, and in that sense they are subjectto social
practicesconnected to the issues of caste that I have been discussing.</p>
      <p>Nothing I have said here is meant to legitimatediscrimination
againstgroupsthat have sufferedand continue to suffer from
private and publicprejudice.Forexample,there is indeed an equality
norm that is offended by discriminationon the basis of religion.
ThoughI cannotsupportthe pointhere, I thinkthe same is truefor
discriminationon the basisof sexualorientation. But the anticaste
principledoes not cover groups simply by virtue of the fact that
they are often subjectto illegitimatediscrimination.The anticaste
principlehas special meaningsand uses. It does not exhaust the
several constitutionalprinciplesof equality.</p>
      <p>C. Some Data</p>
      <p>As I have understoodthe matter,the inquiryinto caste has a
large empiricaldimension. The principlefocuses on whether one
groupis systematicallybelow othersalongimportantdimensionsof
social welfare. I offer some relevantinformationhere. Needless to
say, the accountis farfromcomplete. Throughoutthis discussionit
will be useful to recallthat about twelve percentof Americansare
black.</p>
      <p>It is not surprisingto find dramaticdisparitiesbetween whites
and blacks along nearlyall dimensionsof social well-being. Begin
with economicmeasures. The per capitaincomeof whitesis nearly
double that of blacks. The median income of white householdsis
$37,783, as comparedto $21,548for black households.106Nearly
one-third of black Americanslive below the poverty level,
compared to about one-tenth of white Americans.107Ten percent of
whites over sixty-fivelive below the poverty line, as comparedto
about a thirdof blacks.108Perhapsworstof all, 45% of
blackchildrenlive below the povertyline, as comparedto 16%of white
chil106. BUREAU OF THE CENSUS, U.S. DEPT. OF COMMERCE, STATISTICAL ABSTRACT OF
THE UNITED STATES 1993, at 467 tbl. 732, 462 tbl. 721 (113th ed. 1993) [hereinafter
STATISTICAL ABSTRACT].</p>
      <p>107. Id. at 471 tbl. 740.
108. Id. at 470 tbl. 739.
dren.109 About a quarter of black households earn less than
$10,000 per year, compared to fewer than 10% of white
households.110</p>
      <p>Thereare also strikingdisparitieswithrespectto unemployment
levels. In 1992, 6.5% of whites were unemployed,as comparedto
14.1%of blacks.1l Disparitiesof this sort persistover time.
Consider the charton the followingpages:
109. Id. at 469 tbl. 736.
110. Id. at 464 tbl. 725.
111. Id. at 413 tbl. 652.
1950
1951
1952
1953
1954
1955
1956
1957
1958
1959
1960
1961
1962
1963
1964
1965
1966
1967
1968
1969
1970
1971
[Percent; monthly data seasonally adjusted]
112. ECONOMICREPORTOFTHEPRESIDENT315 tbl. B-41 (1994) (footnote omitted).</p>
      <p>BY DEMOGRAPHIC
[Percent; monthly data seasonally adjusted]</p>
      <p>We might turn to education, longevity, and crime. Over 80% of
whites have completed high school, while about two-thirds of blacks
have their high school diplomas.113 About 23% of whites have
completed a college degree, as compared to about 13% of blacks.114
The life expectancy of a white American is four years longer than
the life expectancy of a black American.115 From 1970 to 1990,
about ten people per 100,000 were murdered each year.116 During
this same period, the annual murder rate for white men ranged
from seven to ten per 100,000, compared to a range of fifty to eighty
for black men.117 Similarly, the murder rate for white women was
between two and three per 100,000, compared to ten to fifteen for
black women.118 In 1991, thirty whites out of a thousand were
subject to a crime against their person, down from thirty-two in 1973,
but forty-four blacks out of a thousand were subject to such a
crime, up from forty-two in 1973.119</p>
      <p>Consider political representation. Of the 435 members of the
House of Representatives, only forty are black. In the Senate, the
numbers are even more striking: of the one hundred senators, only
one is black.120There are also inequalities in political participation.
About 70% of white people were registered to vote, as compared to
64% of blacks, in the 1992 elections. There are slightly higher
disparities for voting itself, showing about a 10% differential in the last
presidential election.121</p>
      <p>With respect to sex inequality, most of the numbers are far less
dramatic. Women's life expectancy is higher than that of men.122
The educational attainment of men and women is about the same,
especially in light of changes over the past twenty years - though
white men are significantly more likely to be college graduates than
white women.123 Most of the disparities between men and women
involve income, wealth, and political representation.</p>
      <p>113. STATISTICAALBSTRACT, supra note 106, at 153 tbl. 232.
114. Id.
115. Id. at 85 tbl. 115.
116. Id. at 94 tbl. 129.
117. Id.
118. Id.
119. Id. at 197 tbl. 309.</p>
      <p>120. Telephone Conversation with the Office of the Congressional Black Caucus (Sept. 1,
1994).</p>
      <p>121. STATISTICAALBSTRACT, supra note 106, at 283 tbl. 454.
122. Id. at 85 tbl. 116.
123. Id. at 153 tbl. 231.</p>
      <p>The basic economic indicatorsshow large differences. About
69.3% of women are in the labor force, as comparedto 88.9% of
men. The median yearly earningsof women is $24,000,compared
to $35,850for men. At every stage of educationalattainment,men
out-earn women by a substantialmargin. The average annual
income of a womanhighschool graduateis about$19,000;for a man,
the averageis about $28,000. For a womanwith some college
education, the annual figure is over $22,000, as compared to over
$33,000for a man. For a womanwho has at least a
bachelor'sdegree, the annual figure is about $33,000, as compared to over
$50,000for a man.124</p>
      <p>The poverty rate for single-mother families is 59%.125 Note in
this regardthat 15,396childrenundereighteen live only with their
mother, comparedto the 2182 who live with their father only.126
And after divorce,the averagestandardof living of men increases
by 42%, whereas that of women decreases by 73%.127 There are
388 male representativesin the House of Representatives and
forty-eight women.128Of one hundred senators, only seven are
women.129</p>
      <p>This is merely a brief collection of
informationshowinggroupbased disparitiesthat bear on the question of
second-classcitizenship. As we will soon see, the informationsuggestsa need to shift
from judicial to legislative forums - and also, ironically,to use
race- and gender-neutralremedies.</p>
      <p>III. THE FUTURE</p>
      <p>A. From Antidiscrimination to Anticaste</p>
      <p>Equality law has had two principalstages. The first was
concerned with preventing explicit discrimination,public or private,
againstblacks and women. This includedthe attackon American
apartheid,led by ThurgoodMarshalland culminatingin Brown v.
Board of Education,130and also the attackon explicitsex
discrimination,led by Ruth Bader Ginsburg.131The legal assaulton public
124. Id. at 394 tbl. 624,467 tbl.731.
125. Id. at 470 tbl. 737.
126. Id. at 63 tbl. 79.</p>
      <p>127. OKIN,supra note 18, at 161. These are contested figures, though the claim of a
general disparity is uncontroversial.</p>
      <p>128. 1994 CONGRESSIONASLTAFFDIRECTORYat xix-xxvi (Ann L. Brownson ed., 1994).
129. Id. at xvii-xviii.
130. 347 U.S. 483 (1954).
131. See, e.g., Califanov. Goldfarb,430 U.S. 199(1977).
discrimination was eventually matched by the statutory attack on
private discrimination.132The second stage consisted of challenges
to public and private practices that did not involve explicit
discrimination but that stemmed from prejudice or that otherwise had large
and not adequately justified discriminatory effects.133 This second
stage built on the first. Neither has entirely run its course.</p>
      <p>Both of these movements for reform had substantial success,
certainly in eliminating the most conspicuously unsupportable
public and private practices. Both were connected with anticaste goals,
and to the extent that they operated within the judiciary, they were
also well adapted to the limited institutional capacities of the
judiciary.134 On the other hand, the successes, important as they have
been, have had ambiguous effects on the inequalities discussed
above. From what has been said thus far, it should be clear that if
the elimination of second-class citizenship is an important social
goal, it would be valuable to start in new directions, some of which
have not typically been associated with civil rights at all.</p>
      <p>If opposition to caste is a basic goal, civil rights policy should
concern itself first and foremost with such problems as lack of
opportunities for education, training, and employment; inadequate
housing, food, and health care; vulnerability to crime, both public
and private; incentives to participate in crime; disproportionate
subjection to environmental hazards; and teenage pregnancy and
single-parent families. Policies of this kind suggest a major shift in
direction from the more narrowly focused antidiscrimination
policies of the past.</p>
      <p>This is hardly the place for a full program for legislative reform.
But in resolving current problems, most of the traditional claims of
civil rights law provide incomplete help. The problem is not rooted
in explicitly race- or sex-based classification, nor does it lie in
prejudice, at least not in any simple sense.135 It lies instead in policies
and programs that contribute to second-class status, often in
ex132. See, e.g., Civil Rights Act of 1964, Pub. L. No. 88-352, tit. VII, 78 Stat. 241, 253-66
(codified as amended principally at 42 U.S.C. ?? 2000e to 2000e-17 (1988 &amp; Supp. III 1991)).</p>
      <p>133. See, e.g., Voting Rights Act Amendments of 1982, Pub. L. No. 97-205, 96 Stat. 131
(codified at 42 U.S.C. ? 1973b (1988)); Civil Rights Act of 1964, Pub. L. No. 88-352, tit. VII,
78 Stat. 241, 253-66 (codified as amended principally at 42 U.S.C. ?? 2000e to 2000e-17 (1988
&amp; Supp. III 1991)).</p>
      <p>134. But see ROSENBERGsu,pra note 48, at 169, 226-27 (arguing that the Court has been
unable to improve the lot of women or blacks and that any progress achieved by these two
groups usually resulted from extrajudicial forces).</p>
      <p>135. The problem may well lie in a form of selective racial empathy and indifference, but
this notion is hard to administer, for reasons well discussed in Strauss, supra note 38, at 939,
988-90.
tremely complex ways involving interactions between past practices
and a wide array of current policies.136</p>
      <p>In proposing reforms, we might look quite eclectically at a range
of protections against the sorts of disparities discussed above. For
example, policies promoting economic growth are an important
part of equality law insofar as growth is associated with
employment and the reduction of poverty. But because the association is
imperfect,137many other steps are necessary. I simply note a few
possibilities here; of course a range of details would be required in
order to assess any of them.</p>
      <p>Targeted educational policies, including efforts to promote
literacy and Head Start programs, provide promising models.138 At
least partial successes have resulted from parental leave and
"flextime" policies.139 Certainly, employment-related policies are
important insofar as job increases are closely connected with the
reduction of poverty. In the area of voting rights law, the race-neutral
remedy of cumulative voting might be preferable to racially explicit
approaches.140 Consider as well recent initiatives designed to
reduce violence generally and violence against women in particular
- through education, additional government resources for crime
prevention and punishment, and new legal remedies for victims of
sex-related violence.141 We might compare these with President
Clinton's recent executive order on environmental justice, designed
to prevent disproportionate health and safety effects from the
existence of environmental hazards.142</p>
      <p>136. A model discussion is CHRISTOPHEJRENCKST,HE HOMELESS(1994) (tracing the
causes of increased homelessness to a variety of indifferent or well-intentioned governmental
and social actions, such as the destruction of skid row housing and the deinstitutionalization
of the mentally ill).</p>
      <p>137. See Sunstein, supra note 64, at 1307-08 (arguing that the productivity gains leading
to economic growth can actually fail to help the poor).</p>
      <p>138. See Laura A. Miller, Head Start: A Moving Target,5 YALEL. &amp; POLY.REV. 322
(1987) (portraying Head Start as one of the clear success stories of the Great Society).</p>
      <p>139. See Ruth Bader Ginsburg &amp; Barbara Flagg, Some Reflections on the Feminist Legal
Thought in the 1970's, 1989 U. CHI.LEGALF. 9.</p>
      <p>140. See LANIGUINIERT,HETYRANNYOFTHEMAJORITY149 (1994); Richard H. Pildes,
Gimme Five, NEWREPUBLICM,ar. 1, 1993, at 16.</p>
      <p>141. See, e.g., Violence Against Women Act, S. 11, 103d Cong., 1st Sess. (1993); H.R.
1133, 103d Cong., 1st Sess. (1993).</p>
      <p>142. Exec. Order No. 12,898, 59 Fed. Reg. 7629 (1994).</p>
      <p>Of course there are limits to how much legal reformcan do to
redressthese problems,at least in the shortrun. But there is much
that law can do to help.143</p>
      <p>B.</p>
      <p>On the accountI have offered, there is no
constitutionalobjection to genuinelyremedialrace- and sex-consciouspolicies,at least
as a general rule.144If a basic goal is oppositionto caste,
affirmative action policies are ordinarilypermissible. Partly this lesson
stems from the historyof the Civil WarAmendments;if historyis
relevant,it is hard to supportthe view that affirmativeaction
programsare invalid.145But partlyit is a lesson of logic. We have seen
that in an importantway the antidiscriminationprincipleis
continuous with the affirmativeaction principle. Insofaras
statisticaldiscriminationis outlawed,the governmenthas singled out one form
of rationalcategorizationand subjectedit to special disability. At
least along this dimension,the antidiscriminationprinciplepartakes
of an affirmativeaction principle.</p>
      <p>To be sure, it may be possible to generalizefrom the Civil War
Amendmentsa generaloppositionto the use of skin color as a basis
for the distributionof social benefits and burdens. Perhaps we
should say that governmentought never or rarelyto considerskin
color in its officialdecisions,becauseuse of skin color has bad
educational and expressiveeffects, and because it legitimatesthe view
that people should see each other, and themselves,in racialterms.
But this view is historicallyadventurous,14a6nd it would also
involve a highly intrusiverole for the courts.
Race-consciousprograms occupy an exceptionallywide range. They can be found in
143. See, e.g., CASS N. SUNSTEIN, AFTER THE RIGHTSREVOLUTION77-81 (1990);
Donohue, supra note 94 (arguing that employment discrimination laws successfully reduced
discrimination); Miller, supra note 138 (describing the successes of the Head Start program).</p>
      <p>144. A qualification is necessary here. Many race- and sex-conscious programs may be
only pretextually remedial, especially in the gender context, in which purportedly remedial
measures may in fact be discriminatory. See, e.g., Weinberger v. Wiesenfeld, 420 U.S. 636
(1975) (striking down a social security law giving benefits to women but not to men because
the provision actually reflected irrational gender stereotypes). Also, some approaches might
be too crudely connected with remedial goals, see, e.g., Metro Broadcasting, Inc. v. Federal
Communications Commn., 497 U.S. 547 (1991) (upholding a race-conscious approach despite
its crudeness), or perhaps with rigid quotas, see, e.g., City of Richmond v. J.A. Croson Co.,
488 U.S. 469 (1989).</p>
      <p>145. See Schnapper, supra note 89, at 789-98 (arguing that history does not support
opposition to affirmative action programs).</p>
      <p>146. See id. at 797-98 (arguing that courts categorically condemning "benign racial
distinctions" such as affirmative action programs ignore the 130-year-old intentions expressed
by Congress in the Freedmen's Bureau Act).
education, employment, licensing, and elsewhere.147They have
been accepted at local, state, and federal levels and by
courts,administrators,presidents,and legislatures;14t8hey have come from
people whose views sharply diverge, includingconservativesand
liberalsalike - both Democratsand Republicanshave supported
them.149In these circumstancesj,udges shouldbe
extremelyreluctant to say that there is anythinglike a flat ban on race-conscious
programs.</p>
      <p>It mightbe
concludedthatrace-andsex-consciousremedialpolicies are not merelyunobjectionablebut even mandatoryunderan
anticasteprinciple. Perhapssuch policies are necessaryin orderto
counteract second-class status; certainly many people have so
thought. But suchpolicieshave a mixedrecord,andin some places
and ways, they have been a conspicuousfailure. Some platitudes
are worth repeating: In some places, race-consciousjudgments
have stigmatizedtheir purportedbeneficiaries,by making people
think that blacks are present only because of their skin color. In
some places, such judgmentshave fueled hostility and increased
feelings of second-classcitizenship.Some people who woulddo
extremely well in some good institutions - schools or jobs - are
placed by affirmativeactionin programsor positionsin whichthey
perform far less well, with harmful consequences for their
selfrespect. Ironically, affirmative action programs can aggravate
problemsof caste by increasingthe social perceptionthat a highly
visible feature like skin color is associated with undesirable
characteristics.</p>
      <p>In part the failureshave stemmedfrom resistanceto any
remedies at all for the legacyof discriminationa,ndit wouldbe wrongto
discount the extent to which opposition to affirmativeaction can
stem from oppositionto any changein the statusquo. But in part
the failure has stemmedfrom a general convictionthat skin color
and gender should not matterto social outcomes. In view of both
history and principle,that convictionshould not be discountedor
147. See, e.g., Freeman v. Pitts, 112 S. Ct. 1430 (1992) (busing to desegregate Georgia
schools); Metro Broadcasting, Inc. v. Federal Communications Commn., 497 U.S. 547 (1990)
(minority preferences for broadcast licenses); Wygant v. Jackson Bd. of Educ., 476 U.S. 267
(1986) (layoffs allocated partly by race).</p>
      <p>148. See, e.g., City of Richmond v. J.A. Croson Co. 488 U.S. 469 (1989) (local
construction set-aside program); Fullilove v. Klutznick, 448 U.S. 448 (1980) (congressional set-aside
program in construction grants); Regents of the Univ. of Cal. v. Bakke, 438 U.S. 265 (1978)
(state-level university admission program).</p>
      <p>149. See 448 U.S. at 461-62 &amp; n.38 (citing 123 CONG.REC. 12,941-43, 13,242-57 (1977))
(discussing the overwhelming passage of the minority business enterprises program at issue
in Fullilove by both the Senate and the House).
trivialized. It is relevant in this regard that many defenses of
affirmative action programs are hard to offer in public. Often the nature
of affirmative action programs is not discussed publicly because to
do so would be humiliating to the supposed beneficiaries or
intolerable to the public at large.</p>
      <p>Perhaps this is partly a product of the unfortunate rhetoric of
affirmative action.150 But partly it is a result of a deep-seated
resistance to "racialism" as producing frequent unfairness in individual
cases and as inconsistent with widespread convictions about the
relationship between individual achievement and social reward.
Elaborate arguments might be and have been offered to try to
undermine this resistance and these convictions.151 But it is at least
revealing that sometimes these arguments seem too elaborate to
carry much weight before the very people to whom they are aimed.</p>
      <p>I do not mean to say that all or most affirmative action
programs should be abolished. There is too much variety to allow for
sensible global judgments. But we know enough to know that such
programs have often failed and that race-neutral alternatives are
often better.</p>
      <p>These considerations suggest both a presumption in favor of
race- and gender-neutral policies and the need to develop legal
reforms that are not gender- or race-conscious - that do not give rise
to widespread fears that government is playing favorites or is
subject to the lobbying pressure of well-organized private groups. And
it would be possible to administer an anticaste principle in race- and
gender-neutral terms. We can think of many examples, including
broad-based anticrime and antidrug measures; literacy and
educational programs; policies designed to protect children from poor
health and from poverty, including neonatal care and childhood
immunizations;152and programs designed to discourage teen
pregnancy and single-parent families. Policies of this kind could easily
be designed in race- and sex-neutral terms, and such policies would
be directed against many of the important problems faced by both
blacks and women.</p>
      <p>150. See Margaret J. Radin, Affirmative Action Rhetoric, in REASSESSINCGIVILRIGHTS
130, 136-38 (Ellen Paul et al. eds., 1991); see also Thomas Hill, The Message of Affirmative
Action, in REASSESSINGCIVILRIGHTSs,upra, at 108.</p>
      <p>151. See, e.g., Strauss, supra note 19 (arguing that antidiscrimination and affirmative
action are indistinguishable in principle).</p>
      <p>152. Note the enormous disparity between infant mortality rates for blacks and the
corresponding rates for whites. See Gaps in Infant Mortality Rate Still Widening Between Blacks,
Whites, CHI. TRIB.,Apr. 30, 1994, at 19.</p>
      <p>These are some of the directions in which equality law might
move in the future. It is ironic but true that a third stage of civil
rights policy, directed most self-consciously against race and gender
caste, might also be self-consciously designed - for reasons of
policy and principle - so as to avoid race- and gender-specificity.</p>
      <p>CONCLUSION</p>
      <p>In this essay I have criticized three approaches to the problem
of race and sex equality in law. Free markets can accomplish
considerable good in the area of equality as everywhere else, but they
are only a mixed blessing for race and sex equality. Reliance on
existing preferences has related problems, at least to the extent that
those preferences are an artifact of an unjust status quo. The
notion that the law forbids unreasonable distinctions is purely formal.
As often interpreted, the idea has substance behind it, and perhaps
it is well suited to the institutional limits of the judiciary. But the
substance is not simple to defend. It sometimes requires identical
treatment in cases in which distinctions make sense, and ignores
inequality when inequality is present. Sometimes the cause of
equality requires people who are differently situated to be treated
differently, and this is a major gap in constitutional doctrine.</p>
      <p>I have suggested that one of the prevailing constitutional norms
ought to be an anticaste principle, one that forbids social and legal
practices from turning highly visible but morally irrelevant
differences into a basis for second-class citizenship. I have also sought to
show realms in which a system with castelike features persists in
modern American society; this is an area in which a good deal of
information is indispensable. Partly for this reason, the anticaste
principle is mostly for legislative rather than judicial enforcement.
Courts lack the requisite fact-finding capacity and electoral
legitimacy. But this does not mean that others, prominently including
Congress, are relieved of an important and even constitutional
duty, violated by widespread current practices, to eliminate the
castelike features of American society.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          11.
          <article-title>A more detailed discussion, with citations, can be found in Cass R</article-title>
          . Sunstein, Why Markets Don'
          <source>t Stop Discrimination, 8 Soc. PHIL.&amp; POLY</source>
          .
          <volume>22</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          23.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Michael</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>McConnell</surname>
            , How Not To Promote Serious Deliberation About Abortion, 58
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>CHI.L. REV</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>1181</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1190</issue>
          &amp; nn.
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(book review). 2</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

