<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta />
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The President and the Administration</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein &amp; Lawrence Lessig, "The President and the Administration</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>" 94 Columbia Law Review 1</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1994</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>94</volume>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information, please contact unbound@law.uchicago.edu.</p>
      <p>JANUARY 1994</p>
      <p>NO. 1</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Lawrence Lessig* and Cass R Sunstein**</title>
      <p>* Assistant Professor of Law, University of Chicago Law School.</p>
      <p>** Karl N. Llewellyn Professor ofJurisprudence, University of Chicago, Law School
and Department of Political Science. We are grateful to Akhil Amar, Bruce Ackerman,
Steve Calabresi, David Currie, Dan Kahan, Abner Greene, Harold Krent, Alan Meese,
Richard Ross, and Peter Strauss for helpful comments. Cyrus Amir-Mokri provided
exceptional research assistance. For financial support, we are grateful to The Russell Baker
Scholars Fund and The James H. Douglas,Jr. Fund for the Study of Law and Government.</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 1 1994</p>
      <p>INTRODUCTION</p>
      <p>Many think that under our constitutional system, the President must
have the authority to control all government officials who implement the
laws. 1 The text, structure, and history of the Constitution, we are told,
plainly require this result. 2 Under this view, it is therefore something of
an embarrassment that the Supreme Court has permitted conspicuous
exceptions to this constitutional imperative. We now have independent
special counsels, independent agencies, and other such exceptions,
commonly thought to be inconsistent with the basic founding commitment to
a "unitary executive."</p>
      <p>Some believe that this conception of unitariness derives from
something that the framers decided-that the framers constitutionalized a
strongly unitary executive, and that anyone following the original design
must follow this structural pattern.</p>
      <p>We think that the view that the framers constitutionalized anything
like this vision of the executive is just plain myth. It is a creation of the
twentieth century, not the eighteenth. It derives from twentieth century
categories applied unreflectively to an eighteenth century document. It
ignores strong evidence that the framers imagined not a clear executive
hierarchy with the President at the summit, but a large degree of
congressional power to structure the administration as it thought proper.</p>
      <p>We reach this conclusion with reluctance. A strongly unitary
executive can promote important values of accountability, coordination, and
uniformity in the execution of the laws, and to whatever extent these
were the framers' values, they are certainly now ours. If these values are
1. See, e.g., Steven G. Calabresi &amp; Kevin H. Rhodes, The Structural Constitution:
Unitary Executive, Plural Judiciary, 105 Harv. L. Rev. 1153 (1992); David P. Currie, The
Distribution of Powers After Bowsher, 1986 Sup. Ct. Rev. 19; Geoffrey P. Miller,
Independent Agencies, 1986 Sup. Ct. Rev. 41; Theodore B. Olson, Founders Wouldn't
Endorse America's Plural Presidency, Legal Times, Apr. 27, 1987, at 11 [hereinafter Olson,
Plural Presidency]; Theodore Olson, Separation of Powers Principle is No 'Triviality'
(Bowsher v. Synar), Legal Times, July 21, 1986, at 4 [hereinafter Olson, Separation of
powers].</p>
      <p>2. See, e.g., Calabresi &amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1167; Currie, supra note 1, at 31-36;
Miller, supra note 1, at 58-60; Olson, Plural Presidency, supra note 1, at 11-12; Olson,
Separation of Powers, supra note 1, at 4.</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 2 1994
not advanced by the original design, we seemingly face an unpleasant
dilemma-either we adhere to that design and sacrifice important
institutional values, or we advance these institutional values and sacrifice fidelity
to the original design. History apparently leads us to choose between the
original design and a design many now view as indispensable.</p>
      <p>At least this is so unless there is a compelling nonhistorical3
argument supporting a strong unitary design. We believe that there is indeed
a plausible structural argument on behalf of the hierarchical conception
of the unitary executive. This is an argument that emphasizes changed
circumstances since the eighteenth century, and that accommodates the
framers' design within this changed constitutional context-an
argument, that is, that translates 4 the framers' original design from the
language and context of the eighteenth century into the world today.</p>
      <p>3. We use the term "nonhistorical" rather than "nonoriginalist," though at many
points we will speak of originalism, a term that seems to us decreasingly helpful. Just as the
"interpretivist-noninterpretivist" division now seems unsatisfactory, for reasons explained
in Ronald Dworkin, The Forum of Principle, in A Matter of Principle 33, 34-35 (1985), so
it is necessary to question the "originalist-nonoriginalist" division in the context of many
legal disputes, especially those that involve an effort to maintain fidelity to constitutional
commitments in the face of changed circumstances. When circumstances have changed, a
supposedly nonoriginalist interpretation may well have a stronger claim of fidelity to the
original understanding, for reasons suggested in Part III below. The approach that we
advocate may therefore be described as an originalist one. See infra text accompanying
notes 37-47.</p>
      <p>
        4. The metaphor of translation has been used by many people, though in somewhat
different ways. See, e.g., Paul Brest, The Misconceived Quest for the Original
Understanding, 60 B.U. L. Rev. 204, 218-22 (1980) (arguing for nonoriginalist
constitutional interpretation using a historical interpreter as translator); MichaelJ. Perry,
The Authority of Text, Tradition and Reason: A Theory of Constitutional "Interpretation,"
58 S. Cal. L. Rev. 551, 599 (1985) (discussing Robert Bennett as translator); H. Jefferson
Powell, Rules for Originalists, 73 Va. L. Rev. 659, 672 (1987)("[tlo converse with the
founders, you need a translator") (emphasis deleted); Terrance Sandalow, Constitutional
Interpretation, 79 Mich. L. Rev. 1033, 1067-69 (1981) (arguing that no inflexible "core" of
the founders' values exist but that instead each generation must interpret these values
itself); Cass R. Sunstein, Interpreting Statutes in the Regulatory State, 103 Harv. L. Rev.
405, 494-95 (1989) (discussing effect of changed circumstances in interpreting old texts);
Mark V. Tushnet, Following the Rules Laid Down: A Critique of Interpretivism and
Neutral Principles, in Interpreting Law and Literature 193 (Sanford Levinson &amp; Steven
Mailloux eds., 1988) (comparing neutral principle and interpretivist approaches to
interpreting the Constitution). The notion of course was not born with Brest. Perhaps its
most creative pre-Brest appearance was in an extraordinary piece by Felix Cohen, which
linked the process of interpretation across contexts to the theory of relativity, to suggest
that "[t]he achievements of modem mathematics and physics... give ground for hoping
that we shall some day achieve a powerful new organon for mutual understanding,-a
theory of translation." Felix S. Cohen, Field Theory and Judicial Logic, 59 Yale LJ. 238,
272 (1950). Most recently, James Boyd White has discussed the notion of reading as
translation in James B. White, Justice as Translation: An Essay in Cultural and Legal
Criticism (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">1990</xref>
        ). Much earlier, Francis Lieber may have captured much of the sense of
translation in his distinction between "interpretation" and "construction." See Francis
Lieber, Legal and Political Hermeneutics 11, 44 (St. Louis, F.H. Thomas &amp; Co., 3d ed.
1880) ("Interpretation is the art of finding out the true sense of any form of words," while
"[c]onstruction is the drawing of conclusions respecting subjects that lie beyond the
      </p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 3 1994</p>
      <p>After outlining the debate over the origins of a unitary executive in
Part I, this Article goes on to make two basic points. The first, set out in
Part II, is historical. Conventional wisdom insists (1) that the framers
believed in a hierarchical executive branch, with the President in charge
of all administration of the laws,5 and (2) that we must also ensure a
hierarchical executive branch, at least if we are to be faithful to the
framers' constitutional design.6 We think that the conventional wisdom is
wrong on both counts. There is no historically sound reading of the
Constitution that compels anything like the first claim. Any faithful
reader of history must conclude that the unitary executive, conceived in
the foregoing way, is just myth.</p>
      <p>But we also think that this conclusion does not mean that a strongly
unitary conception of the constitutional design is wrong. Part III of this
Article offers a justification of that conception, relying not on false
history, but on the best reading of the framers' structure translated into the
current, and radically transformed, context. Carried into this context,
certain crucial aspects of the unitary executive view make most sense of
the framers' design, even if the application of that design differs
dramatically from the application in the framers' own context.</p>
      <p>In Part III, we therefore discuss the basic commitments of the
original constitutional system-the avoidance of factionalism, political
accountability, a degree of centralization in government, and expedition in
law enforcement-and show that in the face of post-New Deal
developments, those founding commitments would be compromised by limiting
presidential power over the administration of the laws. However ironic it
may be, the claims on behalf of the strongly unitary executive, while
implausible as a matter of simple history, may nonetheless be right as a
matter of constitutional interpretation.</p>
      <p>
        In Part IV, we apply these general propositions to a wide range of
current disputes about the relationship between the President and the
administration. We discuss Congress' power to create independent
prosecutors and independent agencies. We also attempt to sort out a set of
issues that have become prominent in the wake of the Supreme Court's
surprising reentry into this area in the period from 1976 to the present.
expression of the text."). Alfred Hill has described a practice of constitutional
interpretation that may in result be quite similar to the translator's practice. See Alfred
Hill, The Political Dimension of Constitutional Adjudication, 63 S. Cal. L. Rev. 1237 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">1990</xref>
        )
(asserting probable intent of founders was that common practice of the times be
observed). For general treatment of the idea of fidelity as translation, see Lawrence Lessig,
Fidelity in Translation, 71 Tex. L. Rev. 1165 (1993).
      </p>
      <p>5. By administration of the laws, we refer very broadly to all tasks that involve
implementation or execution of legislative enactments.</p>
      <p>6. See infra notes 19-32 and accompanying text.</p>
      <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 4 1994</p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>I. AN OLD (BuT QuITE LWVELY) DEBATE</title>
        <p>Whether the founders framed a strongly unitary executive, or
whether we should continue to recognize what they framed, is not a new
debate. Throughout our history the question has been the subject of
intense controversy.7 Fueled more recently by the work of Presidents,
judges, and academic observers,8 the question has regained center stage.
Before the late 1970s, the question seemed well settled, even if the
answers were to some observers quite-jarring. It was clear that "executive"
functions must be performed by officers subject to the unlimited removal
and broad supervisory power of the President.9 But it was equally clear
that Congress had the constitutional power to remove from the
President's authority officers having "quasi-legislative" and
"quasijudicial" functions.1 0</p>
        <p>In these two sentences could be found the basic wisdom about the
relationship between the President and administrative agencies. Some
unsettled questions remained. But it appeared that those questions
would be answered through accommodations, formal and informal,
between Congress and the President, and not as a matter of constitutional
law.</p>
        <p>All this changed in the 1980s. Spurred by President Reagan's efforts
to assert hierarchical control over the bureaucracy,' the entire field
ex7. See especially the various opinions in Myers v. United States, 272 U.S. 52 (1926);
see also, e.g., Nathan -D. Grundstein, Presidential Power, Administration and
Administrative Law, 18 Geo. Wash. L. Rev. 285, 300 (1950) (discussing debate over extent
of autonomy that executive has in appointing and removing administrators); Miller, supra
note 1, at 52-58 (laying out pragmatic and neoclassical approaches to separation of powers
debate); Peter L. Strauss, The Place ofAgencies in Government: Separation of Powers and
the Fourth Branch, 84 Colum. L. Rev. 573, 599-600 (1984) (noting that the Convention
was "ambivalent" about the President's relation to those who would actually administer the
laws).</p>
        <p>8. See infra text accompanying notes 11-18.</p>
        <p>9. See Myers, 272 U.S. at 161-64. The dispute in Myers involved over President
Wilson's power to remove a regional postmaster without first gaining the consent of Senate
as the statute required. The Court found unconstitutional the statutory provision limiting
the President's removal authority. Myers also sets out three exceptions to this rule. See
infra text accompanying notes 102-108.</p>
        <p>10. See Humphrey's Executor v. United States, 295 U.S. 602, 629 (1935). Humphrey's
involved the power of President Roosevelt to remove a Commissioner from the Federal
Trade Commission. The statute provided for removal by the President only for
"inefficiency, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office." The Court held that, because of
the quasi-legislative and quasijudicial nature of the Commission, these limitations on the
removal power were constitutional.</p>
        <p>11. Reagan's efforts came primarily in the form of executive orders. See Exec. Order
No. 12,291, 3 C.F.R. 127, 128 (1981), reprinted in 5 U.S.C. § 601 (1988) (requiring
agencies to conduct cost-benefit analyses and submit "Regulatory Impact Analyses" of such
analyses to OMB); Exec. Order No. 12,498, 3 C.F.R. 323, 323 (1985), reprinted in 5 U.S.C.
§ 601 (1988) (directing agencies to create and publish yearly regulatory agendas for OMB
approval); see also Thomas 0. McGarrity, Reinventing Rationality: The Role of Regulatory
Analysis in the Federal Bureaucracy 19-24 (1991) (reviewing President Reagan's executive</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 5 1994
perienced a minor revolution. Sharp new battle lines were drawn. In
several cases, the Supreme Court limited congressional efforts to insulate
administration of the laws from presidential control. 12 These cases
seemed to suggest that the whole idea of independent administration
could no longer be sustained-a change in understanding that, if
accepted, would dramatically alter the framework of American government.</p>
        <p>This shift in the Court-toward greater solicitude for presidential
control over implementation-inspired an even greater shift in the
academy. Scholars began to assert more forcefully that the conventional view
of the executive power-in particular, the idea that Congress could
create independent agencies-was constitutionally unfounded.'8
Perhaps the Court could eventually be persuaded to conclude that the
Constitution prohibited Congress from creating "independent agencies."
But in several more recent cases the Supreme Court unambiguously
committed itself to the idea that Congress may, at least sometimes and at least
to some extent, make administration independent of the President. 14
Indeed, the Court has allowed Congress to go beyond independent
"quasilegislators" and "quasijudges" and create independent prosecutors1 5-an
innovation from the previous cases that appears to expand congressional
authority.</p>
        <p>The recent cases leave many questions unanswered, involving the
precise relationships among the President, the so-called executive
agencies, and the so-called independent agencies. These questions assumed
special importance in connection with efforts by President Bush to assert
orders); Peter L. Strauss &amp; Cass t Sunstein, The Role of the President and OMB in
Informal Rulemaking, 38 Admin. L. Rev. 181, 185-97, 202-03 (1986) (describing
President Reagan's executive orders and arguing that their application can and should be
extended to independent agencies). President Reagan's efforts should be seen as the
culmination of a long historical trend, beginning with President Nixon. See, e.g., Harold
H. Bruff, Presidential Management of Agency Rulemaking, 57 Geo. Wash. L. Rev. 533,
546-52 (1989) (reviewing evolution ofpresidential management programs beginning with
President Nixon).</p>
        <p>12. See, e.g., INS v. Chadha, 462 U.S. 919, 965-67 (1983) (striking down the use of
legislative veto); Buckley v. Valeo, 424 U.S. 1, 118-37 (1976) (holding that Congress does
not have constitutional power to appoint members to Federal Election Commission, which
is responsible for administration and enforcement of election laws).</p>
        <p>13. See, e.g., Calabresi &amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1167-68; Currie, supra note 1, at
32-36; Lee S. Liberman, Morrisonv. Olson: A Formalistic Perspective on Why the Court was
Wrong, 38 Am. U. L. Rev. 313, 318 (1989); Miller, supra note 1, at 43.</p>
        <p>14. In Mistretta, the Court upheld the constitutionality of the United States
Sentencing Commission. See Mistretta v. United States, 488 U.S. 361, 408-12 (1989). The
Commission consists of seven members, at least three of whom must be federaljudges, and
has the authority to promulgate binding sentencing guidelines. See id. at 368-70. Under
the statute, the President may remove Commissioners only for "good cause." See id. at
368. In Morison, the Court upheld a statute that allowed the President to remove an
"independent prosecutor" only for "good cause." See Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654,
685-93 (1988).</p>
        <p>15. See 487 U.S. at 685-93.</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 6 1994
close control over government regulation; 16 they have new urgency as a
result of likely new efforts by President Clinton to claim authority over a
government staffed largely by Republican Presidents. 17 Heated struggles
arose between President Bush and Congress over a range of unresolved
issues.18 Similar issues are likely to rematerialize during the Clinton
Administration, and these debates will undoubtedly raise new issues about
exactly how unitary the executive branch can claim to be.</p>
        <p>It is time again to ask whether the executive is "unitary" in the sense
that the President must have plenary power to control administration
and execution of the laws. It seems clear that the belief in a unitary
executive has captured the high ground of principle, so that arguments for an
"evolving Constitution," for flexibility in interpretation, or for judicial
deference to political compromise, have become moves of compromise
or mere politics. But is this really a debate between principle and
politics? Or more precisely, is this a debate where principle favors the unitary
view?</p>
        <p>16. See, e.g., Memorandum on Reducing the Burden of Government Regulation, 28
Weekly Comp. Pres. Doc. 232 (Jan. 28, 1992) (asking executive and independent agencies
to refrain from issuing new regulations during 90 day period, and to review existing
regulations with goal of minimizing economic impact); Memorandum on Implementing
Regulatory Reform, 28 Weekly Comp. Pres. Doc. 728 (Apr. 29, 1992) (extending
moratorium for another 120 days). President Bush also formed the Council on
Competitiveness on March 31, 1989, to exercise power granted by Reagan's executive
orders. See supra note 11.</p>
        <p>17. Clinton has replaced President Reagan's Executive Orders 12,291 and 12,498 with
Executive Order 12,866. The new order provides that OMB and the Office of Information
and Regulatory Affairs will oversee agency regulation, requires that agencies undertake
regulatory analyses under the new principles, and effectively places Vice President Gore in
charge of the overall regulatory policymaking function. See Exec. Order No. 12,866, 58
Fed. Reg. 51,735 (1993); see also Marshall Ingwerson &amp;John Dillin, Vacancy Signs Abound
in Capital, Christian Sci. Monitor, Feb. 1, 1993, at 3 (reviewing continuing Republican
control of many agencies).</p>
        <p>18. For example, President Bush lost his battle to control the Board of Governors of
the Postal Service. He had attempted to prevent the board from exercising its statutory
authority to represent itself in challenging a Postal Rate Commission decision, either by
having the Department ofJustice dismiss the suit on behalf of the board, or by removing
the board. See Mal Order Ass'n of Am. v. U.S. Postal Serv., 986 F.2d 509, 512 (1993). The
D.C. District Court enjoined President Bush from removing the board, see id., and the
D.C. Circuit Court held that the board can represent itself in court if its position is
inconsistent with that of the Department ofJustice. See id. at 515.</p>
        <p>Possibly the most intense battle during the Bush presidency was fought between Vice
President Quayle and Congress over the role of the Council on Competitiveness. Before
the issue became moot with the election of President Clinton, Congress threatened to cut
all appropriations for the Council if it failed to increase public accountability. See, e.g.,
138 Cong. Rec. 13,214-15 (1992) (statement of Sen. Glenn); Eric Pianin &amp; Steven Mufson,
Administration Seeking Showdown on Spending, Wash. Post, Sept. 13, 1992, at Al.</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 7 1994</p>
        <p>We begin with some basics? 9 No one denies that in some sense the
framers created a unitary executive; the question is in what sense.20 Let
us distinguish between a strong and a weak version. The strong
versionheld by those whom we will call the modem unitarians-contends that
the President has plenary or unlimited power over the execution of
administrative functions, understood broadly to mean all tasks of
lawimplementation. All officers with such functions must either be
removable at the President's discretion or be subject to presidential
countermand in the context of policy disagreements. The Constitution creates "a
hierarchical unified executive department under the direct control of the
President," 21 with consequences we develop in detail below. 2 2 In the
19. This account draws on a recent statement of the modem position. See Calabresi
&amp; Rhodes, supra note 1; see also Saikrishna B. Prakash, Note, Hail to the Chief
Administrator. The Framers and the President's Administrative Powers, 102 Yale LJ. 991
(1993) (building on the work of Calabresi &amp; Rhodes).</p>
        <p>20. See, e.g., Strauss, supra note 7, at 599-600 ("While it was understood that there
would be departments responsible for daily administration, the Convention clearly and
consciously chose a single and independent executive over a collegial body subject to
legislative direction."); Prakash, supra note 19, at 998-99 (Convention chose a single
executive based on values of accountability and efficiency).</p>
        <p>21. Calabresi &amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1165. The modem unitarian view was
recently, and helpfully, summarized by Calabresi and Rhodes. As they describe it, the
position is grounded in the Vesting Clause of Article II, which provides: "The executive
Power shall be vested in a President." U.S. Const. art. If§, 1. This clause, together with the
Take Care Clause, id. § 3,
creat[es] a hierarchical, unified executive department under the direct control of
the President. ...[Thus,) the President alone possesses all of the executive power
and .. . he therefore can direct, control, and supervise inferior officers or
agencies who seek to exercise discretionary executive power. The practical
consequence of this theory is dramatic: it renders unconstitutional independent
agencies and counsels to the extent that they exercise discretionary executive
power.</p>
        <p>Calabresi &amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1165 (footnotes omitted).</p>
        <p>The Constitution embraces, the modem unitarians conclude, a single organizational
structure, with the Take Care Clause empowering the President to exercise control over
subordinates, at least so far as those subordinates exercise "purely executive power."
"Unitary executive theorists reject the view that the Take Care Clause contemplates merely
a housekeeping role for the President, who 'takes care' from a distance while unnamed
others 'faithfully execute' the laws." Id. at 1167-68.</p>
        <p>Of course Congress has some role in filling in the details, but that role, according to
the modem unitarian view, is crucially limited: "Unitary executive theorists concede that
Congress has broad power under the Necessary and Proper Clause to structure the
executive department. .. . They maintain, however, that '[n]o matter what structure
Congress selects ... the President must retain the authority to give directives to the officers
who assist' him." Id. at 1168 (footnotes omitted).</p>
        <p>Finally, the modem unitarian rejects textual clues that may suggest a structure
somewhat to the contrary. Thus, though the Constitution contemplates some
appointments being vested (and hence some loyalty engendered) in heads of departments,
and not the President, and though the framers oddly (for the unitarian) felt it necessary to
make explicit that the President could get reports from his officers,
unitary executive theorists reject the contention that Congress's power to vest the
appointment of inferior officers in the "Heads of Departments" necessarily</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 8 1994
modem unitarian's view, the Constitution constitutionalizes a single
organizational value-unitariness-at the expense of other possible
governmental values-such as disinterestedness or independence. The
conclusion is that any organizational structure that violates unitariness
violates the Constitution.</p>
        <p>The weak version offers a more unruly picture. It contends that
there are functions over which the President has plenary powers; that
these functions are the "executive" functions in the constitutional sense;
but that in the founding vision, "executive" functions-which must of
course be specified in detail23 -are not coextensive with all the functions
now (or then) exercised by the President.24 As for these nonexecutive
functions exercised by the executive, the original unitarian-as we will
refer to those who believe in the weak version-contends that Congress
has a wide degree of authority to structure government as it sees fit.
Under this view, unitariness is a significant constitutional value, but it is
not a trumping constitutional value. Other values may at times override
unitariness, and it is Congress that is to choose among these competing
values.</p>
        <p>In outline form, the belief in a strongly unitary executive is
grounded in the Vesting Clause of Article II: "The executive Power shall
insulates these officers from presidential control. Rather, these theorists
contend, this Clause was an insignificant housekeeping provision added at the last
minute. Unitary executive theorists also deny that the President's explicitly
delineated power to "require the Opinion, in writing, of the principal Officer in
each of the executive Departments" implies that the President has no inherent
power to tell principal officers what to do. Unitarians contend that the Opinions .
Clause represents too slender a reed to support this qualification of the
substantial grant of power embodied in the Article II Vesting Clause.</p>
        <p>Id. (footnotes omitted).</p>
        <p>Charles Tiefer provides a similar description of the modem unitarian view.
This view posits constitutional mandates for executive organization, not only in
areas with traditional Executive hierarchies such as communicating with foreign
governments and directing the military, but also in the area of access to the
courts. Under this view, the Executive branch consists of agencies organized in a
unitary body under the President's control either directly or through a chain of
command. Congress' checks on abuse within this unitary body consist of
hearings, investigations, new legislation, political pressures, and impeachment,
but Congress cannot shield agencies within this unitary body from presidential
control or removal. Thus, even in conflict of interest situations, such as when the
Executive department is called upon to conduct investigations of the President or
his top officials, proponents of this approach maintain that Congress cannot
divest the President of control over the investigation.</p>
        <p>Charles Tiefer, The Constitutionality of Independent Officers as Checks on Abuses of
Executive Power, 63 B.U. L. Rev. 59, 61 (1983) (footnotes omitted).</p>
        <p>22. See infra notes 25-32 and accompanying text.
23. See infra Part II.D.</p>
        <p>24. See Peter L. Strauss, Formal and Functional Approaches to Separation-of-Powers
Questions-A Foolish Inconsistency?, 72 Cornell L. Rev. 488, 492-96 (1987) (arguing
Constitution's silence about administration was product of "explicit purpose to leave
Congress free to make whatever arrangements it deemed 'necessary and proper").</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 94 Colum. L. Rev. 9 1994
be vested in a President."25 This clause creates "a" President, not several;
it is powerful, and to some decisive, textual evidence in favor of the view
that the Constitution creates a hierarchy with the President at the top.26
Moreover, the President is given all executive power. The framers did
not split up that power among different national entities. The Take Care
Clause is said to reenforce this view. This clause explicitly gives the
President the power to "take Care that the Laws be faithfully executed." 27
It may be true that the Take Care Clause is a duty at least as much as it is a
power; but the duty is the President's, and as with any duty, it implies
certain powers. If we take the two clauses together, the argument goes,
the President exercises hierarchical control over everyone within the
executive department, and people who exercise discretionary authority
must serve either at the President's pleasure or remain subject to his will
in the sense that he can countermand their decisions. Congress'
authority to structure the executive branch cannot intrude on this basic
principle. 28</p>
        <p>On this view, the founders imagined a hierarchical 29 executive
branch, with the President operating at the head of that hierarchy. From
this structure, certain limitations on the power of Congress naturally
flow-limitations on Congress' power to restrict or control the extent of
the President's authority over subordinates who execute the laws. It
follows that the so-called independent agencies are in conspicuous violation
of the Constitution."° It also follows that the Independent Counsel Act, 1
like all other efforts to separate the President from the administration, is
unconstitutional under Article 11.32</p>
        <p>One could approach the question whether the Constitution
embodies the strong version of unitariness from at least two perspectives, one
labeled broadly "originalist," the other not.3 3 We understand originalism
to require the interpreter to ask whether the modem unitarian's
limitations on Congress' power were indeed understood as such by those who
ratified the Constitution. AsJustice Scalia has stated the test, the
originalist would ask whether (1) the text standing alone contains strong
unitarian limitations, or (2) whether strong unitarian limitations were so well
25. U.S. Const. art. II, § 1.
26. See, e.g., Calabresi &amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1165.
27. U.S. Const. art. II, § 3.
28. See supra note 21.</p>
        <p>29. As we emphasize below, we are not claiming that the founders must have
imagined an entirely hierarchical executive for the unitarian's claim to be in substance
correct. See infra text accompanying notes 73-75; notes 58, 96 and accompanying text.
We simply begin with what is (for us) a natural assumption here, and relax it later on.
30. See supra note 21.
31. See 28 U.S.C. §§ 591-598 (1988).
32. See infra text accompanying notes 48-53.
33. For a qualification of the originalist/nonoriginalist distinction, see supra note 3.
understood at the founding so as to be implied by the document itself.3 4
A nonoriginalist who is nonetheless insistent on maintaining fidelity with
founding commitments would ask either (1) whether such limitations
should be understood to follow from the best understanding of the
framers' design,3 5 or (2) whether such limitations follow from the original
understanding translated into the current (and quite different)
context.3 6 We now proceed to explore, on originalist grounds, which version
of unitariness is embodied in the Constitution.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-2">
        <title>THE ORiGINAL EXECUTrvE</title>
        <p>How can we know whether the framers believed in a strongly unitary
executive branch? Many originalists would approach this question
through a (by now) standard formula-by considering almost
mechanically the key sources of interpretation, "text, structure, and history," as
the basis for uncovering the Constitution's original meaning.3 7 And so,
beginning with the framers' text, we could read in Article II that "the
executive power" is to be "vested in a President" who shall "take Care that
the laws be faithfully executed." This is quite likely to yield (for us) a very
strong conception of the President's power-after all, it says "the
executive power," not "some" executive power, and "all" this executive power is
vested in "a" President.3 8</p>
        <p>There are of course other bits of text added to this core-text that
defines some additional power and a few minor duties 3 9-but in the
main, the document might appear quite clear. Any question about this
clarity is easily resolved by considering the second originalist
step-structure. Article II's Vesting Clause is less conditional than Article I's: Article
I vests legislative power "herein granted," while Article II vests "the
executive power" without such a qualification. And so with text and structure,
we quite quickly come to a conception of the executive that fits well with
a familiar picture of the modem presidency-a strong, constitutionally
empowered "chief-administrator" of the executive branch. 40</p>
        <p>But we might ask up front how well this method can serve us in this
setting. For when we "begin" with an old text, we are likely also to begin
with a range of modem presuppositions about the meaning of that
textmodem, not founding, presuppositions. The text is not self-interpreting,
and the presuppositions with which we begin will color our reading of the
words, possibly more than they illuminate the world the words were
meant to construct.4 1 "Executive power" means to us all power not
legislative and not judicial; but we might ask, was this its meaning for the
framers? "A President" is for us the center of national policymaking, both
such a limitation should be understood to follow from the best understanding of the
framers' design. On this question, we remain agnostic. Finally, as we suggested above, see
supra note 3, it may be that an understanding of this form of "nonoriginalism" is the best
way of understanding what "originalism" should be. For further discussion of this point,
see infra Part III.</p>
        <p>
          37. See, e.g., Akhil R. Amar, The Two-Tiered Structure of the Judiciary Act of 1789,
138 U. Pa. L. Rev. 1499, 1505 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">1990</xref>
          ) [hereinafter Amar, The Judiciary Act of 1789].
        </p>
        <p>38. See Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654, 705 (1988) (ScaliaJ., dissenting); Calabresi
&amp; Rhodes, supra note 1, at 1165. It might be revealing that much of this debate is a debate
through italics.</p>
        <p>39. See U.S. Const. art. II, §§ 2, 3.</p>
        <p>40. See, e.g., Prakash, supra note 19, at 991 (arguing that "[h]istorical evidence...
indicates the Framers attempted to establish an executive who alone is accountable for
executing federal law and who has the authority to control its administration").</p>
        <p>41. This is a pervasive problem with one version of formalism in law. If we aim to
recover original meaning, we cannot rely on text "alone."</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>THE PRFSIDENTAND THE ADMINISTRATION</title>
      <p>foreign and domestic; was this who he was at the start of the nation?42 A
power to "take Care" that the laws be faithfully executed yields for us an
implied power to control and direct all those in the executive branch who
administer the law; would the framers have understood this to follow?
The Opinions Clause 43 (giving the President the power to demand
written opinions), the Commission Clause" (requiring the President to
commission officers), and the Inferior Officers App6intment Clause 45
(allowing Congress to vest the appointment of some officers somewhere
else) all for us read plainly, but for the most part insignificantly; were they
also unnecessary scribbles for the founders?</p>
      <p>It is our suspicion that much of the conventional reading of Article
II's text is informed by very modern ideas, and this leads us to adopt a
distinctive interpretive strategy. Rather than beginning with text or
structure alone, we begin with history. Our aim is to dislodge modem
preconceptions about the nature of the President and executive power by
contrasting these conceptions with those of the framers and with the
actual theory and practice of the early Congress. It is an important truism
that the framers were quite skeptical of broad executive authority, a
notion that they associated with the tyrannical power of the King.46 Their
skepticism about executive authority-their rejection of the monarchical
legacy-at least raises doubts about the idea that the President was to be
entrusted with control over all of what we now consider administration.</p>
      <p>We rely, however, not on general ideas about the executive, but on a
more particular examination of how well the strongly unitarian claim fits
with the founding vision. We begin with three puzzles presented by the
original practice. In each, we compare the actual historical practice of
the framers and the early Congresses with what the unitarian would
predict that same practice would be. The practice is important, even if not
decisive, because it is relevant to an assessment of the original
understanding.47 While the practice does not prove the original
understand42. On the question of policymaking alone, consider President Washington's
selfconception of his role in the legislative process:
"Motives of delicacy," [President Washington] once wrote, "have uniformly
restrained the P- from introducing any topick which relates to Legislative
matters to members of either house of Congress, lest it should be suspected that
he wished to influence the question before it." He would not permit
congressional committees to solicit his opinion, but intimated his willingness to
express his views, "when asked," to a friend.</p>
      <p>Leonard D. White, The Federalists: A Study in Administrative History 55 (1948) (quoting
Draft Letter by George Washington (Feb. 1792), in 31 The Writings of George Washington
491, 493 (John C. Fitzpatrick ed., 1939)).</p>
      <p>43. U.S. Const. art. II, § 2, cl. 1.
44. Id. cl. 3.
45. Id. cl. 2.</p>
      <p>46. See Gordon S. Wood, The Creation of the American Republic 1776-1787, at 521
(1969).</p>
      <p>47. No doubt there are important questions that can be raised about the usefulness of
post-enactment practice for interpreting the meaning of the Constitution. The mere fact
ing, an original practice widely inconsistent with a proposed original
understanding should draw that understanding into doubt. As we
suggest, in every case the original practice conflicts sharply with the practice
predicted by the modem unitarian's theory. Together, we suggest, the
three puzzles force us to ask whether there is a different model of the
original executive that better captures the original design. We conclude
that there is.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>OriginalUnderstandingsand UnitarianPuzzles: The Executive and</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>Prosecution</title>
      <p>We begin with the narrow but revealing question of criminal
prosecution, as presented in the contest over the independent counsel and
resolved in Morrisonv. Olson. 48 The Ethics in Government Act of 1978, 49
enacted in the wake of Watergate, established the office of the
independent counsel to investigate and prosecute offenses against certain officers
of the administration. 50 Without exploring the details of the Act, suffice
it to say that under certain circumstances, the statute vested in the special
counsel full prosecutorial authority for some limited period of time,
uncontrolled by the President except to the extent that the Attorney
General could discharge the special counsel for "good cause."5 1 The
claim of Theodore Olson (the prosecuted) was that the power of Alexia
Morrison (the prosecutor) was power from "the executive power," and
hence "vested" in the President alone. For Justice Scalia, writing in
dissent,52 the case was quite straightforward: The Constitution vests
executhe early Congresses enacted a bill certainly cannot show that the bill is
constitutionaltake for example, the Alien and Sedition Acts. The Sedition Act, ch. 74, 1 Stat. 596 (1798)
(expired Mar. 3, 1801); The Alien Enemies Act, ch. 66, 1 Stat. 577 (1798) (current version
at 50 U.S.C. §§ 21-23 (1988)); The Alien Act, ch. 58, 1 Stat. 570 (1798) (expiredJune 25,
1800); The Naturalization Act, ch. 54, 1 Stat. 566 (1798) (repealed by Act ofApril 14, 1802,
ch. 28, § 5, 2 Stat. 153, 155). In this area, Congress' self-interest appears to be at stake, and
we may therefore discount its conclusions. We do believe the practice is relevant, even
persuasive, and we will rely upon it below. But we are not using the practice to prove a
particular theory; rather our aim is to use it to raise doubts about a reigning, strongly
unitarian theory. A complete picture of the original understanding would include a much
broader survey of practice notjust after, but before the Constitution's enactment. Our aim
here, however, is not the final history of the founding. It is enough to jar current
understandings by emphasizing the inconsistencies they produce. Note that this practice
of looking to the early Congresses as an understanding of the framers' meaning is
common in the Supreme Court as well. See, e.g., Harmelin v. Michigan, 111 S.Ct. 2680,
2694 (1991) ("The actions of the First Congress... are of course persuasive evidence of
what the Constitution means, [Marsh v. Chambers, 463 U.S. 783 (1983); Carroll v. United
States, 267 U.S. 132, 150-52 (1925); cf. McCulloch v. Maryland, 17 U.S. (4 Wheat.) 316,
401-02 (1819)].").</p>
      <p>48. 487 U.S. 654 (1988).</p>
      <p>49. Pub. L. No. 95-521, 92 Stat. 1824 (1978) (codified as amended at scattered
sections of 2, 5, 18, 28 &amp; 39 U.S.C.).</p>
      <p>50. See 28 U.S.C. §§ 49, 591-598 (1988).
51. See id. § 596.
52. See 487 U.S. at 697 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
tive power in the President, and prosecution is an executive power; the
independent counsel exercises prosecutorial discretion, but without the
President's control; the act creating the independent counsel is therefore
unconstitutional. ForJustice Scalia, the President must in some way
control the exercise of all executive power, and this statute did not furnish
that control.53</p>
      <p>So much certainly follows as a matter of modem unitarian theory;
but what about the framers' actual practice? At the core ofJustice Scalia's
argument was an implicit claim about that practice. In defining the scope
of "executive power," Justice Scalia wrote:</p>
      <p>In what other sense can one identify "the executive Power" that is
supposed to be vested in the President (unless it includes
everything the Executive Branch is given to do) except by reference to
what has always and everywhere-if conducted by government
at all-been conducted never by the legislature, never by the
courts, and always by the executive .... Governmental
investigation and prosecution of crimes is a quintessentially executive
function.5 4
This is a textually plausible claim. To many modem readers, it seems
certainly correct. But has "the executive Power" "always and everywhere"
been so understood?</p>
      <p>In answering this question, again, we proceed in two steps. First,
does the constitutional text in its original context speak to the question at
issue? Second, if the text does not squarely answer the question, does the
original practice reveal an understanding uniformly shared by the
framers that itself resolves the question?5 5 The text of course does not say
whether prosecution is within the term "executive Power."56 So the
originalist must turn to the second step, and ask whether despite textual
ambiguity, the framers clearly understood prosecution to be within the
term "executive Power."</p>
      <p>If the framers' and early Congresses' actual practice is any indication
of their original understanding, then they did not understand
prosecution to be within the notion of "executive Power" exclusively, and
therefore did not understand it to be within the exclusive domain of the
President. While the argument for this conclusion has been discussed
before in depth,5 7 we can quickly summarize the important points here.</p>
      <p>Consider first the original structure of federal prosecution. If the
modern unitary model were the framers' model, one might think that the
framers would have established a hierarchical department of legal affairs,
responsible for all federal prosecution, with officers answerable to the
President or the President's agent (for example, the Attorney General).58
In fact, the record is not at all so neat. The first Congress established no
hierarchical department of legal affairs-as we discuss below, the
Department ofJustice was not even born until 1870.- 9 Nor did the
framers establish a general or centralized body for federal prosecution. Most
importantly, they established no absolute rule that prosecution must be
conducted solely by those answerable to the President. In each of these
three design elements, the unitary model mispredicts the original
practice. We consider these in turn.</p>
      <p>First: For the first eighty years of the Republic, there was no
centralized and hierarchical department of legal affairs in the executive branch.
While the Judiciary Act of 1789 did create the office of Attorney General,
it did not create a "department" under him. 60 By statute, the Attorney
General had just two duties: to represent the United States in the
Supreme Court (only), and to answer legal questions submitted to him by
the President or heads of departments on matters relating to the
operation of those departments 6 1 -though from the start, the Attorney
General also served as the President's legal advisor.6 2 The same act
created district attorneys who prosecuted suits on behalf of the United States
in the district courts.63 Until 1861, however, these district attorneys did
not report to the Attorney General, and were not in any clear way
answerable to him. Before 1861, the district attorneys reported either directly to
no one (1789 to 1820) or to the Secretary of the Treasury (1820 through</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>THE PRESIDENTAND THE ADMTNISTRATION</title>
      <p>Second: The first centralized federal prosecution was outside the
direct control of the President. Within the Department of the Treasury,
Congress established the office of the Comptroller, and in 1797 charged
him with the power "to institute suit for the recovery of" a "sum or
balance reported to be due to the United States, upon the adjustment of any
[revenue officer's account]."66 This power was expanded in 1817, giving
the Comptroller the power "to direct suits and legalproceedings, and to take
such measures as may be authorized by the laws to enforce prompt
payments of all debts to the United States."67 But the Comptroller himself
was not directly within the President's control, and most commentators
understood the Comptroller to be "relatively independent."6 8 So special
was the Comptroller's position that it led Madison, who ordinarily
supported an absolute removal power by the President over executive
officers, to comment that "there may be strong reasons why an officer of
this kind should not hold his office at the pleasure of the Executive
branch of the Government."6 9 At one point in the debate, Madison
argued that the Comptroller should hold his office for a fixed tenure. 70
64. Note that during this period the Secretary of the Treasury reported to Congress.
See infra text accompanying note 156.</p>
      <p>65. Leonard White describes the early control of district attorneys as follows:
By clear implication and subsequent practice the district attorneys thus became
subject to the comptroller's instructions for this class of cases, as well as the fifth
auditor's instructions after 1820 in cases involving delinquent collectors of
revenue. They also assisted the Postmaster General in suits against delinquent
postmasters and their sureties, and in the prosecution of offenses against the
mails. The attorneys might, therefore, receive instructions from three major
federal agencies, to none of which they were clearly responsible.</p>
      <p>Leonard D. White, TheJeffersonians: A Study in Administrative History 1801-1829, at 340
(1951); see also Tiefer, supra note 21, at 75 ("The Attorney General did not control or
supervise federal district attorneys; his function was merely to advise the President and the
Cabinet. Federal revenue collectors obtained legal enforcement for their collection cases
in decentralized fashion, paying fees to the federal district attorneys or to private counsel."
(footnotes omitted)).</p>
      <p>66. Act of Mar. 3, 1797, ch. 20, § 1, 1 Stat. 512, 512; see also Tiefer, supra note 21, at
75. For a general discussion of the Comptroller's office, see Harvey C. Mansfield, The
Comptroller General (1939).</p>
      <p>67. Act of Mar. 3, 1817, ch. 45, § 10, 3 Stat 366, 367 (emphasis added); see also
Tiefer, supra note 21, at 75.</p>
      <p>68. See Darrell H. Smith, The General Accounting Office: Its History, Activities and
Organization 22 (1927); Tiefer, supra note 21, at 73-74.</p>
      <p>69. 1 Annals of Cong. 636 (Gales &amp; Seaton eds., 1834); see also Tiefer, supra note 21,
at 74.</p>
      <p>70. See 1 Annals of Cong. 636 (Gales &amp; Seaton eds., 1834). It should be noted, as
lawyers are wont to do, that much of the argument against modem unitarians hangs on
this single reference. to one debate by Madison. Indeed, Madison the next day "withdrew
the proposition which he yesterday laid upon the table," id. at 639, though it is not entirely
clear to what proposal this refers. The point that must be stressed, however, is that too
much of the anti-unitarian case may be resting upon this single speech by Madison.
Congress did not entirely follow Madison's suggestion, 71 but nonetheless
the Comptroller's decisions to prosecute were independent, as were his
final determinations of disputes referred by statute to him.72 More
importantly, whether Madison's initial thoughts prevailed or not, what is
clear is that all thought the matter open for Congress'
determinationthat is, that Congress had significant flexibility in structuring the duties of
this "executive" officer.</p>
      <p>Thus, the organizational structure of the original executive, at least
with respect to prosecution, was not hierarchical. But perhaps the
essence of unitarianism is not organizational structure. Perhaps instead the
essence is mere control, through whatever structure. If the President
retained either directory authority over the district attorneys, or removal
authority over all exercising prosecutorial power,73 the unitary position
may seem unimpaired, at least so far. While acknowledging that there
was no clear organizational hierarchy, the unitarian could still claim that
the essential requirement of presidential control was preserved 74 : Even if
the story just told shows that the Attorney General could not direct or
remove district attorneys, nothing yet shows the President could not.75</p>
      <p>Third: But so far this story ignores a crucial fact about federal
prosecution at the founding-federal officers were not the only ones who
conducted federal prosecutions. State officials also conducted federal
prosecutions, and these officers were clearly not subject to control by the
71. The Act contained a general removal clause that stated: "if any person shall
offend against any of the prohibitions of this act, he shall be deemed guilty of a high
misdemeanor,... and shall upon conviction be removed from office." Act of Sept. 2, 1789,
ch. 12, § 8, 1 Stat. 65, 67. Compare this with the-Temoval provision for the Secretary, which
stated simply "[t]hat whenever the Secretary shall be removed from office by the President,"
without providing any limitations on the President's removal power. § 7, 1 Stat. at 67.</p>
      <p>72. See Tiefer, supra note 21, at 74. We believe that Madison's concern here certainly
was that the Comptroller be independent of the President for checks and balances reasons.
But the modern unitarian could perhaps argue that the real motive for the independence
was simply efficiency, and therefore that the Comptroller's position is not strongly
probative of the framers' understanding of any constitutionally required control of the
President.</p>
      <p>73. On the distinction between directory and removal authority, seeJames Hart, The
Ordinance Making Powers of the President of the United States 188-97 (1925); Itzhak
Zamir, Administrative Control of Administrative Action, 57 Cal. L. Rev. 866, 877 (1969).</p>
      <p>74. Though as Susan Bloch convincingly argues, it is not at all clear the framers
believed they were vesting in the President removal authority over the Attorney General.
See Susan L. Bloch, The Early Role of the Attorney General in our Constitutional Scheme:
In the Beginning There Was Pragmatism, 1989 Duke L.J. 561, 582.</p>
      <p>75. Jefferson at least exercised the directory power when he ordered district attorneys
to cease prosecution under the Alien and Sedition Acts. See, e.g., Letter from Thomas
Jefferson to Wilson C. Nicholas (June 13, 1809), in 12 The Writings of Thomas Jefferson
288 (Andrew A. Lipscomb ed., 1905) [hereinafter Lipscomb, Writings ofJefferson]; Letter
from ThomasJefferson to Edwin Livingston (Nov. 1, 1801), in 8 The Writings of Thomas
Jefferson 57-58 n.1 (Paul L. Ford ed., New York, G.P. Putnam's Sons 1897) (hereinafter
Ford, Writings ofJefferson]. In 1897, the Supreme Court concluded the President had the
power to remove a U.S. attorney, despite his being granted a four-year term under the
appointment statute. See Parsons v. United States, 167 U.S. 324, 343 (1897).
President. Perhaps it would be possible to say that state officers enforcing
federal law were not exercising "the Executive power of the United
States"; but it seems quite reasonable to think that insofar as enforcement
of federal law is at stake, this was indeed their responsibility. As Harold
Krent writes,</p>
      <p>Congress vested jurisdiction in state courts over actions seeking
penalties and forfeitures, granted concurrent jurisdiction to
state courts over some criminal actions, and assigned state
officials auxiliary law enforcement tasks. Thus, Congress assigned
law enforcement responsibility to state officials who were far
removed from control of the executive branch.76
Even when actions were criminal, "[t]he decisions whether to sue and
what punishments to seek remained in the discretion of individuals
outside the Executive's control."77 The original practice thus violated the
unitarian's plan, even in its most minimal form.78 Here at least, some
federal prosecution was exercised that was clearly beyond the President's
control.</p>
      <p>But not here only. For not only was federal prosecution vested in at
least some federal officers not subject to direct presidential control, 79 and
in some state officers far removed from executive control,8 0 but federal
76. Krent, supra note 57, at 303. Krent's very careful analysis makes three distinct
points: (1) "Congress limited the Executive's effective control over law enforcement by
dispersing supervisory responsibility among various executive officials," id. at 286; (2)
Private actions constituted prosecution outside the executive's control, see id. at 290-303;
(3) States exercised some federal prosecutorial authority, see id. at 303-10. The last two
points are discussed below, see infra text.accompanying notes 77, 81-83. For an example
of a statute giving control of prosecution to state officials, see Act ofJuly 6, 1798, ch. 66,
§ 2, 1 Stat. 577, 577 (respecting alien enemies); see also Thomas Sergeant, Constitutional
Law 269-70 (Philadelphia, Abraham Small 1822). Finally, one should note that there is an
important difference between vesting executive authority in a state official and vesting
executive authority in a federal official not directly responsible to the President. Only the
latter is subject to the machinations of Congress, and hence the former might be
considered constitutionally distinct. We do not address that difference, pointed out to us
by Alan Meese, in the analysis that follows.</p>
      <p>77. Krent, supra note 57, at 304.</p>
      <p>78. One should ask what the appropriate baseline is for evaluating unitariness, or
alternatively, the extent of original executive control. For obviously one cannot carry over
modem conceptions, built upon modem capacity and technology, to'the eighteenth
century world. What may appear to us to be lax control may have, in context, appeared
quite centralized. And indeed, as Charles Thach argues, against the background of state
executives, and the continental executive, Article II's executive was quite strong. See
Charles C. Thach, Jr., The Creation of the Presidency 1775-1789: A Study in
Constitutional History, Johns Hopkins University Studies in Historical and Political
Science, No. 4 1922, at 1, 77. It would remain possible for the modem unitarian then to
argue that compared to the degree of control existing before 1787, the new Constitution
was a more centralized and unitarian structure. Nonetheless, that it was more centralized
would not entail a present understanding of it as fully centralized.</p>
      <p>79. Recall the discussion of the district attorneys and the Comptroller, supra notes
64-72 and accompanying text.</p>
      <p>80. See supra text accompanying notes 76-77.</p>
      <p>It was in the nineteenth century that one of the features
distinguishing the framers' world from ours changed. Here was the rise of a massive
federal bureaucracy;4 14 but unlike the legal culture today, the culture of
the nineteenth century theorists was firm in its faith in the scientific
model of administration, so that the theorists did not see constitutional
problems with relatively independent agencies. The nineteenth century
culture could accommodate the growth in bureaucracy by approving
relatively independent agencies while staying within the bounds of fidelity.</p>
      <p>But for us, the central fact of the eighteenth century executive
(limited national government and limited delegations to federal
administrators) has changed, and the central assumption of the nineteenth century
solution (neutral, scientific administration) has failed. For now, we not
only have a large administrative bureaucracy, but we also have profound
skepticism about whether it is possible and desirable for that bureaucracy
to operate free from politicaljudgment. EchoingJustice Brandeis
(quoting Justice Holmes) in ErieR.R. Co. v. Tompkins,4 15 we could say that
administration "in the sense in which courts speak of it today" can no longer
be understood to be neutral, or scientific. Politics is at its core, in the
sense that valuejudgments are pervasive and democratic controls on
policymaking are indispensable. 4 16 This raises a central problem for a
modem bureaucratic state. The question the interpreter must answer is how
best to accommodate this current skepticism-what structure makes most
sense of the framers' design, given the change in the extent of the
bureaucracy and the change in our understanding of what bureaucracy is.</p>
      <p>The answer to this question is not simple. No doubt our
understandings are complex and multiple, and no doubt the principal place for
registering changes in understanding is the legislature, not the judiciary.
Congress' diminished enthusiasm for the independent agency form
attests to the possibility that new views about expertise and factionalism can
influence legislative judgments, informed by constitutional
considerations, about appropriate structures. 4 17 It would be possible to say that
courts should not take account of changed understandings in the process
of constitutional interpretation. But it is also possible to think that
changes of this kind are relevant to interpretation as well as to
lawmaking, as the Court itself recently insisted in describing the shifts from Pessy
to Brown and Lochner to West Coast Hotel.4 18</p>
      <p>A structural argument for a unitary executive, then, comes down to
this: Where the framers allocated a power that they thought of as
political, that power was allocated to people who were themselves politically
accountable. This was part of the fundamental commitments to
account414. See Young, supra note 401, at 47-48.
415. 304 U.S. 64, 79 (1938).
416. It is not necessary to claim that such control must take any particular form.
417. See Sunstein, supra note 396, at 478-83.</p>
      <p>418. See Planned Parenthood v. Casey, 112 S.Ct. 2791, 2812-14 (1992); Lessig, supra
note 350, at 27-31, 67-71.
ability and avoidance of factionalism. At the founding period, the
existence of a degree of independence in administration could not
realistically have been thought to compromise these commitments.
Today, by contrast, a strong presumption of unitariness is necessary in
order to promote the original constitutional commitments. The
legislative creation of domestic officials operating independently of the
President but exercising important discretionary policymaking power
now stands inconsistent with founding commitments.</p>
      <p>It follows that in order to be faithful to the founding vision in
changed circumstances, courts must now bar Congress, at least as a
presumption, from immunizing from presidential control the activities of
officials who exercise discretionary policymaking authority-at least if those
officials are not adjudicators. 4 19 In order to be faithful to the original
design, that is, the interpreter must see as part of the constitutional
structure a constraint not explicitly stated in that design, requiring that certain
kinds of policymaking remain within the control of the executive.</p>
      <p>This general statement leaves many unanswered questions and
ambiguities, and we will address some of them below. But the basic
conclusions of the argument are not obscure. To the extent that Congress has
authorized executive officials to engage in adjudicative tasks, it may
immunize those officials from presidential control by, for example,
preventing presidential interference in ongoing cases and offering "for cause"
protection against discharge. To the extent that an employee has truly
ministerial tasks, and is not engaged in policymaking activity, "for cause"
protections are entirely acceptable. The Court was correct in Myers; the
Civil Service Act is constitutional. 420 But to the extent that an agency
official makes discretionary decisions about the content of public policy,
the best reading of the constitutional plan is that in general, the official
may not be insulated from presidential supervision. The President must
retain the power to discharge him if his decisions are contrary to
presidential dictates.</p>
      <p>A contrary view, set out forcefully by Abner Greene, could also be
suggested by this same history--one that argues against a strongly unitary
executive. 42 1 Perhaps the original design reflected a carefully calibrated
set of judgments about institutional authority, with a division between
lawmaking and law implementation; perhaps the most important
changed circumstance was the disturbance of this calibration through the
delegation of policymaking authority to the President. On this view, the
key founding commitments call for diffusion of power and for checks and
419. Here we mean adjudicators in the sense of non-policymaking adjudication
discussed in Martin v. Occupational Safety &amp;Health Rev. Comm'n, 111 S. Ct. 1171, 1178
(1991).</p>
      <p>420. See Myers v. United States, 272 U.S. 52 (1926).</p>
      <p>421. See Abner S. Greene, Checks and Balances in an Era of Presidential Lawmaking,
61 U. Chi. L. Rev. 123, 125-26 (1993).
balances between the legislature and the executive. 422 The principal
threat of the post-New Deal period lies in the concentration of lawmaking
and law-executing power within the presidency. To restore the original
balance, courts must now allow a high degree of independence from
presidential power, so as to prevent what the framers dreaded most: the
concentration of governmental power in a single institution-here, the
executive. 423</p>
      <p>This argument also stresses the need to maintain fidelity with the
original constitutional design. It too is an argument of translation. But it
takes the post-New Deal developments as a reason for more rather than
less caution about unitariness in administration. The new circumstances
mean that unitariness is a far greater threat than it once was-not that
unitariness is a constitutionally compelled solution.4 24</p>
      <p>More particularly, this view fears that the new delegations have
threatened to confer excessive power on the executive branch-to create
an "imperial presidency." The changed circumstances argue in favor of a
narrow reading of "executive power" and for broad congressional
authority under the Necessary and Proper Clause, precisely in the interest of
maintaining the original commitment to a system of checks and
balances.4 25 On this view, congressional power to insulate administration
from presidential control is a necessary quid pro quo for the exercise of
discretionary lawmaking power by people other than legislators. 426 The
rise of lawmaking by nonlegislative bodies-most especially, the downfall
of the nondelegation doctrine 427-makes it especially necessary to insist
on congressional prerogatives under the Necessary and Proper Clause, in
order to prevent an aggregation of powers in the presidency. In short,
Greene urges, the post-New Deal developments mean that modern
interpreters should place less value on unitariness than did the framers,
because of the need to maintain fidelity with the commitment to the
diffusion of power.4 28</p>
      <p>This argument is hardly without force. It shows that there is no
algorithm for deciding how to maintain fidelity with past instructions in the
face of changed circumstances. But we do not believe that the argument
422. See id.
423. See id.
424. See id.
425. See id. at 137-38.</p>
      <p>426. A view of this kind has been prominently set out by Justice White. See INS v.
Chadha, 462 U.S. 919, 967 (1983) (White, J., dissenting) (arguing that legislative veto is
appropriate means by which Congress can secure accountability of executive and
independent agencies that have significant delegated power).</p>
      <p>427. The nondelegation doctrine bans open-ended grants of discretionary authority
to agencies. See A.L.A. Schechter Poultry Corp. v. United States, 295 U.S. 495 (1935). For
the brief history of the doctrine-not invoked to invalidate a statute since
Schechteritselfsee Stephen G. Breyer &amp; Richard B. Stewart, Administrative Law and Regulatory Policy:
Problems, Text, and Cases 66-91 (3d ed. 1992).</p>
      <p>428. See Greene, supra note 421, at 141-42.
is ultimately persuasive. The first and most fundamental problem is that
the argument treats diffusion of power as an end in itself, rather than as
an instrument for serving various purposes connected with the
preservation of liberty. The second problem is that even if broad delegations of
authority are the problem, independent agencies are not the solution.</p>
      <p>We can make these points by considering two lessons of the post-New
Deal experience. First, there is the problem of administrative
accountability, one of the important founding values. The rise of independent
regulatory commissions compromises that value. 429 Second, there is the
problem of faction, the very problem that the system of checks and
balances was intended to solve. To the extent that we multiply (and
specialize) the bodies exercising lawmaking power (without a presidential or
congressional check), we increase geometrically the opportunities and
the costs of faction. From the standpoint of constitutional structure and
constitutional commitments, the creation of a body of independent
entities seems to be a cure worse than the disease. Both theory and practice
support this conclusion. 430</p>
      <p>The original diffusion of power was supposed to protect liberty, in
large part by limiting the authority of factions. 431 The rise of a large
bureaucracy immunized from presidential control tends to endanger rather
than promote that original goal.4 32 Through concentrating power in
bureaucracies that combine lawmaking and law-executing authority, we do
not promote a healthy system of checks and balances, but instead
aggravate the relevant risks to liberty.4 33 The insulating arm of the President is
not free from risk. But because the President has a national
constituency-unlike relevant members of Congress, who oversee independent
429. Jerry Mashaw argues in fiavor of administrative rather than legislative
policymaking discretion, see Jerry L. Mashaw, Prodelegation: Why Administrators Should
Make Political Decisions, 1J.L. Econ. &amp; Org. 81, 81-82 (1985); but the argument depends
crucially on the assumption of presidential direction of bureaucracy.</p>
      <p>
        430. See Bernstein, supra note 390, at 291-97 (concluding that independent agencies
"have proved to be more susceptible to private pressures, to manipulation for private
purposes, and to administrative and public apathy than other types of government
agencies"); Cass R Sunstein, Paradoxes of the Regulatory State, 57 U. Chi. L. Rev. 407,
426-28, 439-40 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">1990</xref>
        ) (arguing that independent agencies have been "highly susceptible
to the political pressure of well-organized private groups").
      </p>
      <p>431. See The Federalist Nos. 47-51 (James Madison).
432. See supra note 429.</p>
      <p>433. See Bernstein, supra note 390, at 293. Barry Weingast and Mark Moran have
discussed the problems of control over independent agencies by congressional
committees, noting that committees are not the same as Congress. Weingast argues that
there is too simple a slippage from legislative control to committee influence. See Barry R.
Weingast &amp; MarkJ. Moran, Bureaucratic Discretion or Congressional Control? Regulatory
Policymaking by the Federal Trade Commission, 91 J. Pol. Econ. 765, 777-79, 788-92
(1983) [hereinafter Weingast &amp; Moran, Bureaucratic Discretion]; Barry R. Weingast &amp;
Mark J. Moran, The Myth of Runaway Bureaucracy. The Case of the FTC, Regulation,
May/June 1982, at 33, 33-34 [hereinafter Weingast &amp; Moran, Runaway Bureaucracy]; see
also INS v. Chadha, 462 U.S. 919, 946-48 (1983).
agencies with often parochial agendas-it appears to operate as an
important counterweight to factional influence over administration. 43 4</p>
      <p>Perhaps Congress can point to the need to limit presidential
authority in order to support some isolated efforts to prevent concentration of
power in the President. We will offer some examples below. But it seems
clear that the changed circumstances do notjustify the immunization of
all or most bureaucratic power from the President. This is because it is
hard to identify how independent administration is a realistic solution to
the constitutional problems caused by changed circumstances. Indeed,
independent administration would sacrifice many values the founders saw
as essential.</p>
      <p>We conclude that if the framers thought that the realm of
"executive" power was roughly coextensive with the realm of political choice, it
makes sense to say that most of modem administration must fall under
the power of the executive; and this is so even if the framers had a
relatively capacious, but not specifically constitutionalized, conception of
what counted as "the administrative." Their conception of administrative
(or permissibly nonexecutive) power certainly did not extend to the
broad-scale selection of domestic policies for the country as a whole. If
we are to translate their structural choices into current conditions, we
may conclude that a largely hierarchical executive branch is the best way
of keeping faith with the original plan. At least this is so if we are asking
whether the President has a degree of removal and supervisory power
over people who are authorized to make high-level discretionary
decisions about the content of national policy.</p>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>IV. CURRENT ISSUES</title>
        <p>In this section, we briefly discuss the implications of our approach on
the resolution of current issues involving the relationship between the
President and the administration. Our goal is not to reach final
conclusions about these questions, many of which would require far more
elaborate treatment than we can provide here. We are concerned principally
with a general approach, not with specific solutions. We are attempting
to see how the argument from translation might bear on contemporary
disputes, a surprisingly large number of which are unsettled.</p>
        <p>We have noted that the 1980s saw a surprising rebirth of contestation
about the issue of presidential control over administration of the laws. 43 5
It is clear from the recent cases that the so-called independent agencies
are constitutional-at least in the sense that Congress has the power to
provide that some administrative officers do not serve at the pleasure of
434. See Frank H. Easterbrook, Public Choice and Our Vision of the State, 107 Harv.
L. Rev. (forthcoming 1994).</p>
        <p>435. See supra notes 11-18 and accompanying text.
the President.4 36 To this extent, the constitutional assault on
independent administration, at least in its broadest forms, has been decisively
repudiated. And to this extent, we think that current law is entirely
unobjectionable. The independent agencies perform a large number of
adjudicative functions; consider the NLRB, the FTC, and the FCC. More
important, and in our view crucially, it is possible to interpret the statutes
conferring independence on certain agencies in such a way as to
maintain the essentials of presidential power, that is, the power necessary to
maintain basic presidential authority over the relevant areas.4 37 It follows
from this interpretation that, for example, President Clinton has a degree
of supervisory authority over the FCC, the FTC, and the NLRB, insofar as
broad policymaking authority is involved. This conclusion is inconsistent
with current understandings in Congress and the executive branch,43 8
but it is, in our view, consistent with a proper understanding of the
constitutional scheme.</p>
        <p>Insofar as we emphasize this last point, we claim that complete
independence from the President-if Congress sought to create it-would in
many cases raise serious problems. But the unitary structure for which we
argue would produce no question about independence in cases in which
special institutional considerations support a legislative judgment that it
is proper to achieve a degree of immunity from the President. Here the
Necessary and Proper Clause provides ample authority, and here the
argument from changed circumstances is not decisive, since it does not
supply considerations that argue sufficiently against limiting presidential
authority. The Federal Reserve Board is a good example. There is no
question that the Federal Reserve Board exercises policymaking
authority; but just as the framers sought to insulate the Comptroller from the
President, and vested the discretion over deposits in the U.S. Bank in the
Secretary of the Treasury,43 9 so too the value of separating the "purse
from the sword" wouldjustify keeping the Federal Reserve Board (holder
of the post-Keynesian purse) distant from the President.</p>
        <p>436. See, e.g., Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654 (1988) (upholding constitutionality of
independent prosecutor); Bowsher v. Synar, 478 U.S. 714 (1986) (upholding lawmaking
Comptroller General removable only by congressional initiative, but limiting Comptroller's
ability to perform executive functions).</p>
        <p>437. See infra Part IV.C.</p>
        <p>438. For example, in their Executive Orders requiring administrative agencies to
undertake cost-benefit analyses before enacting new regulations, both President Reagan
and President Clinton expressly exempted those agencies that are considered independent
under 44 U.S.C. § 3502(10) (1988). See Exec. Order No. 12,866, 58 Fed. Reg. 51,735
(1993) (but requiring all agencies to comply with regulatory agenda for interagency
coordination); Exec. Order No. 12,291, 3 C.F.R. 127, 128 (1981), reprinted in 5 U.S.C.
§ 601 (1988); see also 139 Cong. Rec. 12,909 (1993) (statement of Sen. Exon, comparing
the "independent forum of the Interstate Commerce Commission to the politically
controlled Department of Transportation").</p>
        <p>439. See supra text accompanying notes 123-125, 139-143; see also the discussion in
Froomkin, supra note 120, at 810 &amp; n.149.</p>
        <p>This is a historical point; but it is supported by a distinctive structural
consideration. If the Federal Reserve Board were subject to day-to-day
presidential supervision, there would be a risk that in reality, or in public
perception, the money supply would be manipulated by the President for
political reasons. Even a perception of this sort would have corrosive
effects on democratic processes; it would mean that the state of the
economy would be perceived to be an artifact of short-term partisan
considerations. This would be intolerable from the democratic point of
view; it would likely have adverse effects on the economy as well.
Congress could permissibly decide that it is proper to prevent this state of
affairs. But this argument is limited to the particular concerns
surrounding the Federal Reserve Board; it could not easily be invoked for such
agencies as EPA, OSHA, or even the nominally independent NLRB.</p>
        <p>To be sure, it would be possible to say that independence is quite
generally required to protect against distortions of elections by political
interest. If, for example, the EPA is subject to presidential authority,
perhaps environmental enforcement will be influenced by electoral
considerations. It would be most surprising if this has never happened in the
past. But independence would pose obvious difficulties for a range of
constitutionally recognized policies such as coordination 4 40 and
accountability. The risks to democratic elections are far greater for a political
Federal Reserve than for a political EPA. And if independence were
acceptable for the EPA, it would probably be acceptable nearly everywhere
else. We do not think that the argument that independence is necessary
should be accepted without a very strong congressional showing; the
model of the Federal Reserve could not be easily adopted elsewhere
without compromising central (if translated) constitutional commitments.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>B. Immunizing Specific Functionsfrom the President</title>
      <p>The relevant history suggests that Congress may indeed immunize
some specific functions from the President, and nothing in subsequent
circumstances should draw this conclusion into question. As we have
seen, the framers did not believe that prosecutorial authority need be
concentrated in the President operating through the Attorney
General.44 ' Moreover, our argument based on changed circumstances
does not lead to the conclusion that the Independent Counsel Act is
unconstitutional. We have emphasized the need to promote accountability
and to limit factionalism by ensuring that large-scale domestic
policymak440. Consider in this regard the large number of agencies enforcing environmental
policy and the importance of a coordinating presidential role in order to produce rational
regulation. See generally Al Gore, From Red Tape to Results: Creating a Government that
Works Better &amp; Costs Less (National Performance Committee, 1993) (concluding that
helpful method to eliminate waste would be to give the President greater power); see also
Breyer, supra note 189, at 10-29 (cataloguing problems in lack of coordination and
systematization of policy).</p>
      <p>441. See supra Part II.A.
ing is not placed in independent actors.44 2 It would be an unwarranted
expansion of the argument to apply it to the independent counsel, who
does not engage in domestic policymaking in the sense in which we
understand that term.44 3</p>
      <p>There is a further consideration. As in the case of the Federal
Reserve Board, a special structural justification applies to the
independent prosecutor. The structural consideration lies in the notion, of course
familiar to the framers, that no person should be judge in his own
cause.44 4 It is at least unseemly4 45 to say that the prosecution of
highlevel executive branch officials will be controlled by other high-level
executive branch officials. Congress could reasonably decide that the
appearance or reality of favoritism requires an independent prosecutor for such
officials. If the congressional judgment is reasonable on this point, courts
should defer, especially in light of the complexity and delicacy of the
underlying questions. To be sure, many people have offered plausible
objections to the Independent Counsel Act,446 but these objections raise
issues of policy, not of constitutional obligation, at least in light of the
Constitution's structural commitment to preventing self-dealing by
government officials.</p>
      <p>The Court's validation of the Independent Counsel Act is probably
the largest and most controversial innovation in the recent cases. Before
1980, there was general agreement that executive officers must be under
the authority of the President; the Court distinguished Humphrey's
Executor from Myers on precisely this ground.447 Now the distinction lies
elsewhere, in the line between independence, which is sometimes
constitutional, and encroachment, which is not.44 8 On the old view,
independent agencies performed adjudicative and legislative functions as well as
executive functions, and it was for this reason that they could be insulated
442. See supra text accompanying notes 401-402.</p>
      <p>443. To say this is not to deny that the independent counsel has discretion, or to say
that the Act is desirable as a simple matter of policy. Note too that the statute upheld in
Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654 (1988), allowed the Attorney General to discharge the
counsel for "good cause," a provision that meant the counsel is not truly independent, and
that therefore makes the constitutional issue simpler. See infra text accompanying notes
465-466.</p>
      <p>444. See, e.g., The Federalist No. 78, at 467 (Alexander Hamilton) (Clinton Rossiter
ed., 1961).</p>
      <p>445. Cf.Ex parte Siebold, 100 U.S. 371, 397-98 (1879) (agreeing with Congress that it
is most appropriate for circuit courts to appoint officers to monitor elections for federal
officials).</p>
      <p>446. See Brief for Edward H. Levi, Griffin B. Bell, and William French Smith as
Amicus Curiae in Support of Appellant at 11, Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654 (1988) (No.
87-1279).</p>
      <p>447. See Humphrey's Executor v. United States, 295 U.S. 602, 627 (1935)
(distinguishing Myers on grounds that office of postmaster is purely executive, unlike a
commissioner of FTC).</p>
      <p>448. See infra Part IV.E. For an earlier suggestion to this effect, see Strauss, supra
note 7, at 667-68 (advocating a separation of function and checks and balances analysis
rather than formal separation of powers analysis).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>COLUMBIA LAW REViEW</title>
      <p>from the President. But after Morrison v. O1son,449 execution of the laws
can be split off from the President if the splitting does not prevent the
President from performing his "constitutionally appointed functions."45 0
This is a lamentably vague standard; but it has considerable historical
support insofar as it turns on whether the authority in question is within the
Article II enumeration. 45 ' For present purposes our conclusion is very
modest: At least insofar as we are dealing with prosecutors for whom
there is a special claim for independence-as is of course the case for
investigation of high-level presidential appointees-some degree of
independence is constitutionally acceptable. Other efforts to insulate
prosecution would be more difficult, because the prosecutorial power is now
intermingled with substantive policymaking. 452</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>What Does "Good Cause" Mean?</title>
      <p>In Morrison, the Attorney General was able to discharge the
independent counsel for "good cause," and the Court emphasized this
point in upholding the (for this reason misnamed?) Independent
Counsel Act. 453 But the Court has not said what "good cause" means.
The Court has also failed to define "inefficiency, neglect of duty, or
malfeasance in office"-the ordinary standards for presidential removal of
members of the independent commissions. 45 4 Nor does anything in
Humphrey's Executor speak to the particular issue, notwithstanding some
casual dicta suggesting a high degree of independence. 455</p>
      <p>This is an extremely important matter. There is no controlling
judicial decision on how "independent" the independent agencies and
officers can legitimately claim to be. If the statutory words allow for
considerable presidential removal (and hence supervisory) power, the
notion of independent administration of the laws can be solved simply as
a matter of statutory construction. Perhaps Congress has not, in fact,
created any truly independent administrators.</p>
      <p>We think that it would indeed be possible to interpret the relevant
statutes as allowing a large degree of removal and supervisory power to
remain in the President. At the very least, the statutory words do not
entirely immunize commissioners from the control of the President, but
449. 487 U.S. 654 (1988).
450. Id. at 685.
451. See supra Part II.B.
452. Consider environmental policy, immigration policy, and the "war on drugs."
453. 487 U.S. at 696.</p>
      <p>454. See, e.g., 15 U.S.C. § 41 (1988) (establishment of FTC); 29 U.S.C. § 661(b)
(1988) (appointment of commissioners for OSHRC). But see 26 U.S.C. § 7443(f) (1988)
(Tax Courtjudges may be removed by the President, "after notice and opporlunityfor public
hearing,for inefficiency, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office, but for no other reason."
(emphasis added)).</p>
      <p>455. In dicta, Justice Sutherland describes the commissioners of the FTC as
"independent of executive authority, except in selection." Humphrey's Executor v. United
States, 295 U.S. 602, 625 (1935); see also Greene, supra note 421, at 166.
instead allow him to remove them in certain circumstances. Purely as a
textual matter, the words "good cause" and "inefficiency, neglect of duty,
or malfeasance in office" seem best read to grant the President at least
something in the way of supervisory and removal power-allowing him,
for example, to discharge, as inefficient or neglectful of duty, those
commissioners who show lack of diligence, ignorance, incompetence, or lack
of commitment to their legal duties. The statutory words might even
allow discharge of commissioners who have frequently or on important
occasions acted in ways inconsistent with the President's wishes with respect
to what is required by sound policy. Perhaps in some such cases, the
statutory basis for discharge has been met.</p>
      <p>Of course, the case would be easier if the President could show that
the officer's policy judgments amount not just to policy disagreements
but to unquestionable inefficiency, neglect, or malfeasance-because
they reflect (for example) incompetence or a refusal adequately to
consider consequences. But perhaps the President's power could go further.
A commissioner of the FTC might well, for example, be thought to
neglect her duty if she consistently ignores what the President has said, at
least if what the President has said is supported by law or by good policy
justifications. At the minimum, we suggest that the statutory words could
be taken to allow a degree of substantive supervision by the President.</p>
      <p>This result might seem strongly counterintuitive in light of the
frequent understanding that independent agencies are entirely immunized
from presidential policymaking. 456 But there is a partial precedent for
precisely this conclusion: Bowsher v. Synar.457 In that case, the Court
held that Congress could not delegate power to administer the
GrammRudman-Hollings Act to the Comptroller General, because-and this is a
central claim-the Comptroller was subject to congressional will. In the
Court's view, those who execute the law must not be subject to the
policymaking authority of the Congress except insofar as legislative
instructions are embodied in substantive law. 458 The relevant statute allowed
the Congress to discharge the Comptroller for "inefficiency," "abuse of
office," "neglect of duty," or "malfeasance." 459 The Court said that these
words conferred on Congress "very broad" removal power and would
authorize Congress to remove the Comptroller for "any number of actual or
perceived transgressions of legislative will."460</p>
      <p>The words governing congressional power over the Comptroller
General and presidential power over independent agencies are
substantially the same. If those words have the same meaning in these admittedly
different contexts, the President turns out to have considerable power
over the commissioners. If the words have the same meaning, the
456. See, e.g., Humphrey's Executor, 295 U.S. at 628; see also supra note 438.
457. 478 U.S. 714 (1986).
458. See id. at 726.
459. 31 U.S.C. § 703(e) (1) (B) (1988).
460. 478 U.S. at 729.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>COLUMBIA LAW REWEW</title>
      <p>President has "very broad" removal power over the commissioners of the
independent agencies, with correlative powers of supervision and
guidance. It would follow that the independent agencies are in fact subject
to a considerable degree of presidential control "for any number of
actual or perceived transgressions of presidential will." They are not, as a
matter of statute, "independent" of him at all.</p>
      <p>This is an adventurous and not unassailable conclusion. As we have
noted, it is inconsistent with the general 461 understanding that
independent agencies are immune from the policy oversight of the President. It
would of course be plausible to suggest that because of the difference in
the contexts, the same words should have different meanings. Perhaps a
statute restricting congressional power over the Comptroller General
should be understood to impose thinner limitations than a statute
controlling presidential power over independent commissioners-even if the
words are the same. Such a reading would hardly be an implausible
reconstruction of legislative goals. Congress unquestionably created many
of the independent agencies in a period in which it sought to limit
presidential supervisory power.</p>
      <p>In view of what we see as the constitutional backdrop, however,
courts should probably invoke a "clear statement" principle;46 2 one that
interprets statutes to grant the President broad supervisory power over
the commissions. On this approach, courts would allow the President
such power unless Congress has expressly stated its will to the contrary.
Such an approach would minimize the risks of the independent agency
form and promote coordination and accountability in government. It
would recognize that many independent agencies perform important
policymaking functions, and that the performance of such functions by
truly independent agents is plausibly inconsistent with the constitutional
structure. 463 At the very least, we would require Congress to speak
unambiguously if it wants to compromise those goals.4 4 These suggestions do
not answer the question of precisely when the President may discharge
the commissioners. But they do indicate that he has far more authority
than is usually thought.</p>
      <p>461. This common understanding is not, however, universal; the American Bar
Association appears to agree with the point we are making here. See American Bar Assoc.
Recommendation, reprinted in Strauss &amp; Sunstein, supra note 11, app. at 206-07. The
Department ofJustice also holds this view. See Memorandum for Hon. David Stockman
Director, Office of Management and Budget, reprinted in Peter M. Shane &amp; Harold H.
Bruff, The Law of Presidential Power: Cases and Materials 355, 357-58 (1988).</p>
      <p>462. Cf. Kent v. Dulles, 357 U.S. 116, 129 (1958) (declaring the Court will construe
narrowly all delegated powers that may curtail citizens' right to travel).</p>
      <p>463. See supra Part V.A.
464. See also Strauss &amp;Sunstein, supra note 11, at 197-205.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>May Congress Create Truly IndependentAdministrators?</title>
      <p>Suppose that the independent counsel could never be removed by
the Attorney General, even "for good cause." Or suppose that Congress
amended the statute governing the FTC so as to provide that the
commissioners are independent of both Congress and the President, in the sense
that they could be removed by the President only for "high crimes and
misdemeanors" or "gross misconduct amounting to criminality." Would
such statutes be constitutional?</p>
      <p>Nothing in the relevant cases clearly decides these questions.
Probably the best answer is that the independent counsel must be removable
for "good cause" in order to qualify as an "inferior officer" (and thus be
appointable, as the current law provides, by judges465 ). The notion of
"inferior" implies the existence of a superior, and a truly independent
counsel-that is, one not at all controllable by the Attorney General or
the President-would have no superior. We may therefore infer from the
Morrison Court's emphasis on the "good cause" provision that some sort
of control by the Attorney General (or otherwise through the chain of
command headed by the President) is a constitutional imperative for
"inferior officers."466 Nothing we have said here is inconsistent with this
understanding.</p>
      <p>The question is more difficult for the Federal Trade Commissioner.
He is not an inferior officer appointed byjudges, and indeed he has been
appointed through the normal channels, that is, by the President subject
to advice and consent by the Senate. The question is therefore one of
permissible constraints on the power of removal and supervision. In
Bowsher and indeed Myers itself, Congress reserved to itself a role in
removal-raising the problem of encroachment 467-and a truly
independent commissioner (or head of OSHA, or the EPA, or the Department of
Education) would not suffer from that infirmity. On the question
whether Congress can create genuinely independent administrators,
there is precious little guidance.</p>
      <p>Probably the best answer is that as a general rule (and subject to
important exceptions), Congress is without constitutional power wholly
to immunize administrative officers exercising important discretionary
policymaking authority from presidential control. Congress is therefore
without power to create a "headless Fourth Branch" of government.4 68
465. See U.S. Const. art. II, § 2, cl. 2; 28 U.S.C. § 593(b) (1988).
466. See Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654, 691-93 (1987).</p>
      <p>467. See Bowsher v. Synar, 478 U.S. 714, 727 (1986) (statute made Comptroller
General removable only at initiative of Congress); Myers v. United States, 272 U.S. 52, 107
(1926) (Act required consent of Congress to remove Postmaster).</p>
      <p>468. See Freytag v. Commissioner, 111 S. Ct. 2631, 2661 (1991) (Scalia, J.,
concurring) (agreeing that ChiefJudge of Tax Court isa "head of a department"); see also
FTC v. Ruberoid Co., 343 U.S. 470, 487 (1952) (Jackson, J., dissenting) ("[Administrative
bodies) have begun to have important consequences on personal rights.... They have
become a veritablefourth branch of the Government, which has deranged our three-branch
To be sure, true independence in administration does not create the
distinctive dangers of encroachment and aggrandizement; 46 9 but it does
threaten the core constitutional commitments to political accountability,
expedition in office, and coordinated policymaking. If our argument
from changed circumstances is persuasive, Congress cannot properly
immunize such officers from the President without violating the Vesting
Clause of Article II and thus exceeding its power under the Necessary and
Proper Clause.</p>
      <p>There are important exceptions to this general proposition. These
would include (1) purely adjudicative officers, 470 (2) people who
perform ministerial duties, 47 1 and (3) people who perform merely
investigatory and reportorial functions-recall that Congress can have a staff.472
All three exceptions have historical roots. But subject to these
exceptions, we believe that Congress could not create fully independent
officials without offense to the constitutional structure, at least in the
absence of special circumstances. This conclusion follows from the
constitutional commitments to coordination, accountability, and prevention
of factionalism.</p>
      <p>Whether current courts should so conclude is another question. It
may be that in light of the difficulty of the relevant line-drawing
problems, courts should defer to legislative judgments, and the
constitutional prohibition should be under-enforced by judges.4 73 Certainly
courts should give Congress the benefit of the doubt in close cases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>E. Independence Versus Aggrandizement</title>
      <p>Here we arrive at a crucial innovation in the post-1980 cases-the
distinction between encroachment and independence. The cleanest line
between Bowsher and Chadhaon the one hand and Mistrettaand Morrison
on the other is that in the first two cases Congress attempted to give itself
a degree of ongoing authority over the administration of the laws.474 The
legal theories much as the concept of a fourth dimension unsettles our three-dimensional
thinking." (emphasis added)).</p>
      <p>469. See infra Part IV.E.
470. See supra text accompanying note 420.
471. See id.</p>
      <p>472. This was the meaning of the reference to quasi-legislative duties in Humphrey's
Executor, the Court was not discussing rulemaking power, in which the FTC was not
engaged at the time. See Humphrey's Executor v. United States, 295 U.S. 602, 628 (1935).</p>
      <p>473. This isJustice Scalia's approach to the nondelegation doctrine. See Mistretta v.
United States, 488 U.S. 361, 415-16 (1989) (Scalia, J., dissenting); see also Richard B.
Stewart, The Reformation of American Administrative Law, 88 Harv. L. Rev. 1667,
1693-97, 1799-1800 (1975).</p>
      <p>474. Compare Bowsher v. Synar, 478 U.S. 714, 734 (1986) (finding unconstitutional
simultaneous grant of executive powers to and retention of congressional control over
Comptroller General) and INS v. Chadha, 462 U.S. 919, 959 (1983) (finding
unconstitutional congressional reservation of veto power over executive decision to allow
deportable alien to remain in United States) with Mistretta,488 U.S. at 411 (upholding Act
limiting President's removal power over Federal Sentencing Commissioners to "good
Court has firmly set itself against such aggrandizement. In the Court's
view, independence in administration is one thing; congressional
encroachment into the administrative process is quite another.
"Aggrandizement" and "encroachment" are defining constitutional evils.
Separation of administration from the President and Congress does not
involve either aggrandizement or encroachment, and is far less
objectionable.</p>
      <p>The Court has not given a clear rationale for this sharp distinction.
In some ways it seems quite puzzling. For one thing, independence can
be understood as a form of aggrandizement. Congress might make
agencies independent not to create real independence, but in order to
diminish presidential authority over their operations precisely in the interest of
subjecting those agencies to the control of congressional committees. 4 75
Independence, in short, might be a way of increasing legislative power
over agencies. More fundamentally, the distinction sometimes reads like
a kind of "turf protection" model of the Constitution, one that is
disassociated from text, history, or structure, and also from any underlying
values that maintenance of the relevant "turfs" are supposed to preserve. 4 76</p>
      <p>The question, in short, is this: How is the presence of a
congressional role in law-execution worse than an absence of a presidential role?
It might be thought that the two pose equivalent risks to constitutional
commitments.</p>
      <p>But there are in fact plausible structural reasons for the distinction.
First, congressional control over administration creates a specter of
combination of lawmaking functions and law-executing functions. The
decision to divide the two is unambiguous in the Constitution, and that
decision is in turn a product of a belief that the division is an important
guarantor of private liberty, democratic control over government, and
protection against factionalism. Encroachment is plausibly a greater
threat to these values than independence. 477
cause") and Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654, 691 (1988) (upholding Act requiring that
Attorney General have "good cause" for removing independent counsel).</p>
      <p>475. See Sunstein, supra note 430, at 430; Weingast &amp; Moran, Bureaucratic
Discretion, supra note 433, at 768-70; Weingast &amp; Moran, Runaway Bureaucracy, supra
note 433, at 33-34.</p>
      <p>476. See Rebecca L. Brown, Separated Powers and Ordered Liberty, 139 U. Pa. L. Rev.
1513, 1546-48 (1991) (arguing for substantive, individualist approach to separation of
powers rather than a structural "turf"-oriented one).</p>
      <p>477. To be sure, the broad discretionary authority of an agency may also combine
functions. But the Administrative Procedure Act (APA) helps counter this problem, see 5
U.S.C. §§ 554, 556, 557 (1988), and we think these provisions have constitutional
foundations. It is not an adequate answer to say that independence itself threatens this
value. Independent agencies are subject to a degree of internal separation of functions.
See id. § 554 (precluding agency employees who engage in prosecution from participating
or advising in decisions). This provision, together with other safeguards in the APA,
counteracts some of the risks involved in combination of execution and legislation. We
think that provisions of this kind are responsive to genuine constitutional concerns; they</p>
      <p>Second, the prohibition on congressional participation operates as a
check against open-ended delegations of power. If Congress may not
delegate administrative authority to its own agents, it is likely to be clearer
in delegating policymaking authority in the first instance. We can
understand the Court's hostility to encroachment as having roots in the
structural commitment against open-ended delegations of authority, a
commitment with clear connections to the goal of providing a kind of
accountability. 478 Congress may be content not to set out law in advance
if it knows that it may control implementation decisions on a case-by-case
basis. Even if the Court will not play a large role in enforcing the
nondelegation doctrine directly, mostly for institutional reasons, 4 79 it can
discipline the prospect of delegation through institutionally acceptable
devices that impose incentives on Congress to limit the scope of
delegation.</p>
      <p>Courts have not yet explained the distinction between independence
on the one hand and encroachment and aggrandizement on the other.
We do not suggest that it should be made as critical as the Supreme Court
has made it. But if the foregoing arguments are right, the distinction can
be explained by reference to constitutional structure. It makes sense as a
means of separating functions and discouraging broad delegation of
lawmaking authority.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-13">
      <title>F. Cross-BranchAppointments</title>
      <p>Morrison upholds cross-branch appointments,48 0 but the Court was
properly cautious about the basic idea, which could produce many
oddities. Suppose, for example, that Congress said that judges would
henceforth appoint the Assistant Secretaries of State and Defense and the
Assistant Attorneys General. In such cases, there would have to be an
implicit structural limit on Congress' power under the Inferior Officers
have a kind of constitutional status, not in the sense that courts should mandate them, but
in the sense that they grow out of constitutional commitments.</p>
      <p>478. We think that this idea does have roots in Article I of the Constitution, see A.L.A.
Schechter Poultry Corp. v United States, 295 U.S. 495, 529 (1935) (citing Necessary and
Proper Clause as support for prohibiting congressional abdication or transfer of "essential
legislative functions"); TheodoreJ. Lowi, The End of Liberalism: The Second Republic of
the United States 92-97 (2d ed. 1979) (criticizing as unconstitutional liberal delegations of
power by Congress to administrative agencies); see also Theodore J. Lowi, Two Roads to
Serfdom: Liberalism, Conservatism and Administrative Power, 36 Am. U. L. Rev. 295
(1986) (describing how broad delegations of power defeat the rule of law as embodied in
the Constitution), even though we do not believe that courts should carefully police the
prohibition, see Richard B. Stewart, Beyond Delegation Doctrine, 36 Am. U. L. Rev. 323,
324 (1987) (arguing against court invalidation of statutes based on over-delegation).</p>
      <p>479. See Mistretta v. United States, 488 U.S. 361, 371-74 (1989); id. at 413-16 (Scalia,
J., dissenting) (but concurring on fall of nondelegation doctrine); Stewart, supra note 478,
at 326.</p>
      <p>480. See Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654 (1988).
Appointment Clause.4 8 ' Otherwise Congress could wreak havoc with the
system of checks and balances.</p>
      <p>But when are cross-branch appointments constitutional? Probably
the answer lies in the Court's emphasis in Morrison on the absence of an
"incongruity" in the vesting of appointment power in another branch.48 2
We should understand the term to refer to principles of constitutional
structure, having to do with the integrity of each branch. Where there is
incongruity, the Constitution contains a structural barrier to the
placement of appointing authority. It follows that in the cases we have
hypothesized, there would be a valid objection based on the system of checks
and balances. But this idea casts no doubt on Morrison itself. Indeed, in
Morrison presidential appointment might itself have been incongruous in
light of the obvious conflict of interest. The congressional judgment was
permissible only for this reason.</p>
      <p>If this is the relevant concern, cross-branch appointments should be
permitted only in the narrowest circumstances. On this view, Morrison
was a case about the oddity of allowing the President to be the judge in
his own cause. It does not stand for any broader proposition.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-14">
      <title>G. Precisely Which Officers May Be Protected with a Good Cause Standard?</title>
      <p>Both Mistretta and Morrison allow certain officials exercising
important governmental responsibilities to be immunized from plenary
presidential control.48 3 But it is surely true that some employees must serve at
the will of the President. Without offering a detailed analysis of the
complexities here, we suggest that there are four distinct categories of cases,
and that the categories should be treated differently.</p>
      <p>(1) High-level officials who exercise foreign affairs powers and other
authorities included in the enumerated authority of the President 484
must be at-will employees. This much follows from adherence to the
original understanding. As we have seen, the founding belief in a unitary
executive entailed presidential control over a range of important
functions.485 Nothing in current circumstances argues in the other direction.
Thus (to take the two principal examples) the Secretary of State and the
Secretary of Defense must be at-will employees.</p>
      <p>481. See U.S. Const. art. II, § 2, cl. 2.</p>
      <p>482. See 487 U.S. at 676. One may question, however, whether this judgment of
congruity is one the Constitution allows the Supreme Court to make. Article II, section 2,
clause 2 provides that Congress may "by Law vest the Appointment of such inferior
Officers, as they think prper,in the President alone, in the Courts of Law, or in the Heads of
Departments." The emphasized language may indicate that thejudgment as to propriety is
left to Congress alone. Consider section 3 of Article II, which provides that the President
"may adjourn them to such Time as he shall think proper," which likewise would appear to
vest thejudgment in the President alone. See also U.S. Const. art. I, § 9, ci. 1 (states may
continue migration of people as they "think proper" to admit).</p>
      <p>483. See 488 U.S. at 410; 487 U.S. at 691.
484. See U.S. Const. art. II, § 2.
485. See supra text accompanying notes 121-122, 131.
(2) Good cause limitations are permissible for officers who exercise
adjudicative or ministerial functions. The original understanding
exemplified this judgment,48 6 and our argument for changed circumstances
does not undermine or complicate that analysis.</p>
      <p>(3) The same conclusion applies to those few officials who have the
sorts of conflicts of interest exemplified by the Federal Reserve Board and
independent counsels. This conclusion builds on historical
understandings.48 7 It also fits comfortably with current institutional arrangements.</p>
      <p>(4) Domestic officials who do not fall within (1), (2), or (3) may be
protected by "good cause" provisions, but for the most part only if those
provisions are interpreted so that the relevant officials are controllable
through general policy directions of the President. As we have said, a
good cause standard should be interpreted to allow for a high degree of
presidential supervisory authority.488 At least in most cases involving
important policymaking functions, a removal standard would be
unconstitutional if it were inconsistent with this idea, that is, if it entirely eliminated
presidential control over general policy decisions. It follows that
Congress could allow many officials to be protected by a "good cause"
provision-not merely the heads of such traditionally "independent"
agencies as the FCC, FTC, and SEC, but also those of (for example) the
EPA and some of the Cabinet departments as well. But on our
understanding, a good cause limitation does not immunize the relevant officials
from the policy direction and oversight of the President.48 9</p>
      <p>CONCLUSION</p>
      <p>The framers did not constitutionalize presidential control over all
that is now considered "executive"; they did not believe that the President
must have plenary power over all we now think of as administration. The
textual argument to the contrary uses twentieth century understandings
to give meaning to eighteenth century terms.</p>
      <p>With respect to implementation of the laws, history suggests that the
framers understood Congress to have broad power to structure
government arrangements as it saw fit. Many prosecutors, state as well as
federal, were free from the control of the Attorney General and the
President. The first Congress also made the Comptroller free from
presidential control, because some of his functions were related to those of
Congress and the judiciary. The Postmaster General was similarly
immu486. See supra text accompanying notes 103, 126-130, 236-248 (discussing original
view that ministerial functions, and also those involving adjudicative powers, could be
immunized from the President).</p>
      <p>487. See supra note 137 and accompanying text (discussing founders' desire to keep
separate the purse and sword); supra text accompanying note 444 (noting Hamilton's
concern that no person should be judge in his own cause).</p>
      <p>488. See supra Part 1V.C.</p>
      <p>489. Of course, this notion leaves a degree of vagueness, and it does not resolve many
particular issues that might arise through assertions of presidential authority.
nized from presidential control, because of his distinctive role in
spending taxpayer funds. The Opinions Clause would be entirely superfluous if
the framers understood the President to have plenary control over
administration; why would the framers deem it necessary to give the
President the power to demand written opinions from people over whom
he had full control as a matter of constitutional compulsion? Finally, the
text and history of the Necessary and Proper Clause suggest that Congress
had considerable authority to structure the executive branch as it chose.</p>
      <p>In light ofall these considerations, our first goal has been to respond
to the persistent notion that if we care about constitutional text and
history, independent prosecutors and independent agencies are an
embarrassing accommodation to political necessity, or a shameful compromise
with expediency. We have shown that the belief in a strongly unitary
executive does not derive from the framers themselves.</p>
      <p>We reach this conclusion about the framers with reluctance. The
belief in a strongly unitary executive has considerable appeal. It is simple
and unambiguous. It fits well with important political and constitutional
values, including the interests in political accountability, in coordination
of the law, and in uniformity in regulation. Believing that these interests
have constitutional status, we have ventured an argument on behalf of
the strongly unitary executive, one that emphasizes changed
circumstances and an interpretive practice concerned with fidelity to original
commitments and labeled here as translation.</p>
      <p>The crucial development in this regard is the downfall of the
nondelegation doctrine and the rise of unforeseen administrative
agencies exercising wide-ranging discretionary power over the domestic
sphere. In view of this development, it would not be faithful to the
original design to permit officers in the executive branch, making
discretionary judgments about important domestic issues, to be immunized from
presidential control. We have therefore sketched an argument on behalf
of a strongly unitary executive, in which the President has a high degree
of supervisory and removal authority over most officials entrusted with
discretion in the implementation of federal law. We have applied this
argument to many areas of current dispute.</p>
      <p>We believe that this view is consistent with constitutional
commitments and that it maintains fidelity with those commitments in
dramatically changed circumstances. But it is important to acknowledge that our
argument is based on a distinctive method, one that rejects ahistorical
claims about the unitary executive. It follows that the constitutional
commitment to unitary execution of the laws should not be rooted in the
supposed mandates of history. It should be based instead on the effort to
interpret the Constitution faithfully over time, an effort that will
inevitably involve a large measure of pragmatic judgment, and historical
understanding.
Cu 4 )
-o
UcI.</p>
      <p>U</p>
      <p>0
0)4
40 c
04
044
Z44
0)-4
4)0
'v 0
,.4</p>
      <p>Cu</p>
      <p>Cuu</p>
      <p>0404
i0'0* 00 00
4.t.(l
0c 0 0</p>
      <p>C"</p>
      <p>CC</p>
      <p>0
mC.
0~U</p>
      <p>c
WbE
m</p>
      <p>0
s.</p>
      <p>0
w</p>
      <p>C/)i
...</p>
      <p>CIS.0j
a,
*</p>
      <p>t4
0</p>
      <p>0 qw
CLr~d
cl</p>
      <p>0
V.</p>
      <p>.
0)0).
00
0
40CC
0
d0 r.)
00~</p>
      <p>C~
bO 0</p>
      <p>0C1C0
.0,0. C) U)
0
W U00
0
0d
C)</p>
      <p>U)d
cn
4
0
0 o
0
*</p>
      <p>V</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-15">
      <title>COLUMBIA LAW REVIEW</title>
      <p>w * 00 0 t40
0~
c 0 Cd
0 000
o~ 0 b )
o
0 CIS
0
" 0
w 0
0 0
0
0 "AEE
040c
CSo</p>
      <p>C,0
a
0
0U
o~ C.
0</p>
      <p>0
0-0 U4
w 01
w
1 0
z 0 '
S.~010
oUC 01C. )</p>
      <p>01 0</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          120
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          . In Harmelin v.
          <source>Michigan</source>
          , 111
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>2680</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ),
          <article-title>Justice Scalia sketched the</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Construction</surname>
            , 11 Harv.
            <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Pub</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Pol'y
          <volume>59</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ); Richard S. Kay, Adherence to the
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>Original Intentions in Constitutional Adjudication: Three Objections and Responses</source>
          ,
          <volume>82</volume>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Nw. U. L.</given-names>
            <surname>Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>226</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Michael W. McConnell, The Origins</article-title>
          and Historical
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>Understanding of Free Exercise of Religion</source>
          ,
          <volume>103</volume>
          Harv. L. Rev.
          <volume>1409</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ). Compare
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Ollman v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Evans</source>
          ,
          <volume>750</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>970</volume>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>995 (D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1984</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Bork</article-title>
          , J., concurring) (following
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>denied</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 471 U.S.
          <volume>1127</volume>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          )
          <article-title>with 750 F.2d at 1038 n.2 (ScaliaJ., dissenting) (arguing that</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>the method that we are using here can be described ds one form of originalism</article-title>
          . 35.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cf</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Ronald Dworkin,
          <source>Law's Empire 361-63</source>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          )
          <article-title>(showing how fidelity to beliefs</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Constitution</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>See id. at 398</source>
          . 36.
          <article-title>For examples of cases that can be understood to use this methodology of</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          translation, see Lessig,
          <source>supra note 4</source>
          , at 1214-
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>The most famous of these may well be</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          319 U.S.
          <volume>624</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>639</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          (
          <year>1943</year>
          )
          <article-title>(emphasis added). It is significant that Justice Jackson was</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>context may be a more precise way of describing the first question posed, that is, whether 53</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>See id</article-title>
          . at 705-
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          (Scalia, J.,
          <source>dissenting)</source>
          .
          <volume>54</volume>
          . Id. at 706 (Scalia, J.,
          <source>dissenting)</source>
          .
          <volume>55</volume>
          . Again,
          <article-title>this method was used byJustice Scalia in Harmelin v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Michigan</source>
          , 111
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <volume>2680</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>2691</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <source>See supra note 34</source>
          . 56.
          <article-title>While the Constitution explicitly grants the President five executive powers,</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Political</given-names>
            <surname>Departments</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 1
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Hastings</given-names>
            <surname>Const</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L.Q.
          <volume>13</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          ). Compare Peter Strauss'
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>list</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Strauss,
          <source>supra note 7</source>
          , at 598 (
          <article-title>listing only Article II powers, thereby omitting veto</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>power)</source>
          .
          <volume>57</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Harold</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Krent</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Executive Control Over Criminal Law Enforcement
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Some</given-names>
            <surname>Lessons From History</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>38</volume>
          Am. U. L. Rev.
          <volume>275</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ); Daniel N. Reisman,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Executive</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 53 Alb. L. Rev.
          <volume>49</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Stephanie A</article-title>
          .J. Dangel, Note, Is Prosecution a
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Core</given-names>
            <surname>Executive</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Function? Morrison v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Olson and the Framers' Intent, 99 Yale LJ. 1069</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>It is important to emphasize that we are not saying a unitarian must link this</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>consider it here first as just one possibility</article-title>
          .
          <source>59. See Act ofJune 22</source>
          ,
          <year>1870</year>
          , ch.
          <volume>150</volume>
          ,
          <issue>16</issue>
          <year>Stat</year>
          .
          <volume>162</volume>
          . 60. SeeJudiciary Act of 1789, ch.
          <volume>20</volume>
          , §
          <volume>35</volume>
          , 1 Stat.
          <volume>73</volume>
          , 93; Lawrence Lessig, Readings by
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>our Unitary Executive</source>
          , 15 Cardozo L.
          <year>Rev</year>
          .
          <volume>175</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          . See id.
          <volume>62</volume>
          . See White,
          <source>supra note 42, at 164-68. 63. See Judiciary Act of 1789 § 35</source>
          , 1 Stat. at 92.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <year>1861</year>
          .
          <article-title>6) Throughout this period, they operated without any clear organi-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>zational structure or hierarchy. 65</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

