<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Incommensurability and Valuation in Law
Author(s): Cass R. Sunstein
Reviewed work(s):
Source: Michigan Law Review</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>92</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>779</fpage>
      <lpage>861</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at . http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp . JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org. http://www.jstor.org</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>The Michigan Law Review Association is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to
Michigan Law Review.</p>
      <p>This content downloaded on Thu, 27 Dec 2012 21:04:53 PM</p>
      <p>All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions
780
782
782
785
790
* Karl N. Llewellyn Professor of Jurisprudence,University of Chicago. A.B. 1975, J.D.
1978, Harvard. - Ed. Participants in workshops at the Columbia, University of Chicago,
Harvard, Hofstra, New York University, and Yale Law Schools provided extremely valuable
help. Bruce Ackerman, Albert Alschuler, Anne-Marie Burley, Ruth Chang, Jon Elster, Richard
Epstein, Stephen Gilles, Abner Greene, Charles Larmore, Larry Lessig, Martha Nussbaum,
Richard Pildes, Richard Posner, Eric Rakowski, J. Mark Ramseyer, Joseph Raz, Henry
Richardson, Stephen Schulhofer, David Strauss, Lloyd Weinreb, and Steven Winter provided
helpful remarkson a previous draft. For financial support I am grateful to the Russell Baker
Scholars Fund and the James H. Douglas, Jr. Fund for the Study of Law and Government.</p>
      <p>779</p>
      <p>In this article I explore two claims and discuss their implications
for law. The first claim is that human values are plural and diverse.</p>
      <p>By this I mean that we value things, events, and relationshipsin ways
that are not reducible to some larger and more encompassing value.</p>
      <p>The second claim is that human goods are not commensurable. By
this I mean that such goods are not assessed along a single metric. For
reasonsto be explored, the two claims, though related,are importantly
different.</p>
      <p>These claims are emphatically not meant to deny the existence of
grounds for evaluating private and public choices, both among kinds
of valuation and among incommensurablegoods. But efforts to insist
on a single kind of valuationand to make goods commensurable,while
designed to aid in human reasoning, actually make such reasoning
inferior to what it is when it is working well.</p>
      <p>For the moment these claims must remain obscure; I will devote
considerablespace to the effort to make them more clear. If they are
plausible, views of this sort are likely to have important implications
for law. To be sure, endorsement of the two claims need not lead to
any particular view about legal problems. To say that law ought to
value something in a certain way, we need to make a substantiveclaim
about some issue of the good or the right, and a mere referenceto the
diversity of values does not supply that claim. Nonetheless, I hope to
show that debatesover ways of valuing things, and over issues of
commensurability,help to reveal what is at stake in many areas of the law.</p>
      <p>A unifying claim involves the expressivefunction of law - the law's
role in reflecting and communicating particular ways of valuing
human goods. Many legal debates actually involve the
appropriateness of differentkinds of valuation in differentareas of law.</p>
      <p>For example, a liberal society containing diverse social
spheresfamilies, markets, politics, religious organizations - makes space for
different kinds of valuation. With an understanding of these diverse
kinds, we will be able to see why voluntary exchanges should usually
be protected, and also why they should sometimes be blocked. Some
otherwise puzzling anomalies in the theory of environmental
protection will take on new aspects. An understanding of diverse kinds of
valuation will help shed light on certain claims about the nature of sex
discrimination. I suggest that a Kantian norm, having to do with
appropriate ways of valuing human beings, accounts for widespread
views about abortion, the distributionof labor within marriage,sexual
harassment, prostitution, pornography, surrogacy, and much else
besides. With an understandingof this sort, it will be possible as well to
understand some features of practical reason in law, especially in the
old area of analogical thinking, but also in new areas involving the
theory and practice of the regulatory state.</p>
      <p>In pressing claims about incommensurabilityand diverse kinds of
valuation, I have both a general target and a positive goal. The target
consists of monistic theories of value, particularly as these appear in
the study of law.' Monistic theories are pervasive;they have a strong
philosophical pedigree;and, in various guises, they come up in many
discussions of particularlegal issues. To be sure, it may seem that few
people really subscribe to such theories. Surely most people do not
deny that human values are plural. But there is a distinguished
tradition of thought, found in such diverse thinkers as Plato and Bentham,2
that insists that values should be seen as unitary and that human
goods should be seen as commensurable. In their most austere forms,
these ideas are rarely endorsed explicitly in law; but more modest
versions play a large role in the legal context - not simply in economic
analysis,3but also in some aspects of rights-basedthinking insofar as it
takes a unitary value as the basis for evaluating law.4 In any case,
problems of commensurabilityhave yet to receive sustained attention
in law; and it is importantto see exactly how goods are diverse, and in
what ways goods are incommensurable,even if some version of these
claims might turn out, upon reflection, to be widely shared.</p>
      <p>1. For a general account of and challenge to monistic theories, see ELIZABETHANDERSON,
VALUEIN ETHICSANDECONOMIC1S17-40 (1993).</p>
      <p>2. On Plato, see MARTHAC. NUSSBAUMP,lato on Commensurabilityand Desire, in LOVE'S
KNOWLEDGE100, 106-24 (1990); David Wiggins, Weaknessof Will. Commensurability,and the
Objectsof Deliberationand Desire, 79 PROCO.FTHEARISTOTELIASNOCY2.51 (1978-1979). The
best discussion of Bentham remains JOHN STUART MILL, MILL ON BENTHAM AND COLERIDGE
(F.R. Leavis ed., 1962) (1838).</p>
      <p>3. See generallyGARYS. BECKERA, TREATISEONTHEFAMILY(2d ed. 1991);RICHAR)A.</p>
      <p>POSNERT,HEECONOMICOSFJUSTICE(1981).</p>
      <p>4. See RONALDDWORKINT,AKINGRIGHTSSERIOUSLY180-83. 272-78 (1978) (applying a
neo-Kantian value of "equal concern and respect" to various legal problems).</p>
      <p>I particularly want to show some distinctive ways in which
economic analysis of law, and most forms of utilitarianismas well, miss
important commitments of a well-functioning legal system. I hope
also to establish that a surprisinglywide range of legal disputes can be
illuminated by an understanding of incommensurability and diverse
kinds of valuation. The value of this enterpriseconsists not in
dictating particular conclusions, which depend on the details, but in
enabling us to see an important basis for widespread concerns and
convictions. I emphasize that to see values as incommensurable,and
to say that people are really disputing appropriatekinds (not levels) of
valuation, is not by itself to resolve legal disputes. It is necessary to
say something about the right kind - to offer a substantivetheory
and to investigatethe particularsin great detail, in order to make
progress in hard cases in law. But an understandingof problems of
incommensurabilitywill make it easier to see what is at stake.</p>
      <p>This article is organized into six Parts. The first three Parts
explore some foundationalissues. Part I describesdiverse kinds of
valuation and responds to the claim that we value different things in the
same way. Part II offers a working definition of incommensurability.</p>
      <p>Part III discusses an important challenge to the claims in Parts I and
II. It also offers some notes on the stakes, attempting to show why
these issues matter.</p>
      <p>Part IV makes general remarksabout law, with
particularemphasis on law's expressive function. The fifth and most detailed Part
surveys areas in which an understandingof kinds of valuation and of
incommensurabilitymay affectour understandingof law. In this Part,
I discuss a wide range of issues, including social differentiation,the
EstablishmentClause, political equality, cost-benefitanalysis, contract
remedies, environmental regulation, and feminism. The sixth Part
ventures some preliminary remarks on the important issue of choice
- choice among differentkinds of valuation and choice among
incommensurable goods. In the sixth Part, I also offer a few notes on the
importance of the sense of tragedy in law.</p>
      <p>I.</p>
      <p>A.</p>
      <p>KINDS OF VALUATION5</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Definitions and Examples</title>
      <p>Human beings value goods, things, relationships, and states of
affairs in diverse ways.6 Begin with the distinction between
instrumen5. I owe much help in the discussion here to ANDERSON, supra note 1, at 8-16. Anderson
uses the term modes of valuationto refer to the same basic idea.</p>
      <p>6. For an especially instructive discussion of this point, see id. at 8-11. See also MICHAEL
tal and intrinsic goods. We value some things purely or principally for
use; consider hammers, forks, or money. But we value other things at
least in part for their own sake; consider knowledge or friendship.
Because it is so pertinent to law, the distinction between instrumental
and intrinsic value will play an important role here. But that
distinction captures only a part of the picture. Intrinsically valued things
produce a range of diverse responses. Some bring about wonder and
awe; consider a mountain or certain artistic works. Toward some
people, we feel respect; toward others, affection; toward others, love.
People worship their deity. Some events produce gratitude; others
produce joy; others are thrilling; others make us feel content; others
bring about delight. Some things are valued if they meet certain
standards, like a musical or athletic performance or perhaps a pun.7</p>
      <p>Negative valuations are similarly diverse. To lose money is to lose
an instrumental good - though one that might be used for intrinsic
goods, like the preservation of human life. To lose a friend is a
different matter. So, too, our responses to intrinsic bads are diverse. We
might be horrified by an act of cruelty, disgusted by an ugly scene,
shocked by a betrayal of friendship or love, made indignant by a
failure of respect, frightened by the prospect of loss, angered by the
infliction of a wound, saddened by undeserved hardship, or frustrated by
the failure of our plans. These various terms themselves include a
variety of experiences that embody diverse ideas about evaluation. Not
all forms of sadness - very much an umbrella term - are the same;
so too with disgust - compare reactions to cruelty and reactions to
ugliness - and so on.</p>
      <p>There are, then, different kinds of goods, and human beings
experience their lives in ways that reflect a wide variety of kinds of
valuation.8 The term is meant to draw attention to our diverse stances
toward relationships or prospects, or to the disparate theories of
valuation through which we conceive and evaluate relationships, events, or
prospects. Every kind of valuation embodies a qualitatively distinctive
judgment or response. People react to events, to things, and to one
another in accordance with the nature and clarity of distinctions
STOCKERP,LURALANDCONFLICTINVGALUES213 (1990); R.E. Chang, Irredeemabilitiesand
Constitutive Incommensurabilitiesor Buying and Selling Friends (July 1993)
(unpublishedmanuscript, on file with author). One could express the same general thought through a reference
not to diverse kinds of valuation, but to diverse goods. For my purposes here, I do not believe
that much is at stake between the two formulations. I refer to kinds of valuation because the
term points explicitly to the interactive nature of valuation; goods are goods for reasons that
human beings attribute to them.</p>
      <p>7. See ANDERSON, supra note 1, at 3-4.
8. Id. at 6.
among possible kinds of valuation. Someone who does not make
appropriate distinctions might be labeled odd or even weird.9 Someone
who does not make enough distinctions might seem thick or obtuse.</p>
      <p>We could categorize kinds of valuation in many different ways.
For purposes of law, it might make sense to focus on such things as
love, affection, respect, wonder, worship, and use;10 these notions
come up in many places of legal dispute. But each of these terms
captures a range of qualitatively distinct kinds of valuation. Love for a
parent is different from love for a child, which is in turn different from
love for a friend, a spouse, a pet, or a house. We might feel wonder
toward an act of selfless courage, and also toward a musical
performance or a beautiful beach. We might feel awe toward an athletic
performance and also toward a mountain. How, and how finely, we
should categorize kinds of valuation depends on the uses to which the
categories will be put. For law and politics, the number of useful
categories is undoubtedly smaller than it is for literature or poetry, which
may be especially concerned to offer fine-grained accounts.</p>
      <p>Distinctions among kinds of valuation are highly sensitive to the
particular setting in which they operate. People do not value goods
acontextually. In one setting - say, the workplace - the prevailing
kinds of valuation might be quite different from what they are
elsewhere - say, the home or the ballot box. Moreover, particular goods
typically do not admit of a single kind of valuation. The prevailing
kind has everything to do with the relationship among the various
actors. Thus a cat might be valued in a certain way by its owner, but in
a different way by a landlord, and in still a different way by a
government agency. Much of social differentiation stems from this
perception. 1 So, too, several kinds of valuation might be directed toward a
single object. A person might, for example, both love and respect a
friend or a lover.</p>
      <p>Different kinds of valuation cannot without significant loss be
reduced to a single "superconcept," like happiness, utility, or pleasure.12
Any such reduction produces significant loss because it yields an
inadequate description of our actual valuations when things are going well.</p>
      <p>9. Cf CHARLESTAYLOR, What Is Human Agency?, in 1 PHILOSOPHICALPAPERS 15, 15-27
(1985) (discussing evaluative depth).</p>
      <p>10. Cf ANDERSON, supra note 1, at 8-11.
11. See infra section V.A.</p>
      <p>12. By "reduced to" these things, I mean treated as simple aspects of them, in a way that
erases qualitative differences. Consider John Dewey's criticism of utilitarianism'scommitment
to the idea of "a fixed, final and supreme end":</p>
      <p>Such a point of view treats concrete activities and specificinterestsnot as worth while in
themselves, or as constituents of happiness,but as mere external means to getting pleasures.
The upholdersof the old traditioncould thereforeeasily accuse utilitarianismof making not
The inadequatedescriptionwill impair predictiveaccounts13 of human
behavior. It will also impair normativejudgments about ethics, law,
and politics. In making this latter point, I mean to reject relativist or
purely conventionalist accounts of kinds of valuation'4 and to suggest
that some kinds are more appropriatethan others. Judgments about
what is appropriatedepend of course on theories of the good or the
right; from the bare fact that kinds of valuation are diverse, we have
no basis for evaluating any legal or social practice. But it is important
to have diverse kinds of valuation - indeed we could not make sense
of our lives without them - and no matter what current conventions
may be, some kinds are poorly suited to some contexts because they
produce inferior lives. I begin to defend these controversial claims in
more detail below.15</p>
      <p>B. ConflictsAmong Kinds of Valuation, with Special Reference to</p>
      <p>Uses of Money</p>
      <p>Conflicts among diverse kinds of valuation permeate private and
public choice. Suppose that Smith has arrangedto have lunch with a
friend today, but that he has become very busy and perhapswould like
to cancel. Suppose Smith thinks in this way: if he cancels, his friend
will be disappointed,because he would like Smith's company, and also
a bit insulted, because it is cavalier and disrespectfulto cancel lunch at
the last minute. Maybe Smith should make it up to him, or provide
compensation, by offeringa nontrivial cash payment. This would be a
hopelessly inadequate response. A cash payment would be
inconsistent with the way that someone values a friend. Even if the friend
would prefer $1, or $10, or $100, or $1000 to lunch with Smith
even though at some point the payment would in some sense be worth
far more than the lunch and be readily accepted as an alternative
the offer of cash would be perceived as an insult rather than as
compensation. In this context, the differencein kinds of valuation means
only virtue but art, poetry, religion and the state into mere servile means of attaining
sensuous enjoyments....</p>
      <p>... The idea of a fixedand single end lying beyond the diversityof human needs and acts
renderedutilitarianismincapable of being an adequate representationof the modern spirit.
JOHN DEWEY, RECONSTRUCTIONIN PHILOSOPHY180-81, 183 (1920).</p>
      <p>13. Certainaspects of decision theory are untouched by these claims. A purely ordinal
ranking, for example, would be possible even if the point in text is right. But the point may give us
reason to question cost-benefitanalysis, see infra text accompanying notes 235-42, and also the
Coase Theorem, see infra text accompanying notes 232-33 (discussing offer-askingdisparity),
without necessarily questioning the use of indifference curves and utility functions to predict
human behavior.</p>
      <p>14. For one account verging on conventionalism, see the discussion of just distribution
within caste societies in MICHAEL WALZER, SPHERESOF JUSTICE312-16 (1987).
15. See infra Part II.
that a financial exchange would be inappropriate. The kind of
valuation of a friend blocks the use of otherwise acceptable grounds for
action.16 As we will see, the law is pervadedby principlesof this kind
- principles that forbid resort to reasons for action that are
acceptable in other contexts.</p>
      <p>The case is not exotic. Similar issues permeate the exceptionally
complex cluster of social norms regulating the appropriate use of
money as an incentive for action. For example, if an employer tells
you that, as an employee performinga certainjob, you must spend a
month away from your home and family, you might well agree. But if
someone tells you that he will pay you a monthly salary in order to
persuade you to spend a month away from home and family, you will
probably feel insulted and degraded, and you may well turn him
down.17 This second offer reflects an inappropriatevaluation of you
and your family - it suggests that your relationshipwith your family
is simply up for sale. The employer's offer treats you as an object of
contempt and perhaps ridicule. In the first case, the same cannot be
said. Even though in the first case the relationship might be thought
to have been "tradedfor" cash, the absence from family is a
by-product of employment, rather than something brought about as an end in
itself, desired for its own sake by one's boss. To see the two cases as
the same - as instances of trade-offs between family and income - is
to overlook an importantdistinction in the meanings of the two offers.</p>
      <p>Or suppose that we feel awe toward something. If we do, we will
not believe that it should be valued in the same way as its cash
equivalent. A simple or flat judgment that a mountain is "really
worth" $10 million is inconsistent with the way that we (or most of us)
value the mountain. This is because the mountain is valued through a
differentkind of valuation from the $10 million; the former produces
awe and wonder, whereas the latter is for human use - though
admittedly $10 million may produce a (different)sort of awe and wonder as
well. These points hold even if many people might be
indifferentbetween $10 million and the mountain in the sense that they do not
16. See infra the discussion of exclusionary reasons in section II.C. Note in this regardthe
social norm requiringthat, in some circumstances,gifts should not take the form of cash, which
is regardedas excessively impersonal. As compared with a gift of (say) $30, a gift of (say) a tie
costing $30 establishes a distinctive and often preferablerelationshipbetween the recipient and
the giver - even if in some contexts $30 in cash would be worth more to the recipient than the
$30 tie, and even if in some contexts a gift of $30 would be less costly, to the giver, than the gift
of a $30 tie. This point is interestinglymissed in Joel Waldfogel, TheDeadweightLoss of
Christmas, 83 AM. ECON.REV. 1328, 1336 (1993), which finds four billion dollars in annual
deadweight losses from noncash gifts and which assumes that cash gifts are always more efficientand
therefore generally preferable.</p>
      <p>17. The example comes from JOSEPHRAZ, THE MORALITYOF FREEDOM 348-49 (1986).
know which they would choose if both were offered;even if $10
million is in some sense the right amount to invest in protection of the
mountain from degradation;and even if, as seems clear, infinite
valuation of the mountain would be an irrationalallocation of scarce social
resources. The point does not suggest that pristine areas cannot be
degraded. But it does have a range of important and sometimes
overlooked consequences for how people involved in the legal system
might think about environmental protection.'8 It also suggests that
indifferencecurves have quite limited purposes and that they may be
misleading on some important matters. It may even suggest that we
should question the whole notion of indifferencecurves. Some people
may not be "indifferent"between two goods even though they do not
think that one is better than another.19</p>
      <p>Attention to diverse kinds of valuation casts general light on the
phenomenon of exchanges that are blocked by social norms. If
someone offersto pay an adult neighbor to mow his lawn, the neighborwill
often regardthe request as an insult, because it reflects an
inappropriate valuation of the neighbor. The request embodies an
improperconception of what the relationship is, or of the attitude with which
neighbors render services for each other. The impropriety remains
even if the offeree ordinarily would regard the offered wage as a fair
price for an hour of mowing services. In an extreme case, if someone
asks an attractiveperson (or a spouse) for sexual relations in returnfor
cash, the same would be said even more vehemently. Because of the
existence of diverse kinds of valuation, we may not be able to
generalize acontextual preferencesfrom particulardecisions. The point bears
on law as well. For example, decisions not to insure certain
goodsfreedom from pain and suffering, the well-being of one's children
need not suggest a global judgment about whether injuries to those
goods deserve compensation.20</p>
      <p>There is often a connection between blocked exchanges and ideas
about equal citizenship. The exchange may be barredby social norms
or law because of a perception that, while there may be disparities in
social wealth, the spheres in which people are very unequal ought not
to invade realms of social life in which equality is a social goal.21
Often this idea comes from the existence of a kind of valuation based
on equal respect. The legal prohibition on vote trading is an example.
So too with certain complex social bans on the use of wealth to buy
services or goods from other people, such as a shoveled walk or a body
part.22 An intricate web of norms covers the exchange of money
among both friends and strangers. Some of these norms are connected
with the principle of civic equality. Monetary exchange would reflect
forms of inequality that are not legitimate in certain spheres. In
making these points, I am disregarding many complexities, and I have not
tried to justify any particular set of outcomes in hard cases. I want to
suggest only a general point: the refusal to allow economic exchanges
is often based on familiar notions of equality that such exchanges
would compromise.</p>
      <p>There is a further point. We should distinguish between cases in
which a monetary offer is entirely inappropriate - say, a large check
offered in exchange for an academic article endorsing the offeror's
position - and cases in which the monetary sum, while appropriately
offered, does not reflect a full or fully accurate valuation of the item in
question. Artists, actors, and teachers might well believe that dollar
sums cannot truly reflect the social value of what they produce
certainly in the sense that money is not valued in the same way as art
or education - without believing that monetary compensation itself is
inappropriate. It is a pervasive and intriguing feature of markets that
financial compensation is challenged as too low, rather than as
inappropriate, or indeed willingly accepted, even in contexts in which the
transaction involves a good that is not valued in the same way as
money. But it is equally intriguing to note the occasional presence of
norms and law that block exchanges on the grounds of an
inappropriate kind of valuation.</p>
      <p>An understanding of diverse kinds of valuation thus helps explain
the anticommodification position for law or social norms - the view
that some things ought not to be traded on markets and that market
exchanges should therefore be prohibited.23 The objection to
commodification should be seen as a special case of the general problem of
diverse kinds of valuation. The claim is that we ought not to trade (for
21. This theme recurs in WALZER,supra note 14. See especially his discussion of the case of
the company town of Pullman, Illinois. Id. at 295-303.</p>
      <p>22. I do not mean to approve of the blocking of these exchanges, a matter that turns on a
complex range of considerations. See infra section V.H.</p>
      <p>23. See STEVEN KELMAN, WHAT PRICE INCENTIVES? 54-83 (1985); Margaret J. Radin,
Market-Inalienability,100 HARV. L. REV. 1849 (1987).
example) sexuality or reproductivecapacities on markets because
economic valuation of these "things" is inconsistent with and may even
undermine their appropriatekind (not level) of valuation.24 The
objection is not that markets value sexuality "too much" or "too little";
it is that markets value these activities in the wrong way. Judge
Posner's well-known writings on the "babymarket"25do not quite
address this particularobjection. A judgment about the appropriateway
of valuing babies must itself be defended on some basis, and such a
judgment does not automatically lead to a particularview about legal
rules for adoption or the sale of young children. But the question of
appropriatekinds of valuation plays a major role in these debates.26</p>
      <p>Thus far I have dealt with cases that involve objectionsto the kind
of valuation expressed through cash payments. But we can think of
many cases not involving the issue of monetary equivalence. Imagine,
for example, that John treats a beautiful diamond in the same way that
most people treat friends, or that Jane values a plant in the same way
that most people value their children, or that Sandy values her car like
most people value art or literature. All of us know people with
occasional tendencies of this sort. Indeed, all of us are people with
occasional tendencies of this sort. But sometimes an improper kind of
valuation seems odd, or disrespectful, or even pathological - and all
these in part because it makes it impossible to sustain certain sorts of
desirable social relationships. Disputes over law and social norms,
which are related and sometimes mutually enforcing behavioral
influences, often reflect disagreementsover proper kinds of valuation, with
adjectives of this sort moving to the fore.</p>
      <p>Consider, for example, the animal rights movement. Some people
think that animals should be treated with dignity and respect, and not
as if they exist solely for human consumption and use.27 This view
need not entail the further claim that animal life is infinitely valuable.
It is best taken as a recommendation of a shift in the kind of valuation
of animals, accompanied by a judgment that the new kind will have
consequences for what human beings do. The recommendation may
be based on the view that if we see animals (and nature) in this way,
we will solve collective action problems faced by human beings in
preserving animal life that is important for human lives; it may be based
on a noninstrumental effort to extend ideals of basic dignity to all
living things.28 I reiterate that substantive judgments of this sort must be
defended; by itself, the reference to diverse kinds of valuation gets us
nowhere. The important point is that such judgments are a frequent,
though often overlooked, part of social and legal discussion.</p>
      <p>The existence of diverse kinds of valuation explains a good deal of
private behavior. Norms governing address provide a familiar
example. By using some part of a name - last name preceded by
"Professor," "Doctor," "Mr.," "Ms.," "Mrs.," "Miss"; last name by itself;
first name; nickname or diminutive; some term of endearment - a
good deal of signaling takes place about prevailing kinds of valuation.
Some of these signals connote respect and admiration; others show
contempt; others show affection or love. Of course different cultures
vary greatly on this score, and of course individual relationships
change over time from one kind to another. Note in this regard that
the Constitution forbids both the federal government and the states
from conferring any "Title of Nobility."29 In this way, it commits
itself to a certain view of equality among human beings. Though the
provision may seem like a historical curiosity to current observers, to
the Framers it crucially exemplified this view; as we will see,30 it is the
forerunner of the Equal Protection Clause, with a close connection to
judgments about appropriate kinds of valuation.</p>
      <p>C.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Clarifications and Cautionary Notes</title>
      <p>Three major clarifications are necessary here. First, my claim
about diverse kinds of valuation has largely been a claim about
widespread current attitudes. I do believe that those attitudes go very deep
and that it would be quite impossible to make sense of our experience
28. On intrinsicvalue and the sanctity of life, see
RONALDDWORKINL,IFE'SDOMINION67101 (1993). Dworkin's claim that life is "sacred"or "inviolable"is best taken, I think, as a claim
about the appropriatekind of valuation of life, and his descriptionof certain courses of action as
showing "contempt" for life is highly compatible with the account I offer here.</p>
      <p>
        29. U.S. CONSTa.rt. I, ? 9, cl. 8. For a descriptionof the antiaristocratictendenciesof
political thinking in the Revolutionary period, see GORDONS. WOOD,THE RADICALISMOFTHE
AMERICANREVOI-UTIO1N45-68, 229-43, 271-86 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
        ).
      </p>
      <p>30. See infra notes 179-81 and accompanying text.
without reference to diverse kinds of valuation.3' But I do not intend
to offer anything like a transcendental or metaphysical claim about
valuation; I am speaking about how we value, not about nature or
about valuation of goods apart from human attitudes.</p>
      <p>Nor are existing kinds of valuation fixed and immutable. Norms
change, and prevailing social conceptions about kinds of valuation
change as well. Shifts from one kind of valuation to another are
perfectly commonplace, both at the individual and social level. Respect
can turn into love; love can turn into use; use can become love; love
can become respect; love may or may not be accompanied by respect;
respect can become affection; so too for love. Within societies, kinds
of valuation change over time. The shift from feudalism to capitalism
can hardly be described in a sentence, but one of its features involved
changes in kinds of valuation of work and workers, and this was a
prime area of contestation.32 Marriage may once have involved more
use, and less love and affection, than it now does.33 The abolition of
slavery represented a shift from use to a certain measure of respect; so
too with the attack on racial hierarchy in the aftermath of Brown v.
Board of Education.34 Much of the change in race relations in the
South involved a shift from connections built on deference and what
was believed to be a sort of affection to principles of civic equality and
respect.35</p>
      <p>Some of the most heated disputes about law and policy actually
turn on the appropriateness of a shift from one kind of valuation to
another. In labor law, for example, many important controversies
involve the appropriate kind of valuation of workers.36 The dispute over
at-will employment seems to turn in part on this issue. Critics of the
at-will rule claim that the rule reflects an inadequate kind of valuation
of workers because it subjects them to the whim of employers.37 Here
too notions of equality are at work in calling into question certain
voluntary exchanges.38</p>
      <p>Much of the theory of environmental protection involves similar
issues. It is not entirely accurate to say that environmentalistsvalue
pristine areas "more"than do economists. It is also important to say
that environmentalistsvalue pristineareasin a differentway. Whereas
economists tend to think of the environment as something for human
use and exploitation,39environmentaliststend to claim that we should
view the environmentwith awe and wonder or value it for its own sake
rather than as an instrumental good.40 The debates over pollution
taxes and tradable emissions permits are partly debates over kinds of
valuation.41 Of course it is unclear how these differentkinds of
valuation will or should affect environmentalpolicy, a point to which I will
return.42</p>
      <p>Second, the existence of diverse kinds of valuation does not by
itself have any clear implications for law, policy, or even social
attitudes. There is a differencebetween how people should value and how
law should value. I do not claim that, because people now value
relationships, events, objects, or each other in certain ways, it follows that
law should adopt those diverse kinds of valuation. We need not be
conventionalists. If a particularkind of valuation were really superior
with respect to what is appropriatelyvalued in public or private life,
the law might well adopt that kind of valuation notwithstanding its
inconsistency with prevailing social norms. A good deal of
constitutional law can be taken as an effort to constrain prevailing kinds of
valuation; this is true both for principles of religious liberty and for
antidiscriminationnorms.43 Or law might embody a certain kind of
valuation precisely because it is law; we might think that cost-benefit
analysis is appropriatefor law even if we think that it is inappropriate
for spouses or parents. If we are to draw conclusions about
appropriate law, policy, and norms, it is because our best account of the good
or the right supports a particular constellation of kinds of valuation
and because we are able to show that a particularconstellation makes
38. CompareBlades, supra note 37 with Richard A. Epstein, In Defense of the Contractat
Will, 51 U. CHI.L. REV.947 (1984). This dispute implicitly involves diverse kinds of valuation.
Epstein's view rests on a monistic conception of value in which workers "tradeoff" goods along
a single metric; Blades does not directly address this question but appearsto take a stand in the
other direction.</p>
      <p>39. See, e.g., WILLIAMJ. BAUMOL&amp; WALLACE.
OATEST,HETHEORYOFENVIRONMENTALPOLICY(2d ed. 1988).</p>
      <p>40. See, e.g., GOODINs,upra note 27, at 8 ("The value of nature is no longer regardedas
wholly reducible to its value to God or to humanity.").</p>
      <p>41. See KELMANs,upra note 23, at 1-11.
42. See infra section V.D.
43. See infra section V.B.
sense for law.44 I return to this complex issue in Part IV.</p>
      <p>Third, those who believe that goods are valued in different ways
need not reject the possibility of rational choice or even some form of
trade-offamong them.45 On the contrary, believers in diverse kinds of
valuation would do well to insist that choices occur and that they
might well be judged rational or not. People choose among differently
valued goods all the time, and these choices are not immune from
evaluation on rational grounds. My affection for my dog and my desire
for more cash reflect differentkinds of valuation, but it would be quite
irrationalfor me to allow my dog to be sold for fifty dollars. (If I were
desperately poor, and if my family were ill and suffering,it could also
be irrational for me to refuse to trade my dog for one million dollars,
notwithstandingthe presence of distinct kinds of valuation.) Someone
might well sell for a price the products of her capacity to play Mozart
- musical performances - or to write poetry, notwithstanding the
fact that she values her capacity as something other than an
incomeproducing asset. In some circumstances it would surely be irrational
for a musician to refuse to perform for a fee. These claims about
rationality need to be explained in some detail, but they should be
sufficient to show that there may indeed be a point to deliberating about
cases that involve goods that are valued in different ways.46
D. Social Science, Economics, and DiverseKinds of Valuation
Is it useful to note that kinds of valuation are diverse and plural?
Perhaps it is not. Perhaps we can make good predictions about social
life simply by assuming that there is a single kind of valuation.47 On
this view, a claim about diverse kinds of valuation may usefully
describe people's internallives; it may have deeperpsychological truth;it
may better account for how lives and choices are actually experienced.
But it is fully dispensable for social scientists and lawyers, who can
work with an assumption of "as if unitariness" - that is, who can
assume that people act as if they value all things in the same way, and
who can make accurate predictions with that assumption. So long as
we can model choices - so long as ordinal rankings are possible
social scientists need not worry about what I have said here.</p>
      <p>This conclusion seems partly right. If we assume that people want
to maximize one thing
utility, value, welfare, well-being
we
might well be able to make good predictions of various sorts.48 We
might be able to say what sorts of legislation will be enacted in what
circumstances.</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>People do make judgments among goods, and if so we</title>
        <p>need not decide whether they value these goods in the same way.
even with respect to nonmarket transactions.
can make accurate predictions by assuming unitariness, we can indeed
dispense with claims about diverse kinds of valuation.49</p>
        <p>But I believe that, with the assumption of a unitary kind of
valuation, We will sometimes offer inadequate predictions, explanations, and
recommendations for law. The idea of "revealed preferences" is a
predictive failure; to make predictions from choices, we need to offer an
account of what lies behind choices,50 and that account must take into
consideration what I am discussing here. Behavior is often a product
of judgments about what kinds of valuation are appropriate under
what circumstances.</p>
        <p>As we will see, some of the "demand" for
environmental regulation is best understood as a response to claims about
the need to value things in different ways.51 Much of individual
conduct is best understood in similar terms. We might, for example,
puzzle a great deal over the existence of social norms without apparent
"maximizing" explanations.52 Consider a few examples: the norm in
favor of voting, norms of dress and etiquette, norms of vengeance,
48. An influentialapproachcomes from the idea of revealedpreferences,popularwithin
economics. On this view, we do not hypothesize any supervalue such as utility, but work instead
with a rank ordering of individual preferences,based on actual choices (revealed preferences).
This approach will not work. We cannot get a good sense of what people value simply from
choices since choices are a function of context and since they are inarticulate- poor predictors
of futurebehavior- without some account of what lies behind them. See Amartya Sen, Internal
Consistencyof Choice, 61 ECONOMETRIC49A5 (1993). Sen shows that even the weakest axioms
of revealedpreferencetheory can fail. For example, it is usually assumed that if someone prefers
A to B in a situation of binary choice, he should also preferA to B if some third alternativeC is
introduced. But this is wrong. Someone may preferA to B, but B to A and C, because the choice
of A over B shows no global or acontextualjudgment. For example, the choice of A (a medium
sized piece of cake) over B (a large piece of cake) may reflect a desire to be moderate, a desire
that can alsojustify the choice of B overA and C (a huge piece of cake). Id. at 498- 503. Thus we
cannot rank order individual preferenceson the basis of choices alone or without some account
of what values underlie choices. See also RAZ, supra note 17, at 327; Richard H. Pildes &amp;
Elizabeth S. Anderson, Slinging Arrowsat Democracy: Social Choice Theory, Value Pluralism,
and DemocraticPolitics, 90 COLUML.. REV. 2121 (1990).</p>
        <p>49. The most striking example here is Gary Becker, who assumes a single kind of valuation
in his work on nonmarketbehavior, most notably in BECKERs,upra note 3.</p>
        <p>50. See supra note 48.</p>
        <p>52. See JONELSTERT,HE CEMENTOFSOCIETY97-152 (1989); JONELSTERS,OIOMONIC
JUDGMENT3S2-35 (1989).
norms against sale.53 Some anomalies in expected utility theory might
result from diverse kinds of valuation.54 There is much more to say
about these complex matters. Nothing said in this paragraphrefutes
the possibility of complete ordinal rankings. But we can make some
progress in thinking about human behavior by examining the role of
diverse valuations.</p>
        <p>In this light, we can also make sense out of a familiardebate within
the legal culture. In some subjects - contracts, torts, property
people often propose that something important - like a risk to life or
health - is in some deep sense equivalent to a certain amount of cash.
At this point, some participantin the conversation (perhapsa student)
rejects the proposal, whereupon the original speaker suggests that the
resistancemust depend on a claim of infinite valuation, at which point
it is clear that the original proposal was correct. But perhaps the
resistancerests on a claim about appropriatekinds, not levels, of
valuation.55 If so, the participant who is making this claim has a lot to
explain. She has to explain how to make choices among goods that are
valued in different ways. But at least we will be able to understand
what she is saying.</p>
        <p>We might also begin to see why it might be jarring to conceive of
the various harms imposed by law as simple "costs." This formulation
begs important questions and ignores qualitative distinctions. It does
so by assuming a unitary kind of valuation. In that way, this
formulation loads the dice - that is, it prejudices analysis by pointing it in
certain controversialdirections. As we will see, the point bears on the
question of commensurability.56</p>
        <p>II. INCOMMENSURABILITY</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>A. A ProvisionalDefinition</title>
        <p>The subject of incommensurabilityraises many complexities, and I
want to bracketat least some of the philosophical debate here,
concentrating instead on what is particularlyrelevant to law.57 Begin with a
53. Many of these are subjectto intriguing,but in my view incomplete, analysis on economic
or utilitariangrounds. See, e.g., RICHARDA. POSNER, LAW AND LITERATURE26-70
(discussing vengeance).</p>
        <p>54. Consider offer-askingdisparitiesand wide variations in expendituresper life saved. See
infra note 219 and accompanying text.</p>
        <p>55. The point seems to me to require some qualifications of the discussion in Gul)o
CALABRESI,THE COSTSOF ACCIDENTS 16-20 (1970) (discussing trade-offs between human
fatalities and offsettingsocial benefits). It also helps explain the account of the "sacred"in
DWORKIN, supra note 28, at 68-101.</p>
        <p>56. See infra notes 231-33 and accompanying text.
57. For discussions of commensurability, see ANDERSON, supra note 1, at 44-73; JAMi:S
rough working definition,designed especially for the legal context:
Incommensurabilityoccurs when the relevant goods cannot be aligned
along a single metric without doing violence to our
consideredjudgments about how thesegoods are best characterized. Let me
brieflydescribe the four major elements of this definition. First, by "our
consideredjudgments," I mean our reflective assessments of how
certain relationshipsand events should be understood, evaluated, and
experienced. Such reflectioninvolves identifying the nature and depth of
various goods in our lives.</p>
        <p>Second, the notion of a "single metric" should be understoodquite
literally.58 By this I mean a standard of valuation that (1) operates at
a workable level of specificity;(2) involves no qualitative distinctions;
and (3) allows comparison of different goods along the same
dimentant for present purposes
sion. One example of a real-world metric
is money. Ten dollars and $100 can be
indeed the most
imporconfidently measuredby such a standard, so that ten dollars is simply
a small quantity of the same thing of which $100 is a substantial
amount. If two goods are fungible, they are also commensurable.
Other metrics include feet, yards, pounds, and of course meters. The
difference between lengths of ten yards and 100 yards, or between
1000 pounds and 400 pounds, involves no qualitative distinctions.</p>
        <p>
          An important and contested utilitarian claim is that "utility"
furnishes a single metric along which goods can be evaluated. Some
utilitarians believe that a single metric is indeed available for ordering
valuations. The great utilitarian John Stuart Mill, of course, was
unwilling to commit himself fully to this view.59 I use the term metric
GRIFFINW,ELL-BEING75-92 (1986); NUSSBAUMs,upra note 2, at 106-24; RAZ,supra note 17,
at 321-66; STOCKER, supra note 6, at 130-207; CHARLES TAYLOR, The Diversityof Goods, in
PHILOSOPHAYNDTHEHUMANSCIENCE2S30, 243 (1985); Elizabeth Anderson, Values, Risks,
and MarketsNorms, 17 PHIL.&amp; PUB.AFF.54, 57-59 (1987); Pildes &amp; Anderson, supra note 48,
at 2145-66; Amartya Sen, Plural Utility, in 81 PROC.OFTHEARISTOTELIASNOCY.193, 197-89
(1981); Richard Warner,Incommensurabilityas a JurisprudentialPuzzle, 68 CHI.-KENTL. REV.
147 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          ); Richard H. Pildes, Conceptionsof Valuein Legal Thought,90 MICH.L. REV. 1520
(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          ) (book review);cf Radin, supranote 23. Comparethe discussion of an
"integratedpersonality" in Frank Hahn, Benevolence,in THOUGHTFUELCONOMIMCAN7, 8 (J. Gay T. Meeds ed.,
1991) (asserting intrapersonalcomparability of options grounded in self- and other-regarding
motives) with the response in Amartya Sen, Beneconfusion,in THOUGHTFUELCONOMIMCAN,
supra, at 12, 12-14 (denying this thesis).
        </p>
        <p>58. Charles Larmore says that incommensurabilityoccurs when there is no "common
denominatorof value,"an understandingthat parallelsthe notion of a metric, but is not identical to
it. Charles Larmore,Pluralism and ReasonableDisagreement, 11Soc. PHIL. &amp;
POLICY(forthcoming 1994) (manuscriptat 65, on file with author). At least for purposesof law, I think that
the notion of a single metric is more useful than that of a common denominator of value. We
could identify common denominatorsof value at a high level of generality- excellence,
generosity, and so forth - but because such common denominators, including qualitatively different
features, can be found for most legal problems, the term may lead to confusion.
59. See JOHNSTUARTMILL,UTILITARIANIS(MOskar Priest ed., 1957) (1861).
criteria, but not as metrics. Kinds of valuation
der, worship</p>
        <p>embody no metric at all.61
largely because of the special importance of the metric of dollars to
law. As we will see,60the use of a single metric is often unhelpful for
law, and this point has a wide range of consequences for particular
legal disputes. Under this general definition of metric, many possible
standards
excellence,
well-being, affective allegiance</p>
        <p>count as
love, respect,
wonthis form</p>
        <p>Third, with the phrase "doing violence," I mean to suggest that the
use of a single metric is inconsistent with the way certain goods are
actually experienced,or tend to be experiencedwhen people's lives are
going well. The phrase is intended to show that a single metric,
nominally descriptive of experience, would actually transform it, in a way
that would make a great deal of difference. It would make a great deal
of differencebecause it would elide certain qualitative differencesthat
are important in both life and law. We might label many choices
involving commensurablegoods investmentdecisions. The decision how
to invest so as to maximize expected return does indeed involve
commensurable goods. Some people write as if all or most decisions have
as if all or most decisions are investment decisions. Some
people write as if life is full of investment decisions, so that a decision
made in one context will show a global, acontextual judgment about
valuation.62 It is these points that I am rejecting here. If we saw all
human decisions as investment decisions, we would make human
exIt is quite compatible with the principle of utility to recognize the fact that some kinds of
pleasure are more desirable and more valuable than others. It would be absurd that, while
in estimating all other things quality is considered as well as quantity, the estimation of
pleasure should be supposed to depend on quantity alone.</p>
        <p>Id. at 12. See also Mill's criticism of Bentham:</p>
        <p>Nothing is more curious than the absence of recognition in any of his writings of the
existence of conscience, as a thing distinct from philanthropy, from affection for God or man,
and from self-interest in this world or in the next ....</p>
        <p>Nor is it only the moral part of man's nature . . .that he overlooks; he but faintly
recognises, as a fact in human nature, the pursuit of any other ideal end for its own sake.
The sense of honour,and personaldignity ... the love of beauty,the passion of the artist;the
love of order ... the love of power ... the love of action . . . the love of ease: - None of
these powerful constituents of human nature are thought worthy of a place among the
"Springs of Action;" ....</p>
        <p>MILL, supra note 2, at 66-68.</p>
        <p>Other general meditations on this theme appear in JOHN STUART MILL, AUTOBIOGRAPHY
(1873); for an illuminating discussion see Elizabeth Anderson, John Stuart Mill on Experiments
in Living, 102 ETHICS4 (1991).</p>
        <p>
          60. See infra Part V.
61. Hence ordinal rankings do not produce commensurabilityas I understand it here.
62. See, e.g., W. KIP VISCUSIF,ATALTRADEOFF3S4-74 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          ) (discussing risk trade-offs).
Compare Viscusi's analysis with Amartya Sen, Freedom and Needs, NEW REPUBL.ICJa,n. 10 &amp;
17, 1994, at 31, 32-33 ("There are deep and fundamentaland intuitively understood grounds for
rejecting the view that confines itself merely to checking the parity of outcomes, the view that
matches death for death, happiness for happiness, fulfillment for fulfillment, irrespectiveof how
all this death, happiness, and fulfillment comes about.").
answer to the two questions: "How much would you have to be paid
to allow degradation?" and "How much would you pay to avoid
degradation?" People are perfectly willing to answer the second question
with numbers that are systematically lower than those produced by
the first. In the environmental area, the asymmetry is especially large,
and it creates a considerable puzzle for conventional views about
rationality. But it would be wrong to think that the answers to the
second question are in some deep sense more revealing of "true"
preferences, while the responses to the first question are mistaken.
        </p>
        <p>The asymmetry may have a good deal to do with diverse kinds of
valuation. In particular, people may believe that a species or a pristine
area has intrinsic rather than instrumental value. When this is so,
they do not want to assume the sort of responsibility that is entailed by
allowing its elimination for cash.233 The asymmetry reflects a belief
that an answer to the first question above entails a different sort of act
from an answer to the second. This may not be irrational at all. In
the first case, the reference state or status quo is nondegradation, and
the respondent is asked to interfere with that state of affairs. In the
second case, the reference state is degradation, which the respondent is
asked to help alleviate. The asymmetry reflects a judgment that these
are answers to two very different questions.</p>
        <p>The asymmetry thus suggests that people think that the loss,
through their deliberate action, of a pristine area or an endangered
species is incommensurably bad, and that this thought should be
expressed through regulatory proscriptions. To say the least, this view
raises many complexities. It is by no means clear that the relevant
judgments about responsibility can be defended. I mean to suggest
only that the idea is both common and intelligible.</p>
        <p>E.</p>
        <p>Cost-Benefit Analysis234</p>
        <p>One of the most hotly disputed issues in law and policy involves
the role of cost-benefit analysis (CBA). In the most dramatic victory
for CBA, the Reagan administration adopted two important executive
Bias in DecisionMaking, 1 J. RISK&amp; UNCERTAINT7Y(1988); W. Kip Viscusi et al.. An
Investigation of the Rationalityof Consumer Valuationsof Multiple Health Risks. 18 RAND J. ECON.
465 (1987).</p>
        <p>
          233. See Rebecca R. Boyce et al., AntExperimental Examination of Intrinsic Values as a
Source of the WTA-WTPDisparity. 82 AM. ECON.REV. 1366, 1366-67 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          ). See also the
discussion of responsibilityand the action-omissiondistinction in Williams,supra note 88, at
93100.
        </p>
        <p>234. I draw in this section on Sunstein, supra note 69, at 25-26.
orders calling for the applicationof CBA to all regulatorydecisions.235
These orders were withdrawn by President Clinton and replaced by a
new executive order, which also places a high premium on cost-benefit
analysis.236</p>
        <p>There is of course much to be said in favor of CBA. Federal
regulation is notoriously and pervasively chaotic and irrational.237Who
could object to the idea that we should systematize costs and benefits
and compare them? The question seems especially powerful when
combined with the plausible claim that some opponents of CBA are
confused about their real objection. In fact, it is sometimes said,238the
opponents' real complaint is that some of the relevant variables have
been insufficientlyvalued. Would it not be a sufficientresponse to say
to the critics of this form of analysis that perhaps we should place a
higher premium on, for example, human health, or the environment,
and then proceed with CBA?</p>
        <p>It would be difficult to challenge the view that law and policy
should be assessed on the basis of an inquiry into the advantages and
disadvantagesof differentcourses of action, and CBA often appearsto
be a way of systematizing that sort of approach. But at least for some
purposes, I do not think this response would be sufficient. Nor is it
entirely adequate to say, as critics of CBA typically do, that this sort
of approach fails to address distributional issues or is biased against
the poor.239</p>
        <p>The real problem with any form of conventional CBA is that it is
obtuse. CBA is obtuse because it tries to measure diverse social goods
along the same metric.240Suppose, for example, that we are told that
the "cost" of a certain occupational safety regulationis $1 million, and
that the "benefit"is $1.2 million. To make a sensible evaluation, we
need to know a great deal more. To what do these numbersrefer? Do
they include greater unemployment, higher inflation, and the
scaledback production of important goods? Do they mean more poverty?
At least in principle, it would be much better to have a highly
disaggregated system for assessing the qualitativelydifferenteffects of
regulatory impositions. People should be allowed to see those diverse
effects for themselves and to makejudgments based on an
understanding of the qualitative differences. If all of the relevant goods are
aligned along a single metric, they become less visible, or perhaps
invisible.</p>
        <p>Through considerations of this sort, we might be able to make
some progress toward assessment of the Reagan and Clinton
administrations' executive orders on regulation. Instead of conventional
costbenefit analysis, what is necessary is a full accounting of the various
social consequences of regulation. Those consequences should be
described in a way that allows a detailed view of what the costs and
benefits specifically are. Once greater specificity is added, we will not
be thinking in terms of simple costs and benefits at all. President
Clinton's order241makes some modest steps in this direction, but the
steps are erratic and unconnected with any clear theory of how to
assess regulation.242</p>
        <p>The best response to this claim is pragmatic and institutional. It
would be that at least for law and public policy, it makes sense to act
as if diverse goods were commensurable,because this way of
proceeding makes decisions tractable where they would otherwise be ad hoc,
and because ad hoc decisions lead to a systematic misallocation of
resources and a perversesystem of priorities. CBA may offera less than
full description of what is really at stake, but perhaps it counteracts
the forms of inconsistency and ultimate irrationalitythat result in the
public sector if we proceed without quantitative help.</p>
        <p>This is a plausible defense of CBA in the real world. Whether it is
right depends on pragmaticjudgments that cannot be resolved in the
241. See supra note 236 and accompanying text.</p>
        <p>242. The Clinton order is cautious and even ambiguous about cost-benefitanalysis as a tool
of decision. It says "qualitative"costs and benefits will be included as part of the analysis:
"Costs and benefits shall be understood to include both quantifiable measures (to the fullest
extent that these can be usefullyestimated)and qualitativemeasuresof costs and benefitsthat are
difficult to quantify, but nevertheless essential to consider." Exec. Order No. 12,866, 58 Fed.
Reg. 51,735, at 51,735 (1993). The order furtherstates: "Each agency shall assess both the costs
and the benefits of the intended regulation and, recognizing that some costs and benefits are
difficult to quantify, propose or adopt a regulationonly upon a reasoneddeterminationthat the
benefits of the intended regulationjustify its costs." Id. at 51,736. The order also contains a
vague referenceto the relevance of "equity" and "distributiveimpacts." Id.</p>
        <p>But these are odd and in some ways not entirely coherent formulations. If quantificationis
impossible or misleading, we are not weighing costs and benefits at all, but instead assessing
advantagesand disadvantages. "Qualitative"costs and benefitsare not easy to conceive. In any
case, some of the advantagesand disadvantagesof regulatoryaction are not adequatelydescribed
as costs and benefitsat all. The Clinton order should be seen as a halfway house between CBA
and a more differentiatedanalysis that draws close attention to the diverse goods at stake. Of
course it remainspossible that this halfway house is the best way of combining good theory with
administrativeconcerns and sensible priority setting, but the current theory seems confused.
abstract. My point is that if goods are diverse and valued in different
ways, there will be considerablecrudeness in this approach to
regulation. Much will be lost even if much is also gained. We should
therefore have a presumption in favor of a much more disaggregated
accounting of the effects of regulation, one that exposes to public view
the full set of effects.</p>
        <p>F. Specific Performance,Damages, PrivateLaw Remedies: Another</p>
        <p>Viewof the Cathedral</p>
        <p>The legal system usually insists on an award of damages for the
infliction of harm; a damages award appears to reflect a judgment in
favor of commensurability. But sometimes damages are insufficient.
We can approach a large subject- the relationshipbetween
compensation and commensurability243- by examining a pervasive issue in
the law of contract: whether to award a damages remedy or instead to
requirespecific performance.244From an exploration of this issue, we
may be able to offer a few tentative generalizations.</p>
        <p>It is typically said that specific performancewill be awarded when
damages are "inadequate." But what could this possibly mean?
Suppose that Jones has contracted to buy a painting, and that the seller
defaults on the agreement. It is far from clear why a court should
order the seller to hand over the painting, rather than to pay damages
to Jones. If the damages seem inadequate, we might think that they
have been set too low, and that the right solution is simply to require
the seller to pay more. Surely there is some level at which the court
will set the proper amount. Why, then, is specific performance ever
available?</p>
        <p>A conventional answer is that damages remedies are inadequate
when the good at issue is unique.245But the notion of uniqueness is
itself a puzzle. At least for economists, the term points at most to
"questionsof degree."246All goods have substitutes of some sort; this
is part of the usual understanding of choice amidst scarcity. In
explaining the notion of uniqueness, some people have stressed that a
damages remedy might well be inaccurate for certain goods.
Subjective value is peculiarly hard to ascertain in some cases, and the goods
may involve high search costs that judges cannot easily determine.</p>
        <p>243. See generally MargaretJ. Radin, Compensationand Commensurability.43 DUKF L.J.
56 (1993).</p>
        <p>244. For a good modern treatment of this issue, see generally Anthony Kronman, Specific
Performance,45 U. CHI. L. REV. 351 (1978).</p>
        <p>245. See, e.g., id. at 355-58.
246. Id. at 359.
The subjective value of Jones's painting is nearly impossible to know
and may well substantiallyexceed the market value, if a market exists.
The particularcosts incurredby Jones in finding that
particularpainting are hard to establish. In these circumstances, the existence of a
specific performanceremedy can be seen as a natural response to
information costs faced by the legal system in ascertaining the appropriate
damages remedy.</p>
        <p>We might conclude that, when it is especially expensive to
determine damages, courts will order specific performance. In a brief but
notable description of the doctrine, Judge Posner says that the
doctrine representsan exception to the usual damages decree for cases in
which "damages are difficult to compute because of a lack of good
market substitutes for the performance of the contract breaker."247
This is a notable description because it suggests that behind the
specific performance remedy lies the simple problem of cost of
computation.</p>
        <p>There is undoubtedly a good deal of truth to this; but another
factor may be at work. The specific performance remedy can be
understood to stem from a resistance to commensurability. Specific
performance must be awarded because the good in question is not
commensurable with cash. This is not to say that it is more valuable
than cash. Indeed, it is less valuable, often, than a great deal of cash.
The claim is instead that the good is valued in a way that is
inconsistent with cash valuation. What the plaintiff wants, and what she is
entitled to get, is a good that she values in the way that she values the
object for which she has contracted. A good that she values
"equally," in market terms, is not a perfect substitute.248Hence one
would expect the specific performance remedy to reflect a stand in
favor of diverse kinds of valuation.</p>
        <p>There is no simple way to test this hypothesis against its economic
competitor. The two would suggest parallel results. But both the
rhetoric and the outcomes of some of the cases suggest that specific
performance is awarded at least in part because cash does not reflect
the way in which the promisee values the good in question.249
247. POSNERs,upra note 130, at 130.
248. See supra note 94 on why the quotation marks are necessary.</p>
        <p>249. See, e.g., Nemer Jeep-Eagle, Inc. v. Jeep-Eagle Sales Corp., 992 F.2d 430, 436 (2d Cir.
1993) (granting specific performance when franchisee's very existence as business was
threatened);Semmes Motors, Inc. v. Ford Motor Co., 429 F.2d 1197, 1205 (2d Cir. 1970)
(granting temporary injunction when plaintiff sought right to continue 20-year-old business); City
Stores Co. v. Ammerman, 266 F. Supp. 766, 776 (D.D.C. 1967) (granting specific performance
when there was a disputed lease critical to future expansion of business);Forman v. Benson. 446
N.E.2d 535, 541 (111.App. Ct. 1983) (granting specific performance for breach of contract for
sale of land); Kitchen v. Herring, 42 N.C. 137, 138 (1851) (same); see also David Cohen, The</p>
        <p>This point suggests the need to supplement Guido Calabresi and
Douglas Melamed's well-known discussion of the choice between
liability and property rules.250In their terminology, a right is protected
by a liability rule if it can be taken upon a payment of compensation.
A right is protected by a property rule if it can be taken only through
voluntary exchange, and if market compensation is thereforean
inadequate justification for the taking. Calabresiand Melamed's important
discussion rightly emphasizes the relevance of transactions costs,
including information costs, to the choice between the two methods of
legal protection.251 But this account provides only part of the picture.
As the discussion above suggests, property rules are also appropriate
when the relevant right or good is valued in a different way from
money. In such cases, courts hesitate to use liability rules, not only
because courts doubt their ability to calculate a proper cost for the
forgone good, but also because a dollar amount will reflect the wrong
kind of valuation of the good at issue. The litigant is entitled to the
good and its existing kind of valuation, ratherthan to a substitute
valued in a differentway, even if in some aggregativesense "equally."252</p>
        <p>The point bears on damage remedies generally, most obviously for
emotional distress or pain and suffering.253As Margaret Jane Radin
Relationshipof ContractualRemedies to Political and Social Status: A PreliminaryInquiry, 32 U.
TORONTOL.J. 31 (1982).</p>
        <p>251. Id. at 1093-98.</p>
        <p>252. The point may help justify the requirementthat a "public use" be shown before
government may undertakeeven a compensated taking of private property. See U.S. CONSTa.mend. V
("nor shall private property be taken for public use, without just compensation").
253. Thus RESTATEMEN(TSECONDO)FTORTS? 903 cmt. a (1977) states:
[C]ompensatorydamages [for pecuniary loss] are designed to place [the damaged party] in a
position substantially equivalent in a pecuniary way to that which he would have occupied
had no tort been committed. When[,] however, the tort causes bodily harm or emotional
distress, the law cannot restore the injured person to his previous position. The sensations
caused by harm to the body or by pain or humiliation are not in any way analogous to a
pecuniary loss, and a sum of money is not the equivalent of peace of mind .... There is no
scale by which the detriment caused by sufferingcan be measured and hence there can only
be a very rough correspondencebetween the amount awarded as damages and the extent of
the suffering.</p>
        <p>See generally Radin, supra note 243, at 269-83.</p>
        <p>Consider in this regard the debate on whether people's failure to insure for nonpecuniary
harms reflectsa social judgment against mandating insurance through the tort system. See supra
note 20 and accompanying text. It is possible to think that the failure to insure has no such
implications. Perhaps there is a norm against purchasing insurance for certain risks. Perhaps
commodifying - in the form of insuring against - those risks would reflect a strange kind (not
amount) of valuation of the underlying good. People do not ordinarily insure against death of
their children, or their own physical pain, in part because their attitudes make the decision to
insure seem peculiar, as if one viewed one's children or freedom from pain as a sort of asset or
commodity. On this view, the failure to insure reflects a quite particularjudgment, and it does
not mean that these events are not harms deserving compensation when they occur. Hence the
inferencedrawn in Priest, supra note 20, at 1546-47, 1553, and Shavell, supra note 20. at 228- 35.
has argued, we might think of financialcompensation not as
commensurablewith many injuriesat issue in tort law, and thus not as a means
of truly restoring the status quo ante, but less ambitiously as an effort
to establish and recognize that a wrong has been done and to deter
wrongdoing while ensuring that some redresshas been paid. Even if a
legal system can do no better, that redress does not fully rectify the
wrong, because monetary sums are not commensurablewith the
relevant injury.254</p>
        <p>The same ideas underlie an important debate in environmental
law, having to do with the appropriatemeasure of damages for injury
to natural resources. The "restorationcost" for, say, a portion of the
Alaska seashore may diverge from its "use value," understood as
aggregated private willingness to purchase the area in question.
Through an importantregulation,the Department of the
Interiorindicated its preference for use value if it was lower than restoration
cost.255 The Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit
invalidatedthe regulationon the theory that Congresshad expresseda
preferencefor restoration.256The decision of the court reflects an
understandingthat those who injurenaturalresourcesshould be required
to restore the status quo ante, not because it is more valuable, but
because the public is entitled to have a good that it values in the way
that it values natural resources, rather than the so-called cash
equivalent.257
may be unwarranted. See Croley &amp; Hanson, supra note 20, at 59-67. The
unwarrantedinference is a version of that committed in Viscusi, supra note 222, at 362-65 - seeing particular
choices as reflecting global or acontextual judgments. See also Sen, supra note 57, at 206
(rejecting such an inference). Alan Schwartz illuminates this puzzle by describing financial
remedies for nonpecuniary losses as involving "substitutes rather than replacements":
"Nonpecuniaryharms are not replaceableby insurance payments or damagejudgments; rather.
these transfers are used to purchase substitutes that make up for or assuage the pain of
accidents." Alan Schwartz, Proposalsfor Products Liability Reform: A TheoreticalSynthesis. 97
YALE L.J. 353, 408 (1988).</p>
        <p>254. See Radin, supra note 243, at 60-61.
255. 43 C.F.R. ? 11.35(b)(2) (1987).
256. Ohio v. U.S. Dept. of Interior, 880 F.2d 432, 441 (D.C. Cir. 1989).
257. The court stated:</p>
        <p>The fatal flawof [the Departmentof the] Interior'sapproach.however, is that it assumes
that natural resources are fungible goods, just like any other .... [But] Congress was
skeptical of the ability of human beings to measure the true "value" of a natural resource.
Indeed, even the common law recognizes that restorationis the proper remedy for injuryto
propertywhere measurementof damagesby some other method will fail to compensate fully
for the injury .... [N]atural resourceshave value that is not readily measuredby traditional
means.
880 F.2d at 456-57 (footnotes omitted). There are complex relationsamong restorationcost. use
value, option value (the amount people would pay to have an option to see a naturalasset). and
existence value (the amount that people would pay to ensurecontinued existence of a good). The
latter two measures help respond to people's concerns about the need to replicate the original
kind of valuation. The Departmentof the Interioris now wrestling with these issues. For
example, see the proposal in 56 Fed. Reg. 19,756 (1991), using the term compensablevalue to include
G.</p>
        <p>Feminism in Law</p>
        <p>An understanding of issues of commensurability, and of diverse
kinds of valuation, should help explain a number of claims by and
debates among feminists, both inside law and elsewhere. Some of
these claims and debates have been inadequately understood in the
legal culture, in part because of the importanceof kinds of valuation258
and because of the infrequencywith which such kinds are understood
to be part of legal theory and practice.</p>
        <p>To offer a brief summary: In a statement that has now been
frequently quoted (by, among others, MacKinnon herself259),Richard
Rorty takes Catharine MacKinnon to have claimed that "being a
woman is not yet a way of being a human being."260 What does this
mean? It may well mean that women are often not valued in the way
that a human being is entitled to be valued. More concretely, we
might understandsome feminist thought to be insisting that, as human
beings, women are entitled to be treated with dignity and respect,26'
and that frequentlythey are not so treated. Instead women are treated
with affection or love, or, much worse, as objects for the use and
control of others.</p>
        <p>
          Consider in this regarda frequent response - offeredfamously by
former heavyweight champion Mike Tyson, but also by an astonishing
number of other people - to claims of sex discriminationor even
sexual assault: "I love women."262 It is interesting to think about the
nature of this response and the reason that it is inadequate. It is
tempting, but not sufficient,to say that such responses are insincere or
false. Instead the response connotes a high level of valuation or a sort
of intense and real appreciation. But the response is obtuse when the
"all of the public economic values associated with an injured resource, including use values and
nonuse values such as option, existence, and bequest values." 56 Fed. Reg. at 19,760. A leading
textbook, interestingly, comments that: "the concept of 'compensable value' recognizes that
resources are valued for many differentreasons, not all of which are reflectedaccurately in market
prices." ROBERTV. PERCIVALETAL.,ENVIRONMENTARLEGULATIONL:AW,SCIENCEA,ND
POLICY362 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          ). For subsequent public commentary and updating of the proposed
regulation, see 58 Fed. Reg. 39,328 (1993).
        </p>
        <p>258. See, e.g., Hampton, supra note 165, at 236-38; see also ANDERSONs,upra note 1, at
811, 117-40.</p>
        <p>259. See, e.g., CatharineMacKinnon, Reflectionson Sex Equality UnderLaw, 100 YALEL.J.
1281, 1299 &amp; n.85 (1991).</p>
        <p>260. Richard Rorty, Feminism and Pragmatism, 30 MICH.Q. REV. 231 (1989).
261. Of course some feminists have questioned Kantian understandings. See NOI)INGS,
supra note 168; Tronto, supra note 168.</p>
        <p>262. TysonPleads Not Guiltyto Rape Charge,N.Y. TIMES,Sept. 12, 1991, at B18. A recent
LEXIS search discovered 124 entries containing the phrase"I love women," many of which were
responsive to charges of sexism, sexual discrimination, or sexual assault. Search of LEXIS,
Nexis library, Major Papers file (Dec. 27, 1993).
claim is that women have not been treated with basic dignity and
respect. The invocation of love or affection, even if sincerely and
intensely felt, is unresponsive to the relevant concern, which is about the
appropriate kind and not the appropriate level of valuation.</p>
        <p>In fact many claims about issues related to sex equality -
including the distribution of labor within marriage, pornography, sexual
harassment, and abortion</p>
        <p>might be taken to be claims that law and
social norms should treat women in a certain way, one that involves
dignity and respect, or a principle of civic equality. On this account, a
distinctive norm underlies the objection to certain forms of sex
inequality, and the norm is connected with a claim about proper kinds of
valuation.263 Hence the objection to sexual harassment is that this
practice treats women as objects for the enjoyment and use of men.
Hence the objection to legal proscriptions on abortion is that the law
ought not to use women's reproductive capacities against women's will
and for the protection of third parties, at least when it does not
similarly use men's capacities. Similarly, the objection to pornography has
a good deal to do with the way in which certain forms of sexually
explicit material treat women's sexual capacities as objects for the use
of others, especially through sexual violence.264 Thus pornography is
challenged not as offensive, but as embodying an improper means of
valuing human beings.265 Similar issues are raised by the sale of sexual
and reproductive capacities through markets, as in the practices of
prostitution and surrogacy.266</p>
        <p>A good deal would have to be said in order to support the view
that these claims entail any particular legal reform. All I mean to say
is that an important strand in recent writing about sex discrimination
263. Compare Locke's assertion, as a governing principle in the State of Nature, that "there
cannot be supposed any such Subordination among us, that may Authorize us to destroy one
another, as if we were made for one another's uses." JOHNLOCKET,wo
TREATISEOSFGOVERNMENT271 (Peter Laslett ed., student ed. 1988) (3d ed. 1698). This is an essentially liberal
idea. It shows the deep continuity between certain strands of feminism and the liberal tradition,
notwithstanding the purported antiliberalism of some feminist thought. See, e.g., CATHARINE
MACKINNONF, EMINISM UNMODIFIED (1987); cf OKIN, supranote 33, at 61 ("[A] number of
the basic tenets of liberalism .. have been basic tenets in the development of feminism, too.");
Susan M. Okin, Reason and Feeling in ThinkingAbout Justice, 99 ETHICS229 (1989) (drawing
connections between Rawls's work and feminist thought).</p>
        <p>264. For one such unifiedtreatment of abortion and pornography,see SUNSTEIN, supra note
139, ch. 9.</p>
        <p>265. See MACKINNONs,upra note 263, at 154 ("To define the pornographicas the 'patently
offensive'furthermisconstrues its harm.... [P]ornography,in a feminist view, furthersthe idea
of the sexual inferiority of women . . .").</p>
        <p>
          266. See Elizabeth Anderson, Is Women'sLabor a Commodity?. 19 PHIL.&amp; Pun. AFF. 71
(1990) (arguing that commercial surrogacy improperlycommodifies reproductivecapacity). But
see Debra Satz, Markets in Women'sReproductiveLabor. 21 PHIL.&amp; PUB. AFF. 107 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
          )
(questioning the view that reproductive labor is not a commodity).
should be taken to argue that an improper kind of valuation has
pervaded norms and law relating to women, and that changes are
required that would embody a different kind.
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>H. Blocked Exchanges</title>
        <p>An understandingof diverse kinds of valuation helps explain why
liberal regimes generally respect voluntary agreements. If people
value things in different ways, the state should allow them to sort
things out as they choose. If values were commensurable,perhaps we
could seek to block certain voluntary exchanges simply because we
had better information about relevant costs and benefits than the
parties themselves. But, in the face of diverse kinds of valuation, it is best
to permit people to value as they like.267</p>
        <p>But even a system that generally respects freedom of contract may
block exchanges on several grounds. Typically such grounds involve
some form of market failure: a party may lack relevant information,a
collective action problem may exist, third parties may be affected, a
party may be myopic. But an additional and distinct reason is that
some exchanges involve and encourage improper kinds of valuation.</p>
        <p>I think that more common
argumentsstressingdistributiveconsiderations or unequal bargaining power often depend, upon reflection,
on an unarticulatedclaim about inappropriatevaluation. The claim is
that to allow purchase and sale of a good will mean that the good will
be wrongly valued in a qualitativesense.268Consider, for example, the
right to vote. Vote trading is objectionable in part because it would
allow inappropriateconcentration of political power in the hands of a
few. The prohibition therefore overcomes a collective action
problem.269But perhapsthe ban on vote tradingalso stems from a concern
about kinds of valuation. If votes were freely tradable,we would have
a differentconception of what voting is for - about the values that it
embodies - and this changed conception would have corrosive effects
on politics.</p>
        <p>267. This is a large partof the argumentin FRIEDRICHA. HAYEKT,HEROADTOSERFI)OM
57-59 (1944):</p>
        <p>The welfare and the happiness of millions cannot be measuredon a single scale of less and
more. The welfare of people . . . cannot be adequately expressed as a single end ....
[N]othing but partial scales of value exist - scales which are inevitably differentand often
inconsistent with each other. From this the individualist concludes that the individuals
should be allowed, within defined limits, to follow their own values and preferencesrather
than somebody else's.</p>
        <p>268. These claims are made explicit in Radin, supra note 23, at 1863-70, and KEIMAN.supra
note 23, at 77-84.</p>
        <p>269. See Richard A. Epstein, Why Restrain Alienation?. 85 Coi UM. L. REV. 970. 984-88
(1985).</p>
        <p>Some reactions to Judge Posner's argument on behalf of a form of
"babyselling" stem from a similar concern.270Judge Posner contends
that a market for babies would serve most of the relevant policies
better than does the current system. In some ways his argument is
persuasive. Certainly the desire of infertile couples for children would be
better satisfied through a market system. But part of the objection to
free markets in babies is not quite engaged by Judge Posner. Instead
the objection is that a system of purchase and sale would value
children in the wrong way. This system would treat human beings as
commodities, a view that is itself wrong, and a practice with possible
harmfulconsequencesfor social valuation in general. This is at most a
summary of a complex argument,based partly on uncertain empirical
judgments, and it is hardly by itself decisive. But we cannot get an
adequate grasp on the problem without seeing this concern.</p>
        <p>Or consider a possible application of the widely held view that
market incentives are preferableto command-and-controlregulation.
Might it not be preferable,for example, to allocate tradableracial
discrimination rights, so that discriminators,or people who refuse to act
affirmatively,can purchase rights from people who do not
discriminate or who engage in affirmative action?271 Suppose it could be
shown that an approach of this sort would be more efficient than the
approach in the current civil rights laws, and also that it would
produce equal or better outcomes in terms of aggregatehiring of minority
group members. Even if this were so, it might be thought
unacceptable to permit employers to discriminate for a fee, because the way
that we do or should value nondiscrimination is inconsistent with
granting that permission. This argument might be educative: if
discriminators could buy the right to discriminate, perhaps
discrimination would not be stigmatized in the way we want. Or it might be
expressive: perhaps society would like to condemn discrimination
quite apart from consequential arguments.272</p>
        <p>In coming to terms with the issue of blocked exchanges, some
further points are important. As noted, the recognition of diverse kinds
of valuationmight well be made part of a conception of law that places
a high premiumon individual liberty and choice. At least as a general
rule, the state should not say that one kind of valuation will be
required. Within broad outlines, people ought to be permitted to value
270. See supra notes 25-26 and accompanying text.</p>
        <p>271. See Robert Cooter, Market AffirmativeAction, 31 SAN DIEGOL. REV. (forthcoming
1994). The idea is proposedas satire in DERRICKBELI.,FACESATTHEBOTTOMOFTHEWELI.
ch. 5. (1993).</p>
        <p>272. Notations to this effect are made in Cooter, supra note 271.
as they wish, though we should recognize that any kind of valuation
will inevitably be affected by social norms and by law.</p>
        <p>Moreover,there is an importantdifferencebetween urging changes
in social norms and urging changes in law. There may be a justified
norm against asking a neighbor to mow one's lawn without a law to
that effect. Similarly, one might speak on behalf of a powerful norm
against certain attitudes toward animals without also recommending
laws that, for example, forbid people to eat meat. It is possible to urge
people to value animals in a certain way without thinking that the law
should require that kind of valuation.</p>
        <p>We might understand the distinction between norms and laws in
two differentways. First, the distinction might be largely pragmatic.
A law imposed on people who do not share the relevant norm may
breed frustrationand resentment. It may be counterproductiveor
futile. Second, the difference might be rooted in a principle of liberty,
one that calls for a strong presumption in favor of governmental
respect for diverse kinds of valuation. A legal mandate may be simply
too sectarian or intrusive for a heterogeneous society. Both
pragmatism and principle seem to argue in favor of a sharp distinction
between norms and law.</p>
        <p>There is a final point. Markets are filled with agreementsto
transfer goods that are not valued simply for use. People purchase music,
even if they regard the performances as deserving awe and wonder.
They buy human care for their children.273They trade the right to see
beautiful areas. They purchase pets for whom they feel affection or
even love, and whom they hardly regardas solely for human
exploitation and use. The objectionto the use of marketsin certain areasmust
depend on the view that markets will have adverse effects on existing
kinds of valuation, and it is not a simple matter to show when and why
this will be the case. For all these reasons, opposition to
commensurability, and insistence on diverse kinds of valuation, do not by
themselves amount to opposition to market exchange, which is pervadedby
choice among goods that participants value in diverse ways.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>I. Legal Reasoning</title>
      <p>A belief in diverse kinds of valuation has consequences for current
debates about the actual and appropriatenature of legal reasoning. If
it can be shown that a well-functioning system of law is alert to these
273. It is interesting,however, that these exchanges are also regulatedby a complex system
of norms. It would be odd to tell a babysitterthat she will get a premiumfor being loving, or a
reduced rate for being merely affectionate. Implicit deals on this front undoubtedlyoccur, but
the fact that they areonly implicit is itself important. Sec supratext accompanyingnotes 130-31.
diverse kinds of valuation, theories of legislation, administration, and
adjudication may be affected.</p>
      <p>Consider, for example, economic analysis of law. It is clear that
this form of analysis has produced enormous gains in the positive and
normative study of law. Nonetheless, the approach has been criticized
on many grounds, most familiarly that it is insufficiently attuned to
distributive arguments.274 But perhaps the resistance to economic
analysis stems from something quite different and less noticed. In its
normative form, economic analysis depends on too thin, flat, and
sectarian a conception of value, captured in the notion that legal rules
should be designed so as to maximize wealth. The problem with this
idea is that the word wealth elides qualitative distinctions among the
different goods typically at stake in legal disputes. Instead of
maximizing wealth, it is desirable to have a highly disaggregated picture of
the consequences of legal rules, a picture that enables the judge to see
the various goods at stake. This is true not only of the law of free
speech and religious liberty, but also of the law of contract and tort.
At least under ideal circumstances, it would be good to have a full
sense of the qualitatively distinct interests at stake before reaching a
decision.</p>
      <p>We still lack an account of practical reason in law. But what I
have said here offers some considerations in support of analogical
reasoning, the conventional method of Anglo-American law. Analogical
reasoning, unlike economic analysis, need not insist on assessing plural
and diverse social goods according to a single metric. The analogical
thinker is alert to the manifold dimensions of social situations and to
the many relevant similarities and differences. In picking out relevant
similarities, the analogizer does not engage in an act of deduction.
Instead she identifies common features in a way that helps constitute
both legal and cultural categories, rather than being constrained by
some particular theory of value given in advance. Unequipped with or
unburdened by a unitary theory of the good or the right, she is in a
position to see clearly and for herself the diverse and plural goods that
are involved and to make choices among them without reducing them
to a single metric.275 This is one description of the characteristic style
274. See, e.g., Morton Horwitz, Law and Economics. Science or Politics?, 8 HOFSTIRAL.
REV. 905 (1980).</p>
      <p>275. See ANDERSONs,upra note 1, at 91-116; Cass R. Sunstein, On Analogical Reasoninlg.
106 HARV.L. REV.741 (1993). The distinction between incommensurabilityand
incomparability, see supra text accompanyingnotes 64- 65, may well suggest that the absenceof
commensurability (as I understandit here) does not endangerthe claim that there are right answers in law. I
cannot, however, discuss that complex issue here. See John Mackie, The Third Theoryof Law, in
RONALD DWORKIN AND CONTEMPORARYJURISPRUDENCE 161, 165 (Marshall Cohen ed..
of Anglo-American law in its idealized form.</p>
      <p>A distinctive feature of analogical thinking is that it is a
"bottomup" approach, building principles of a low or intermediate level of
generality from engagement with particular cases. In this respect, it is
quite different from "top-down" theories, which test particular
judgments by reference to general theory.276 Because analogy works from
particular judgments, it is likely to reflect the plural and diverse goods
that people really value. Of course there are nonanalogical approaches
that insist on the plurality of goods,277 and those approaches also have
a "top-down" character.</p>
      <p>Of course this approach has disadvantages as well. The use of a
single metric makes things simple and orderly where they would
otherwise be chaotic. In certain areas of the law, this may be a
decisive advantage, all things considered. Certainly it has been taken as an
important advantage in many areas of contemporary law, in which the
displacement of common law courts by legislation has been designed
to promote rule-of-law virtues inaccessible to ordinary adjudication.278</p>
      <p>CHOICES</p>
      <p>I have not yet dealt with two major questions. The first involves
the choice among different kinds of valuation and, more particularly,
the decision whether or not to make things commensurable. The
second involves the issue of how to make choices among
incommensurable goods. The two questions are obviously related. They are also
large and complex; to answer them, we would need to answer many of
the major questions in ethical and political theory. As I have
emphasized, most answers must be developed in the context of particular
problems. I offer only a few notations here.
1984) (questioning Dworkin's right-answerthesis on the grounds that strengths are not always
commensurableon a linear scale).</p>
      <p>276. See Smart, supra note 68, at 56:
In science general principles must be tested by reference to particularfacts of observation.
In ethics we may well take the opposite attitude, and test our particularmoral attitudes by
referenceto more general ones. The utilitariancan contend that since his principle[] rests
on something so simple and natural as generalized benevolence it is more securely founded
than our particularfeelings, which may be subtly distorted by analogies with similar looking
(but in reality totally different) types of case[s], and by all sorts of hangovers from
traditional and uncritical ethical thinking.</p>
      <p>For discussion of related issues, see Sunstein, supra note 275, at 767-90.</p>
      <p>
        277. An example is Sen's "capabilityapproach." See AMARTYA SEN,
INEQUALITYREEXAMINED 39-55, 73-87 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">1992</xref>
        ); see also Sen, supra note 57, at 207-10. Rawls's list of primary
goods has similar characteristics. See RAWLS, supra note 81, at 181.
      </p>
      <p>278. Cf Bruce Ackerman, The CommonLaw Constitutionalismof John Marshall Harlan. 36
N.Y. L. SCH.L. REV. 5 (1991).
A.</p>
      <sec id="sec-4-1">
        <title>WhichKinds of Valuation?</title>
        <p>To come to terms with the question of appropriatekinds of
valuation, we should begin by asking whether diversity in kinds is desirable
at all. Perhapswe should adopt a unitary kind of valuation, or seek to
obtain some sort of commensurability. In many ways this project
unites such diverse thinkers as Plato, Bentham, and, in law, Richard
Posner.279It seems clear that this approach would have many
advantages. It would simplify and order decisions by placing the various
goods along a single metric. According to one familiar conception of
rationality, this step would increase rationality. Would it not be a
large improvement if commensurabilitycould be obtained?</p>
        <p>Let us put law to one side for the moment and think about claims
for unitariness and commensurability in human life generally. It
seems obvious that an answer to this question should turn on what
leads to a better conception of the human good. There is no
transcendental or external standpoint from which to offer this answer. Our
evaluation will inevitably be a reflection of what we think. But this
should hardly be thought disabling.280We might make some progress
by considering what the world would be like if kinds of valuation
really were unitary or if commensurabilityreally did obtain. In such a
world, for example, a loss of friendshipor the death of a parent would
really be like a loss of money, though undoubtedly a lot of it.281 An
achievement in something that one prizes - like art or
musicwould be valued in the same way as an increase in net worth, or the
birth of a new child, or falling in love, or the relief of human suffering,
or the victory of a favorite sports team. Offersof cash exchange would
really be evaluatedsolely on the basis of their amount. The distinction
between instrumentaland intrinsic goods would collapse, in the sense
that many intrinsic goods would become both fungible and
instrumental.</p>
        <p>A great deal would be lost in such a world.282A life with genuine
commensurabilitywould be flat and dehumanized. It would eliminate
279. See supra notes 2-3 and accompanying text.</p>
        <p>280. Note the fallacy of thinking that, without transcendentalor externalgrounds,our
evaluations have no basis at all; they are ultimately grounded in human experience, and none the
worse for that. See generally HILARYPUTNAM, RENEWINGPHILOSOPH(Y1992).</p>
        <p>281. This is related to Putnam's attack on utilitarianism,captured in the tale of the
superBenthamites,whose understandingof experiencewould not be readilyaccessibleto us. See supra
note 65.</p>
        <p>282. In this vein Williams criticizes utilitarianismfor "its great simple-mindedness.... [It
has] too few thoughts and feelings to match the world as it really is." Williams,supranote 88, at
149;cf RAZ,supra note 17, at 344 ("There is no need, nor any way, to justify pervasivefeatures
of human thought. But there is a need for an explanation which make them intelligible.").
delight, bewilderment,and surprise. It would be inconsistent with an
appropriately diversified approach to a good human life. It would
eliminate desirable relationships and attitudes. In fact it would be
barely recognizable.283</p>
        <p>On the other hand, nothing in this brief account is fatal to the view
that law and public policy sometimes ought to rest on unitary kinds of
valuation or on assumptions of commensurability. It is possible to
think that under ideal conditions, the best system of valuation is
diverse and plural, but that in light of the weaknesses of human
institutions and the constant prospect of bias and arbitrariness, public
choices should assume a single kind or a unitarymetric as the best way
of promoting all of the relevant goods.284This question cannot be
answered a priori or in the abstract. But those who favor legal
approaches based on unitary kinds of valuation and commensurability
should understandthat their approach is best defended as a means of
overcoming certain institutional obstacles, and not as reflectinga fully
adequate understandingof the relevant problems. I have suggested as
well that even if, say, government officials align the diverse effects of
regulation along a single metric, they should also provide a
disaggregated picture, so that citizens can be aware of qualitative differences
and of the various goods at stake.</p>
        <p>All this leaves much uncertainty. But it does suggest that,
institutional issues aside, we should approve of a large degree of diversity in
kinds of valuation. From this it does not follow that any particular
kind of valuation is appropriatefor any particularsphere. To evaluate
kinds of valuation, we also have to think very concretely about what
kinds in what places are parts of a good life or a good political system.
To come to terms with this question, it would be necessary to say a
great deal. For present purposes, a few observations may suffice to
give a sense of the sorts of things that might emerge.</p>
        <p>Some families exist in which people are valued solely for their use,
and this is a pervasivesource of deprivationand injustice.285A family
283. Thus Wittgenstein:
Some philosophers(or whatever you like to call them) sufferfrom what may be called "loss
of problems." Then everythingseems quite simple to them, no deep problemsseem to exist
any more, the world becomes broad and flat and loses all depth, and what they write
becomes immeasurablyshallow and trivial.</p>
        <p>LUDWIGWITTGENSTEINZ,ETTELpara. 456 (G.E.M. Anscombe &amp; G.H. von Wright eds. &amp;
G.E.M. Anscombe trans., 1967). For Mill's related critique of Bentham, see supra note 59.</p>
        <p>284. "[Risk analysis] allows many environmentalproblemsto be measuredand compared in
common terms, and it allows different risk reduction options to be evaluated from a common
basis." RELATIVERISK REDUCTIONSTRATEGICCOMMITTEES,CIENCEADVISORYBD.,
REDUCING RISK: SETTING PRIORITIESAND STRATEGIESFOR ENVIRONMENAI. PROTECTION
2 (1990).</p>
        <p>285. See Okin, supra note 33.
in which reason-givingis the sole or pervasivekind of valuation would
have differentproblems;but it seems clear that it would have problems
as well. The bonds that unite people in a family are not adequately
captured by the exchange of reasons. But this is not to say that
injustice within families cannot be exposed through that exchange. A
measure of respect is a condition for a well-functioning relationship
between spouses.286</p>
        <p>So, too, a political system dominated not by reasonsbut instead by
self-interestedbargainingmay well produce inferiorlaw, and precisely
because the absence of reason-giving will fail to uncover difficulties
with some of the various proposals.287Such a political system will
also violate principles of political equality to the extent that it allows
the translation of economic disparities into law. A political system
that depended on bonds of affection or love would probablyprove
unworkable, certainly in a large, heterogeneous society.</p>
        <p>These various observationsare no more than assertions. They are
meant simply to point toward the sorts of concrete inquiries that are
requiredfor an evaluation of what kinds of valuation are appropriate
in what contexts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-2">
        <title>B. ChoicesAmong IncommensurableGoods</title>
        <p>How are choices made among incommensurablegoods? How can
those choices be assessed? The first point is that there is no algorithm
or formula by which to answer this question. If we are looking for a
certain sort of answer - the sort characteristic of some believers in
commensurability- we will be unable to find it. Relatively little can
be said in the abstract. Instead we need to offer detailed descriptions
of how such choices are made, and how to tell whether such choices
turn out well. Here there are many possible criteria for public and
privateaction, and a mere referenceto the existence of
incommensurabilities will be unhelpful standing by itself.</p>
        <p>The search for criteria may well emphasize the need to secure a
form of narrative continuity within a life or within a society. When
someone chooses one option over another, it may be because the
chosen option makes for coherence over the course of time, whereas the
disregardedoption, even if attractive, would ensure that things make
little or no sense. There is also a connection between different
selfunderstandings and the choice between incommensurable options A
286. See Hampton, supra note 165, at 251.</p>
        <p>287. See Robert Goodin, Laundering Preferences, in THE FOUNDATIONSOF SOCIALCHOICE
THEORY 75 (Jon Elster &amp; Aanund Hylland eds., 1986).
and B. The selected option may conform to the agent's
preferredselfunderstanding. To achieve that self-understanding, we need to be
clear about what we value most deeply and to make choices that
properly express the deepest valuations.288Thus, for example, it may be
irrational to value a certain amount of cash over spending time with
one's family, because this would lead to a self-understandingthat is
either inconsistent with what has gone before or otherwise indefensible
for those asking what a good life contains. Individual and social ideals
play a large role in this assessment.289These are inadequate and
abstract remarks, but they may help explain how choices are made
among incommensurables,and how choices tend to go right or wrong.</p>
        <p>Some of the same things can be said of law and the public sphere.
Suppose that a society is deciding whether to sacrificea numberof jobs
in return for protecting an endangeredspecies. No unitary metric can
be helpful here. But perhaps the people entrusted with the power of
decision will ask, as part of the inquiry, about the society's prevailing
ideals, about ways minimally to damage relevant goods, and about
what decision best fits with the community's self-understandingas this
has been established over time. This is not merely a descriptive
inquiry. It involves asking what choice puts that self-understandingin
its best or most attractive light. On this view, choice among
incommensurablesis an act of interpretation,one that involves a dimension
of fidelity to the past, but that is also constructive.290</p>
        <p>In law and politics, a diverse set of standards - liberty, equality,
prosperity,excellence, all of these umbrellaterms - will be brought to
bear on hard cases. A particular goal is to find solutions that will
minimally damage the relevant goods. Perhaps an approach that
promotes a recognizableform of liberty will only modestly compromise a
recognizableconception of equality. Here too there is no escape from
close examination of particular cases.
288. For the view that choice reflects the articulation of value commitments, see Charles
Taylor, Responsibilityfor Self in FREEWILL111 (Gary Watson ed., 1982). I am suggestingthat
this point applies to legal and political choice as well. See also the discussion of commitment in
Amartya Sen, Rational Fools, reprinted in BEYONDSFI.F-INTIEREST25, 31-43 (Jane J.
Mansbridgeed., 1991).</p>
        <p>289. See supra section I.B.</p>
        <p>290. Cf. DWORKINs,upra note 74, at 45-113 (describing legal interpretation in similar
terms).
after birth.291 Criminalization would entail difficult enforcement
problemsand might also discouragearrangementsthat do much good
and little harm. We can understand why surrogacy arrangements
might be thought to be connected with sex inequality, but the
contribution to discriminationis probablytoo attenuatedto justify
criminalization. On the other hand, it may be damagingto the birth mother to
force her to hand over a child against her will, especially because
before the fact it may be quite difficult for her to know exactly what
this action entails. The failure of the legal system to order specific
performanceis unlikely to have serious adverse consequences on
prospective participantsin such arrangements. This is of course an
inadequate treatmentof a complex problem. All I mean to do is to suggest
some of the lines along which the inquiry might occur. (Compare an
approach that would insist on commensurability. Such an approach
would be laughably inadequate;it would prevent us from seeing what
is really at stake.)</p>
        <p>Much of the relevant work here is done in two ways: through
analogies and through understandingconsequences, mediated as these
are through expressive norms. When incommensurablegoods are at
stake, it is typically asked: What was the resolution of a previous case
with similar features? Through this process, people seek to produce
vertical and horizontal consistency among their various judgments.
This system of testing is designed not to line goods up along a single
metric, but to producethe sort of consistency and rigor that
characterizes the successful operationof practicalreason. The inquiryinto
consequences avoids monism while still examining the real-world effects
of differentcourses of action. How, for example, will a
particularresult compromiseor promote the relevantgoods? This is a
characteristic part of practical reasoning in law.</p>
        <p>In the context of emissions trading in environmental law, for
example, it seems hard to support the empiricalclaim that the shift from
command-and-controlgovernmentto financialincentives will have
serious adverse effects on people's thinking about pollution. Many
claims about the educative function of law are actually claims about
real-world consequences, understood through expressive norms on
which there is no dispute. It is possible to think well about those
consequences, and sometimes we can see that the feared effects will not
materialize. In this way it is possible to explore whether there will be
damage to some of the goods that are allegedly threatenedby certain
291. See JONATHANGLOVER,ETHICSOF NEW REPRODUCTIVTEECHNOIOGIEST:HE
GIlOVERREPORTTOTHEEUROPEANCOMMISSIO7N7-78, 151 (1989).
initiatives. Of course it is true that, on some issues, we will lack
relevant data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-3">
        <title>C. A Note on Tragedy</title>
        <p>There is a final point. A recognition of incommensurabilityis
necessary to keep alive the sense of tragedy, and in certain ways this is an
individual and collective good, perhaps especially in law.292
Recognition that all outcomes "impose costs" is not quite the same thing as a
sense of tragedy. Though I can hardly discuss this complex matter
here, the very notion of tragedy seems to embody a commitment to an
understandingof the uniquenessof certain goods, or the irreversibility
and irreplaceabilityof certain losses.293If tragedy were understood to
mean instead high costs, or the existence of losses that accompany
benefits (Kaldor-Hicks rather than Pareto improvements, for
example), the sense of tragedy would be dramaticallychanged. Here too we
would not have a simple redescriptionof the problem.</p>
        <p>A sense of tragedy is an individual good because it accompanies
certain relationshipsand attitudes that are an importantpart of a good
life. It is a collective good for this reason and also because it focuses
attention on the fact that, even when the law is doing the right thing,
all things considered, much may be lost as well. This is valuable in,
for example, currentthinking about the environmentand occupational
safety. In the presence of tragedy, there is a large incentive to create
social arrangementsso that people do not face that prospect.</p>
        <p>This is so with respect to pervasiveconflicts among valuablethings
- employment versus environment, diminishing poverty versus
national security, attention to family versus attention to work. Such
conflicts themselves may be an artifact of legal and social arrangements.
On monistic theories of value, it is easy to believe that nothing is really
lost - or at least nothing that is unique, intrinsicallyvaluable, or
irretrievable. This understandingdiminishes the incentive to find a
solution that will not create tragic choices. When tragedy is understoodto
be present, there is a constant and conspicuous social interest in
seeking solutions that simultaneously promote all of the relevant goods.</p>
        <p>At its best, the Anglo-American legal system is alert to the fact
that diverse goods are at stake in many disputes. Judges know that
not all of these goods can simultaneously be preserved. This
awareness is itself desirablebecause of the pressurethat it tends to exert on
292. Cf GUIDOCALABRES&amp;I PHILIPBOBBITTT, RAGICCHOICES57-64 (1978).
293. For discussions of the defining characteristicsof tragedy, see id. See also MAiRI\H C.
NUSSBAUMT, HEFRAGILITYOFGOODNES2S3-84 (1986) (discussing the role of conflict amolng
ethical claims in Greek tragedy).
judges and legislatorsas well. A redescriptionof tragedyin terms that
assume a monistic theory of value would not create the same sort of
pressure.</p>
        <p>CONCLUSION</p>
        <p>Human beings value goods, events, and relationships in diverse
and plural ways. Sometimeswe face serious problemsof
commensurability. This problem does not entail paralysis, indeterminacy,or
arbitrariness. Decisions are made all the time among incommensurable
goods, at the personal,social, and legal levels, and these decisions may
well be rational or irrational. It might even be possible to convert our
kinds of valuation for use on a unitary metric, or to make goods,
events, and relationshipscommensurable. But if what I have said here
is correct, this would be a sort of tragedy, not least because it would
make the very fact of tragedy puzzling or even incomprehensible.</p>
        <p>The fact of diverse kinds of valuation, and the existence of
incommensurable goods, have not yet played a major role in legal theory.
But these issues underlie a surprisingly wide range of legal disputes.
No unitary "top-down" theory can account for the complexities of
most controversiesin law. Perhaps most dramatically, the liberal
insistence on social differentiation- markets, families, religious groups,
politics, and more - is best justified as an attempt to make a space for
distinct kinds of valuation and to give each of them its appropriate
place in human life. The Establishmentand Equal Protection Clauses
are centrally concerned with regulating kinds of valuation. In
environmentallaw, the majorissue of contestation is frequentlythe
appropriate kind of valuation of environmental amenities; if beaches,
species, and mountains were valued solely for their use, we would not
be able to understandthem in the way that we now do.</p>
        <p>The same issue arisesin the law of contract, especially in the award
of specificperformanceremedies. It also plays a role in thinking about
the point of damage remedies in tort. In both settings, it is wrong to
ignore the highly contextual nature of choice and to act as if a
particular decision - not to take out insurancefor a certain danger, to accept
a job at a certain risk premium- reflects some global judgment
simply adaptablefor policy use. No globaljudgment need
underlieparticular choices. Many blocked exchanges, moreover, attest to social
resistanceto commensurability. I have also suggestedthat attention to
these issues shows that cost-benefitanalysis is obtuse, because it aligns
qualitativelydistinct goods along a single metric. Instead of
cost-benefit analysis - which might of course be helpful in our at most
secondbest world - what is desirableis a disaggregatedpicture of the effects
of differentcourses of action, so that officialsand citizens can see those
effects for themselves.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>V. LAW IN PARTICULAR .................................. A. Social Differentiation ................. .............. B.</given-names>
            <surname>Religion</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Civic Equality, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Political Liberalism..... C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Broadcastingand Free Speech, with a Note on Rights</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Generally........................................... D. EnvironmentalProtection ........................... E. Cost-BenefitAnalysis ..................... ...........</surname>
          </string-name>
          18. See infra section V.
          <source>D. 19. See infra notes 91-105 and accompanying text</source>
          . For challenges to utilitarianismbased on
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>rejectionof the claim that goodness is always of a particularkind, see ANDERSONs</article-title>
          ,upra note 1;
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          ASSN.,Oct.
          <year>1993</year>
          , at
          <volume>145</volume>
          . 20.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>STEVEN SHAVELL</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>ECONOMICANALYSIS OF ACCIDENT LAW 153-54</source>
          ,
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          ,
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          -
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <volume>54</volume>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ); Steven P. Croley &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jon D. Hanson</surname>
          </string-name>
          , WhatLiability Crisis?,8 YALE J.
          <source>ON REG. 1</source>
          ,
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          -
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <volume>67</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>; cf George L. Priest, The CurrentInsurance Crisisand Modern TortLaw, 96 YALE</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>L.J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1521</year>
          ,
          <issue>1553</issue>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
          <article-title>I am grateful to Jon Hanson for a helpful discussion of this point. 24. We should be wary, however, of a rapid movement from judgments about appropriate</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>kinds of valuation to a particularposition about law</article-title>
          .
          <source>See infra notes 134-40 and accompanying</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>ANDERSONs</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,upra note 1, at 168-89
          <source>(discussing surrogatemotherhood)</source>
          ,
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          (discussing envi-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>ronmental regulation)</source>
          .
          <volume>25</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>RICHARDA</given-names>
          </string-name>
          .
          <article-title>POSNERS,EX</article-title>
          AND REASON409-
          <volume>17</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ); Elisabeth M. Landes &amp;
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Richard A.</given-names>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>TheEconomicsof the Baby Shortage</source>
          ,7
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>LEGALSTUD</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>323</volume>
          (
          <year>1978</year>
          ); Richard
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Regulation of the Market in Adoptions</article-title>
          .67
          <string-name>
            <given-names>B.U. L.</given-names>
            <surname>REV</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>59</volume>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>See the discussion of symbolic value in ROBERTNOZICKT</article-title>
          ,HENATUREOFRATIONAL-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <fpage>ITY26</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generally</surname>
            <given-names>PETERSINGERA</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>NIMALLIBERATIO(N1975); see also PAULW</article-title>
          . TAYLOR,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>RESPECTFORNATURE</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguingthat humans owe duties to all living things); LaurenceA.</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tribe</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Ways Not To Think About Plastic Trees, 83 YALE L.J.
          <volume>1315</volume>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          )
          <article-title>(challenging the</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>provides a good overview of related issues. 31. This view is defended in ANDERSON, supra note 1</article-title>
          , at 65-
          <fpage>90</fpage>
          .
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>KARL POLANYI</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>THE GREAT TRANSFORMATION33-102</source>
          (
          <year>1944</year>
          ).
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g. POSNER,supra note 25, at 36- 50 (
          <article-title>sketching a history of Western sexual mores</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>equality and respect, see SUSAN M. OKIN, JUSTICE</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>GENDER</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>AND THE FAMILY 134-69</source>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <volume>34</volume>
          . 347 U.S.
          <volume>483</volume>
          (
          <year>1954</year>
          ).
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          . See generally RICHARD KLUGER,
          <string-name>
            <surname>SIMPLE JUSTICE</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1976</year>
          ).
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>This is a general theme of Mark Barenberg, The Political Economy of the WagnerAct:</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Power</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Symbol, and WorkplaceCooperation,
          <volume>106</volume>
          HARV.L. REV.
          <volume>1379</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Jack M. Beermann</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Joseph W. Singer</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Baseline Questionsin Legal Reasoning: The</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>Example of Propertyin Jobs</source>
          ,
          <volume>23</volume>
          GA. L. REV.
          <volume>911</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ); Lawrence E. Blades, Employmenitat
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Willvs.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>IndividualFreedom: OnLimiting the AbusiveExerciseof EmployerPower,67 COI</article-title>
          .UNML.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          REV.
          <volume>1404</volume>
          (
          <year>1967</year>
          ).
          <fpage>44</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>See the discussion of lexical ordering</article-title>
          ,
          <source>infra text accompanying notes 206-10. 45. See the attack on incomparabilityin Chang, supra note 6, at 1-4</source>
          ,
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          .
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>This suggestion is contrary to the claim in Donald H</article-title>
          . Regan, Authorityand Value. Re-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>flections on Raz's Moralityof Freedom</source>
          ,62
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>CAL.L. REV</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>995</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1058</issue>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
          <article-title>See infra Part III. 47</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <source>Douglas</source>
          Baird et al.,
          <source>StrategicBehaviorand the Law (forthcoming</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(man-</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>uscript at 1-56, on file with author) (using simplifiedassumptions in game-theoreticanalysis to</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>predict consequences of alternative tort regimes)</source>
          .
          <source>51. See infra notes 231-33</source>
          and accompanying text; see also Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Preferences</surname>
            ,EnvironmentalLaw, 22
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>LEGALSTUD</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>217</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>248</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          . Exec.
          <source>OrderNo</source>
          .
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <issue>498</issue>
          , 3
          <string-name>
            <surname>C.F.R.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>323</year>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          ), reprintedin 5 U.S.C. ?
          <volume>601</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ); Exec.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Order</given-names>
            <surname>No</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <issue>291</issue>
          , 3
          <string-name>
            <surname>C.F.R.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>127</year>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ), reprintedin 5 U.S.C. ?
          <volume>601</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Exec</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Order No.
          <volume>12</volume>
          ,
          <issue>866</issue>
          , 58 Fed. Reg.
          <volume>51</volume>
          ,
          <issue>735</issue>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <source>BREYERs,upra note 219</source>
          . 238.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See PETER</surname>
            <given-names>ASCH</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>CONSUMERSAFETY REGULATION 1-13</source>
          ,
          <fpage>64</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>69</lpage>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>There is something to these objections. Willingness to pay. the typical criterion for</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>tive impacts." 240. I am assuming here that diverse kinds of valuation are an affirmativegood, a claim</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>defended in Part III. 250</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Guido</given-names>
            <surname>Calabresi</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>Melamed</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , PropertyRules, Liability Rules, and Inaliena-
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>bility: One Viewof the Cathedral</source>
          ,
          <volume>85</volume>
          HARV.L. REV.
          <volume>1089</volume>
          (
          <year>1972</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

