<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cass R. Sunstein, "Problems with Rules,"</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Problems with Rules</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>953</volume>
      <issue>1995</issue>
      <fpage>985</fpage>
      <lpage>1026</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>JULY 1995
Copyright © 1995 by California Law Review, Inc.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Problems with Rules</title>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein</title>
        <p>TABLE OF CONTENTS
No. 4
978
978
980
984
984
986
990
991
992
993
994
994
995
995
996
997
998
998
998
999
999
1000
1000
1001
1001</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Problems with Rules</title>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunsteint</title>
        <p>Many of the most difficult issues in law involve the choice between
rules and rulelessness in cases where both seem unacceptable. The
principal goal of this Article is to point the way toward a more refined
understanding of the ideal of the rule of law, one that sees a degree of
particularity,and a degree of law-making at the point of application, as
importantparts of that ideal. The Article defends aform of casuistry and
describes the potentially democraticfoundations of the casuistical
enterprise in law. It begins by describingthe distinctiveadvantages ofrules and
law via rules, especially as a meansfor providing a consensus on what the
law is from people who disagree on much else. It also discusses three
attacks on decisions accordingto rules: the view that rules are excessively
conservative; the view that controversialpoliticaland moral claims always
play a role in the interpretationof rules, and thus that rules are not what
they appearto be; and the view that rules are obtuse because they are too
crude to cover diverse human affairs, and becausejudges should not decide
cases without closely inspecting the details of disputes. The Article
suggests several ways to avoid the dilemmas posed by rules and rulelessness:
(a) a presumption in favor ofprivately adaptable rules, that is, rules that
allocate entitlements without specifying outcomes, in an effort to promote
goals associatedwith free markets; (b) a recognitionoflegitimate rule
revision, in which public officials andprivate citizens are allowed to soften the
hardedges ofrules; and (c) highly contextualizedassessments ofthe virtues
Copyright © 1994 California Law Review, Inc.</p>
        <p>t Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, Law School and
Department of Political Science, University of Chicago. This essay is an expansion of certain sections
of the second of my 1994 Tanner Lectures on Human Values, delivered at Harvard University in
November 1994; the lectures themselves will appear under the title Political Conflict and Legal
Agreement in 17 THE TA ER LEcruR~s ON HUMAN VALuEs (Grethe B. Peterson ed., forthcoming
1996). I am especially grateful to my audiences at Harvard for their extraordinary graciousness and for
their probing comments and questions. Of the many people who offered help on that occasion, I single
out for special thanks my commentators Jean Hampton and Jeremy Waldron, and also Joshua Cohen,
Christine Korsgaard, Martha Minow, Martha Nussbaum, John Rawls, Tim Scanlon, and Amartya Sen.
For extremely helpful comments on the manuscript I am thankful to Bruce Ackerman, Ruth Change,
Joshua Cohen, Einer Elhauge, Jon Elster, Charles Fried, Amy Gutman, Don Herzog, Stephen Holmes,
Elena Kagan, Dan Kahan, Larry Lessig, Saul Levmore, William Meadow, Frank Michelman, Martha
Minow, Martha Nussbaum, Susan Moller Okin, Wictor Osiatynski, Richard Posner, Joseph Raz,
Frederick Schauer, Steven Schulhofer, Anne-Marie Slaughter, Mark Tushnet, Candace Volger, and
Lloyd Weinreb. I am also indebted to participants in a work-in-progress lunch at the University of
Chicago and to members of legal theory workshops at Oxford University and the University of
California, Berkeley. I am also grateful to Sophie Clark for research assistance. Parts of this Article
will appear in a book, LEGAL REAsoNWG AND PoLmcAL CowFucr (forthcoming 1996).
andpathologiesofboth options, in an effort to promote democraticgoals of
responsiveness and open participation.</p>
        <p>[T]he highest ethical life of the mind consists at all times in the
breaking of rules which have grown too narrow for the actual case.
-William James'
[T]he establishment of broadly applicable general principles is
an essential component of the judicial process ....
-Justice</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>Antonin Scalia2</title>
        <p>One other capital imperfection [of Common Law is] . ..the
unaccommodatingnessof its rules.... Hence the hardness of heart
which is a sort of endemical disease of lawyers ....Mischief being
almost their incessant occupation, and the greatest merits they can
attain being the firmness with which they persevere in the task of
doing partial evil for the sake of that universal good which consists
in steady adherence to established rules, a judge thus circumstanced
is obliged to divert himself of that anxious sensibility, which is one
of the most useful as well as amiable qualities of the legislator.
-Jeremy Bentham3</p>
        <p>INTRODUCTION</p>
        <p>There are two stylized conceptions of legal judgment. The first,
associated with Jeremy Bentham 4 and more recently with Justices Hugo
Blackand Antonin Scalia,6 places a high premium on the creation and application
of general rules. On this view, public authorities should avoid "balancing
tests" or close attention to individual circumstances. They should attempt
instead to give guidance to lower courts, future legislators, and citizens
through clear, abstractrules laid down in advance of actual applications.</p>
        <p>The second conception, associated with William Blackstone and more
recently with Justices Felix Frankfurter7 and John Marshall Harlan,8 places
a high premium on law-making at the point of applicationthrough
case-bycase decisions, narrowly tailored to the particulars of individual
circum</p>
        <p>I. GEORGE AINSLIE, PICOECONOMics 218 (1992) (citing WILLIAM JAMES, PRINCIPLES OF
PSYCHOLOGY 209 (1890)).</p>
        <p>2. Justice Antonin Scalia, The Rule of Law as a Law of Rules, 56 U. CH. L. Rzv. 1175, 1185
(1989).</p>
        <p>3. JEREMY BENTHAM, OF LAWS INGNRA., ch. XV, 12 n.1(H.L.A. Hart ed., 1970).
4. See GERALD J. POSTEMA, BENTHAM AND THE COMMON LAW TRADmON 403-13 (1986), which
shows, however, that Bentham's views on rules are quite complex.</p>
        <p>5. See Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube Co. v. Sawyer, 343 U.S. 579, 585-89 (1952) (the "Steel
Seizure Case").</p>
        <p>6. See generally Scalia, supra note 2.
7. See Youngstown, 343 U.S. at 594 (Frankfurter, J., concurring).
8. See Poe v. Ullman, 367 U.S. 497, 525 (1961) (Harlan, J., dissenting).
stances. On this view, public authorities should stay close to the details of
the controversy before them and avoid broader principles altogether. The
problem with broad principles is that they tend to overreach; they may be
erroneous or unreasonable as applied to cases not before the court.9</p>
        <p>It would be hard to overstate the importance of the controversy
between the two views. The controversy arises in every area of law; 10 it
often involves fundamental liberties. 1 Of course, familiar understandings
of the rule of law prize, as a safeguard of freedom, broad rules laid down in
advance; but the American legal system also values close attention to the
details of each case. In every area of regulation-the environment,
occupational safety and health, energy policy, communications, control of
monopoly power-it is necessary to choose between general rules and
case-bycase decisions.</p>
        <p>In its purest form, enthusiasm for genuinely case-specific decisions
makes no sense. Few if any judgments about particular cases are entirely
particular. Almost any judgment about a particular case depends on the use
of principles or reasons. Any principles or reasons are, by their very nature,
broader than the case for which they are designed. Case-by-case
particularism is not a promising foundation for law.</p>
        <p>In many circumstances, however, enthusiasm for rules seems senseless
too. Sometimes public authorities cannot design general rules, because they
lack relevant information. Sometimes general rules will fail, because the
legal system seeks subtle judgments about a range of particulars. Often
general rules will be poorly suited to the new circumstances that will be
turned up by unanticipated developments; often rulemakers cannot foresee
the circumstances to which their rules will be applied. Often rules will be
too crude, since they run up against intransigent beliefs about how
particular cases should be resolved.</p>
        <p>One of my principal goals in this Article is to respond to a pervasive
social phenomenon: extravagant enthusiasm for rules and an extravagantly
rule-bound conception of the rule of law. 2 Case-by-case decisions are an
important part of legal justice. We are familiar with a conception of
procedural fairness based on rules. In this conception, people have a right to be
told about prevailing requirements and a correlative right to test whether
those requirements have been violated. But there is another, more
particu9. The point is treated prominently in Board of Education v. Grumet, 114 S. Ct. 2481, 2498-99
(1994) (O'Connor, J., concurring in part).</p>
        <p>10. See infra App. accompanying notes 284-323.</p>
        <p>11. For example, see the attack on the undue burden standard as unacceptably open-ended in
Planned Parenthood v. Casey, 112 S. Ct. 2791, 2876-80 (1992) (Scalia, J., concurring in part and
dissenting in part).</p>
        <p>12. As examples of such enthusiasm, see F.A. HAYEK, THE CONSTITUrrON OF LmERTv 148-61
(1960); F.A. HAYEK, THE RoAD TO SERoM 72-87 (1944); Scalia, supra note 2. Justice Scalia's
approach is not unqualified. Id. at 1177. For an attack on extravagant enthusiasm for rules, overlaping
with what I suggest here, see generally KENNET C. DAVIS ET AL., DISCRETIONARY JUSTICE IN EUROPE
AND AMERICA (1976).
laristic conception of procedural fairness, one that is also worthy of respect.
Under that conception, people are entitled to argue that they are relevantly
different from those that have come before, and that when their case is
investigated in all its particularity, it will be shown that special treatment is
warranted. On this view-with potentially democratic
foundations-people who are affected by rules should be allowed to participate in the creation
of the very rule to be applied to their case. 13</p>
        <p>I argue here that the disadvantages of rules and rule-bound justice are
often insufficiently appreciated, and that legal systems sometimes do and
should abandon rules in favor of a form of casuistry.4 In the casuistic
enterprise, judgments are based not on a preexisting rule, but on
comparisons between the case at hand and other cases, especially those that are
unambiguously within a generally accepted norm. Bounded rationality-in
the form of ignorance about relevant facts, values, and future developments
or circumstances-provides an important reason for proceeding in this way.
When people lack sufficient information to design (satisfactory or
sufficiently finely tuned) rules, they might resort to case analysis instead. But
bounded rationality is not the only problem. The argument for case analysis
depends as well on the diversity and plurality of values. t5 These ideas have
an obvious bearing on law, and they have consequences for ethics, too,
though I will not discuss ethical issues here.</p>
        <p>I urge as well that both the old art of casuistry and the old domain of
equity can be given democratic foundations. A legal system committed to
casuistry might insist that every litigant is entitled to urge that he is
distinctive, that he deserves distinctive treatment, and that his claims to this effect
warrant a public response. Insofar as a legal system recognizes this claim,
its form of casuistry embodies norms of participation and responsiveness.
Such a system also seeks to ensure against premature judicial foreclosure of
issues that should be subject to democratic deliberation.</p>
        <p>I do not deny that quite serious risks are associated with any effort to
proceed through case-by-case judgments. These risks include the abusive
exercise of discretion, lack of predictability or of the capacity to form
expectations, high costs of decisions, failure of political accountability, and
much more. As a way of reducing those risks, we might evaluate solutions
through both economic and democratic criteria. For this reason I argue
against an ingenious solution proposed by Jeremy Bentham,"6 and suggest
instead three principal alternatives. The first is founded principally in
market rather than democratic norms. It involves a presumption in favor of
13. See infra notes 155-156 and accompanying text.
14. See ALBERT R. JONSEN &amp; STEPHEN E. TouLmmN, THE ABUSE OF CASUISTRY 11-16 (1988).
15. See infra text accompanying notes 185-190. See generally ELIZABETH ANDERSON, VALUE IN
ETmics AND ECONOMICS (1993) (discussing plural values);.</p>
        <p>16. See Meir Dan-Cohen, Decision Rules andConductRules: On Acoustic Separationin Criminal
Law, 97 HARV. L. REV. 625 (1984).</p>
        <p>PROBLEMS WiTH RULES
what I will call privately adaptablerules-rulesthat allocate initial
entitlements but do not specify end-states, and that harness private forces to
determine outcomes. Such rules can help break through some of the dilemmas
posed by the choice between rules and rulelessness; the crudeness of rules
is alleviated by virtue of the power of private adaptation to particular
circumstances. Allowing the remedy of "exit" rather than "voice," " privately
adaptable rules are typically invoked in support of economic markets. I
argue here that they also deserve an honored place in a legal system
committed to correcting the operation of economic markets.</p>
        <p>The second approach involves legitimate rule revisions. It recognizes
that officials and citizens sometimes have the power to moderate rules, or
applications of rules, that no longer make sense. Juries, police, and
prosecutors all have some power to revise rules. Ordinary people sometimes
exercise this power as well.</p>
        <p>The third approach is pragmatic and more self-consciously casuistical;
its major goal is to make space for the democratic goals of participation and
responsiveness that I have just described. This last approach involves a
highly contextualized inquiry into the levels and kinds of error and injustice
via rules or via rulelessness, with special attention to the nature of the
forum that will be making the crucial decisions. Rules cannot be favored or
disfavored in the abstract; everything depends on whether, in context, rules
are superior to the alternatives. It is therefore important to know something
about the character of the institutions that will give rise to rules in the first
instance or apply them after the fact.</p>
        <p>I</p>
        <p>SouRcEs OF LAW</p>
        <p>Law has a toolbox containing many devices. Lawyers have
customarily compared standards ("do not drive unreasonably fast") to rules ("do
not go over 60 miles per hour"), with rules seeming hard and fast, and
standards seeming open-ended. 8 There are indeed differences between
rules and standards. But the rules-versus-standards debate captures only a
part of what is at stake, and it is important to have a fuller sense of the
repertoire of available devices. In this section I outline a number of these
devices; my goal is to clarify some terms that will come up throughout the
discussion.</p>
        <p>First, however, a cautionary note. Whether a legal provision is a rule,
a presumption, a principle, a standard, a guideline, a set of factors-or
something else-cannot be decided in the abstract. Everything depends on
the understandings and practices of the people who interpret the provision.
Interpretive practices can convert an apparently rule-like provision into
17. The terms come from ALBERT 0. HIRSCHMAN, Exrr, VOICE, AND LOYALTY 4 (1970).
18. See infra text accompanying notes 22-26 and 33-35.
something very unrule-like. The American Constitution, for example, says
that "Congress shall make no law ...abridging the freedom of speech."' 9
This provision might operate as a rule if people take it as a flat ban on
certain sorts of regulations. It could operate as a presumption if people see
it as saying that Congress can regulate speech only if it makes a
demonstration of harm of certain kinds and degrees. Or it could be understood as a set
of factors: once we parse notions like "abridging" and "the freedom of
speech," perhaps we will decide cases on the basis of an inquiry into two,
three, or more relevant considerations.2 0 The content and nature of a legal
provision cannot be read off the provision. It is necessary to see what
people take it to be.</p>
        <p>For this reason we should distinguish among three kinds of actors.
The first is the person or institution that issues the relevant legal provision.
The second is the person or institution that is subject to the provision. The
third is the person or institution charged with the power to interpret the
provision. If we take a rule to be a provision that minimizes law-making
power in particular cases, 2' a lawmaker may intend to issue a rule, but the
interpretive practices of the interpreting institution may turn the provision
into something very different. Whether a provision is a rule or not is a
function of interpretive practices. The lawmaker has only limited power
over those practices.</p>
        <p>A.</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-1">
          <title>UntrammeledDiscretion</title>
          <p>By "untrammeled discretion," I mean the capacity to exercise official
power as one chooses, by reference to such considerations as one wants to
consider, weighted as one wants to weight them. A legal system cannot
avoid some degree of discretion, in the form of power to choose according
to one's moral or political convictions.22 As we will see, the interpretation
of seemingly rigid rules usually allows for discretion. But a legal system
can certainly make choices about how much discretion it wants various
people to have.</p>
          <p>A system of untrammeled discretion exists when there are no limits on
what officials may consider in reaching a decision and on how much weight
various considerations deserve; hence there are no limits on the officials'
power to decide what to do. Both inputs and outputs are unconstrained. In
the real world, untrammeled discretion is quite rare. Even people with
considerable discretion usually understand that some factors are irrelevant in
light of their roles. In practice, however, some police officers may come
very close to exercising untrammeled discretion in light of the practical
unavailability of review.</p>
          <p>19. U.S. CONST. amend. 1.
20. See Dennis v. United States, 341 U.S. 494, 508 (1951).
21. See infra text accompanying notes 22-26.
22. See JOSEPH RAz, ETmics IN THE PUBLIC DOMAIN 310, 334 (1994).</p>
          <p>As we will soon see, it is too simple to oppose rules to discretion.
Interpretation of rules necessarily involves discretion, and so-called
discretion is rarely untrammeled in the legal context.</p>
          <p>Often a system of rules is thought to be the polar opposite of a system
of untrammeled discretion. As I have noted, there is no such polar
opposition. Provisions that appear to be rules may not eliminate discretion. There
is a continuum from rules to untrammeled discretion, with factors,
guidelines, and standards falling in between.</p>
          <p>The key characteristic of rules is that they attempt to specify outcomes
before particular cases arise. Rules are largely defined by the ex ante
character of law.23 By the aspiration to a system of rules, I therefore mean to
refer to something very simple: approachesto law that try to make most or
nearly all legaljudgments under the governing legalprovision in advance
of actual cases.2 4 We have rules, or (better) "rule-ness," to the extent that
the content of the law has been set down in advance of applications of the
law. In the extreme case, all of the content of the law is given before cases
arise. This is an ambitious goal-impossibly ambitious. As we will see, no
approach to law is likely to avoid allowing at least some legal judgments to
be made in the context of deciding actual cases. 25 Rules do not, and indeed
cannot, contain all of the instructions necessary for their own interpretation.
Nonetheless, it is possible to ensure that a wide range of judgments about
particular cases will occur before the point of application.</p>
          <p>On this view, we have a rule, or rule-ness, to the extent that decisions
about cases have been made ex ante rather than ex post. If a key function
of law is to assign entitlements, a rule can thus be defined as the full or
23. A qualification is necessary for rules whose content depends on ex post factors not within the
control of the judge-as in "the outcome depends on what the Pope says" or "an amount not higher than
Frank Thomas' batting average." These are rules, but their content is not supplied in advance. This
point shows that an alternative definition of rules could look to the extent to which the relevant criteria
are easy to ascertain for individual cases. See Stephen McG. Bundy &amp; Einer R. Elhauge, Knowledge
About LegalSanctions, 92 MICH. L. REv. 261,271 n.25 (1993). On this view, rules cannot exist where
it is hard to know relevant criteria. One source of uncertainty would be discretion to make decisions ex
post, but uncertainty could also arise if, for example, an adjudication under provisions specified ex ante
would depend on certain facts that are hard to ascertain. Consider, for example, the ban on insider
trading under Rule 10(b)(5) of the Securities and Exchange Act of 1933, which is well-specified ex ante,
but which requires determinations of knowledge, materiality, and so forth that cannot be made easily
and that will depend on educated, but error-prone, guesses. See id., supra, at 270-71. For some
purposes, the "easy to ascertain criteria" conception of rules is preferable to the "ex ante specification"
conception, especially if we are concerned with predictability. While the two conceptions overlap, the
latter is a bit easier to describe and work with, and therefore I use it here.</p>
          <p>24. This understanding is close to that in Louis Kaplow, Rules Versus Standards:An Economic
Analysis, 42 Dutn L.J. 557, 559-60 (1992), and I am much indebted to Kaplow's illuminating
treatment.</p>
          <p>25. For a discussion of the open texture of law, see H.L.A. HART, THE CONCEPT or LAW 124-29
(2d ed. 1994), infra at text accompanying notes 100-101.
nearly full ex ante assignment of legal entitlements, or the complete or
nearly complete ex ante specification of legal outcomes.</p>
          <p>When a rule is in play, the decision of cases does not depend on ex
post assignments, as it likely does under a standard-understood to operate
when, for example, a judge decides whether someone is liable for nuisance
by determining whether his conduct was "unreasonable" (assuming this
term has not been given precise content in advance) or when a judge
decides whether a restriction on abortion imposes an "undue burden" 6
(making the same assumption). In the purest case, the responsibility of the
decision-maker is to find only the facts; the law need not be found. When
rules are operating, an assessment of facts, combined with an ordinary
understanding of grammar, semantics, and diction-and of conventions and
more substantive ideas on which there is no dispute-is usually sufficient
to decide the case.</p>
          <p>Rules may be simple or complex. A law could say, for example, that
no one under eighteen may drive. It could be somewhat more complex,
saying that people under eighteen may not drive unless they pass certain
special tests. Or it could be quite complex, creating aformula for deciding
who may drive. It might look, for example, to age, performance on a
written examination, and performance on a driving test. Each of these three
variables might be given a specified numerical weight.</p>
          <p>Rules can also be specific or abstract. Specific rules apply to a narrow
class of cases; abstract rules apply to a broad class of cases. An abstract
rule might say, for example, that no one may drive over sixty miles per hour
or that all cars must be equipped with catalytic converters. A specific rule
might say that President Nixon's papers are public property; that the First
Amendment allows government to ban advertisements for casino gambling
when gambling has been unlawful in the recent past; or that sixth-grade
students may be suspended without a hearing for a period of less than two
weeks, if there has been a serious allegation of criminal activity. All rules
are defined in terms of classes, but sometimes the rule is narrowly tailored
so as to pick up only a few cases, or perhaps only one.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-2">
          <title>C. Rules with Excuses: Necessity or Emergency Defenses</title>
          <p>It is familiar to find rules that have explicit or implicit exceptions for
cases of necessity or emergency. It is unfamiliar to find rules without any
such exceptions. For example, a person may be banned from taking the life
of another; this is a rule, but self-defense is a valid excuse. Many
constitutions allow abridgements of individual rights in case of emergency. The
American Constitution allows the suspension of the writ of habeas corpus in
time of war.' Other constitutions say that certain rights can be abridged
under unusual circumstances.28</p>
          <p>The consequences of making exceptions depend on the details. An
exception could be narrow but vague, as in the idea that reasonable limits
on free speech can be made only under conditions of war. The conditions
are rare and the exception therefore narrow, but the meaning of the
exception is vague (what are "reasonable limits?"). Or the exception could be
narrow and specific, as in the idea that under conditions of war, members
of the Communist party may not work for the military in any capacity. An
exception might be broad and vague or broad and specific. A specific
exception might well convert the rule with exceptions into a complex rule
or a formula.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-3">
          <title>D. Presumptions</title>
          <p>A legal system may contain presumptions or presumptive rules. The
law may presume, for example, that when the government regulates speech
on the basis of its content, the regulation is unconstitutional. 29 But the
presumption might be rebutted by claims of a certain kind and strength, as
when government can show a clear and present danger. The law might
presume that an employer may not discriminate on the basis of race; but the
presumption might be rebutted by a showing that, for example, a black
actor is necessary to play the part of Othello.</p>
          <p>The legal system is pervaded by rules that operate as presumptions and
that can be countered by showings of a particular kind and degree. The line
between presumptions and rules with emergency exceptions can be thin. A
rule with necessity or emergency exceptions might be described, somewhat
imprecisely, as a strong presumption. With presumptions, it is necessary to
know what counts as a rebuttal, and whether the presumption and the
rebuttal are specific or vague, broad or narrow.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-4">
          <title>E. Factors</title>
          <p>We might contrast both untrammeled discretion and rule-bound
procedures with approaches that allow particular judgments to emerge through
the decision-maker'sassessment and weighing of a number
ofrelevantfactors, whose precise content has not been specified in advance3.0 The key
point is that several factors are pertinent to the decision, but there is no rule,
27. U.S. CoNsr. art. I, § 9, cl. 2 ("The Privilege of the Writ of Habeas Corpus shall not be
suspended unless when in Cases of Rebellion or Invasion the public Safety may require it.").</p>
          <p>28. See, e.g., CAN. CONST. pt. 1, § 1 (rights or freedoms are subject "to such reasonable limits
prescribed by law as can be demonstrably justified in a free and democratic society"); S. AxR. CoNsr.
art. 34, § 4 (constitutional rights may be suspended with a declaration of a state of emergency).</p>
          <p>29. See, e.g., Turner Broadcasting Sys. v. FCC, 114 S. Ct. 2445,2459 (1994) (requiring "exacting
scrutiny" of content-based regulation of speech).</p>
          <p>30. I refer to "factors" rather than "balancing tests," because the latter term is imprecise. See infra
notes 157-190 and accompanying text (discussing judgments based on factors).
simple or complex, to apply. There is no rule because the factors are not
described exhaustively and precisely in advance, and because their weight
has not been fully specified. Hence the decision-maker cannot rely simply
on "finding the facts" and "applying the law." The content of the law is not
given; part of it must be found. There is a degree of ex post allocation of
legal entitlements.</p>
          <p>On this score, the difference between rules and factors is one of degree
rather than kind. As we will see, those who interpret provisions that appear
to be rules may be required to determine at least some of their content. In a
system of factors, moreover, the decision-maker cannot do whatever she
wants. But under a system of factors, the content of the law is created in
large part by those who must apply it to particular cases, and not by people
who laid it down in advance. To a considerable extent, we do not know
what the law is until the particular cases arise.</p>
          <p>
            Consider the Emergency Petroleum Allocation Act of 1973, which
regulated pricing and allocation of petroleum products from 1973 to 1981.
The statute required the agency to "provide for" nine factors, "to the
maximum extent practicable." 3' These factors were (1) protection of public
health, safety, and welfare; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2</xref>
            ) maintenance of all public services; (3)
maintenance of agricultural operations; (4) preservation of an economically
sound and competitive petroleum industry; (5) operation of all refineries at
full capacity; (6) equitable distribution of crude oil and petroleum products;
(7) maintenance of exploration for and production of fuels; (8) economic
efficiency; and (9) minimization of interference with market mechanisms.32
          </p>
          <p>Congress added that each of the nine factors is equally important.
There is much to be said about this quite bizarre list. What is important
here is that an enumeration of factors may be possible.</p>
          <p>In most contexts, however, any given list of relevant factors is not
exhaustive. Life may turn up other relevant factors that are hard or
impossible to identify in advance. In most areas of law governed by factors rather
than rules, it is understood that the identified factors, if described at a level
of specificity, are not complete-or that if they are intended to be complete,
they are stated in a sufficiently general and abstract way, so as to allow
unanticipated, additional considerations to apply.</p>
          <p>F.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-5">
          <title>Standards</title>
          <p>Rules are often compared with standards.3 3 A ban on "excessive"
speeds on the highway is familiarly thought to involve a standard; so too
with a requirement that pilots be "competent," or that behavior in the
classroom be "reasonable." As standards, these might be compared with rules: a
fifty-five miles per hour speed limit, a ban on pilots over the age of seventy,
or a requirement that students sit in particular, assigned seats.</p>
          <p>The contrast between rules and standards is quite useful. It identifies
the fact that with some legal provisions, interpreters have to do a great deal
of work in order to generate the necessary content for a legal provision.
With a standard, it is not possible to know what we have in advance. This
can be a decisive political advantage: Sometimes people can agree on a
standard when they cannot agree on its specification. An incompletely
specified provision may be the best the political (or judicial) system can do,
as with many constitutional provisions and many standards governing
administrative agencies.</p>
          <p>The meaning of a standard depends on what happens with its
applications. Standards share with factors a refusal to specify outcomes in
advance. Standards depart from factors in refusing to enumerate
considerations that are relevant in particular applications.3 4 It would not be accurate,
however, to say that standards offer more discretion than factors. The
amount of discretion depends on the context and on the nature of the
particular factors and standards.</p>
          <p>Here too, moreover, the character of the provision cannot be read off
its text, and everything will depend on interpretive practices. Once we
define the term "excessive," we may well end up with a rule. Perhaps
officials will decide that a speed is excessive when and only when it is over
sixty miles per hour. If a standard is transparent, in the sense that there is a
clear ex ante understanding of its meaning, it is a rule. We may instead end
up with a set of factors or a presumption. Perhaps anyone who goes over
sixty miles per hour will be presumed to have gone excessively fast, unless
special circumstances are shown. Or perhaps the judgment about excessive
speed will be based on need, weather conditions, traffic, time of day, and so
forth. It is a familiar hope that standards will receive a degree of
specification as they are interpreted, since officials may generate categories of cases
that, under the standard, receive predictable treatment. 35</p>
          <p>G.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-6">
          <title>Guidelines</title>
          <p>Avoiding factors, rules, or standards, the law might establish ceilings
and floors, or it might identify positions from which officials or citizens
may deviate if they can demonstrate good cause. Guidelines of this sort
may be mandatory or they may be merely suggestive. Mandatory
guide34. See Kaplow, supra note 24, at 559-60.</p>
          <p>35. See Planned Parenthood v. Casey, 112 S. Ct. 2791, 2821 (1992) (opinion of O'Connor,
Kennedy, and Souter, JJ.).
lines3 6 may be preferred to rules because they allow a degree of flexibility;
they may be preferred to standards insofar as they can discipline behavior in
a way that allows better monitoring of discretion. Thus guidelines may
establish firm boundaries beyond which no one may go, and they may
require reasons to be given publicly for any departure from the norm. On
the other hand, the flexibility of guidelines may be a vice rather than a
virtue.</p>
          <p>H.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-7">
          <title>Principles</title>
          <p>Principles are not an alternative to rules, factors, guidelines, or
standards. Their legal status is obscure, in part because the term "principles"
refers to several different phenomena. In law, principles are often said to be
both deeper and more general than rules.37 We might say that rules are
justified by principles, usually political or moral in character. The
justification of the rule might be used to interpret its meaning; courts may resort to
the principle in trying to understand the rule. For example, there is a
(moral) principle to the effect that it is wrong to take human life without
sufficient cause; the law implements this principle with a range of rules
prohibiting homicide. Similarly, there is a (moral) principle to the effect
that it is wrong not to keep your promises; the law contains a range of rules
for enforcement of contractual obligations. Commonly, the term
"principle" in law refers to the moral or political justifications behind rules.</p>
          <p>There is another and quite different understanding of the notion of
principle in law. Any legal system contains explicitly formulated (legal)
principles as well as rules; these principles do not lie behind rules but
instead are brought to bear on the resolution of cases.3 1 Thus it is said that
no person may profit from his own wrong; that he who seeks equity must
do equity; that ambiguous statutes should be construed so as not to apply
outside the territorial boundaries of the United States. 39 The status of legal
principles is somewhat mysterious; they differ in weight, ranging from
strong presumptions to tie-breakers when cases are otherwise in
equipoise.40 Sometimes they operate as factors. But principles are not rules.
We might say that principles are more flexible than rules, in the sense that
principles tend to bear on cases without disposing of them.4 1 This
distinc36. One example is the Federal Sentencing Guidelines. See generally UNITED STATES
SENTENCING COMMISSION, FEDERAL SENTENCING GUIDELINES MANUAL (West 1994).
37. See FREDERICK SCHAUER, PLAYING BY TmERuLtr 12-16 (1991).</p>
          <p>38. See RONALD DwoPciN, TAKING RIGHTS SERIOUSLY 4-7 (1977) (discussing the difference
between laws and legal principles used by courts, for instance to invalidate laws).</p>
          <p>39. Compare the discussion of the Rehnquist Court's canons of construction in the appendix to
William N. Eskridge, Jr. &amp; Philip P. Frickey, Foreword:Law as Equilibrium, 108 HARV. L. Rv. 26,
97-98 (1994).</p>
          <p>40. See HART, supra note 25, at 259-63 (discussing Dworkin's approach).
41. See Dwoxrn', supra note 38, at 24-27.
tion should not be overstated.42 Any given rule X is unlikely to resolve all
cases that fall under the literal language of rule X 43 and principles can be
crucial to the disposition of cases.</p>
          <p>What is the relationship between a principle and a standard? If we see
a principle as the justification for a rule, the difference seems obvious: a
standard is not a justification for an (already specified) rule, but instead a
legal provision that needs a good deal of specification to be used to resolve
individual cases. If, however, we understand a principle to be a relevant
consideration in the decision of cases, the distinction between principles
and standards is more complex. As I understand it here, a legal principle is
different from a legal standard in the sense that the latter "covers"
individual cases without specifying the content of the analysis in particular
instances, whereas a principle is a background notion that does not by itself
cover an individual case, but is instead brought to bear on it as a relevant
consideration. This is a lamentably vague formulation, but the distinction
should make intuitive sense. Compare a standard banning unreasonable
risks with a principle that statutes should be construed to avoid
constitutional doubts.'</p>
          <p>One final complication. A decision in a case sometimes seems to turn
on a "principle," as in the idea that speech may not be restricted unless there
is a clear and present danger, or that discrimination on the basis of race is
presumed invalid, or that no contract is valid without consideration. In this
usage, a principle is not distinguishable from a standard or a presumption,
and at some points below, I will use the terms interchangeably.</p>
          <p>I.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-8">
          <title>Analogies</title>
          <p>The last category is not a simple alternative to the others, but it is quite
an important tool that helps provide a clue to how law often operates.
Sometimes a legal system proceeds by comparing the case at hand to a case
(or to cases) that have come before.4" The prior case is inspected to see
whether it "controls," or should be extended to, the case at hand. The prior
case will be accompanied by an opinion, which may contain a rule, a
standard, a set of factors, or something else. The court deciding the present
case will inspect relevant similarities and differences. That court, not bound
by the previous opinion, may produce a rule, a standard, a set of factors, or
something else. With analogy, we do not have a decision by rule, because
the rule is not specified in advance of the process of analogical thinking.</p>
          <p>When courts proceed with analogies, then, the nature of the legal
provision-its content and even its character as a rule, a standard, a set of
factors, or a guideline-is not known before the analogical process takes
place. The nature of the provision is specified in the case at hand by
grappling with the precedent; we do not know what we have before the
grappling occurs. It is unusual, however, for analogical thinking to yield rules.
Most of the time, an analogy will produce a standard, one that makes sense
of the outcomes in the case at hand and the case that came before.4 6</p>
          <p>II</p>
          <p>RULES AND THE RULE OF LAW</p>
          <p>A system of rules is often thought to be the signal virtue of a system of
law. Indeed, the rule of law might seem to require a system of rules.47 The
idea has a constitutional source. The due process clause of the American
Constitution is sometimes interpreted so as to require rules, or rule-like
provisions, and to forbid a system based on analogies, standards, or factors.48
This is particularly important in the areas of criminal justice and freedom of
speech, where the "void for vagueness" doctrine requires the state to set
forth clear guidance before it may punish private conduct.49</p>
          <p>
            Vagueness exemplifies a failure of the rule of law. But what
specifically does the concept of the rule of law entail? It is possible to identify
several characteristics. 50 A system committed to the rule of law seems to
require (1) clear, general, publicly accessible rules laid down in advance;
(
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2</xref>
            ) prospectivity and a ban on retroactivity; (3) a measure of conformity
between law in the books and law in the world;5 ' (4) hearing rights and
availability of review by independent adjudicative officials; (5) separation
between law-making and law-implementation; (6) no rapid changes in the
content of law; and (7) no contradictions or inconsistency in the law. These
are the customary characteristics of a system committed to the rule of law.
Of course, no legal system is likely to comply with these seven goals;
failures of the rule of law, understood in such terms, are commonplace.
          </p>
          <p>A particular advantage of a system of rules is that people who disagree
on much else may nonetheless agree about the meaning of a rule. A rule
that forbids people from going over fifty-five miles per hour has the same
meaning to Republicans and Democrats, libertarians and socialists,
anarchists and members of the Ku Klux Klan. When a rule of law is in place,
people can know what the rules are without adverting to basic principles.
Indeed, adverting to basic principles is generally illegitimate, short of civil
disobedience.</p>
          <p>This is an oversimplification, as we will see.52 Disagreements about
basic principles may break out in disputes over the meaning of rules. But
the oversimplification contains fundamental truth. And in this
oversimplification also lies some of the enduring truth of legal positivism, the
lawpolitics distinction, and the view that ours is a government of law, not
human beings.</p>
          <p>III</p>
          <p>THE CASE FOR RULEs</p>
          <p>A great virtue of rules is that they circumscribe permissible grounds
for both action and argument; by doing so, they reduce costs of many
diverse kinds. In a heterogeneous society containing people of limited time
and capacities, this is an enormous advantage. I am suggesting that rules
can help people cope with pluralism (even though the existence of pluralism
can make it difficult to generate rules.)5" Once generated, rules save a great
deal of effort, time, and expense. By truncating the sorts of value disputes
that can arise in law, rules also ensure that disagreements will occur along a
narrowly restricted range.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-9">
          <title>Different Kinds of Rules</title>
          <p>I now discuss some of the characteristic virtues of decisions according
to rules. First, however, it is important to note that rules fall in several
different categories. Here is a nonexhaustive account, tied to my special
concerns.</p>
          <p>1. Often rules are a summary of wise decisions; they are defended on
the grounds that they are a good summary, and that they are desirable as
rules, rather than mere advice or rules of thumb, so as to save the costs of
making individualized decisions. These costs involve time, labor, and risk
of error. Of course, a rule that counts as a summary of wise decisions iay
operate, for good pragmatic reasons, not as a rule of thumb but as a truly
mandatory rule-one that cannot be revisited during particular applications.
If people over the age of sixty are banned from being commercial pilots, it
is because this is probably a pretty accurate summary of good individual
52. See infra notes 98-118 and accompanying text.
53. See infra notes 233-251 and accompanying text.
decisions, and far less costly to administer than any alternative. (Consider
the expenditures that would be required to assess competence in every
case.) If we say that people with SAT scores below 500 will not be
admitted to a certain college, it is for a similar reason.</p>
          <p>2. Often rules establish conventions, or otherwise enable people to
coordinate their behavior so as to overcome collective action problems.
This is true, for example, with respect to rules of the road. The rule that
people must drive on the right-hand side of the road is valuable because it
tells people where to drive, not because it is any better than its opposite.
We do not think that people must drive on the right because it is a wise
decision, in the individual case unaccompanied by rules, to drive on the
right. So too, rules may solve prisoner's dilemmas, in which a series of
individually rational decisions can lead to social irrationality or even
disaster. The rules governing emission of pollutants are an example. If each
polluter felt free to revisit the justification for the rules, the prisoner's
dilemma might not be solved. The best solution is probably to fix a rule
and to require everyone to adhere to it.</p>
          <p>3. Some rules have an expressive function.54 The rules governing
who may marry whom, for example, say something about the institution of
marriage and about social convictions about who is entitled to public
recognition of a relational commitment. Three people cannot be married, nor can
people of the same sex. These rules do not summarize individually wise
decisions, but instead express a social judgment about relations and
valuations. We might say that the expressive function of law includes the effects
of law on social attitudes about relationships, events, and prospects, and
also the "statement" that law makes independently of such effects. 5 Of
course, some such statements and expressions might be challenged.</p>
          <p>4. Some rules amount to precommitment strategies,designed to
overcome the problems of myopia, lack of information, weakness of will, or
time inconsistency. Suppose that in order to succeed in your plans, you
need to engage in consistent behavior over time. Perhaps an exercise
program requires you to work out for one hour, and just one hour, every day; or
perhaps a good diet requires you to eat the same things, more or less, at the
same time for a given period. In these circumstances, a rule that is
enforceable through some mechanism-perhaps social sanctions-may be the best
way to proceed.</p>
          <p>Societies face similar problems. Perhaps good monetary policy for a
certain period requires the Federal Reserve Board to do the same thing each
month; suppose that without a rule, and with particularized consideration of
what to do each month, the Board would do inconsistent things. Adoption
54. See Cass R. Sunstein, Incommensurabilityand Valuationin Law, 92 MIcH. L. REv. 779,
82024 (1994).</p>
          <p>55. See Richard H. Pildes &amp; Cass R. Sunstein, Reinventing the Regulatory State, 62 U. Cm. L.
REv. 1, 66-71 (1995).
of a rule may ensure the requisite consistency. In this way, a rule may be a
precommitment strategy that overcomes predictable problems with ruleless
decisions.5 6</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-10">
          <title>Defending Rules as Rules</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-11">
          <title>Rules might produce incompletely theorized agreements-agreements</title>
          <p>among people who disagree on questions of theory or on fundamental
values.57 Rules might do this in three different ways. First, people can
sometimes agree that a rule is binding, or authoritative, without agreeing on a
high theory of why it is binding, and without agreeing that the rule is good.
Theories of legitimate authority are highly pluralistic, and acceptance of
rules can proceed from diverse foundations5. 8</p>
          <p>Second, people can sometimes converge on a particular rule without
taking a stand on large issues of the right or the good. The rule of stare
decisis-acceptanceof precedents -is a familiar example; we can accept
that rule from diverse theoretical perspectives. So too, people can urge a
sixty miles per hour speed limit, a prohibition on bringing elephants into
restaurants, a ten-year minimum sentence for homicide, and much more
without taking a stand on debates between Kantians and utilitarians, and
indeed without offering much in the way of general theory at all.59 Of
course acceptance of any legal provision requires a reason or a principle;
my point is only that a wide range of starting points can sometimes yield
the same rule and even the same reason or principle, so long as these are
described at a low or intermediate level of generality. When legislatures
and bureaucracies issue rules, they often do so without getting into
highlevel theory.60</p>
          <p>Third, people may agree on the meaning of a rule despite their
disagreement on much else. Rules also sharply diminish the level of
disagreement among people who are subject to them, and among people who must
interpret and apply them. Once a rule is in place, large-scale theories need
not be invoked in order for us to know what the rule means, and whether it
is binding. This generalization is a bit crude; 6' but it is fundamentally right.
In the following section, I am concerned principally with the advantages of
representatives' own political commitments or electoral self-interest.
Similar considerations apply to a decentralized, hierarchical judiciary. In
such a system, there will be some incentive for the Supreme Court to avoid
making rules and to transfer the costs of rulelessness to others. 194 But the
incentive can be overcome by other considerations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-12">
          <title>Notes on England andAmerica</title>
          <p>Some of these speculations are borne out by comparing the legal
system in England with that in the United States.' 9 5 In England, lawmaking
and law-interpretation are far more rule-bound than in the United States.
The Parliament is less likely to delegate discretionary authority to judges.1 96
For their part, English judges treat statutes as rules, interpreting them
literally and sometimes refusing to investigate whether the particular
application of the rule makes sense as a matter of policy or principle.' 9 7 In
contrast, in the United States, lawmaking often takes place in the process of
confrontation with particular cases.' 98</p>
          <p>How might this be explained? Is it possible to say that one or the other
nation is proceeding more sensibly? Perhaps not; perhaps the differences
are attributable to contextual differences.' 99 It is notable that laws in
England are drafted by an Office of Parliamentary Counsel, a highly
professional body that consists of skilled authors of laws.2 00 The Parliamentary
Counsel brings about a uniform style of drafting. It is also closely attuned
to the interpretive methods of English judges, and the Counsel drafts
legislation with close knowledge of literalism and of the prevailing canons of
construction.20 ' The judges' practice is itself uniform and relatively simple.
In a parliamentary system, the government and the legislature are allied,
and the high degree of party control means that there is a level of
homogeneity in England at the lawmaking stage.2 °2 Moreover, and critically,
Parliament revisits statutes with some frequency, and it fixes mistakes that
are shown as such when particular cases arise.20 3</p>
          <p>The situation in the United States is very different. There is no
centralized drafting body, and hence no uniformity in terminology, and little
professionalization. In America, the drafters of legislation are multiple and
uncoordinated.2 °4 The party system imposes less discipline, and the
executive and legislature are hardly aligned.20 5 Congress appears only
intermittently aware of the judges' interpretive practices, which are themselves not
easy to describe in light of the sheer size of the federal judiciary and the
existence of sharp splits, on just this point, in the Supreme Court. Congress
does overrule statutory decisions to which it objects.20 6 But it is not in the
business of responding rapidly and regularly to particular cases in which
literal interpretations misfire. Hence both lawmaking and law-interpreting
practice are very different from what they are in England.</p>
          <p>This brief description of the two systems supports the contextual
arguments offered above. There tends to be more disagreement in America than
in England at the lawmaking stage. In America, the quality of drafting ex
ante is lower, as is the possibility of legislative correction ex post. None of
this suggests that England or America has the optimal level of rules in light
of its own institutional characteristics. None of this suggests that
interpretive practices in the relevant nations are immune from challenge. But it
does suggest that the two legal systems are highly responsive to distinctive
contextual features.</p>
          <p>X</p>
          <p>REFORM STRATEGIES</p>
          <p>How can a legal system minimize the problems posed by unreasonable
generality on the one hand and those of potentially abusive discretion on the
other? The best approaches involve (a) a highly contextualized, indeed
casuistical inquiry into the likelihood of error and abuse with either rules or
rulelessness, and hence an "on balance" judgment about risk; (b) a large
space for legitimate rule revisions; and (c) a presumption in favor of a
particular kind of rule, that is, the privately adaptablerule that allocates initial
entitlements but does not specify outcomes.</p>
          <p>A.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-13">
          <title>Bentham andAcoustic Separation</title>
          <p>Jeremy Bentham favored clear rules, laid down in advance and broadly
communicated.2" 7 In at least some of his writings, he also favored
adjudicative flexibility, allowing judges to adapt rules to the complexities of
individual cases.20 8 Bentham was aware that rules could misfire as they
encountered particular controversies, especially if we understand the notion
204. Id. at 318-20.
205. Id. at 306-15.</p>
          <p>206. See WILLIAM N. EsrmDE, JR., DYNAMIc STATUTORY INTERPRETATION 151-54 (1994). See
generallyWilliam N. Eskridge, Jr., OverrulingSupreme CourtStatutory InterpretationDecisions, 101
YALE L.J. 331 (1991).</p>
          <p>207. See PosTEmA, supra note 4, at 411-13.
208. Id. at 409-10.
of misfiring in utilitarian terms.20 9 In courts of law, Bentham concluded,
the rules should not be fully binding.210</p>
          <p>This suggests a paradox: How could someone advocate clear rules
without asking judges to follow them? Bentham's ingenious answer
involved the different audiencesfor law. The public should hear general
rules; the judges should hear individual cases. 2 11 This is the important idea
of an "acoustic separation" for legal terms,2 12 justified on utilitarian
grounds. There is such a separation in many areas of law, including the law
relating to excuses for criminality, and perhaps in tax law as well.2 13</p>
          <p>Following this idea, we might suggest that legislatures should lay
down rigid rules for the public-"conduct rules"--but that interpreters
should feel free to ignore them in contexts where they produce absurdity.
Officials might follow more flexible "decision rules" that deviate from
conduct rules and indeed that work as standards. In some ways this is the
American legal practice. 2 14 American judges do not create systematic
deviations between conduct rules and decision rules; but they do make
exceptions to literal language in cases of absurdity. Of course it is important to
develop subsidiary principles to discipline the development of decision
rules and the general idea of "absurdity," and to give these ideas concrete
application in the modem regulatory state. Modem administrative agencies,
more than courts, might be entrusted with the job of adapting general rules
to particular circumstances.2 1S</p>
          <p>There are, however, two large difficulties with the Benthamite
strategy. The first involves the right to democratic publicity-more
particularly, the right to know what the law is. The Benthamite strategy severely
compromises that right. The rule of law-and democratic values-would
be jeopardized if people are unaware that the law is not what the statute
books say that it is. Benthamite approaches are therefore unacceptable to
the extent that utilitarian judgments about acoustic separation run into
liberal principles of publicity.2 16 In a similar vein we might think that it is an
insult to the moral autonomy of the citizenry to be told that the law is
something other than what it is in fact. There is a serious problem from the
standpoint of democratic citizenship, since members of the polity, given the
right and duty to decide on the content of law, will by hypothesis lack
knowledge of what the law really is. This ignorance will compromise the
process of democratic assessment of law.</p>
          <p>209. Id.
210. Id. at 418-21.
211. See id. at 195-96.
212. For an illuminating discussion of this concept, see generally Dan-Cohen, supra note 16.
213. See id. at 637-48.
214. See Church of the Holy Trinity v. United States, 143 U.S. 457, 458-59 (1892).
215. I try to support this view in Cass R. Sunstein, Law and AdministrationAfter Chevron, 90
CoLum. L. Rev. 2071 (1990).</p>
          <p>216. See the discussion of publicity in Jom RAwLs, A THEORY OF JUSTICE 16 (1971).</p>
          <p>The second problem with the Benthamite strategy is that it fails to take
account of the fact that general rules can create bad private incentives as
compared with more contextualized approaches. Consider, for example, a
speed limit that creates improper incentives in cases in which speeding is
necessary to save (the optimal level of) life and limb, or an environmental
regulation that requires adoption of expensive technology in cases in which
the environmental risks are trivial.2 17 The secrecy of the Benthamite
approach-the distinction between the law as it is publicly known and the
law as it operates in courts of law-will do nothing at all about the problem
of bad incentives from crude rules. Indeed, publicizing the exceptions, and
telling everyone about the possibility of close judicial attention to the
particulars of your case, may well be a good idea if we seek optimal incentives.
At least this would be so if people would not react to the presence of
exceptions by believing that they can do whatever they want and that the rule
effectively does not exist at all.</p>
          <p>Too often, then, the Benthamite strategy is neither democratic nor
efficient. But there is still a place for what might be thought to be a version of
it. A legal system might sometimes provide that in exceptional cases,
interpreters should be permitted to change rules, by exploring whether their
justifications create absurdity or injustice in particular cases.2 18 We might
even see a judicial (or administrative) power of this kind as part of the
interpretation of rules, not as an authority to change rules. This power
should be publicly known-a fully disclosed aspect of interpretation. In
some contexts, of course, the possibility of changing rules, or of
interpreting them with close reference to whether they make sense in particular
circumstances, might be too damaging to the project of rule-following. But
this judgment cannot be made in the abstract.</p>
          <p>B.</p>
          <p>Many legal systems allow people to deviate from rules in certain
circumstances. Indeed, many public officials have at least a tacit power to
revise the rules when rule-following would be senseless. Citizens as a
whole often have the same power.219 Legitimate rule revisions make rules
"on the books" operate differently from how they appear. Moreover, rule
revisions can help promote the democratic character of the law, by allowing
constraints on the application of rules to cases where they no longer fit with
public convictions.</p>
          <p>The class of legitimate official revisions is large; it helps supplement
legislation with a set of post-enactment, or extra-enactment, constraints on
217. See Bruce A. Ackerman &amp; Richard B.Stewart, Reforming EnvironmentalLaw, 37 STAN. L.
REv. 1333, 1335 (1985).</p>
          <p>218. See id. See generally SCHAumR, supra note 37.</p>
          <p>219. I borrow extensively in this section from the excellent discussion in MORTiMER R. KADISH &amp;
SANFoRD H. KADIsH, DISCRETION TO Disoaa" (1973).
what government may do. Consider the fact that juries sometimes "nullify"'
outcomes that the law, if interpreted in a rule-bound way, seems to
mandate. 2 ° The practice of jury nullification is widely understood as
legitimate, 22 ' so long as it does not occur very often. There is a democratic
justification for the practice: it allows a salutary public check on rules, or
applications of rules, that produce unjust or irrational outcomes.</p>
          <p>So, too, police have a widely acknowledged authority to revise rules,
by deciding which crimes warrant arrest, and criminal prosecutors have a
widely acknowledged authority to revise rules, by refusing to punish certain
rule violations. In exercising this authority, police and prosecutors may
legitimately depart from rules governing private behavior. Officials refuse
to punish conduct that, while violative of rules on the book, is not widely
perceived as deserving criminal punishment. Prosecutions are rarely
brought for sodomy or adultery, in part because such behavior, even if
condemned, is no longer so deplored as to call for jail sentences or criminal
fines. We might also understand judicial "softening" or "moderation" of
rules-sometimes under the guise of interpretation uuu -as an exercise of a
tacitly legitimated authority to reject rules when they make no sense.</p>
          <p>Of course, people might question these various exercises of discretion
to depart from rules. If, for example, the police refuse to stop domestic
violence-because they think that spousal abuse is acceptable or that
government should not intervene in the family-we might respond that the
refusal is unacceptable, because it produces injustice. The judgments that
underlie rule revisions might properly be criticized as confused or unjust. I
am suggesting only that when there is no such problem, the revisions, if
democratically grounded, are a good response to the problems posed by
rule-bound law.</p>
          <p>Certainly the existence of enforcement discretion raises doubts about
certain understandings of the rule of law.3 If what I am saying is right,
there will often be a gap between law on the books and law in the world,
and for good democratic reasons. We might conclude that officials in
certain social roles-jurors, prosecutors, police-should believe that rules are
generally binding, but that they have authority to depart from the rules in
compelling circumstances. This authority has democratic foundations; it
might promote liberty as well.</p>
          <p>Now let us turn to the situation of the citizen. Ordinarily we think that
people must obey the law or face the consequences of violating it. If they
are conscientious objectors-consider as examples Martin Luther King, Jr.,
or abortion protestors-their violation of the law may be a product of
220. Id. at 45-66.</p>
          <p>221. See id.; Alan Scheflin &amp; Jon Van Dyke, Jury Nullification: The Contoursof a Controversy,
43 LAW &amp; CoNTEMP. PROBS. 51 (1980).</p>
          <p>222. See supra text accompanying notes 101-118.
223. See generally FULLER, supra note 47.
deeply felt moral judgments, or even heroic; but they must nonetheless face
the consequences. This picture has much truth in it, but it is too simple.
Often citizens, like officials, are authorized to depart from the rules.</p>
          <p>Consider, for example, the fact that citizens who object to the
constitutionality of a rule are permitted to violate the rule and seek a judicial
judgment on the constitutional issue. Since there is an overlap between moral
argument and constitutional argument, the power to test rules against
constitutional standards might well be seen as a power to ask that rules be
revised when they are especially unjust.</p>
          <p>Perhaps this power should not be treated as a genuine power to revise
rules, since the Constitution is part of the rules of the American legal
system. But citizens have other powers as well, and these powers should
certainly be understood as a power to change or to soften rules. Consider the
fact that people are allowed to depart from the rules in cases of
"necessity"2'24 and also in a more controversial category of cases, in which the
legal rule no longer claims public support.</p>
          <p>We have seen that if someone violates a speed limit law in order to
escape from a terrorist, a criminal conviction is highly unlikely. In all
probability, the driver will be held to have acted out of necessity, or to have
created a "lesser evil." The same result will be reached if Jones trespasses
on property in order to prevent someone's death, or if Smith steals a
weapon from a third party in order to prevent bodily harm to Young.22 Of
course, citizens are not permitted to decide freely and for themselves
whether compliance with a rule is justified in a particular case. But in most
legal systems, a citizen will have a legally sufficient excuse for violating the
rule if the violation was necessary to avert a greater harm, and the excuse
will exist whether or not any legal decision has previously recognized it as
such.</p>
          <p>The other, more controversial category of legally permissible
violations of law by citizens involves the old notion of desuetudo, which forbids
the invocation of old, unenforced rules to ban conduct in cases in which
people have come to rely on nonenforcement. 226 The idea has a powerful
democratic dimension. If a rule, or a particular application of a rule, is
founded on a social norm that no longer has much support, we might expect
it to be enforced not at all, or only on rare occasions. The rule therefore
will be a tool for harassment and not an ordinary law at all. The rare
occasions of enforcement might well involve arbitrary or discriminatory factors,
resulting, for instance, from a police officer's mood, or personal animus, or
bias of some kind. A prosecution for fornication, brought in 1995, might
well have such features.</p>
          <p>224. KADiSH &amp; KADISH, supra note 219, at 120-27.
225. Id. I am grateful to Michael McConnell for helpful discussion of this point.
226. Id. at 128-30.</p>
          <p>Consider in this regard the controversial case of Griswold v.
Connecticut2,27 involving a ban on the use of contraceptives by a married
couple. The ban was not enforced directly by prosecutors. No such
prosecution could have received public support; it would have been an outrage.
The principal function of the ban was to deter clinics from dispensing
contraceptives to poor people. The problem with the ban was not that it was
unsupported by old traditions but instead that it had no basis in modem
convictions. Few people believed that sex within marriage was acceptable
only if engaged in for purposes of procreation, and those people could not
possibly have commanded a legislative majority, or even made it possible
to bring many actual prosecutions against married couples.</p>
          <p>Instead of relying on an argument about a broad right of "privacy," the
Supreme Court should have invalidated the law on the narrower ground that
citizens need not comply with criminal statutes, or applications of criminal
statutes, that are unenforced and that find no support in anything like
common democratic conviction. A judgment of this kind would have had the
advantage of incomplete theorization: it might have produced broader
support for the decision among a range of people, including those who reject
any "right of privacy" or who are uncertain about its foundations and limits.</p>
          <p>Another controversial case, Bowers v. Hardwick,"2 involving
Georgia's ban on homosexual sodomy, might well be understood as a
repeat of Griswold. The ban on homosexual sodomy is rarely enforced
against consenting adults. Prosecutors simply do not initiate proceedings,
for prevailing social norms would not permit many prosecutions of this
kind. To be sure, citizens did not successfully seek repeal of the statute; but
the statute's nonenforcement made political mobilization most unlikely.
The simple fact of widespread nonenforcement strongly suggests that the
statute was out of keeping with prevailing norms. Realistically speaking,
the ban on consensual homosexual sodomy is instead a weapon with which
police officers and others can harass people on invidious grounds. The
existence of an unenforced law, used for purposes of harassment, is
objectionable for that reason alone. We can draw a general conclusion. Citizens
have engaged in legitimate rule revision (or revision of application of rules)
when they violate rules that lack support in popular convictions-unless
those convictions are themselves demonstrably unjust.</p>
          <p>Griswold and Bowers involved rules that might be thought to be
legitimately disregarded. The same argument would apply to all situations in
which rules or applications of otherwise valid criminal statutes have
entirely fallen out of popular favor. In disregarding palpably outdated rules
227. 381 U.S. 479 (1965).
228. 478 U.S. 186 (1986).
or palpably outdated applications of modem rules, citizens are participating
in a healthy and continuous process of democratic deliberation.22 9</p>
          <p>It is not clear whether American law fully recognizes the citizen's right
to revise rules in this way; the doctrine of desuetudo has no clear place. But
the dilemmas posed by rules and rulelessness might be less severe if
citizens, like officials, were permitted to depart from rules in the cases I have
described. Through this route, we might well respond to Bentham's
problem in a way that avoids the dangers of Bentham's solution.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-14">
          <title>C. PragmaticJudgments</title>
          <p>Often a legal system should make the choice between rules and
rulelessness on the basis of a contextual inquiry into the aggregate level of
likely errors and abuses. 230 In this sense, the choice depends not on any
rule, but on a form of casuistry. I have suggested that when judges or other
interpreters are perceived to be ignorant, corrupt, or biased, or in any case
when they diverge in their judgments from the people who make rules, a
legal system should and probably will proceed with rules.2 31 Even a poor
fit, in the form of overinclusive and underinclusive rules, can be tolerated
when individualized decisions would result in a similar level of inaccuracy.
We might favor ruleness when there is no special reason to distrust those
who make decisions. So too, individualized decisions are likely to be
dispensed with when it is possible to come up with rules that fit well.</p>
          <p>The choice between rules and rulelessness might be seen as presenting
a principal-agent problem. The legislature, as the principal, seeks to control
the decisions of its agents. A problem with rules is that the agents might be
able to track the wishes of the principal better or best if they are free to take
account of individual circumstances. Any rule might inadequately capture
the legislature's considered judgments about particular cases. The costs of
rulelessness might be acceptable if the legislature does not believe that the
court or other interpreter is untrustworthy, perhaps because there is a widely
shared view of the relevant problems.</p>
          <p>On the other hand, without rules the agent might become
uncontrollable. This is so especially in light of the fact that a system of factors usually
allows the agent to weigh each factor as he chooses.232 The result is that a
system of rules might be adopted as the best way, overall, to control the
agent's discretion, at least if there is a measure of distrust of some or all
agents.</p>
          <p>229. See Cass R. Sunstein, PoliticalDeliberationand the Supreme Court, 84 CALIF. L.
REv.(forthcoming 1996) (defending Supreme Court's casuitical approach to affirmative action as a way of
refusing to foreclose options and to allow democratic debate.)</p>
          <p>230. See generallyKaplow, supra note 24, for a discussion of the context-dependent nature of any
inquiry into the benefits of rules and standards.</p>
          <p>231. See supra notes 70-76 and accompanying text.
232. See supra notes 157-190 and accompanying text.</p>
          <p>Rules tend to be sensible-and to be adopted in the first place-when
social consensus exists within the lawmaking body;2 33 risk-free decisions
that make use of factors or standards are more probable when there is
disagreement. It is not hard to obtain a ban on racial discrimination when
people agree that this form of discrimination is illegitimate; it is much harder to
obtain a similar ban on discrimination against the handicapped, so standards
and factors are pervasive.2 34 Consider the fact that Congress often
delegates discretionary power to an agency when it is unable to agree on the
appropriate rule, because of social conflict, and therefore it tells the agency
to act "reasonably." Examples include the areas of broadcasting
regulation2 35 and occupational safety and health. 236 The costs of laying down
rules are increased in the face of disagreement on their content.</p>
          <p>Sometimes, too, it is impossible to come up with an adequate rule in a
multimember body. Often participants in a dispute begin discussion by
attempting agreement on "principles" rather than concrete rules, as in
diplomatic controversies over the Middle East.237 So too people may be able to
agree on a set of relevant factors, or perhaps on some particular set of
outcomes, without being able to agree on a rule, or on the general reasons that
account for particular outcomes.238 Sometimes people will agree on
general principles but disagree on particular cases. Sometimes the opposite is
true. When rules do not emerge from legislatures, it may well be because it
is impossible to get agreement within a heterogeneous body. Return here to
the fact that legislatures that delegate broad discretion can internalize large
benefits of rulelessness: economizing on information costs and on the
political costs of specificity. They can simultaneously externalize the costs of
rulelessness, which will then be faced by administrators. It is
administrators who must compile relevant information and face the political heat of
making hard and specific choices.</p>
          <p>It follows that we are likely to find rules when one group of interests is
well-organized or otherwise powerful, and when its adversaries are not. In
circumstances of this sort, the well-organized interests can press the
governmental body in the direction of rules. A well-organized group is unlikely to
allow itself to become at risk through rulelessness when it need not do so
(unless it believes that it is even more likely to be successful with
discretion-wielding bureaucrats or judges). Consider laws governing the
regulation of agriculture, which are often highly specific, in part because the
farmers' lobby is well-organized, while the opponents of such laws are
not.23 9</p>
          <p>Factors or standards are more likely to be the basis for decision when
opposing interests have roughly equivalent power in the lawmaking body,
and when they are equally willing to take their chances with a bureaucracy
or a judge.24 ° This may be so because they are both highly organized, or
because they are both weak and diffuse. A possible example is the
Occupational Safety and Health Act, which is quite vague,24 in part because its
opponents and adversaries are both powerful.</p>
          <p>On the other hand, two well-organized groups might produce a rule
when compromise is possible and when there are, to both groups, special
risks in relying on an agency or a court. This may be the case, for example,
when the regulated class needs to know what the rule is, so it can plan its
affairs. Perhaps it is better to have fairly bad rules than no rules at all.
When planning is made possible by clear rules, members of the regulated
class may have it within their power to avoid (some of) the costs of
inaccurate rules. Informed of the content of the rule, class members can adjust
their conduct so as to avoid violating the rule in cases in which the rule is
overinclusive. On the other hand, this avoidance may itself be an
undesirable social cost. Return to the problem of site-level unreasonableness,
where application of an overbroad rule forces employers to make workplace
changes that produce possibly little gain, and at possibly high cost. 242</p>
          <p>Rules are also more likely to be unacceptable when the costs of error
in particular cases are very high. The enormous danger of error can make
overinclusive and underinclusive rules intolerable. It is one thing to have a
flat rule that people under the age of sixteen cannot drive: the social and
economic costs of mistaken denials of a license are relatively low. It is
quite another thing to have a flat rule that people falling in a certain class
will be put to death. It is for this reason that rule-bound decisions are
unacceptable in inflicting capital punishment, 243 and to some extent in criminal
sentencing generally. 2 " (But here we must believe not only that rules make
for error, but also that case-by-case decisions will make for less error.)</p>
          <p>This point also helps to explain the dramatic difference between
criminal liability, which is generally rule-bound, and criminal sentencing, which
239. See 7 U.S.C. §§ 601-674 (1980 &amp; Supp. 1995).</p>
          <p>240. See William N. Eskridge, Jr., Politics Without Romance: Implications of Public Choice</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-15">
          <title>Theoryfor StatutoryInterpretation,74 VA. L. REv. 275,288-95 (1988). See generallyTHE POLrTcs OF</title>
          <p>REGULATION (James Q. Wilson ed., 1978); Michael T. Hayes, The Semi-Sovereign PressureGroups, 40
J. PoL. 134 (1978).</p>
          <p>241. See supra note 236 and accompanying text.
242. See supra notes 137-141 and accompanying text.
243. Id.</p>
          <p>244. See generallyUNITED STATES SErENc GCOamssIoN, supra note 36 What is important for
present purposes is that these are guidelines and not rules. See supra notes 36-44 and accompanying
text.
is generally less so. Part of the story is that specificity is needed at the
liability stage, so that people can plan accordingly, and so that the
discretion of the police is sharply cabined. Both interests are weaker at the
sentencing stage. Planning is not so insistently at stake. Errors in degree of
punishment are less objectionable than errors in subjecting an innocent
person to punishment. The discretion of the sentencing judge or jury is also
less prone to abuse than the discretion of the police officer, because the
former, generally speaking, are less likely to decide on the basis of arbitrary
or irrelevant factors.</p>
          <p>I have noted that rules are less acceptable in the face of sharp limits in
information and experience. When information is lacking, or can be
obtained only at high cost, officials will avoid rules. At the same time,
rules-once they are in place-economize on information costs at the point
of application. For example, there was a dramatic shift from adjudication to
rulemaking in American administrative agencies in the 1960s and 1970s,
partly on the theory that rules could resolve many cases at once, and limit
the informational costs, biases, and errors of case-by-case judgments.2 45
But because of the informational demands imposed on those who make
rules in the first instance, rules are now exceptionally difficult to
promulgate, and there has been a shift in the other direction, toward decision
without rules. In the Environmental Protection Agency, for example, it takes
over a year and a half to prepare a rule internally; half a year more to
receive the legally-required public comments; and sixteen more months to
analyze the comments and issue the rules.24 6 It is not at all surprising that
the result is to shift agencies away from rulemaking and toward less costly
options. 47</p>
          <p>Rules are also less acceptable when circumstances are changing
rapidly. When circumstances are changing, rules are likely to be inaccurate.
Consider, for example, a congressional decision to issue a statutory
standard for permissible emissions levels for coal-fired power plants. Surely
any such standard will soon be out of date because of technological change.
In these circumstances it may be best to enact privately adaptable rules, 2 48
to delegate decisions to institutions capable of changing them rapidly, or
perhaps to allow case-by-case judgments based on relevant factors.</p>
          <p>When numerous decisions of the same general class must be made, the
inaccurate fit of a rule becomes far more tolerable.24 9 Consider, for
example, the requirement that all drivers must be over the age of sixteen, or the
245. See STEPHm G. BREYER &amp; RicHARD B. STEwART, ADMINIsTRATv LAW AND REGULATORY
POLICy 555 (3d ed. 1992).</p>
          <p>246. See id. at 107.</p>
          <p>247. See, e.g., Jerry L. Mashaw &amp; David L. Harfst, Inside the National Highway Traffic Safety
Administration:LegalDeterminantsofBureaucraticOrganizationand Performance, 57 U. Cm. L. REv.
443 (1990).</p>
          <p>248. See infra notes 252-257 and accompanying text.
249. See Kaplow, supra note 24, at 563.
use of the social security grid to decide disability claims. Infuriating
bureaucratic insistence on "the technicalities" may result simply because so
many decisions must be made, and because individualized inquiry into
whether the technicalities make sense in each case is too time-consuming.
Similarly, rules can be avoided when few decisions need to be made, or
when each case effectively stands on its own.</p>
          <p>We should conclude that the choice between rules and rulelessness
cannot be made on the basis of rules. That choice is itself a function of
factors. It would be obtuse to say that one or another usually makes sense,
or is justified in most settings. To decide between rules and rulelessness,
we need to know a great deal about the context-the likelihood of bias, the
extent of current information, the location and nature of social
disagreement, the stakes, the risk of over-inclusiveness, the quality of those who
apply the law, the alignment or nonalignment of views between lawmakers
and others, the sheer number of cases. It follows that a well-functioning
legal system should be suspicious of two trends in recent
writing-extravagant enthusiasm for rules2 50 and excessive focus on the possibility of
achieving accurate outcomes through fine-grained encounters with
particulars.25 1</p>
          <p>D.</p>
          <p>An ambitious strategy might emerge from distinguishing between two
sorts of rules, or, more accurately, between rules having and lacking a
certain important characteristic. 2 52 Some rules allocate initial
entitlementsthese unquestionably count as rules-but at the same time maximize
individual flexibility and minimize the informational burden on government, by
allowing private adaptation to determine ultimate outcomes. Consider, as a
defining example, background rules in the law of contract, which can be
adapted by the parties as they choose.25 3 , A background rule states a
presumption: it applies if the parties do not provide otherwise, but the parties
are freely entitled to alter it if they choose.</p>
          <p>Other examples pervade the legal system. The rules of the road are
unalterable in the sense that one cannot make green mean red or vice-versa,
or drive on the wrong side; but the rules of the road allow large room for
private judgment and thus differ from specific commands. By creating
conventions, these rules help facilitate private conduct and permit people to
250. See generally Scalia, supra note 2.</p>
          <p>251. See generally Frank I. Michelman, Foreward:Traces ofSelf-Government, 100 HAuv. L. Rv.
4 (1986); Martha Minow, Foreward JusticeEngendered, 101 HARv. L. REv. 10 (1987).</p>
          <p>252. Related discussion can be found in HAYEK, CoNsn'noN OF LIBERTY, supra note 12, at
14861, distinguishing between "laws" and "commands." This is a highly illuminating but also confused
discussion; I have drawn on some of Hayek's ideas but tried to reduce the level of confusion.</p>
          <p>253. An instructive discussion of these issues appears in Ian Ayres &amp; Robert Gertner, FillingGaps
in Incomplete Contracts:An Economic Theory ofDefault Rules, 99 YALE L.J. 87 (1989).
operate under mutually beneficial arrangements.25 4 Perhaps the most basic
example can be found in common law rules allocating property rights and
thus creating private property, or rules governing entry into agreements. In
the same vein, a promising effort to allow private adaptation in current
health and safety policy involves taxes imposed on polluting sources2. 5
The rules embodied in such taxes are privately adaptable in the sense that
people subject to the tax can alter their conduct so as to eliminate the tax or
to reduce it; it is for them to decide just how to respond. In the same vein it
has been suggested that if stabilizing population is the goal, rigid limits on
family size may be inferior, as a policy tool, to more flexible,
incentivebased strategies, such as greater education and employment for women.2 56
All of these various provisions might be described as privately adaptable
rules.</p>
          <p>By contrast, some laws do not merely allocate entitlements, but also
minimize private flexibility by mandating particular end-states or outcomes.
Consider price controls, or specified technology for new cars, or flat bans
on carcinogens in the workplace. Even if these rules have some flexibility
at the margin, they allow little scope for private adaptation. Rules that
specify end-states are common in modem regulation, in the form of
"command and control" regulation that says exactly what people must do and
how they must do it.257</p>
          <p>The line between privately adaptable rules and commands is one of
degree rather than one of kind. What I am describing is a characteristic
present to a greater or lesser degree in some rules, not a crisply defined
category of rules. Even command-and-control regulation allows a degree of
private adaptation, in the sense that people are permitted to go out of
business or to change their line of work so as to escape regulation entirely.
Notably, all rules, including the most adaptable rules, allocate entitlements.
The allocation may well have an effect on people's preferences, since
people tend to prefer things that have been initially allocated to them;258 it
might also affect distributions and hence end-states as well.2 59</p>
          <p>Indeed, it is insufficiently appreciated that government cannot avoid
the task of allocating entitlements and of doing so through rules.
Laissezfaire is a chimera; what is familiarly described as laissez-faire is actually a
particular set of legal rules. Our rights, as we live them, do not come from
254. See HAYEr, CONSTrrTUoN OF LIBERTY, supra note 12, at 157-58.</p>
          <p>255. See A.LEN V. KIEEsE &amp; CARtaLs L. ScHuLTZE, POLLUTION, PRICES, AND PUBLIC POLICY
69111 (1975); ALLEN V. KNEEE, EcoNoMcs AND Tm ENVIRONMENT 260-63 (1977).
256. See Amartya Sen, Population:Delusion andReality, 41 N.Y. Rv. OF BooKs 62, 71 (1994).
257. See, e.g., Ackerman &amp; Stewart, supra note 217, at 1334-40.
258. See RICHARD H. THALER, QuAsi RATIONAL EcoNomics 143-44 (1991).</p>
          <p>259. Hence the Coase theorem will sometimes be wrong insofar as it predicts the initial
allocation of the entitlement will not affect outcomes. See Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous Preferences,
EnvironmentalLaw, 22 J. LEGAL STUD. 217, 223-24 (1993).
nature. They depend on law.2 6 ° The rules of private property and freedom
of contract are rules, and they are legal in character. What I want to
emphasize here is that these rules are distinctive in the sense that they allocate
initial entitlements, allow private adaptation, and do not specify end-states.</p>
          <p>The claim on behalf of privately adaptable rules is not that laissez-faire
is a possibility for law. It is instead that law can choose rules with certain
characteristics-rules that will reduce the risks of rules, by allowing private
adaptation and by harnessing market and private forces in such a way as to
minimize the ex ante informational and political burden imposed on
government. A large part of the ultimate project of minimizing the costs of
rigid rules is to favor rules that specify and allocate initial entitlements, and
to disfavor rules that specify outcomes. In some cases, of course, private
adaptation should not be allowed, because of effects on third parties, costs
of administration and monitoring, lack of information, collective action
problems, or other factors. 61</p>
          <p>A key feature of privately adaptable rules is their association with free
alienability of rights. Ownership rights are of course freely alienable, and
in this way they respond well to the fact that owners and prospective
purchasers know how valuable the relevant rights are to them. The
informational burden on government is therefore minimized. The surrounding rules
do not operate as personal orders. To be sure, privately adaptable rules are
coercive. The law of property is itself coercive insofar as it prevents
nonowners from claiming what they would otherwise claim and doing what
they would otherwise do.262 The virtue of privately adaptable rules is not
that they are not coercive and not that they are "natural"; it is that they
reduce the costs of rule-making and harness private information and
preferences 6 3 in the service of outcomes that are themselves not identified ex
ante.</p>
          <p>People who favor privately adaptable rules and who distrust rules that
specify end-states are often known as critics of the modem regulatory
state. 64 The distinction between the two sorts of rules might easily be
harnessed in the service of an argument for private property, freedom of
contract, simple rules of tort law, and relatively little else. The same insights
might, however, be used on behalf of reform strategies that take the modem
260. See the instructive discussion of how cooperation must precede competition in JULES L.
CoLEMAN, RISKS AND WRONGS 60-62 (1992). This was an important theme in the New Deal era. For
general discussion, see CASS R. SuNsTErN, THE PARTIAL CoNsnrrtrioN 40-67 (1993). Some important
qualifications emerge from ROBERT C. ELLICKSON, ORDER WrrHotn' LAW 156-66 (1991).</p>
          <p>261. A discussion of all this would take me well beyond the present topic. See generally Anthony
T. Kronman, Paternalismand the Law of Contracts,92 YALE L.J. 763 (1983); Cass R. Sunstein, Legal
Interference with PrivatePreferences, 53 U. Cm. L. REv. 1129 (1986).</p>
          <p>262. Cf SEN, INEQUALITY REEXAMINED, supra note 147.
263. Subject to the qualification in supra text accompanying note 258.</p>
          <p>264. See generally HAYEK, CoNsTrrTmoN oF LIBERTY, supra note 12; EPSTEIN, supra note 144.
Although Hayek would allow the state to go well beyond the common law, he is sharply critical of the
tendencies of post-1945 regulators.
state as an important social good. Many current regulatory rules are
dysfunctional not because they promote the goals of the modem regulatory
state, but because they unnecessarily specify end-states.2 6 5 In so doing,
they produce both injustice and inefficiency, in the form of
overinclusiveness and underinclusiveness, replicating all of the problems typically
associated with a refusal to make inquiries at the point of application.</p>
          <p>A prominent example of this kind of rule is command-and-control
regulation, pervasive in the law of environmental protection; this form of
regulation has produced significant problems because of the pathologies of
rules.26 6 It makes no sense to say that all industries must adopt the same
control technology, regardless of the costs and benefits of adoption in the
particular case.267 Command-and-control should generally be replaced by
more flexible, incentive-based strategies, which invoke privately adaptable
rules. Such strategies could save a great deal of resources by reducing legal
rigidity. Liberty would be promoted as well. Instead of saying what
specific technologies companies must use, a privately adaptable law might
impose pollution taxes or fees, and then allow private judgments about the
best means of achieving social goals. The government might also allow
companies to buy and sell pollution licenses, a system that would create
good incentives for pollution reduction without imposing on government
the significant informational burden of specifying means of pollution
reduction. The familiar economic argument for incentives is a key part of the
argument for privately adaptable rules.26 8</p>
          <p>Or consider the area of telecommunications, an area that has for too
long been burdened by unduly rigid rules. For much of its history, the
Federal Communications Commission has been faced with the task of
deciding how to allocate licenses.2 69 In making this decision, it has
alternated between rules and factors. In using factors, the FCC has referred to
local ownership, minority ownership, participation by owners in public
affairs, broadcast experience, the adequacy of technical facilities, the
background and qualifications of staff, the character of owners, and more. 270
The problems with both rules and factors are entirely
predictable-inaccu265. This is a large theme in recent works on regulation. See, e.g., Ackerman &amp; Stewart, supra
note 217; CASS R. SuNSTEIN, AFTERaTm RiGrrs REVOLurION 74-110 (1990); see also infra note 268
(additional sources).</p>
          <p>266. See Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supra note 55, at 95-124. See generally Ackerman &amp; Stewart, supra
note 217.</p>
          <p>267. It is important to consider the degree to which the legal system can compensate for mistakes in
rules by adjusting sanctions and providing subsidies. See Bundy &amp; Elhauge, supra note 23, at 270-78.</p>
          <p>268. See John P. Dwyer, The Use of MarketIncentives in ControllingAir Pollution: Californias
Marketable Permits Program, 20 EcoLoGY L.Q. 103 (1993); DAVID W. PEaRcE AND R. KERRY
TURNER, ECONOMICS op NA-uRALI.REsouRcEs AN THE ENVIRoNmENT 102-09 (1990). Of course, the
success of any such approach would depend heavily on accurate initial pricing of the pollution license.
On this issue, see Pildes &amp; Sunstein, supra note 55, at 122-23.</p>
          <p>
            269. See STEPHEN BREYE, REGULATION AND ITs RErom 71-95 (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">1982</xref>
            ).
270. Id. at 78-79.
racy through excessive rigidity on the one hand, and discretionary, ad hoc,
costly, potentially abusive judgments on the other. 7 1
          </p>
          <p>What alternatives are possible? In a famous early article, Ronald
Coase argued that the government should allocate broadcasting licenses
through a system of privately adaptable rules17 2 -based on property rights
and market transfers, as property law does (for example) for ownership of
newspapers and automobiles. In the recent past the FCC has experimented
with auctions, and the results have been outstanding.27 3 There is an obvious
objection to Coase's proposal. Perhaps broadcasting licenses should not be
regarded as ordinary property; perhaps the criterion of private willingness
to pay is an inadequate basis for awarding licenses. This objection contains
an important point. 274 Broadcasting may promote a range of "nonmarket"
values, captured in the aspiration to promote education, attention to public
affairs, diversity of view, and high-quality programming. 75 But this
objection is not a justification for departing from privately adaptable rules in
favor of command-and-control regulation. Any non-market values might
be promoted by more flexible means. Thus the rules for auctions might be
designed so as to ensure auction credits for those applicants who promise to
promote nonmarket values.2 76 This example shows that privately adaptable
rules might well be used not to oppose regulatory goals, but instead to
harness market forces in the interest of those very goals.2 77</p>
          <p>E.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-16">
          <title>Abolition</title>
          <p>Sometimes both rules and factors are intolerable; sometimes market
forces cannot or should not be harnessed. Having eliminated both rules and
factors, the law might use a lottery instead as a method of allocating costs
and benefits.2 78 (Of course the decision to hold a lottery is supported by a
rule.) This is a possible solution to the problems posed by a military draft,
where rule-bound judgments seem too crude, and where rule-free judgments
are too obviously subject to discrimination and caprice. Lotteries are used
271. See id. at 71-95.</p>
          <p>272. See R.H. Coase, The Federal Communications Commission, 2 J. LAw &amp; EcoN. 1, 25-35
(1959).</p>
          <p>273. See generallyJohn McMillan, Selling Spectrum Rights 8 J. EcoN. PERSP. 145 (1994).
274. I try to support this view in CAss R. SusTE , DEMOCRACY AND THE PROBLEM OF FREE
SPEECH 53-92 (1993). See generally Sunstein, supra note 130.</p>
          <p>275. See ANDERsoN, supra note 15, at 65-90; Richard B. Stewart, Regulation in a LiberalState:
The Role of Non-Commodity Values, 92 YALE L.J. 1537, 1580-81 (1983).</p>
          <p>276. This route has been taken by the FCC. See McMillan, supra note 273, at 157-59.
277. I am dealing here with private adaptability within contexts that appear not to involve the
symbolic, educative, or expressive problems of (for example) a "discrimination tax" or a "license to
discriminate." For a discussion, see generally Robert Cooter, MarketAffirmative Action, 31 SAN DiEGO
L. REv. 133 (1994); see also ANDERSON, supra note 15, at 190-216 (discussing problems with
commodification).</p>
          <p>278. See the discussion of lotteries as allocation tools in JON ESRER, SOLOMONIC JUDOEMENTs
36122 (1989).
in many other areas as well.27 9 Of course lotteries have an arbitrariness of
their own, and for this reason, they may be an inferior approach. 8 0</p>
          <p>Alternatively, the legal system, having found both rules and
rulelessness inadequate, might abolish the relevant institution or practice itself.
(The abolition must of course be accomplished by rule.) Hence the
narrowest and probably the best argument for abolition of the death penalty takes
the following form. Rules are unacceptable because they eliminate the
possibility of adaptation of criminal sentencing to individual circumstances.2 8 1
Privately adaptable rules would make little sense in the context of criminal
punishment, with the possible and controversial exception of plea
bargaining. Rule-bound death sentences are excessively impersonal. But rule-free
systems, including those based on factors, are unacceptable too, because
they allow excessive discretion and create a risk that irrelevant or
illegitimate considerations will enter the decision to impose capital punishment.
When judgments are to be made about who is to live and who is to die, a
high degree of accuracy is necessary, and errors based on confusion,
variable judgments, bias, or venality are intolerable. The problem is that human
institutions cannot devise a system for making capital decisions in a way
that sufficiently diminishes the risk of error. Rule-bound systems create too
many errors; so too with systems based on factors.</p>
          <p>The strongest argument against the death penalty is not that the penalty
of death is too brutal, but that it cannot be administered in a sufficiently
accurate way. Suppose it could be shown that through individualized
consideration in the form of factors, the rate of error is high, at least in the
sense that irrelevant or invidious factors play a large role in the ultimate
decision of life or death. Suppose that rules are the only way to eliminate
the role of such factors, but that rules are objectionable in their own way,
because they do not allow consideration of possible mitigating factors.
Perhaps evidence to this effect would not be sufficient to convince skeptics
that the death penalty is unacceptable. But if it is possible to persuade a
sufficiently broad range of people of this conclusion, the sources of the
argument lie in evidence of this sort.</p>
          <p>CONCLUSION</p>
          <p>A system committed to the rule of law is committed to limiting official
discretion, but it is not committed to the unrealistic goal of making every
decision according to judgments fully specified in advance. Nonetheless,
rules are an admirable device for obtaining agreement on the content of law,
and also for reducing discretion at the point of application. Often people
279. Id.</p>
          <p>280. Of course, any real-world draft is likely to include some rules and standards as well. Multiple
possible combinations might be imagined.</p>
          <p>281. See Woodson v. North Carolina, 428 U.S. 280, 303-04 (1976) (opinion of Stewart, Powell,
and Stevens, JJ.).
can agree on rules when they disagree about abstract and theoretical issues;
they can agree that rules are binding, that rules are good, and that rules have
a certain identifiable meaning. Frequently a lawmaker adopts rules because
rules narrow or even eliminate the range of disagreement and uncertainty
faced by people attempting to follow or to interpret the law. This step has
enormous virtues in terms of promoting predictability and planning and
reducing both costs and risks of official abuse.</p>
          <p>Rules are sometimes thought to be associated with merely formal
equality; but the association is misconceived. Hayekian understandings of
the rule of law-identifying rules with free markets-introduce into that
notion further ideas that should be distinguished and that require an
independent defense.</p>
          <p>Rule-skeptics say that rules are not what they appear to be. In their
view, full ex ante specification of outcomes is a chimera. The need for
interpretation during encounters with concrete cases means that ex post
assessments of some sort are an inescapable part of law. Casuistry is a
large part of rule-interpretation. There is some important truth in this claim.
Almost any judgment about meaning will partake of ex post substantive
ideas of a sort. It is almost inevitable that some case will arise that will
confound the attempt to use rules to specify all outcomes in advance. What
I have called "the problem of the single exception" is common in
ruleinterpretation.</p>
          <p>These claims are chastening. But they should not be read for more
than they are worth. Certainly they do not defeat the project of those who
are enthusiastic about rules. Usually the question of meaning is easy.
Often ex ante specification is possible for most cases, where shared
understandings permit rule-following.</p>
          <p>Rules have many goals, but as they operate in law, they are often
simple summaries of good decisions in individual cases. In carrying out this
task, they reduce costs, ease choice, limit the errors encountered in
particular decisions, produce coordination, and make it unnecessary to debate
issues of value and fact every time someone does something having social
consequences. Because of their ex ante character, rules will usually be
overinclusive and underinclusive with reference to the arguments that
justify them. They will often be outrun by changing circumstances. Usually
the crudeness of rules is tolerable, and most of the resulting inefficiency and
injustice can be controlled through means short of abandoning rules. But
sometimes the crudeness of rules counts decisively against them.</p>
          <p>Many of the most difficult issues in law involve the choice between
rules and rulelessness in cases in which both seem unacceptable-rules,
because of their crudeness and their insensitivity to particulars that
confound them; rulelessness, because of the likelihood of arbitrariness and
discrimination in application. The Benthamite strategy calls for ex ante rules
for the public and ex post case-by-case particularism for judges. I have
questioned this strategy on both economic and democratic grounds, but
sometimes flexible, contextual interpretation of rules, adapting the general
to the particular, can bring about something like the best of both worlds.</p>
          <p>More generally, privately adaptable rules are a promising effort to
minimize the problems of excessive generality, by opting for rules that allow
private adjustment, harness private ordering, and reduce the informational
costs imposed on government. Some people who favor such rules intend
their arguments to be a challenge to regulation and a basis for approval of
unrestricted (though rule-governed) "free" markets."' 2 But privately
adaptable rules may enjoy an important rebirth in the context of government
regulation-in the creation of rules that are designed to accomplish
regulatory goals, but that do so by specifying initial entitlements rather than final
outcomes, and that harness market forces in the interest of socially chosen
ends.</p>
          <p>I have also suggested that legitimate rule revisions are pervasive, and
that the choice between rules and rulelessness might well be based on a
highly pragmatic, contextualized inquiry into the costs of the two
approaches in the area at hand. Thus understood, the choice would itself be
based on the practice of casuistry, in which judgments for or against rules
emerge not from rules, but from careful assessments of particular
circumstances. I have urged that casuistry may well be given democratic
foundations insofar as it places a premium on rights to participate and to receive a
response.2 83 Casuistry is hardly all there is to a well-functioning legal
system, and it has important limitations. But if what I have argued here is
correct, a form of casuistry plays an important role in the interpretation of
rules themselves, and it occupies a distinguished and prominent place even
in a legal system committed to rule-bound justice and the rule of law.
282. See HAYEK, ROAD TO SERFDOM, supra note 12, at 69-76; see also EPsmw, supra note 144.
283. If casuistry is truly to promote democratic values, as indicated in EDWARD H. Laxi, AN
INTRODUCTION TO LEGAL REASONING 2-6 (1948), a society must ensure that norms of participation and
responsiveness are actually and not just theoretically reflected in relevant institutions.
APPENDIX: SOME DisPuTEs BETWEEN RULES AND RULELESSNESS</p>
          <p>RULE
Roe v. Wade trimester system 28 4
Miranda rules 286
exclusionary rule for illegally
obtained evidence 288
corporate transactions involving
interested director voidable on
demand 290
"place of contracting" rule under
Laws</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-2-17">
          <title>FirstRestatement of Conflict of</title>
          <p>292
Social security grid2 9 4
Presumption that pre-termination
evidentiary hearing is required29 8
Mandatory death penalty for
certain offenses 300 (invalidated)</p>
          <p>RULELESSNESS
Casey "undue burden" standard28 5
"voluntariness" standard2 87
inevitable discovery exception to
the warrant requirement 2 9
corporate transactions involving
interested director voidable when
,,unfair,, 29t
assessment of relevant factors
under Second Restatement of
Conflict of Laws2 93
grid
Judgments before social security</p>
          <p>295
Retirement when incompetence can</p>
          <p>297
be demonstrated
Balancing test in determining the
need for a hearing 99
Untrammeled jury discretion over
imposition of death penalty 30 '
284. Roe v. Wade, 410 U.S. 113, 163-64 (1973).</p>
          <p>285. Planned Parenthood v. Casey, 112 S. Ct. 2791, 2820 (1992) (opinion of O'Connor, Kennedy,
and Souter, JJ.).</p>
          <p>286. Miranda v. Arizona, 384 U.S. 436, 467-77 (1966).
287. See Brown v. Mississippi, 297 U.S. 278, 285 (1936).
288. See Silverthorne Lumber Co. v. United States, 251 U.S. 385, 392 (1920).
289. See Nix v. Williams, 467 U.S. 431, 446 (1984).
290. See Wardell v. Railroad Co., 103 U.S. 651, 658 (1880).
291. See State ex. rel. Hayes Oyster Co. v. Keypoint Oyster Co., 391 P.2d 979, 984 (Wash. 1964).
292. REsrATEMENT (Fn ST) OF CONFLICr OF LAWS § 332 (1934).
293. RESTATEMENT (SEcoND) OF Co ..icr OF LAWS §§ 6, 145, 188 (1969).
294. See 20 C.F.R. pt. 404, subpt. P, app. 2, tbl. 1 (1994).
295. See MAsKIAw, supra note 136, at 114-16.</p>
          <p>296. As upheld, for example, in Massachusetts Bd. of Retirement v. Murgia, 427 U.S. 307, 316-17
(1976).</p>
          <p>297. See Age Discrimination in Employment Act (ADEA), 29 U.S.C. § 623(0(1) (1985).
298. See Goldberg v. Kelly, 397 U.S. 254, 264 (1970).
299. See Mathews v. Eldridge, 424 U.S. 319, 341-49 (1976).</p>
          <p>300. This practice was invalidated in Woodson v. North Carolina, 428 U.S. 280, 303-05 (1976)
(opinion of Stewart, Powell, and Stevens, JJ.).</p>
          <p>301. Upheld in McGautha v. California, 402 U.S. 183, 207-08 (1971), overruled by Pitts v.
Wainwright, 408 U.S. 941 (1972).
Regulation of speech justified by
danger of "imminent and lawless</p>
          <p>302
action"
No barrier under Tenth
Amendment to congressional
authority under Commerce</p>
          <p>3 4
Clause 0
"Per se" rule in antitrust 30 6
No contracts without
consideration 3 8
Absolute protection of endangered
species3 1°
Rule of deference to agency
interpretations of ambiguous</p>
          <p>3 2
statutes t
Caveat emptor3t 4
Contract at will-employer and
employee may fire or quit as they
choose, unless contract provides</p>
          <p>31 6
otherwise</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>Balancing risk against benefit" 3</title>
        <p>Tenth Amendment barrier to
congressional authority under
Commerce Clause when
"traditional governmental
functions" are involved 0 5
"Rule of reason" in antitrust30 7
Promissory estoppel when reliance
30 9
is reasonable
Consideration of loss of species as
a relevant factor3 "
Deference to agency interpretations
when reasonable to defer3 13</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>Seller liable for "latent defects" 3 5</title>
        <p>Employer may not discharge in
violation of public policy317
302. See Brandenburg v. Ohio, 395 U.S. 444, 447-49 (1969) (per curiam). Brandenburg placed
strict limits on the "clear and present danger" principle of speech regulation first set out in Schenck v.
United States, 249 U.S. 47, 52 (1919).</p>
        <p>303. See Dennis v. United States, 341 U.S. 494, 508-09 (1951).
304. See Garcia v. San Antonio Metro. Transit Auth., 469 U.S. 528, 552 (1985).
305. See National League of Cities v. Usery, 426 U.S. 833, 852 (1976), overruledby Garcia v. San
Antonio Metro. Transit Auth., 469 U.S. 528 (1985).</p>
        <p>306. See NCAA v. Board of Regents, 468 U.S. 85, 103-04 (1984).
307. See Standard Oil Co. v. United States, 221 U.S. 1, 60 (1911).
308. See Dougherty v. Salt, 125 N.E. 94, 95 (N.Y. 1919).
309. See Goodman v. Dicker, 169 F.2d 684, 685 (D.C. Cir. 1948).</p>
        <p>310. See Tennessee Valley Auth. v. Hill, 437 U.S. 153, 173 (1978) (interpreting the Endangered
Species Act).</p>
        <p>311. See § 1(b), 80 Stat. 926 (1966) (precursor to Endangered Species Act). The Endangered
Species Act is codified at 16 U.S.C. § 1531 (1985 &amp; Supp. 1995).</p>
        <p>312. See Chevron USA, Inc. v. National Resources Defense Council, Inc., 467 U.S. 837, 844
(1984).</p>
        <p>313. See, e.g., Baltimore Gas &amp; Elec. Co. v. National Resources Defense Council, Inc., 462 U.S.
87, 97-108 (1983) (upholding a rule adopted by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission which was
premised on a conclusion that permanent storage of nuclear waste would have no significant
environmental impact).</p>
        <p>314. See Barnard v. Kellogg, 77 U.S. (10 Wall.) 383, 388 (1871).
315. See Vandermark v. Ford Motor Co., 391 P.2d 168, 171-72 (Cal. 1964).
316. See Payne v. Western &amp; Atlantic R.R., 81 Tenn. 507, 519-20 (1884).
317. See Brockmeyer v. Dun &amp; Bradstreet, 335 N.W.2d 834, 840 (Wis. 1983).
Negligence if conduct is</p>
        <p>323
unreasonable
318. See Tennessee Valley Auth. v. Hill, 437 U.S. 153, 173 (1978).
319. See Citizens to Preserve Overton Park, Inc. v. Volpe, 401 U.S. 402, 410-16 (1971).
320. See Myers v. United States, 272 U.S. 52, 117 (1926).
321. See Morrison v. Olson, 487 U.S. 654, 693-97 (1988).
322. See Osborne v. McMasters, 41 N.W. 543, 544 (Minn. 1889).
323. See ]RESTATEMENT (SECOND) OF TORTS §§ 291, 292 (1965).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Introduction ..................................................... I. Sources of Law ........................................... A. Untrammeled Discretion ............................... B . Rules ................................................. C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Rules with Excuses: Necessity or Emergency Defenses</article-title>
          ..
          <string-name>
            <surname>D. Presumptions .......................................... E. Factors ............................................... F. Standards ............................................. G. Guidelines ............................................. H . Principles ............................................. I. Analogies ............................................. I.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Rules and the Rule of</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Law ................................ III.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>The Case for</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Rules ........................................ A.</given-names>
            <surname>Different</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kinds of Rules ............................... B. Defending Rules as Rules .............................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>1. Rules Minimize the Informational</article-title>
          and Political Costs
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          of Reaching Decisions in
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Particular Cases ........... 2. Rules</given-names>
            <surname>Are</surname>
          </string-name>
          Impersonal and Blind; They Promote
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>and Arbitrariness ................................... 3. Rules</given-names>
            <surname>Serve</surname>
          </string-name>
          Appropriately Both to Embolden and to
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Constrain Decision-Makers in Particular Cases</article-title>
          ...... 4.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Rules</given-names>
            <surname>Promote</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Predictability and Planning for Private</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Actors and for the</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Government ..................... 5. Rules</given-names>
            <surname>Increase</surname>
          </string-name>
          Visibility and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Accountability .........</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>6. Rules Avoid the Humiliation of Subjecting People to</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Case .............................................. 7. Rules</given-names>
            <surname>Promote</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Equal Application of the Law</article-title>
          ........
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>VIII. Rulelessness .............................................. A . Examples ............................................. B. Factors Without Rules ................................. 1.</given-names>
            <surname>Multiple</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Diverse Relevant Criteria ..............</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>2. Difficulty of Describing Relevant Factors Ex Ante</article-title>
          ... 3.
          <article-title>Absence of a Clear, A PrioriSense of the Weight of</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>the Criteria ........................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>4. Attentiveness to (Much of) the Whole Situation</article-title>
          ..... 5. Attentiveness to Particulars; Avoidance of
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Abstractions .......................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          6. Attention to Precedent;
          <article-title>Analogical Reasoning</article-title>
          ....... 7.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Diversely</given-names>
            <surname>Valued</surname>
          </string-name>
          Goods and Problems of
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Conclusion ...................................................... 26. See</given-names>
            <surname>Planned</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Parenthood v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Casey</source>
          , 112
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>2791</volume>
          ,
          <issue>2821</issue>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>(opinion of O'Connor,</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kennedy</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and Souter,
          <source>JJ.)</source>
          .
          <volume>31</volume>
          . Act of Nov:
          <volume>27</volume>
          ,
          <year>1973</year>
          , §
          <article-title>4(b)(I), Pub</article-title>
          . L. No.
          <volume>93</volume>
          -
          <issue>159</issue>
          , 87 Stat.
          <volume>627</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          (
          <year>1973</year>
          ).
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>33</volume>
          . See generally Kaplow, supra note 24;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Duncan</surname>
            <given-names>Kennedy</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Form and Substance in PrivateLaw
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Adjudication</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 89 HAxv. L. REv.
          <volume>1685</volume>
          (
          <year>1976</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>; Kathleen M. Sullivan</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Foreword: The Justices of Rules
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          andStandards, 106 HARv. L. REv.
          <volume>22</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Colin S</article-title>
          .Diver, The OptimalPrecisionofAdministrative
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rules</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 93 YALE L.J.
          <volume>65</volume>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          ).
          <fpage>42</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>HART</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>supra note 25, at 262-63. 43. See infra notes 104-112 and accompanying text. 44</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <article-title>Kent v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Dulles</source>
          , 357 U.S.
          <volume>116</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          (
          <year>1958</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Public Citizen v</article-title>
          . United States Dep't
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>of Justice</source>
          , 491 U.S.
          <volume>440</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>465</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>66</lpage>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          )
          <article-title>(holding that the Court should construe statutes to avoid</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>constitutional questions)</source>
          .
          <volume>45</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generally Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>On Analogical Reasoning</source>
          ,
          <volume>106</volume>
          HARv. L. REv.
          <volume>741</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>(discussing the role of analogical reasoning in law</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>46</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g., Goss. v. Lopez, 419 U.S.
          <volume>565</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>577</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          (
          <year>1975</year>
          )
          <article-title>(applying the Due Process Clause to</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>the temporary suspension of students from public school</article-title>
          ).
          <volume>47</volume>
          . See Scalia,
          <source>supra note 2</source>
          , at 1179; HAYEK, ROAD TO SERFDOM, supra note 12, at 72-87; LON L.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>FULLER</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>THE MORALIT= OF LAW 106</source>
          (
          <year>1969</year>
          )
          <article-title>; JOSEPH RAZ, THE Au'</article-title>
          moRrr
          <source>OF LAW 210</source>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          ). Justice
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>note 2</source>
          , at 1178-
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          .
          <fpage>48</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <article-title>Papachristou v</article-title>
          . Jacksonville, 405 U.S.
          <volume>156</volume>
          ,
          <issue>162</issue>
          (
          <year>1972</year>
          )
          <article-title>(the rule of law requires both</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>or erratic enforcement)</source>
          .
          <volume>49</volume>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .; Gooding v. Wilson, 405 U.S.
          <volume>518</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>520</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          (
          <year>1972</year>
          );
          <article-title>Baggett v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Bullitt</source>
          , 377 U.S.
          <volume>360</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>70</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1964</year>
          );
          <article-title>Smith v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Goguen</source>
          , 415 U.S.
          <volume>566</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>572</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>73</lpage>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          ).
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See generally</surname>
            <given-names>FULLER</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>supra note 47; RAZ, supra note 47</source>
          . 51. For qualifications to this principle,
          <source>see infra notes 219-229 and accompanying text. 56</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>JON ELSTER</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>ULYSSES AND am SIRENs 86-111</source>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          )
          <article-title>; see also Stephen Holmes,</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>Precommitment and the Paradoxof Democracy, in CONSTrTuriONALISM</article-title>
          AND DEMOCRACY 195 (Jon
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Elster</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Rune Slagstad eds.,
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Political Conflict and Legal Agreement</source>
          , 17 The Tanner Lectures on
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Agreements</surname>
            , 108
            <given-names>H~</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Av. L. REv</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>1733</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>JOSEPH RAz</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>THE MoRALrry OF FREEDOM 58</source>
          (
          <year>1986</year>
          )
          <article-title>("More importantly, the practice</article-title>
          [of
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>ultimate foundations, which some seek in religion, others in Marxism or in Liberalism</article-title>
          ,
          <source>etc.")</source>
          .
          <source>59. See id. 60</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>Sunstein</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Incompletely Theorized Agreements. supra note 57. 61. See infra notes 98-118 and accompanying text. 233</source>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Peter H. Aranson</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>A TheoryofLegislativeDelegation</source>
          , 68 CORNELL L.
          <year>Rnv</year>
          .
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>27</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
          <fpage>234</fpage>
          . See Americans With Disabilities Act of
          <year>1990</year>
          , 42 U.S.C. §
          <volume>12112</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          . See Communications Act of
          <year>1934</year>
          , 47 U.S.C. §
          <volume>303</volume>
          (r) (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          .
          <article-title>See the open-ended standards of the Occupational Safety</article-title>
          and Health Act of
          <year>1970</year>
          , 29 U.S.C
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>§ 652(8), as construed in International Union v</article-title>
          .
          <source>OSHA</source>
          ,
          <volume>938</volume>
          F.2d
          <volume>1310</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1316</fpage>
          -17
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D.C. Cir</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          . See Patrick Laurence,
          <article-title>Negotiation Seen As Only Way Out of South African Impasse,</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>CmsTiAN</given-names>
            <surname>Sci. MoNrroR</surname>
          </string-name>
          , July
          <volume>26</volume>
          ,
          <year>1985</year>
          ;
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            <surname>Parks</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Israel and PLO Pave the Way for a Wider</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Peace</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.A. TIMES</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , July
          <volume>8</volume>
          ,
          <year>1994</year>
          , at Al.
          <volume>238</volume>
          . See generally Sunstein,
          <source>Incompletely Theorized Agreements, supra note 57.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

