<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Cost-Benefit State</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <email>unbound@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Economics</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "The Cost-Benefit State", Coase-Sandor Institute for Law &amp; Economics Working Paper No.</institution>
          <addr-line>39, 1996</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <fpage>7</fpage>
      <lpage>48</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics Part of the Law Commons Recommended Citation</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Gradually and in fits and starts, the American regulatory state
is becoming a cost-benefit state. By this I mean that government
regulation is increasingly assessed by asking whether the benefits
of regulation justify the costs of regulation.</p>
      <p>My goal in this essay is to argue, on both economic and
democratic grounds, on behalf of this transformation. I attempt
to bring those arguments to bear on concrete debates over the
appropriate nature of the emerging cost-benefit state. I will also
urge a point that is not easily contested: regulatory legislation has
diverse legitimate purposes, not limited to economic efficiency
alone. This point does not argue against cost-benefit analysis, but
it has important implications for the uses and limits of that
technique. I will also argue against efforts to drown the
administrative state in paperwork through excessive procedural
requirements.</p>
      <sec id="sec-1-1">
        <title>A. Transformative Developments</title>
        <p>For many years, those attempting to assess the performance of
the regulatory state have been interested in statistical measures.
Gross Domestic Product helps capture economic performance;
can something similar be used for regulatory initiatives? The use
of cost-benefit analysis can be understood partly as an effort to
overcome the interest-based and anecdote-driven nature of
contemporary regulation in favor of an approach that examines,
in a readily understandable way, the real-world consequences of
regulatory initiatives.</p>
        <p>Within the national government, the cost-benefit principle
received its most prominent initial recognition via Executive
Order 12291,1 issued by President Reagan in 1981. At least at the
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Law, University
of Chicago, Law School and Department of Political Science.</p>
        <p>1 3 CFR 128 (1981).
symbolic level, the movement in the direction of cost-benefit
analysis was much accelerated in 1985 with the issuance of
Executive Order 12498,2 requiring that cost-benefit analysis
inform the annual regulatory plan to be issued by all executive
agencies. These initiatives were quite controversial insofar as they
threatened to delay regulatory requirements and perhaps to
transfer authority from individual agencies to OMB. But
Presidents Reagan and Bush, among many others, believed that
they provided a crucial mechanism by which the White House
might coordinate and centralize regulation, —and ensure against
measures that would do more harm than good.</p>
        <p>Many people doubted whether President Clinton would
endorse the idea that regulatory judgments should be made with
close reference to cost-benefit balancing. But despite pressure
from some environmental organizations, President Clinton’s
Executive Order 12866,3 issued in 1993, firmly embraces
costbenefit analysis as a central ingredient in regulatory choice. The
new Order does make some departures from the Reagan-Bush
initiatives; but with respect to cost-benefit analysis, the change
consists principally in references to “equity” and “distributional
impacts” as relevant factors. These are modest changes. Thus the
Executive Branch has endorsed cost-benefit balancing for over
fifteen years, and it seems reasonable to suppose that insofar as
the White House is overseeing the federal regulatory process,
cost-benefit analysis will continue to play a central organizing
role.</p>
        <p>The executive branch has not acted alone. In reviewing
regulatory decisions, courts have also enforced a form of
costbenefit balancing, at least where Congress has authorized them to
do so.4 Judges have invalidated regulatory action that imposes
high costs without significant benefits,5 and they have policed
2 3 CFR 323 (1985).
3 3 CFR 638 (1993).</p>
        <p>4 See, e.g., Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (9th Cir. 1991);
Competitive Enterprise Institute v. NHTSA, 984 F.2d 123 (1992).</p>
        <p>5 American Petroleum Institute, 448 US 148 (1980); Corrosion Proof
Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (9th Cir. 1991); AFL-CIO v. OSHA, 965 F.2d
962 (11th Cir. 1992).
agency action to ensure at least a rough kind of proportionality
between costs and benefits. Sometimes courts have been quite
aggressive in requiring proportionality as part of their function in
reviewing agency action to test whether it is “arbitrary, capricious,
or an abuse of discretion.”6</p>
        <p>These developments have not meant that the regulatory state
is now routinely subject to scrutiny for conformity with
costbenefit criteria (a vague notion, as we shall see). In fact it is not.
Presidents and courts of course have sharply limited authority;
they must act consistently with federal statutes, which often
forbid cost-benefit balancing. Consider, for example, the Clear Air
Act, the Clean Water Act, the Occupational Safety and Health
Act, the Delaney Clause, and the Safe Water Drinking Act, many
of whose provisions ban agencies from balancing costs against
benefits. It is partly for this reason that the American regulatory
state contains many regulations imposing costs not justified by
benefits.7 From existing evidence8 it is possible, moreover, to
conclude that in spite of the recent executive orders, efforts at
cost-benefit balancing within the executive branch have been
sporadic and episodic, and that the highly publicized executive
orders have served a largely symbolic and aspirational function.
Hence much of the contemporary interest in regulatory reform is
directed toward Congress.</p>
        <p>It is important to say that the national legislature has not
uniformly rejected cost-benefit balancing. Some statutes enacted
by Congress appear to contemplate a form of cost-benefit
analysis.9 More recently, the Unfunded Mandates Act contains
two potentially relevant “sleeper” provisions, both receiving almost
no public attention even from specialists, and both growing out of
the Contract With America. First, significant regulatory actions
must be accompanied by a statement that includes “a qualitative
and quantitative assessment of the anticipated costs and benefits
of the Federal mandate.”10 Under the second provision, all
agencies must “identify and consider a reasonable number of
regulatory alternatives and from those alternatives select the least
costly, most cost-effective, or least burdensome alternative that
achieves the objectives of the rule.”11 There is an exception if these
steps are inconsistent with law or if the agency explains why it has
not chosen that least burdensome alternative; but this provision
could have significant consequences.</p>
        <p>In 1995, Congress nearly enacted a new statute that would
amend all regulatory statutes to contain a cost-benefit
“supermandate.” If this statute had been enacted, laws now
calling for various forms of absolutism, or indifference to cost,
would call for cost-benefit balancing.12 The failure to enact a new
reform statute in 1995 has spurred fresh interest in solutions to
modern regulatory problems.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-1-2">
        <title>B. Democracy, Efficiency, and Excessive Procedural Demands</title>
        <p>Cost-benefit requirements are of course most easily justified
on economic grounds, as a way of promoting economic efficiency
and thus eliminating unnecessary and wasteful public and
private expenditures. But cost-benefit requirements also have
strong democratic justifications. Indeed, they can be understood
as a way of diminishing interest-group pressures on regulation
and also as a method for ensuring that the consequences of
regulation are not shrouded in mystery but are instead made
available for public inspection and review. Some of the strongest
arguments for cost-benefit requirements are not so much
economic as democratic in character.</p>
        <p>
          The economic and democratic arguments for the emerging
cost-benefit state should be qualified by reference to three points,
and I urge that these points should be kept in mind during the
process of regulatory reform. First, cost-benefit analysis ought not
to be taken to impose undue procedural requirements on agencies.
Government inaction has costs of its own; it may allow severe
10 2 USC 202(a)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">2</xref>
          ).
11 2 USC 202 (a)(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19 ref37">3</xref>
          )-(
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">4</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>12 See Cass R. Sunstein, Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the
Cost-Benefit State, 48 Stan L Rev 247 (1995).
problems to continue; and some forms of cost-benefit analysis
actually fail cost-benefit analysis. They impose extensive
informational demands on agencies. They create excessive delay.
They obstruct desirable regulation. Thus efforts at regulatory
reform should avoid the pervasive risk of excessive proceduralism.</p>
        <p>The second point stems from the fact that some of the most
promising strategies for regulatory reform require a shift from
command-and-control regulation to economic incentives. In
these circumstances, cost-benefit analysis should not be taken as
a modest, procedural step designed to engraft new
informationgathering requirements on top of existing regulatory tools. On the
contrary, it should be part and parcel of a more ambitious and
thorough-going effort to move toward new and better tools, often
replacing federal command and control with disclosure remedies
and with economic incentives. The shift from
command-andcontrol to more flexible methods of obtaining regulatory goals
should, in short, be a central part of the cost-benefit state.</p>
        <p>Third, any transformation of the modern regulatory state
should recognize that by itself, the bare idea of cost-benefit
analysis lacks a theory of how, and how much, to value social
goods. Balancing all relevant variables is of course sensible; but
which variables are relevant, and how should they be valued?
Economists have some instructive answers, and I will discuss
some of those answers below. But in its most rigidly economistic
forms, cost-benefit analysis raises serious problems, since it values
all regulatory consequences under the rubric of private
“willingness to pay.” The willingness to pay criterion has many
uses, and sometimes it should indeed be the foundation for
decision. But that criterion does not capture all of the values that
underlay modern regulation, and sometimes it should be used
only to provide information, and not as the foundation for
decision. I attempt to explain below how this point bears on
regulatory reform.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>I. The New Deal and Its Aftermath: A Very Brief Tour</title>
      <p>Emerging national enthusiasm for cost-benefit balancing
should be understood against the backdrop set by Franklin
Delano Roosevelt’s New Deal, which was of course a substantial
reformation of the original constitutional structure.13 The New
Deal qualifies as a substantial reformation above all because it
refashioned the three basic cornerstones of that structure:
federalism; checks and balances; and individual rights.</p>
      <p>To compress a long story: In the 1930s the powers of the
national government were expanded in an extraordinary way, to
the point where the nation exercised something close to general
authority to control whatever problems it sought to address. The
framers’ original understanding of a sharply constrained central
government was therefore repudiated by the nation. There were
simple grounds for this repudiation. State autonomy seemed an
obstacle to democratic self-government, not a crucial part of it—
especially in the midst of the Depression, when states were
generally perceived as ineffectual entities buffeted about by private
factions. (Of course we have come to see that the national
government may suffer from the same problem.) As a result of the
New Deal, state autonomy was very different in 1940 from what it
had been in 1920.</p>
      <p>During the New Deal, the system of checks and balances also
came under sharp criticism. To many observers, especially during
the Depression, that system seemed dysfunctional for modern
society.14 Good businesses do not operate through checks and
balances; why should good governments paralyze themselves in
this way? Responding to such questions, Congress delegated
enormous, often open-ended policymaking power to the President
and also created a large number of powerful executive and
independent agencies. Crucially, Congress attempted to design
these agencies so as to limit the consequences of the system of
checks and balances by allowing a high degree of administrative
autonomy. Thus the new agencies had a large degree of
discretionary authority under open-ended statutory standards.
They also combined traditionally separated powers of
13 See B. Ackerman, We the People vol. 1 (1993) (discussing New Deal as
creation of third American constitutional regime). I borrow in this and the
following section from Sunstein, Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the
Cost-Benefit State, supra note.</p>
      <p>14 See James Landis, The Administrative Process (1935), for the classic
statement.
adjudication, execution, and legislation. Certainly they were not
limited by requirements of cost-benefit analysis.</p>
      <p>These institutional shifts resulted from a central national
judgment made during the Depression: that individual rights,
properly conceived, included not merely the common law
catalogue of private interests but also governmental protection
against many of the harms and risks of a market economy. The
common law was a regulatory system enjoying no special status. It
should be evaluated pragmatically in terms of its consequences for
the human beings subject to it. Here it often seemed to fail.</p>
      <p>An astonishing feature of the New Deal was its relative
rapidity. Many of the changes came in the brief period from 1932
through 1936. Rapid change was possible partly because it is a
relatively simple step for a legislature to create a range of new
bureaucratic institutions, at least if the legislature does not specify
their duties in advance. The New Deal entities in fact operated
pursuant to little statutory guidance; Congress usually contented
itself with open-ended delegations of authority.</p>
      <p>The New Deal reformation was the foundation for the basic
orientation of the national government until the election of
President Ronald Reagan, and possibly since then. One
development has been of special importance: the “rights revolution” of
the 1 9 6 0 s and 1 9 7 0 s. During that period, many New Deal
tendencies were largely reinforced through the creation of a
remarkable array of new agencies. These agencies were designed
mostly to protect against threats to life, health, and safety from
consumer products, workplaces, and above all the environment in
general.15 Hence this period saw the creation of the
Environmental Protection Agency, the Occupational Safety and
Health Administration, the Consumer Protect Safety
Commission, the Council on Environmental Quality, and more.</p>
      <p>It is notable that during both the New Deal and the rights
revolution, no mechanism was created to evaluate regulatory
performance. There was no system to assess whether agencies
were making things better or worse. In the New Deal, any such
system might have seemed peculiar in light of the widespread
national enthusiasm for the President and for the possibilities of
15 See Cass R. Sunstein, After the Rights Revolution (1990).
benign administration. Of course cost-benefit thinking was quite
foreign to political actors, and hence cost-benefit analysis—which
in any case had not been “invented” in anything like its current
form—played little or no role in the public debate.</p>
      <p>An especially striking feature of the period since 1980 is that
the New Deal reformation has been subject to sustained national
criticism, often as a result of a form of “national performance
review” in which cost-benefit analysis plays a prominent role. It is
worthwhile to pause over the constitution-like character of recent
challenges to the current regulatory arrangements. Often it is
suggested that the national government has far exceeded the
appropriate limits of its authority, and that a return to the
original structure would make a great deal of sense.</p>
      <p>In this way there is a wholesale attack on the existing
allocation of authority between the national government and the
states. But “horizontal” issues of government structure are
receiving similar attention. Many people have expressed concern
about the extent of policymaking discretion given to regulatory
agencies.16 In their view, Congress should reassert its
constitutional prerogatives by narrowing administrative
discretion. Hence it is urged that the New Deal’s enthusiasm for
independent bureaucracy, and for a large lawmaking role by
executive agencies, should be revisited, and that Congress should
make the fundamental choices of policy.</p>
      <p>Finally, and perhaps most fundamentally, pre-New Deal
principles of private right have enjoyed a rebirth with the
suggestion that modern regulatory programs violate liberty, rightly
conceived.17 Thus the movement for deregulation has called for
far more sweeping changes than were urged in the Reagan period
itself. Thus the takings clause has become a rallying cry for a new
enthusiasm for the protection of private property—a rallying cry
that has been brought by way of challenge to such
wellestablished federal programs as the Endangered Species Act and
the Federal Water Pollution Control Act’s protection of wetlands.
16 David Schoenbrod, Power Without Responsibility (1994).</p>
      <p>17 See Richard Epstein, Simple Rules for a Complex World (1995).</p>
      <p>Some of the criticisms of regulatory performance have been far
more pragmatic in character, and it is here that cost-benefit
balancing, accompanied by risk analysis, has played a special role.
As I have noted, the New Deal period was accompanied by no
mechanism for monitoring regulatory performance. But it is now
suggested that national government has failed adequately to
perform the tasks assigned to it and that it has often made things
worse. In this view, there is no suggestion that markets are ideal;
but often markets work better than the regulatory programs
designed as solutions. In sum, the question is whether the
benefits justify the costs.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>II. Post-New Deal Learning About Regulation</title>
      <p>In the last decade, something very close to a consensus has
emerged on some of the most important problems in existing
government regulation. If government were to act on this
consensus, it would introduce important changes. The consensus
has the following features.</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>1. Government should engage in better priority-setting.</title>
        <p>There can be no doubt that resources for risk reduction are
badly allocated.18 As much as $500 billion may be spent each year
on regulation (putting benefits to one side),19 and of this amount,
more than $130 billion is spent on environmental protection.20 A
recent study suggests that better allocations of existing health
expenditures could save an additional 6 0 ,0 0 0 lives at no
increased cost—and that with better allocations, we could save
the same number of lives we now save with $31 billion in annual
savings.21</p>
        <p>There are also serious and apparently unjustified asymmetries
in life-saving expenditures. For transportation, there is a median
per life year saved of $56,000; for occupational regulation, the
number is $3 4 6 ,0 0 0 ; for environmental regulation, it is
$4,207,000.22 There are enormous variations within each group as
well. Annual lives saved are highly variable.2 3 Of course
calculations of costs and benefits are somewhat speculative, and
these numbers are of uncertain reliability. But with better
allocations and more deliberative judgments, much could be done
to make things better by providing more protection at identical
cost.</p>
        <p>It is well-known that cost per life saved tables show enormous
and highly suggestive2 4 : disparities across programs. Some
regulations cost $100,000 or less per life saved; a number cost less
than $1 million; many cost between $1 million and $5 million; and
many range between $5 million and over $1 billion per life saved. A
single number would not make sense, for reasons that we will
explore; but these differences suggest that priorities are not being
set in a sensible fashion.</p>
        <p>The goal of achieving good priority-setting is undermined by
the fact that agencies have quite different standards for deciding
when risks are large enough to require any regulation at all.25 The
International Commission on Radiological Protection
recommends that environmental factors should not be allowed to
cause an incremental cancer risk, for those exposed over a lifetime,
of about 3 in 1 0 0 0 . American agencies do not follow this
recommendation, and their own practices are highly variable. The
Nuclear Regulatory Commission sees 1 in 1000 as acceptable; the
EPA’s acceptable range varies from 1 in 10,000 to 1 in 1,000,000.
22 Id.
23 W. Kip Viscusi, Fatal Tradeoffs, supra, at 264.</p>
        <p>24 No more than that. To know whether there is cost-effectiveness, it is
necessary to know more than cost per life saved. It is necessary to know as well
(at a minimum) cost per unit of benefit; and benefits might include morbidity
as well as mortality gains, improvements in recreation, mortality and
morbidity gains for plants and animals, and improvements in aesthetics.</p>
        <p>25 See Sadowitz and Graham, A Survey of Permitted Residual Cancer
Risks, 6 RISK 17 (1995).
The FDA has tried to use a standard of 1 in 1 million, but under
the Delaney Clause, courts have required a standard of essentially
0.26 OSHA’s understanding of the “significant risk” requirement
found in its governing statute means a risk of 1 in 1000; labor
groups have sought an increase to 1 in 1 million. In the face of
these variations, sensible priority-setting is unlikely.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>2. Government should have a presumption in favor of flexible,</title>
        <p>market-based incentives rather than rigid commands.</p>
        <p>Too often government has chosen to regulate through rigid
commands that forbid more flexible and cost-effective means for
achieving the same goal. In air and water pollution control,
serious problems are caused by the “best available technology”
approach, which mandates control technologies for hundreds or
even thousands of firms in an exceptionally diverse nation.
Compare market-based systems, which do not mandate
particular results but instead impose costs on those who
contribute to social harms. Consider, for example, a gasoline tax
or an emissions trading system, by which people are allocated
licenses that they can trade at a market price. Through such
strategies, billions of dollars might be saved.27</p>
        <p>Existing efforts at seeking better regulatory tools are hobbled
by the statutory status quo, which sometimes forbids such tools,
and which sometimes requires that they be engrafted on a
bureaucratically complex system.28 Thus a 1989 study suggested
that the EPA’s emissions trading program had saved between
$ 5 2 5 million and $12 billion per year.2 9 Thus the Clinton
Administration calculates that its market-oriented proposals for
amending the Clean Water Act could save between $1 and $1 2
billion over alternative approaches. Thus studies show that
incentive-based mechanisms for controlling air pollution could
have accomplished the same amount at one-quarter the cost.30</p>
        <p>An especially valuable incentive-based approach consists of
disclosure of information. Government might disclose risk-related
information on its own, as it has in the case of cigarette smoking,
or it might require companies to provide such information to
workers and consumers. If, for example, companies offer
information about risk, consumer and worker behavior will
probably be affected. The national government has offered many
initiatives in this direction. In particular, the Toxic Release
Inventory of the Superfund Amendments appears to have been
highly successful, spurring voluntary reductions at relatively low
cost, and without requiring governmental mandates.31 A great
deal of work remains to be done in conceiving and designing
appropriate informational approaches to risk.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>3. Government should be aware of, and attempt to counteract,</title>
        <p>harmful unintended consequences.</p>
        <p>Many regulatory initiatives have unintended harmful
consequences, and under existing institutions, there is no systematic
way to ensure that those consequences receive attention. Hence
regulation tends to be based on partial perspectives emerging
from close attention to mere pieces of complex problems. Selective
attention is a hallmark of almost all current institutional
arrangements.</p>
        <p>A particular problem arises from “health-health” tradeoffs,
which arise when regulation of one health risk increases another
health risk.32 It is important to ensure that risk regulation does
not actually increase risks on balance. Suppose, for example, that
elimination of asbestos—a carcinogenic substance—makes cars
less safe, because asbestos is the best substance to use in making
brake linings. Or suppose that the ban on asbestos encourages
companies to use even more dangerous substitutes. It is
pervasively true that controls on one risk may increase another
risk. Unfortunately, risk regulation is not designed with this
problem in mind.</p>
        <p>There is also an incipient literature suggesting that regulatory
expenditures can actually cost lives, since regulatory expenditures
can produce greater unemployment and hence poverty, and since
poor people do not live as long as people who are not poor. A
1990 study attempted to develop a model to quantify the common
sense view that “richer is safer.”33 According to Keeney, a single
fatality might result from an expenditure of from $3 million to $7.5
million. In a concurring opinion in a 1 9 9 1 case involving
occupational safety and health regulation, Judge Williams
invoked this evidence to suggest that OSHA’s refusal to engage
in cost-benefit analysis might not be
beneficial for workers.34 Judge Williams reasoned that if a fatality
results from an expenditure of $7.5 million, some regulations
might produce more fatalities than they prevent. Many
regulations of course cost more than $7.5 million per life saved (see
Table 1). In Judge Williams’ view, an agency that fails to measure
costs against benefits might be failing to measure mortality gains
against losses.</p>
        <p>The claimed relationship between wealth reductions and
mortality is controversial.35 But a number of studies find such a
relationship. Consider the summary in Table 1.36</p>
        <p>These findings should be taken with many grains of salt;
existing evidence is in its infancy. In particular, there is reason to
believe that expenditures that reduce the income of poor people
have far more serious mortality effects than expenditures that
reduce the income of rich people.37 In any case it would certainly
be good for government to know about unintended adverse
consequences and to try to counteract them to the extent feasible.
There is now no systematic mechanism by which government
regulators can be made attentive to harmful unintended
consequences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>4. Government needs more information, and it should create</title>
        <p>better incentives to compile and provide accurate
information.</p>
        <p>Often government lacks information about the harms that
regulation is designed to counteract. Often it must act, or fail to
act, in a context of a considerable scientific uncertainty. It
follows that</p>
        <p>37 See Chapman &amp; Hariharan, Do Poor People Have a Stronger
Relationship between Income and Mortality Than the Rich?, 12 J Risk &amp;
Uncertainty 51 (1996).
any exercise of quantification can be illusory, or at least give the
impression of far more knowledge than people actually have.</p>
        <p>In these circumstances government should put a high
premium on acquiring as much accurate information as possible.
Much of the relevant information can be found in the private
sector, which is in the best position to know about the costs of
controlling risks and about actual emissions levels. The current
regulatory structure does not create good incentives for compiling
accurate information on these counts; indeed, it creates incentives
to distort the facts. Hence industry faces incentives to report that
the costs will be far higher than they will actually be.38 It certainly
does not encounter proper incentives to compile more information
than is now available. Of course there is an omnipresent risk that
governmental risk analysis will be skewed by well-organized
private interests.</p>
        <p>38 See, e.g., Cotton Dust: An OSHA Success Story?, in W. Kip Viscusi,
Fatal Tradeoffs (discussing the extreme overstatement of compliance costs by
industry).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-5">
        <title>5. Technocratic, economic, and democratic judgments all have</title>
        <p>their appropriate place.</p>
        <p>It seems clear that government should respond to reasonable
judgments about risk; but whose judgments should be counted as
reasonable? Countless studies have shown that there are
systematic differences between expert and citizen judgments
about risk.39 This is one of the most robust findings in an
extensive literature. Consider Table 2.</p>
        <p>What is the reason for these differences? Some of them are
attributable to citizens’ ignorance of the facts. The ignorance has
many sources, including sensationalistic media reports and
heuristics that produce systematic biases.40 Thus people tend to
think that an event is more likely when it is “available,” that is,
when its occurrence can come readily to mind. It may be for this
reason that people think that deaths from accidents occur much
more often than deaths from disease, when in fact the numbers
are about the same. The availability heuristic suggests that what
people think will be partly an artifact of what the media
emphasize. Notably, the media tend to emphasize unusual and
provocative events rather than chronic risks.4 1 The result is
substantial distortions in policy, reflected in the “pollutant of the
month” syndrome that characterizes regulatory responses.
6. Chemical leaks from underground storage tanks</p>
        <p>Medium-to7. Pesticides
8. Pollution from industrial accidents
9. Water pollution from farm runoff
10. Tap water contamination
11. Industrial air pollution
12. Ozone layer destruction
13. Coastal water contamination
14. Sewage-plant water pollution
15. Vehicle exhaust
16. Oil spills
17. Acid rain
18. Water pollution from urban runoff
19. Damaged wetlands
20. Genetic alteration
21. Non-hazardous waste sites
22. Greenhouse effect
23. Indoor air pollution
24. X-ray radiation
25. Indoor radon
26. Microwave oven radiation
low
High
Medium-toMedium
High
High
High
Low
Medium-toHigh
Medium-toHigh
Medium
Low
Low
Medium-toLow
High
Not ranked
High
Not ranked
low
low
low
low</p>
        <p>When citizens misperceive the facts, government should not
respond to them. Citizen judgments that are based on mistaken
beliefs should be corrected through education. And when they are
mistaken, government should try to act on the basis of reality
rather than fiction. For public judgments to govern, it is
important to ensure that they are undergirded by sound science,
as opposed to sensationalistic anecdotes or scare tactics. There is
nothing undemocratic about a governmental refusal to respond to
a demand for regulation that is based on factual ignorance. On
the contrary, a system of representative democracy has as one of
its central justifications the “filtering” of ignorant judgments.</p>
        <p>But this is only part of the story. Some of the differences
between citizens and experts have nothing to do with
misunderstanding of the facts; they involve values instead.
Experts focus principally on aggregate lives at stake. By contrast,
ordinary citizens care about a range of other variables: whether
risks are equitably distributed, faced by future generations,
especially dreaded, well-understood, and voluntarily incurred.42
The psychological research can be summarized in the following
way:</p>
        <p>Qualitative distinctions of this kind do not play a role in
expert assessments. But citizen judgments on these points are
entirely reasonable. They deserve respect, at least in a democracy.
It is therefore important to ensure that any regulatory reform
takes account of public judgments about which risks are most
severe—so long as those judgments are both reflective and
informed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-6">
        <title>6 . Government should concentrate on basic ends rather than</title>
        <p>on means.</p>
        <p>A pervasive problem in federal regulation arises when
regulatory policy becomes an arena for interest-group struggle.
This happened most famously with efforts in 1977 to use the
Clean Air Act to promote the interests of eastern coal43 and, in
1990, with interest-group lobbying on behalf of ethanol and other
parochial interests.4 4 Interest-group maneuvering is an
omnipresent issue in federal regulation.</p>
        <p>It is possible to limit interest-group power—and at the same
time to reduce cost—through legislative attention to ends rather
than to means of achieving those ends. When Congress focuses
on ends, it makes it less likely that interest-group struggle over
means will convert regulation into a struggle among groups with
high stakes in particular means. And when Congress focuses on
ends, it makes it more likely that the democratic process will be
attending to the important questions. Thus “performance
standards” are generally better than “design standards.” What
matters is whether the level of emissions is low or high, not
whether the relevant company has installed scrubbers. In general,
Congress should let administrators decide on the appropriate
means for reaching legislatively-decreed ends, and administrators
should, to the extent feasible, be permitted to rely on market forces
to choose those means. If an industry can comply with a sulfur
dioxide emission standard with clean coal, or with energy
conservation methods, government should be entirely satisfied.</p>
        <p>These, then, are the principal lessons of the last generation of
experience with regulation. If we keep them in mind, we might
think that it is well past time to enact what might be described
metaphorically as an Administrative Substance Act,
complementing the Administrative Procedure Act, which now
governs agency behavior. The point of such an act would be to
capture new learning with respect to regulatory successes and
failures.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>III. Cost-Benefit Analysis As A Corrective: Efficiency and Democracy</title>
      <sec id="sec-4-1">
        <title>A. Problems and Solutions</title>
        <p>In light of these considerations, a new and general
requirement of (some form of) cost-benefit balancing seems a
natural corrective. Indeed, such a requirement might well
ensuring close attention to real-world consequences as these can
be understood through the most sophisticated regulatory tools.
For committed technocrats, the idea is to discipline the
administrative state by assessing actual effects. Where the costs
of regulation are low and the benefits high, nothing is wrong with
regulation.54 The second strand is reactionary: an effort to
eliminate regulation whether or not it can be justified. Here
costbenefit requirements are combined with detailed procedural and
information-gathering burdens, and also (ironically) with limits
on appropriations—limits that will make it harder for agencies to
comply with their new duties. Here the goal is not to improve but
to obstruct regulation. Thus recent reform proposals have
included blanket moratoriums on new regulations (a truly crude
and lazy strategy for “reform”) and costly “look back” provisions
requiring agencies to do extended analyses of old regulations and
to defend those analyses in court.</p>
        <p>In the 1 9 9 0 s, enthusiasm for cost-benefit balancing has
stemmed from both technocrats and reactionaries.55 Mutually
beneficial alliances are certainly possible. Good technocrats knows
that regulation often makes little sense, and good reactionaries
know that cost-benefit analysis can slow down regulation. But for
those interested in public-spirited regulatory reform, the task for
the future is to ensure that technocratic goals predominate.
Otherwise cost-benefit analysis will simply serve as an obstacle to
regulation whether or not it is desirable. If this happens,
costbenefit analysis, as a tool for decisionmakers, will ultimately breed
public cynicism and distrust. This would be a disaster for those
who seek to improve administrative performance.</p>
        <p>For current reformers, a central problem is that cost-benefit
analysis can result in excessive proceduralism—in the form of
delay and paperwork requirements unaccompanied by
corresponding gain. It should be unnecessary to emphasize that
cost-benefit requirements can impose costly procedural duties on
agencies, and sometimes it is not clear that those duties produce
benefits that justify the costs. Cost-benefit analysis will, in some
forms, fail cost-benefit analysis.</p>
        <p>There are two more particular problems here. First: If agencies
are required to compile and compare the costs and benefits of
every possible variation on a proposal under review, they will
spend all their time calculating costs and benefits, and there will
be a large incentive to stick with the status quo whatever its
content. Existing procedural requirements have sometimes had
just this effect. If cost-benefit analysis is supposed to be an
engine for reform, status quo bias would be ironic unintended
consequence.56 Second: If agencies are required to defend all their
rules, including existing rules, in complex administrative processes
and eventually in court, they may spend all their resources in the
defense of rules and hence in the employment of lawyers. Private
cooptation of regulatory resources is a serious risk in proposals
that subject agency decisions to excessive judicial control.</p>
        <p>Take the first problem first. We can get some purchase on the
problem by observing that in recent judicial decisions under
statutes that call for balancing, there has been a tendency to
require agencies to calculate the costs and benefits of a wide range
of alternative proposals.57 Naturally agencies resist this step,
sometimes with the plausible argument that the gain of
additional information is not worth the costs of acquiring it
(including the costs of maintaining the status quo in the
reviewing period). To be sure, the agency might be acting
arbitrarily if it makes this decision; perhaps it has failed to
investigate an alternative that is much better and that can be
investigated cheaply. But courts are in a poor position to know
whether this is so, and in general their own institutional ignorance
ought to lead them to accept an agency’s argument to this effect
unless the argument can be shown to be unreasonable.</p>
        <p>A broad lesson emerges from this conclusion. Agencies may
well be reluctant to devote their resources to exploring the costs
56 See the discussion of status quo bias in J. Mashaw and D. Harfst, The
Struggle For Auto Safety (1990).</p>
        <p>57 Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (9th Cir. 1991). See also
AFL-CIO, supra note.
and benefits of, say, ten alternatives to the proposal under
discussion, on the theory that the costs of the exploration would
not justify the benefits. From this point we can conclude that any
legislative requirement of cost-benefit balancing should give
agencies some room to allocate resources as they wish—including
the investigatory resources that are involved in cost-benefit
analysis itself.</p>
        <p>Now turn to the second problem. It is easy to understand the
impetus toward proposals to require agencies to review existing
rules. Many such rules no longer make sense; changed
circumstances have made them obsolete or even
counterproductive.58 Thus a presidential dictate to agencies to ensure
against obsolescence would be highly desirable. It would be even
better for agencies to adopt rules that are likely to make sense over
time, as in consensus standards that draw on private practices or,
even better, performance standards that do not make it necessary
for agencies to change so rapidly over time. Good technocrats are
well-disposed toward ideas of this sort.</p>
        <p>But a special problem will be created if Congress requires
agencies to “look back” and review the costs and benefits of
existing rules and to defend their analyses in court. Hence the
“look back” idea creates real risks; it may allow private parties to
coopt public resources by requiring endless reviews of old rules.
There is no assurance that any private right to require new
assessments of such rules will make much sense. It is easy to
imagine a system in private groups are allowed to challenge
analyses not so as to ensure better policy analysis, but so as to
fend off and delay sensible regulatory initiatives. Of course this
happens all the time. In the last generation, expensive procedural
requirements have produced a kind of “ossification” of
rulemaking, in which agencies are deterred from proceeding at all,
and ultimately pushed toward less effective alternatives.</p>
        <p>Alert to these problems, Presidents Reagan, Bush, and
Clinton did not allow their executive orders to be reviewable by
courts. Hence the requirements of these executive orders play no
role in court, and cost-benefit balancing has been a matter for
agencies alone (except to the extent that governing statutes
mandate cost-benefit balancing). For the future it probably makes
sense to allow court review to ensure that agency judgments about
costs and benefits are not arbitrary. It also seems reasonable for
presidents to impose on agencies a duty to ensure against obsolete
regulations. But it probably does not make sense to surround the
process with “look back” requirements designed to enable courts
to require agencies to do cost-benefit analyses of past rules. Of
course this is an issue that cannot be settled through first
principles; it has large empirical dimensions. A degree of
experimentation would be desirable before Congress attempts a
statutory solution.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>V. Cost-Benefit Balancing and Command-and-Control</title>
      <p>Congress is now considering proposals to amend many
existing statutes to call for cost-benefit analysis. As we have seen,
some such shift is quite promising. A number of statutes forbid
balancing and call for absolutism,59 and such approaches are not
easy to justify. Moreover, it is important to offer some criteria by
which to monitor regulatory performance, and cost-benefit
analysis is probably the best available technique for embarking on
a form of “national performance review” in the regulatory context.</p>
      <p>Standing by itself, however, a shift in the direction of
costbenefit analysis would be only a modest improvement over the
status quo. Unless it is understood in a particular way—as a part
of and a stimulus to a far larger change in direction—a decision
to engraft a cost-benefit requirement onto current law would
represent an insufficiently fundamental departure from the
system of command and control regulation. In fact a skeptic
might say that by itself, a requirement of cost-benefit analysis
allows legislators to take credit for “getting the regulators under
control” without forcing them to make hard choices, which would
remain left to agencies and the President. This credit-claiming
device can hardly substitute for fundamental reform.</p>
      <p>
        59 See, e.g., Clean Air Act, 42 USC 7401-7671q; Endangered Species Act,
16 USC 1531-1544, the Delaney Clause, 21 USC 348(C)(
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19 ref37">3</xref>
        )(A).
      </p>
      <p>Imagine—to take a rough analogy—if the Soviet Union had
decided (in, say, 1986) to replace an “absolutist” five-year plan for
producing wheat with another five-year plan, one that better
recognized the need for balancing competing variables. This step
might well have been an improvement; but a five-year plan based
on governmental balancing is no less a five-year plan than one
based on governmental absolutism. Governmental dictation of
outcomes rooted in cost-benefit analysis is better than
governmental dictation based on absolutism, but neither is ideal.</p>
      <p>In fact it would be easy to imagine a generation of dreary
cycles with respect to regulatory reform. In those cycles,
conservatives might require more balancing, more procedures, and
fewer deadlines for administrators; liberals then argue against
cost-benefit analysis and for solely health-based or solely
technology-based standards, fewer procedures, citizen suits for
regulatory beneficiaries, and stricter deadlines; conservatives, a
few years later, seek greater procedural requirements and more
attention to costs; liberals respond with the familiar litany; and so
on until, say, 2 0 5 0 . Something of this kind is not a bad
description of regulatory debates since 1980. But its continuation
would represent an enormous failure of imagination and
creativity. It would fix American policy in outmoded debates of
the early 1970s, before the outpouring of learning that makes the
“more” or “less” debate seem to unhelpful.</p>
      <p>A cost-benefit state ought not to content itself with
governmental specification of outcomes after governmental
costbenefit judgments. It ought instead t o e n c o u r a g e
nongovernmental actors to generate information and to produce
outcomes on the basis of incentives produced by democratic
j u d g m e n t s . For example, a great advantage of economic
incentives and disclosure remedies is that they reduce the
informational burden on government and shift that burden to
people who know relevant costs and benefits. Instead of requiring
a certain technology for cars—a question that government is
illequipped to answer—government might impose a fee or a tax on
high-polluting vehicles. The latter strategy imposes a far less
severe information-gathering burden on government, which no
longer need choose among technologies. That choice would be
made by the (legally constrained) market.</p>
      <p>As I have suggested, cost-benefit analysis, properly
understood, should help spur use of better regulatory tools. It
should be understood as part of a general movement away from
command-and-control regulation. I will return to this point
below.</p>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>VI. Problems of Valuation</title>
        <p>Advocates of cost-benefit analysis have urged Congress to
enact a “substantive supermandate” requiring all agencies to
calculate costs and benefits and even to make cost-benefit
analysis the “decisional criterion.” Enough has been said thus far
to suggest why such proposals are attractive. But how, exactly, are
costs and benefits to be valued? Should market failure, as defined
by economists, be the basis for understanding all of government
regulation? These points raise large questions about the
foundations of the modern regulatory state. In this section I
suggest reasons for caution about the traditional economic
understanding of regulation, but nonetheless endorse a shift in
the direction of a substantive supermandate.</p>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-1">
          <title>A. Valuing Life and Health</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-2">
          <title>1. Some theoretical issues.</title>
          <p>If a substantive supermandate is to be superimposed on the
regulatory state, it makes sense to try to understand what
costbenefit balancing actually entails. Much of the national debate in
recent years has involved the value of cost-benefit analysis—with
proponents seeing cost-benefit analysis as a method for
disciplinary administrative power by calling for salutary balancing,
and adversaries fearing that cost-benefit analysis is a
coldhearted way of sacrificing human health and life for the sake of
mere dollars. But this is at best a caricature. By itself, the notion
of cost-benefit analysis is very close to empty; everything depends
on how costs and benefits are characterized and on how
underlying issues of valuation are resolved.</p>
          <p>In fact there are two sorts of criticisms that might be made of
a proposed framework (or supermandate) for evaluating
governmental performance. One sort of criticism is that the
framework is wrong—that it ignores certain important variables,
or that it is founded on an indefensible theory of value. Another
sort of criticism is that it is incompletely specified—that its
meaning depends on further subsidiary judgments that have yet
to be offered. Cost-benefit analysis is properly subject to the first
kind of criticism to the extent that it purports to align all social
values along the single metric of aggregated private willingness to
pay, and to evaluate all social and economic regulation by
reference to that criterion. Inventive economists have devised
many intriguing methods for discerning the “shadow prices” of
goods not normally traded on markets; such methods have their
uses, but their value and limitation result from their foundations
in the idea of private willingness to pay. Regulation may be rooted
in redistributive rather than allocative goals, and for fully
legitimate reasons; consider the anti-discrimination laws as
examples. To the extent that cost-benefit analysis is rooted in the
technical economists’ understanding, it has a great deal to offer,
but it cannot capture all of the appropriate goals of regulation.60</p>
          <p>As a political creed—as it operates within Congress and the
executive branch—the principal problem with cost-benefit
analysis is that it is incompletely specified. Its meaning depends
on how costs and benefits are characterized and on how issues of
valuation are resolved. Are equitable concerns a part of
costbenefit analysis? Suppose, for example, that a certain
environmental risk is concentrated among African-Americans.
Can a good cost-benefit analysis take this into account? (We
should hope so, whatever private willingness to pay may suggest.)
Or suppose that some of the benefits of regulation are aesthetic.
How will these benefits be valued? Of course there is an extensive
literature on valuation of human life and environmental goods.61
By itself cost-benefit analysis does not take a stand on the
associated controversies; but regulators must take some such
stand. My suggestion here is that it is always appropriate to
identify costs and benefits so as to inform analysis, and even to
require that benefits justify costs, but that regulators should not
claim that benefits and costs must be grounded in traditional
economic criteria involving private willingness to pay.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-3">
          <title>2. The range of regulatory enactments.</title>
          <p>The modern state includes a diverse array of regulatory
statutes, with diverse legitimate purposes, including but not at all
limited to economic efficiency. Consider the following:
Many important regulatory statutes are of course plausibly
understood in terms of economic efficiency; they can be seen
as efforts to counteract market failures. The Federal
Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act and the Toxic
Substances Control Act are examples. Such statutes may be
designed to overcome an absence of sufficient information;
harms to third parties; or collective action problems of various
sorts.</p>
          <p>Some statutes are designed to eliminate illegitimate
discrimination. Though some people think that such statutes
can be defended on efficiency grounds,6 2 their animating
impulse has little to do with economic efficiency. They should
be understood as an effort to eliminate second-class
citizenship for members of certain social groups. Of course
this does not mean that cost is no object. Such statutes
should have cost-effectiveness as a goal, and effects on
productivity are not irrelevant.</p>
          <p>Some statutes are designed to protect cultural aspirations.63
Examples include measures safeguarding the national parks,
encouraging high-quality programming, and protecting
endangered species.</p>
          <p>Some statutes are designed to transform preferences, perhaps
by altering existing social norms that press choices in a
particular direction. When choices are a product of
reputational incentives and hence social norms, and when
those choices shorten lives, government might attempt to
r e s p o n d . 6 4 Regulation involving smoking, recycling,
educational programming, and sexual harassment can be
understood in these terms.</p>
          <p>Some statutes are designed to redistribute resources to the
poor or to others understood as having a good claim to public
help. To be sure, regulation is a poor tool for this purpose,
and purportedly public-spirited redistribution may really be
benefiting well-organized interest groups with little claim to
public assistance. But redistribution plays a large role in
modern administration. The Social Security Act is an obvious
example of redistributive law; the Agricultural Adjustment
Act can be understood in this way, with appropriate
qualifications for its interest-group dimensions.</p>
          <p>It would undoubtedly be possible to mention other
possibilities. The point is that the highly diverse grounds for
federal regulation raise questions about cost-benefit analysis as
the sole basis for regulation—and even about identifying costs
and benefits as such in a value-free way.</p>
          <p>If it is intended as an amendment to the regulatory state, a
cost-benefit supermandate could be understood in many different
ways. In its most ambitious form, it would amount to an
endorsement of the principle of economic efficiency as the
exclusive basis—the “decisional criterion”—for interpretation and
application of all statutes. This would be a fundamental change
both because it would understand cost-benefit analysis in a
particular way—as a term for the criterion of economic
efficiency—and because it would amend statutes that, when
enacted, seemed motivated by something other than the efficiency
criterion. If this were the understanding of the supermandate, all
of the statutes to which the supermandate applies would
henceforth be understood in efficiency terms. To say the least, this
would be a dramatic shift in national policies and practices.</p>
          <p>Another, less ambitious possibility is that the cost-benefit
criteria would be understood in efficiency terms, but only for those
statutes that were originally designed to promote economic
efficiency. Under this approach, a cost-benefit supermandate
would not alter the basic understandings that underlie existing
statutes. It would instead have a more modest but nonetheless
important goal: imposing a particular understanding of
rationality on statutes formerly understood and implemented in a
less precise, more ad hoc, and more intuitive way.</p>
          <p>A third and least ambitious possibility is that cost-benefit
criteria would be understood in a less technical and more
common-sensical way, as an invitation to balancing a range of
variables under statutes that had formerly been thought to be
absolutist and hence to forbid balancing. On this view, a
supermandate would not be so ambitious as to call for use of
purely economic criteria. Its more modest goal would be to ask
administrators to look at costs, or adverse effects, as well as at
benefits. This has probably been the goal of the majority of those
members of Congress who have been in favor of a substantive
supermandate. And if the supermandate is understood in these
terms, it makes a great deal of sense. As we will see, the principal
objection to such a supermandate is that it is too open-ended;
Congress can and should take steps to make it clearer, though—I
emphasize—without mandating the efficiency criterion outside of
the context of “market failure” statutes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-4">
          <title>3. Theory and practice.</title>
          <p>In legislative proposals dealing with cost-benefit analysis,
almost no guidance has been offered on the crucial issue of how
to value relevant variables. For this reason the provisions look
highly substantive but are in fact largely procedural. Without
guidance to constrain valuation, a requirement of cost-benefit
analysis is quite open-ended.</p>
          <p>To be sure, it would be possible to conclude that Congress
should restrict itself to a call for cost-benefit analysis and leave
the details to agencies. Perhaps Congress lacks the detailed
understanding that would enable it to answer the more specific
questions. Moreover, an open-ended mandate would certainly not
be meaningless. It would send agencies a signal about the need
for balancing a range of considerations, and any such procedural
requirement will affect outcomes. Courts may invalidate outcomes
that, by general understandings, seem out of line with existing
practice or too absolutist.65 Certainly there is a difference between
agency behavior under balancing statutes and agency behavior
under statutes that forbid balancing.66 But those concerned about
administrative discretion would urge some greater guidance from
the national legislature. I offer two suggestions here.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-5">
          <title>4. Qualitative factors.</title>
          <p>
            An important fact here has been encountered in Part I: People
care not simply about aggregate amount of lives lived, but also
about a range of factors involving the nature of the particular risk.
For most people, among the most salient contextual features are:
(
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">1</xref>
            ) the catastrophic nature of the risk; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">2</xref>
            ) whether the risk is
uncontrollable; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19 ref37">3</xref>
            ) whether the risk involves irretrievable or
permanent losses; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">4</xref>
            ) whether the risk is voluntarily incurred; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">5</xref>
            )
how equitably distributed the danger is or how concentrated on
identifiable, innocent, or traditionally disadvantaged victims; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1 ref40">6</xref>
            )
how well understood the risk in question is; (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2 ref41">7</xref>
            ) whether the risk
would be faced by future generations; and (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3 ref42">8</xref>
            ) how familiar the risk
is. Many of these factors are reflected in the willingness to pay
criterion.67
          </p>
          <p>Any required cost-benefit analysis for diverse regulatory
agencies should reflect these points. Any cost-benefit analysis
should, moreover, be accompanied by a more disaggregated and
more qualitative description of the consequences of government
action, so that Congress and the public can obtain a fuller picture
than the crude and misleadingly precise “bottom line” of the
costbenefit analysis. This is not at all to deny that it is important to be
precise and quantitative when agencies can be precise and
quantitative. It is only to say that any “bottom line” about how to
characterize and assess costs and benefits will involve judgments
about values, not about science, and Congress and the public
should see what those judgments are.</p>
          <p>65 Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (5th Cir. 1991).
66 Compare Toxic Substances Control Act and Fungicide, Insecticide,
and Rodenticide Act with Clean Air Act and Delaney Clause and EDA.</p>
          <p>67 See George Tolley et al., Valuing Health for Policy (1994).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-6">
          <title>5. Floors and ceilings.</title>
          <p>It is of course troublesome to assign dollar values for life,
partly for the reasons I have sketched; but since tradeoffs of
multiple kinds are inevitable, it may be best for Congress to set
out some guidelines, floors, and ceilings governing expenditures,
without pretending to say how much a life is “really worth.” In
light of the diversity of regulated risks, no single number would
make sense for valuing life. It may well make sense to set
benchmark standards of, say, $10 million per life saved as the
maximum amount and $3 million as the minimum. These
benchmarks might be accompanied by explicit permission for
agencies to select a lower or higher number if the agency can
explain that special circumstances call for that higher number.
On this view, the data emerging from studies of revealed
preferences would be used not because it reflects “actual” or
acontextual valuations, but because for pragmatic purposes, it
provides a good place to start, one that is better supported and
more usable than any available alternative.</p>
          <p>There is crudeness, however, in the very notion of “dollars per
life saved.” A well-functioning regulatory state should not be
interested in how many lives are saved. but in how many
statistical years, or how many decently livable statistical years, are
added by regulation.68 Hence Congress might set floors and
ceilings not for lives saved but for life-years saved, with
permission to depart on the basis of justifications that are publicly
articulated and are reasonable on the merits.</p>
          <p>Without a figure per life or per “quality life year” saved,
agencies effectively have discretion to weight costs and benefits
however they wish; this is a good reason for Congress to offer
some guidelines. At a minimum Congress should require agencies
to be explicit about their valuations, so that what they do will be
subject to legislative and public oversight and review.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-5-1-7">
          <title>6. Substitute risks.</title>
          <p>We have seen that there is a pervasive problem in risk
regulation, one that is only now receiving public attention. The
problem occurs when the diminution of one risk simultaneously
increases another risk. It would be good for Congress to consider
a new provision to this effect:</p>
          <p>
            “(
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">1</xref>
            ) Agencies shall ensure, to the extent feasible, that
regulations do not create countervailing risks that are greater than
those of regulated risks.
          </p>
          <p>
            (
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">2</xref>
            ) This section shall not apply if it is inconsistent with the
provisions of the enabling statute pursuant to which the agency is
acting.”
          </p>
          <p>A cost-benefit supermandate, properly interpreted, may well
incorporate an understanding of this sort. But it would be best to
make such a requirement explicit.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>VII. Ambitious Thinking for the Cost-Benefit State</title>
      <p>Thus far I have offered some relatively modest suggestions.
For the cost-benefit state, three more ambitious strategies would
accomplish a great deal more.</p>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>1. Rank risks and reallocate resources to more severe problems.</title>
        <p>As Justice Breyer has suggested, a statute might well give the
President some degree of the authority to divert public and
private resources from small environmental problems to large
ones, so as to ensure greater cost-effectiveness in government and
better priority-setting.69 There are some dangers with this
proposal; a small group of bureaucrats should not have the
authority to decide on basic social priorities. But a greater degree
of presidential priority-setting would make sense.</p>
        <p>Justice Breyer’s approach should be qualified by keeping in
mind the fact that people are legitimately concerned with the
various contextual factors discussed above—the voluntariness of
the risk, its potentially catastrophic character, whether it is
especially dreaded, whether it is equitably distributed, and so
forth. Ideas of this sort have received some modest attention in
Congress; but the proposals have not been very ambitious.</p>
        <p>69 This is basically the approach suggested in S. Breyer, Breaking the
Vicious Circle (1993).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-6-2">
        <title>2. Encourage and allow plans from private sector that show</title>
        <p>greater (but cheaper) reductions.</p>
        <p>Often the problem with federal regulation is that the
government lacks knowledge of the least expensive means of
producing the preferred regulatory end. If the private sector were
permitted to select the means, it could do so far more cheaply.
The point has been recognized in Europe and Japan, under the
general rubric of “environmental contracting.”7 0 In the
Netherlands, for example, government has experimented with
comprehensive, multi-media environmental targets for pollution
reduction, accompanied by agreements from industry groups to
achieve overall targets. In return for these agreements,
government agrees to eliminate otherwise applicable
pollutant-bypollutant regulations, and to reduce any changes in requirements
during the length of the contract period.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the EPA has taken modest steps in the
same direction. Thus the EPA has moved toward more
cooperative solutions that use social pressures and moral suasion
to encourage the use of innovative, low-cost pollution reduction
techniques. The Green Lights Program, informing business about
energy-efficient light fixtures, is an example, as is a recent
program designed to encourage voluntary reductions in seventeen
highly toxic chemical emissions.71 Consider also OSHA’s Star
program, allowing companies with a demonstrably good safety
record to rely on self-policing rather than government oversight.
EPA is attempting to develop an Environmental Leadership
program to parallel the Star program.</p>
        <p>So too, EPA and Amoco concluded that a plantwide
approach would do better in decreasing chemical releases than
does the existing command and control system; unfortunately,
nothing happened, but the conclusion should affect regulatory
reform efforts. Under the 1990 Clean Air Act, companies can, in
essence, “contract out” of technology-based controls for five years
70 See Peter Mennell and Richard B. Stewart, Environmental Law and
Policy 420-22 (1995). See Jan M. van Dunne, Environmental Contracts and
Covenants (1993).</p>
        <p>71 See Wilkins and Hunt, Agency Discretion and Advances in Regulatory
Theory, 63 George Washington L Rev 479, 492-98 (1995)
if they achieve a 90% reduction in toxic pollutants before EPA
promulgates relevant regulations.72 Under most federal statutes,
however, EPA cannot approve private plans as substitutes for
public mandates, even if the plans promise better results for less
money. Congress should move in the direction of allowing private
substitutes, so long as government monitoring is maintained. Of
course it remains important to know whether the benefits from the
private alternative are higher than the costs; perhaps the private
alternative is cheaper but still not worthwhile on balance. What I
am suggesting is that more creative, cooperative, and flexible
programs, enlisting the informational advantages of the private
sector, could be a large improvement over the status quo.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-6-3">
        <title>3. Regulate with incentives.</title>
        <p>We have seen throughout that command-and-control
regulation can be highly dysfunctional. Sometimes relevant
statutes forbid agencies from choosing incentive-based strategies
even if agencies know that such strategies would work better.
Congress might enact a particular provision to solve this problem.
It might say, for example, “Notwithstanding any other provision
of law, an agency shall be permitted to regulate with economic
incentives, if it can show that these methods will produce the
same benefits in a more cost-effective manner.”73 Of course such
a provision would involve risks. It could create further litigation,
perhaps initiated by self-interested private groups seeking to stall
desirable regulation. It could allow agencies unenthusiastic about
regulatory mandates to proceed with less effective means of
achieving compliance. But the problems with existing processes—
excessive costs, insufficient regulatory benefits—are sufficient to
make it worthwhile to move in this direction.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The United States is embarking increasingly on the project of
assessing government regulation by asking whether the benefits
justify the costs. The regulatory state is slowly becoming
72 42 USC 112(h)
73 I borrow here from Statement of Jonathan Wiener, Before the
Committee on Governmental Affairs, United States Senate, March 8, 1995.
something like a cost-benefit state; this is an unmistakable feature
of public life in many institutions of American government. Thus
in the last decade and more, the executive branch has attempted
to embrace a form of cost-benefit analysis for specific purposes—
to promote better priority-setting, to move toward market-oriented
tools, to exempt de minimis risks, to attend to informed public
judgments, to foster voluntary and least-cost compliance, and to
focus on ultimate results rather than methods and processes.
Similar steps can be found in Congress and the federal courts;
but they remain tentative and incipient.</p>
      <p>In light of the chaotic and uncoordinated character of modern
regulation, the absence of good priority-setting, and the system of
“legislation by anecdote,” movement in the direction of a
costbenefit state is in many ways a salutary development. As we have
seen, balancing is far better than absolutism. The point is
especially important in light of the fact that with respect to
protection of human health, absolutism may actually be
counterproductive and hence far from what it seems. Indeed,
absolutism may impair rather than improve health. But
costbenefit balancing can lead to excessive proceduralism, especially
insofar as it is required via litigation. Moreover, the idea of
costbenefit analysis needs a great deal of specification, and it is hardly
sufficient to engraft a supermandate of “balancing” on top of a
structure of command and control regulation. Any such mandate
should be part of a general movement toward more flexible
regulatory tools.</p>
      <p>I have suggested that a general background requirement of
cost-benefit balancing—a substantive supermandate—should be
enacted. I have also suggested that in describing costs and
benefits, Congress should allow room for a diverse array of values,
and not limit agencies to the criterion of private willingness to
pay. Sometimes regulation attempts to alter preferences and
norms; sometimes it has little to do with aggregated willingness to
pay. An Administrative Substance Act, amending the regulatory
state, should include the background requirement I have
described and also require agencies to act in a cost-effective
fashion. A cost-benefit state, understood in these terms, could
make large improvements by offering initiatives that make sense
under any reasonable theory of value.</p>
      <p>This Working Paper is a preliminary version of a chapter of a
book, Reforming Federal Regulating (Robert Hahn editor,
forthcoming 1997). Readers with comments should address them
to:</p>
      <sec id="sec-7-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein</title>
        <p>Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor</p>
        <p>The Law School
The University of Chicago</p>
        <p>1111 East 60th Street</p>
        <p>Chicago, Illinois 60637
Chicago Working Papers in Law and Economics
(Second Series)</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body><script/>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>6 5 USC 706</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>7 See W. Kip</surname>
            <given-names>Viscusi</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Fatal
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tradeoffs</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>8 See id</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          9
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Toxic Substances Control Act</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>7</volume>
          USC 136-136y; Fungicide, Insecticide, and Pesticide Act,
          <volume>15</volume>
          USC 2601-2692.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          18
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Stephen</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Breyer</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Breaking the Vicious Circle</source>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Pildes &amp; Sunstein, Reinventing the Regulatory State, 62 U Chi L Rev 1 (</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          19 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Thomas D. Hopkins</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Costs of Federal Regulation, 2 J Reg &amp; Social Costs 5, 25 table 2</source>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>(estimate of $400 million)</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          20
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Portney</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Stavins,
          <source>Regulatory Review of Environmental Policy, 8 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>111</volume>
          , 119 n.
          <issue>1</issue>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          21 Tengs et al.,
          <source>Five Hundred Life-Saving Interventions and their CostEffectiveness</source>
          ,
          <source>Risk Analysis, forthcoming.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          26 Public Citizen v.
          <source>Young, 831 F.2d 1108 (DC Cir</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          27 See T. Tietenburg,
          <source>Emissions Trading 38-59</source>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ); Portney et al.,
          <source>The EPA at Thirtysomething</source>
          ,
          <volume>21</volume>
          Envl. L.
          <volume>1461</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>28 See, for example, the “offset” provisions of the nonattainment program of the Clean Air Act, which impose a “lowest achievable emissions rate” requirement in addition to the offset program</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          29 Hahn and Hester, Marketable Permits, 16 Ecol
          <string-name>
            <surname>L Q</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>361</year>
          ,
          <article-title>374 and Table 2 (</article-title>
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          30 See Tom Tietenburg, Emissions
          <string-name>
            <surname>Trading</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1985</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          31
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Robert</surname>
          </string-name>
          Percival et al.,
          <source>Environmental Law and Policy</source>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          32
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>John Graham and Jonathan Wiener</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Risk-Risk Tradeoffs</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ),
          <article-title>for an excellent overview</article-title>
          ;
          <source>see also Symposium</source>
          ,
          <source>8 Journal of Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>5</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Aaron Wildavsky, Searching for Safety (</article-title>
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          33 Kenney,
          <source>Mortality Risks Induced by Economic Expenditure, 10 Risk Analysis</source>
          <volume>147</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          34 International Union v.
          <source>OSHA&lt; 938 F.2d 1310</source>
          ,
          <fpage>1326</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          (DC Cir.
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Williams</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , concurring).
          <source>See also Building &amp; Constr</source>
          . Trades Dept. v. Brock, 838
          <string-name>
            <surname>F.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>2d 1258 (DC Cir 1988), suggesting that “leaning toward safety may sometimes have the perverse effect of increasing rather than decreasing risk</article-title>
          .
          <source>” Id. at 1267</source>
          . See also New York State v.
          <source>Brown</source>
          , 854 F.2d
          <volume>1379</volume>
          , 1395 n. 1
          <string-name>
            <surname>(D. C.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Cir</article-title>
          .,
          <year>1988</year>
          (Williams,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , concurring):
          <article-title>“extravagant expenditures on health may in some instances affect health adversely, by foreclosing expenditures on items-higher quality food, shelter, recreation, etc.-that would have contributed more to the individual's health than the direct expenditures thereon</article-title>
          .”
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          35
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Portney</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Stavins,
          <source>Regulatory Review of Environmental Policy, 8 J. Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>111</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          3 6
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Lutter</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Morrall,
          <source>Health-Health Analysis, 8 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          ,
          <issue>49</issue>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          39
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Pildes</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Sunstein, Reinventing the Regulatory State, 62
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
            <surname>Chi L Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>1 (</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          40
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Colim</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Camerer</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Individual Decision Making, in The Handbook of Experimental Economics (J. Kagel and A</article-title>
          . Roth eds.
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          41
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Greenberg</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>Network Evening News Coverage of Environmental Risk, 9 Risk Analysis</source>
          <volume>119</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          42 See, e.g., Slovic, Beyond Numbers, in Acceptable Evidence 48 (
          <string-name>
            <surname>D. Mayo</surname>
          </string-name>
          and R. Hollander eds.
          <year>1991</year>
          ); Slovic,
          <source>Perception of Risk, 236 Science 280</source>
          (
          <year>1987</year>
          ); Kraus, Malmfors, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Slovic</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Intuitive Toxicology, 12 Risk Analysis</source>
          <volume>215</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ); W. Kip Viscusi,
          <source>Carcinogen Regulation: Risk Characteristics and the Synthetic Risk Bias, 85 Am Econ Rev</source>
          <volume>50</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          43
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Bruce</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            <surname>Ackerman</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <given-names>William</given-names>
            <surname>Hassler</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Clean Coal/Dirty Air (
          <year>1981</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          44
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Adler</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Clean Fuels, Dirty Air,
          <source>in Environmental Politics</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          (Michael Greve and Fred Smith eds.
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          54 See, e.g., W. Kip Viscusi, Fatal
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tradeoffs</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ),
          <article-title>and consider the Reagan Administration's decision to eliminate lead from gasoline, a decision founded on cost-benefit balancing</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>55 See the discussion in Sunstein, Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the Cost-Benefit State, 48</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Stan. L.</given-names>
            <surname>Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>247</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          58
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Eisner</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Kaleta,
          <source>Federal Agency Review of Existing Regulations, 48 Administrative Law Review</source>
          <volume>139</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>60 See the parallel points in L. Lave, Benefit-Cost Analysis: Do the Benefits Exceed the Costs?</article-title>
          , in Risks, Costs, and Lives Saved (Robert Hahn ed.
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          61 See, e.g., W. Kip Viscusi, Fatal
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tradeoffs</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          62 Lundberg and Starz,
          <source>Private Discrimination and Social Intervention in Competitive Labor Markets, 73 Am. Ec. Rev</source>
          .
          <volume>340</volume>
          (
          <year>1983</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          63 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>After the Rights Revolution 57-60</source>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          64
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Social Norms and Social Roles, 96 Colum L Rev (forthcoming May</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          68
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Zackhauser</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Shepard,
          <source>Where Now For Saving Lives?, 40 Law and Contemp. Probs</source>
          .
          <volume>5</volume>
          (
          <year>1976</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          1.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Copyright Protection of Letters, Diaries and Other Unpublished Works: An Economic Approach (July</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          2.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Epstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Path to The T. J.
          <article-title>Hooper: The Theory and History of Custom in the Law of Tort (August</article-title>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          3.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>On Property and Constitutionalism (September</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          4.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Blackmail, Privacy, and Freedom of Contract (
          <year>February 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          5.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Randal</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picker</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Security Interests, Misbehavior, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Common Pools</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>February 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          6.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tomas</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Philipson</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Richard A. Posner, Optimal Regulation of AIDS (April
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          7.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Baird,
          <source>Revisiting Auctions in Chapter 11 (April</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          8.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Sequential versus Unitary Trials: An Economic Analysis (July</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          9.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>Richard A. Posner, The Influence of Economics on Law: A Quantitative Study</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          10.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Alan O. Sykes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Welfare Economics of Immigration Law: A Theoretical Survey With An Analysis of U.S. Policy</article-title>
          (
          <year>September 1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          11.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Baird</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>1992 Katz Lecture: Reconstructing Contracts (November</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          12.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gary</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Economic Way of Looking at Life (
          <year>January 1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          13.
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. Mark</surname>
            <given-names>Ramseyer</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Credibly Committing to Efficiency
          <source>Wages: Cotton Spinning Cartels in Imperial Japan (March</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          14.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Endogenous Preferences, Environmental
          <string-name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>April 1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>