<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Theories and Tropes: A Reply to Posner and Kelman</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Richard H. Thaler</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Assistant Professor of Law, Harvard Law School</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, Christine Jolls &amp; Richard H. Thaler, "Theories and Tropes: A Reply to Posner</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>50</volume>
      <fpage>1997</fpage>
      <lpage>1998</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>that it is merely one of several equally valid ways of viewing the world, we
disagree; we believe that behavioral law and economics should be regarded as
more than an "interpretive trope" and that it will help to shed light on legal
problems and produce improvements in the legal system.</p>
      <p>A small note at the outset: Both Judge Posner and Professor Kelman
frequently use the word "irrationality," and they write as if "irrationality" and
"irrational behavior" are at the heart of behavioral economics and behavioral
law and economics. But our article intentionally avoided that word, on the
ground that it is not useful and is likely to mislead. We do far better to
specify how human beings actually behave (and depart from the conventional
theory) than to argue whether they are "irrational." Hence we refer to quasi
rational agents and to bounded rationality, bounded willpower, and bounded
self-interest, three ideas of special relevance to Posner's comment, to which
we now turn.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>I. POSNER</title>
      <p>A reader of Judge Posner's commentary might be left with the impression
that there are large disagreements between us. This impression would be
false. Posner accepts the most important points of our article; he
acknowledges the existence of the three bounds, and he agrees that the phenomena we
discuss are real and potentially important to economics and law. Much of his
discussion consists of quibbling about what is really a minor matter: whether
we should call a given behavior rational or not. Posner is also concerned to
show the sources of the three bounds, an important subject to be sure, but one
on which we are agnostic. Our goal here is to reduce the perceived distance
between our views and straighten out the most important misunderstandings.</p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>A- Framingthe Debate</title>
        <p>Seeming to have learned more from the study of cognitive psychology
than he lets on, Judge Posner begins with a clever framing manipulation. He
says that we (implicitly) define behavioral economics negatively as
"economics minus the assumption that people are rational maximizers of their
satisfactions."8 He contrasts this negative approach to what he prefers, the
positive "enriching" approach he claims for standard economic theorizing.9
As readers of our article realize, we offer no such negative definition; in fact
we often use precisely the same concept, "enriching" the standard economic
model, that is offered by Judge Posner.10</p>
        <p>Indeed, as we will make clear below, our goals and tools are remarkably
similar. The primary problem Posner seems to have with our approach is our
reluctance to call all behavior rational. To Posner, a model that is rational is
good, disciplined, scientific, and enriching, whereas a model that is quasi
ra8.Posner, supranote 1, at 1552.
9. Id. at 1567.</p>
        <p>10. Id.; Christine Jolls, Cass Sunstein &amp; Richard Thaler, A BehavioralApproach to Law and
Economics, 50 STAN. L. REV. 1471, 1475 (1998) [hereinafter "JST"].</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan. L. Rev. 1594 1997-1998
tional is bad, undisciplined, unscientific, and subtracting. Posner seems to be
using the heretofore undiscovered "rationality heuristic" (if it uses rational
models, it is good). Like all heuristics, this one sometimes works well, but it
can lead to systematic biases.</p>
        <p>In this case the primary bias is one that Colin Camerer calls, in
conversation, the "sufficiency bias." Throughout Posner's commentary, he goes
through the following ritual. He discusses one of the phenomena we identify
as problematic for economic theory; he offers a modification or elaboration on
the standard theory that could, in principle, be consistent with this
phenomenon; and then he declares victory. Posner seems to think that the fact that it is
possible to tell a rational choice story consistent with the data is sufficient to
establish that this explanation is the correct one. This is obviously a fallacy.
In no case does he offer evidence to suggest that his preferred explanation is
correct, nor even a test that would, in principle, discriminate between his
explanation and ours. For those of us who believe in falsifiability, this is an
unfortunate omission.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-2">
        <title>B. Three Bounds</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-3">
        <title>1. Bounded rationality.</title>
        <p>To his credit, Posner offers a definition of rationality: "choosing the best
means to the chooser's ends."" But at many places he acknowledges that
people often do not choose the best means to their own ends. He agrees that
there is substantial evidence in favor of what he insists, in our view
misleadingly, on calling "cognitive quirks"' 2 (a subtle suggestion that these are minor
and unsystematic departures from the standard model). Still, he claims that,
in general, bounded rationality either can be accommodated within a more
refined rational choice model, or does not upset the predictions of the standard
model, or both. He claims that we are simply willing to "give up on
rationalchoice economics too soon."'13</p>
        <p>Whether this is true of course depends on what the evidence shows.
Posner suggests, for example, that the standard economic analysis of
transportation is unaffected by people's ("irrational"--his term) fear of flying, and that
the economic analysis of voting is unaffected by ("irrational"--again his
term) voting behavior. 14 In some contexts a standard analysis of
transportation and of voting may work (although for the same reasons we gave in our
article, we continue to question assertions such as that standard analysis is
helpful in predicting "why the old vote more than the young"; 5 if in fact the
young voted more, could it not be said that voting for them was more novel
and thus generated greater utility?). A standard analysis cannot, however, tell
us all of what we need to know. Behavioral economists would predict that
11. Id. at 1551.
12. Id. at 1553.
13. Id. at 1556.
14. Id. at 1554-55.
15. Id. at 1554.
both market behavior and government behavior in the airline industry are
affected by bounded rationality, as, for example, when additional safety
measures are taken and mandated in the aftermath of a crash (a prediction of the
availability heuristic)-even if such measures are not defensible on traditional
grounds and even decrease aggregate safety (by producing a shift toward
other, more dangerous modes of transportation, such as driving). We would
also predict that bounded rationality (the availability heuristic, overoptimism,
and framing effects) is relevant to voting behavior-and also that people are
more likely to vote if they think that most people are voting (not a prediction
of the conventional analysis, in fact a conundrum under that analysis, but a
reasonable inference from models involving cooperative behaviorl 6).</p>
        <p>The behavioral economics of transportation and voting are in fact
extremely interesting; the notion that all the important aspects of these behaviors
are well-explained by standard economics strikes us as, well, overoptimistic.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-4">
        <title>Bounded willpower.</title>
        <p>Posner agrees that self-control problems are real: "I do not doubt that
there is such a thing as weakness of will.' u 7 Indeed, he thinks that analysis of
the behavior that presents such problems "may require abandoning a tacit
assumption of most economic analysis-that the self is a unity."' 8 We share the
view that people are often in struggles with themselves-struggles that the
wiser part of their personality sometimes loses. (Posner suggests at one point
that we "do not discuss the 'multiple selves' approach"; 19 but such temporal
inconsistency of preference is precisely what hyperbolic discounting
reflects.2 0)</p>
        <p>We disagree, though, with Posner's view that information provides an
obvious explanation for hyperbolic discounting.2 ' Posner suggests that people
may discount sharply in the relatively near future because they know they
have a particular need for cash now, whereas for times in the distant future it
is hard to envision "what might make [one] pay in effect a huge interest rate
to reallocate consumption. '22 It is true that people may sometimes have less
information about their future needs than about their present ones, but it is not
clear why lack of information alone would cause them to err systematically on
the side of underestimating future needs. Given the lack of information about
the future, it is quite possible that the need for immediate cash will be much
more intense in the future.</p>
        <p>16. See John 0. Ledyard, Public Goods: A Survey of Experimental Research, in THE
HANDBOOK OF EXPERIMENTAL ECONOMICS 111, 121-22 (John H. Kagel &amp; Alvin E. Roth eds.,
1995).</p>
        <p>17. Posner, supranote 1,at 1555.
18. Id.
19. Id. at 1556.</p>
        <p>20. See David Laibson, Golden Eggs andHyperbolic Discounting, 112 Q.J. ECON. 443, 445
(1997).</p>
        <p>21. See Posner, supra note 1, at 1555.
22. Id.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-5">
        <title>Bounded self-interest.</title>
        <p>Posner agrees that people do not act only from financial self-interest, and
he appears to think that this is important to both economics and law. His
chief objection to our discussion of bounded self-interest is that we do not link
it with the two other bounds, making our approach to enriching the standard
economic model appear disconnected and, in his view, antitheoretical. We do
not see how Posner's proposed approach is more theorized, in the relevant
sense, than ours, as we will now explain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-6">
        <title>C. Theory and Antitheory</title>
        <p>As noted, Posner claims that behavioral economics is "undertheorized. 2' 3
Our article should have been entitled, he says, "A Psychological Critique of
Economic Analysis of Law" rather than "A Behavioral Approach to Law and
Economics. '24 In his view, behavioral economics is "purely empirical,"
defined "by its subject rather than by its method," and unable to make
predictions?5</p>
        <p>We intended to create-and to show to be warranted-precisely the
opposite impression. There have been many important theoretical advances in
behavioral economics; a number of them are cited in our article.26 Consider, for
example, prospect theory, the specification of biases and heuristics, and
models of fairness-related behavior-all discussed in some detail in our article.
Though much remains to be done, each of these contains a set of theoretical
claims. Behavioral economists interested in law would predict, for example,
that injunctions will stick in nuisance cases, that participants in lawsuits will
display self-serving bias, that the allocation of a legal entitlement will matter
to the ultimate outcome, that laws will reflect widespread judgments about
fairness organized around reference points, that the pattern of environmental
regulation will reflect the use of familiar heuristics, that people will be
overoptimistic about risk-all topics developed in our article. Of course it is true
that there is much more to be learned and that in many contexts good
predictions are difficult. To the extent that he is saying more than this, we are left
with the impression that Posner's claim of undertheorization is based on
Posner's (undefended but more than implicit) view that an essential part of a good
theory is that it be a rational choice theory.</p>
        <p>Predictions can be hard for any model, standard or behavioral, and a basic
problem in judging the success of any model, rational or quasi rational, is
knowing what constitutes a true prediction of the model rather than a post hoc
explanation. A case in point is Posner's discussion of AIDS. In support of
the rational choice model, he cites the prediction that the AIDS epidemic will
increase the rate of unwanted pregnancies by "inducing a rational substitution
of condoms" for birth-control pills.27 But the example raises two obvious
questions. First, was this really an ex ante prediction? Second, if so, is this
really a victory for rationality? Isn't it quite possible that a rational woman
who viewed both AIDS and pregnancy as undesirable would choose to use
both a condom and a pill (despite the cost of using two forms of protection)?
How would a rational actor model decide, ex ante, between this prediction
and the alternative? How, then, does the rational choice approach provide a
more "theorized" analysis than the behavioral approach?</p>
        <p>Of course, predictions are sometimes robust to departures from
unbounded rationality; an example discussed in our article is downward-sloping
demand.28 If economics only consisted of this sort of prediction, many of the
bounds we discuss would not matter. But in these cases there would also be
no need for (or benefit from) rational choice models. Recall that Posner
defines rational as "choosing the best" in terms of benefits and costs, implying
an optimal tradeoff analysis (including decisionmaking and information
acquisition costs). 29 This optimizing model is much richer than merely buying
less of a good when the price goes up; as we pointed out, even laboratory rats
do this.30 The richness adds precision to the theory and also renders it
falsifiable (and in many cases, false; Posner's own discussion acknowledges many
examples). In defense of rational choice theory, and in urging that we give up
on it too quickly, Posner cites our claim that the fact that random choice (by
rats or human beings) in a situation of scarcity will generate a
downwardsloping demand curve shows that downward-sloping demand "is not evidence
in support of optimizing models."' 31 He declares our analysis "wrong":
"Buyers do not choose randomly. Rationality is the only reasonable
explanation for their reactions to changes in relative prices. '32 Wrong. Gary
Becker's demonstration that random choice yields downward-sloping demand
extends easily to almost any choice behavior.33 A mix of budget-constrained
consumers, some of whom just buy the brand their mother did, some of whom
buy anything with Michael Jordan's picture on it, some of whom always buy
the brand on the right, and so forth, will also buy less of goods whose prices
27. Posner, supranote 1, at 1557.
28. JST, supranote 10, at 1481-82.
29. Posner, supranote 1, at 1551.
30. JST, supranote 10, at 1481-82.
31. Posner, supranote 1, at 1556.
32. Id.</p>
        <p>33. Gary S. Becker, IrrationalBehavior and Economic Theory, 70 J. POL. ECON. 1, 5, 7
(1962).
rise (because they have limited budgets). As Becker says, "[T]he negative
slope of market demand curves... is equally consistent with individual
irrationality [and individual rationality] and cannot distinguish between them." 34
Consumers can be doing almost anything and this result will still hold.
(Would Posner respond that whatever they do, people are "choosing the best
means to the chooser's ends"? If so, does that theory make any falsifiable
predictions?)</p>
        <p>We stress this relatively minor point because much of the evidence Posner
marshals in support of rational choice models falls into just this category. We
are willing to stipulate that demand curves slope down. But we agree with
Becker's analysis that this result depends not at all on unbounded rationality.
We also think that for analyzing behavior related to law, it is necessary to say
much more, by way of theory, than that demand curves slope down and that
people choose the best means to their ends.</p>
        <p>Posner offers a further criticism of the idea that sound predictions about
law must take into account the bounds we emphasize. He says that random
behavior may often be treated as rational actor behavior because "the
distribution of... random behaviors" may have the same mean as rational actors'
behavior.35 This is a common response to behavioral economics, and
conceivably it could be true; but there is absolutely no reason to think it is, and
(as is usually the case) none is offered by the source of the criticism. Each of
the legal applications discussed in our article is an instance in which the
evidence suggests that people are likely to err in a systematic direction-and
hence that they will behave differently in systematic ways from unboundedly
rational agents.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-7">
        <title>D. EvolutionaryBiology</title>
        <p>Following Karl Popper, Posner is enthusiastic about falsifiability as the
essential feature of a successful scientific theory.36 For present purposes we
intend no quarrel with this idea. Posner is even more enthusiastic about
evolutionary biology, and he thinks that it is important to show that behavior
which departs from traditional economic assumptions is a result of
evolutionary forces. 37 For present purposes we do not intend to quarrel with
evolutionary biology either. (As we stated in our article, the notion that the bounds on
human behavior are adaptive is wholly consistent with our approach.38 ) But it
is not easy to stand, as Posner does, with both Popper and evolutionary
biology. The problem is that Popper's views have been subject to criticism in the
34. Id. at 13.
35. Posner, supranote 1,at 1556.
36. Id. at 1560-61.
37. Id.at 1561-64.</p>
        <p>38. JST, supra note 10, at 1477-78. Thus, we do not disagree with the idea that "while it may
appear that the agents are acting irrationally," it is possible that they are "processing incomplete
information as well as it can be processed." Kelman, supra note 4, at 1583. For instance, the use of
"more general rules of thumb about when information is relevant" may be the best approach under
the circumstances, "even if it results occasionally in the use of information that is not in fact
probative." Id.
philosophy of science, and evolutionary biology is part of the standard
criticism of Popper. The reason is that evolutionary biology is an unfalsifiable
theory.</p>
        <p>We are agnostic on the question whether biology can explain the behavior
we discuss in our article, but we do not think that Posner has shown that it
can. Consider, for example, his claim that the endowment effect (in which
opportunity costs are underweighted relative to out-of-pocket costs) or the
sunk cost fallacy can be derived from evolution.39 No doubt it is possible to
produce an evolutionary model in which paying attention to sunk costs, or
displaying loss aversion, is adaptive. The problem is that it is also possible,
indeed easier, to derive another model in which ignoring sunk costs, and
equating opportunity costs to out-of-pocket costs, is also adaptive (based on
the standard reasoning offered to economics students who are being taught
why sunk costs should be ignored and opportunity costs equated with
out-ofpocket costs). Indeed, there is a long tradition in economics, going back at
least to Milton Friedman, of arguing that such forces are precisely why the
assumptions of economics must be true (that competition or evolution will drive
out the people who don't do what they are supposed to).40 It is difficult to see
what conclusions should be drawn from the fact that evolution can be shown
to produce a behavior andthe absence of that behavior.</p>
        <p>Note that we are not saying that biology is not capable of making
predictions. We are simply saying that the fact that one can tell an evolution-based
story for why a particular behavior might have emerged neither implies the
existence of a falsifiable theory nor (more importantly) is particularly helpful.
To do better economic analysis we need theories that can help us predict when
sunk costs are more likely to be ignored, or when opportunity costs are more
likely to be given full weight. So far, however, such insights have come more
from psychology than from biology.</p>
        <p>We agree that much of the behavior we discuss can be considered a
vestige of our long held instincts. In the case ofbounded willpower, this is
obviously true. The instinct to eat when hungry is present in every species, but it
can get one in trouble when food becomes abundant and exercise
unnecessary. Ancient man needed neither Weightwatchers nor Stairmasters. Aspects
of bounded rationality can also be explained, speculatively but plausibly, in
evolutionary terms; the heuristics and biases literature in psychology is
explicitly based on the premise that the heuristics which emerge are those that
are useful on average.41 Availability is highly correlated with frequency, and
using the availability heuristic may be a sensible strategy in most
circumstances. Behavior that has survived the test of time may or may not have a lot
to do with biology, and while it would be interesting (and in some ways
potentially valuable) to know, a behavioral approach to the economic analysis of
law can proceed whether or not the evolutionary account is right.
39. Posner, supranote 1, at 1562-63, 1565.</p>
        <p>40. MILTON FRIEDMAN, The Methodology of Positive Economics, in ESSAYS IN POSITIVE
ECONOMICs 3, 21-22 (1953).</p>
        <p>41. See JST, supranote 10, at 1477-78.</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan. L. Rev. 1600 1997-1998</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-8">
        <title>E. Smaller Points</title>
        <p>We do not intend here to respond to all of Posner's particular claims. In
many places he has raised good questions for further research, behavioral and
otherwise.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-9">
        <title>1. The ultimatum game and the endowment effect.</title>
        <p>Posner claims that our analysis of the ultimatum game is merely a
"labeling of the result of the game. '42 He prefers an analysis that depends on what
he calls "negative altruism" and "signaling. '43 We are not sure that we
understand the difference between his negative altruism explanation and our own;
here is another case where Posner's "enriched" version of economics is
simply a form of behavioral economics. Where we part company has to do with
signaling. If the signaling explanation has any content, then it would seem to
predict that Responders would accept small offers (such as the fifty cents
offered by the least generous of the Proposers in our study) as long as their
actions were completely anonymous (not known to the Proposer or anyone else
including the experimenter.) Of course, these are exactly the conditions in
our experiments (as well as the other ultimatum game experiments in the
literature). How then can their actions be called signaling-unless they are
signaling to themselves?</p>
        <p>Posner also has various explanations for why we might observe the
endowment effect within a rational choice model. 44 Though he claims that these
explanations are falsifiable, he offers neither evidence in support of them nor
tests he would accept as valid. For example, he points out that an endowment
effect might be rational for a good with no substitutes, and that this
observation might explain the large discrepancies that are observed between
willingness to pay and willingness to accept for environmental goods.45 However,
this observation cannot explain the difference in buying and selling prices for
the coffee mugs in the mugs experiments (since the mugs were for sale in the
campus book store). This suggests that the absence of substitutes cannot be
the only explanation for the observed behavior.</p>
        <p>Posner also suggests that the outcome of the mugs experiments might be
explained by rational habit formation. 46 He does not say exactly how this
works; one possibility is that we are used to thinking, correctly, that we like
the things we own because we picked them out ourselves and have
subsequently become accustomed to them. In the mugs experiment, this is not the
case, but perhaps we act, out of habit, as if the mug had been in our
possession for a long time. This is an interesting speculation, though no empirical
support is offered on its behalf. More important, suppose this explanation is
true. This in no way alters the behavioral analysis. Recall that the mugs
ex42. Posner, supra note 1,at 1564.
43. Id. at 1564-65.
44. Id. at 1565-67.
45. Id.at 1566.
46. Id.at 1566-67.
periments were designed to test (i.e., falsify) a prediction of behavioral
economics, namely that the ultimate allocation of property rights would depend
on the initial assignment of those rights even when transaction costs were
zero. The experimenters were unable to reject this prediction. The
"prebehavioral economic analysis" (to use Posner's phrase 47-one we like!) of this
experiment was surely that the mugs market would be identical to the token
market; that is, the Coase theorem would hold. The behavioral economic
analysis is that the granting of property rights will affect the allocation of
those rights. Posner's "habit formation" hypothesis leads to exactly the same
prediction as the behavioral analysis, and hence to rejection of the Coase
theorem. We are not sure about the hypothesis, but we are pleased to agree on the
prediction, and we are looking forward to a revised treatment of the Coase
theorem in the next edition ofEconomic Analysis ofLaw.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-10">
        <title>Crime, Optimism, andChildbirth.</title>
        <p>Posner has various responses to our interpretation of Jon Gruber's
empirical study of childbirth benefits. 48 Many of these responses are acknowledged
in our original discussion; we expressly stated that the endowment effect is
not the only possible explanation for the empirical findings. One response
that we did not mention-and that strikes us as particularly odd-is Posner's
objection to our stressing the role of one variable (the endowment effect)
while retaining the rest of the rational choice apparatus. Why, he asks, do we
not think that other behavioral factors were not also at play?49 The answer, of
course, is simplicity. We add complexity one step at a time just as he does.
When he suggests that signaling, asymmetric information, risk aversion,
altruism, and other traditional rational choice add-ons provide an alternative
explanation for some phenomenon, he does not say why another factor is not
also present. We do not challenge this way of proceeding. Users of both
methods are forced (because of bounded rationality) to enrich their models
one step at a time. It is, of course, possible to combine two features in one
analysis. This is exactly what we have done in our sunk cost ultimatum game.
We used the mental accounting of sunk costs to predict that Responders
would demand even more (closer to half the amount to be divided) if they had
put up the money themselves. We then attempted to falsify this prediction,
unsuccessfully.</p>
        <p>Still, Posner grants that we are "on to something. '50 He just predicts that
rational choice plus evolutionary biology will prove more useful in
understanding these phenomena. Time will tell.</p>
        <p>47. Id. at 1552.
48. Id. at 1568-70.
49. Id. at 1569-70.
50. Id. at 1570.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-11">
        <title>EmpiricalEvidence.</title>
        <p>Posner says that we make "exaggerated claims for the empirical
robustness of behavioral economics." 5 1 What, he asks, is the theoretical or
empirical basis for supposing that the experimental environment is similar to the real
world? This is a perfectly reasonable question that behavioral economists
have been busy exploring. For example, the original research on both mental
accounting and prospect theory was experimental. Yet these concepts have
proven useful in explaining field phenomena as diverse as the asset allocation
decisions of pension plan participants, the behavior of cab drivers, and the
equity premium puzzle.52 We await similar tests of the alternatives Posner
favors.</p>
        <p>One of the best examples of doing precisely what Posner seems to want is
the study of self-serving bias by Linda Babcock, Xianghong Wang, and
George Loewenstein. 53 Posner misinterprets the results of this study. He is
right, of course, that there is nothing surprising in the fact that each side in a
lawsuit will publicly adopt self-serving analogues. And he grants that there is
such a thing as a role bias. But he is wrong in concluding that this study adds
nothing, or that the survey respondents are just posturing to the researchers (as
well as to their counterparts).5 4 What the authors show is that the answers the
two parties give to the survey help explain the incidence of strikes. Why, if
the two sides are just posturing, would their "meaningless" answers help
explain their actual behavior? It seems that, while posturing to the other side (or
even to the researchers), the bargainers end up posturing to themselves in a
way that they have difficulty overcoming. We also refer readers once again to
the study's own discussion of the problem of strategic behavior and the
evidence against this explanation for the study's findings. 55</p>
        <p>Posner is also incorrect in asserting that the empirical findings on whether
parties bargain around court orders "vindicate rather than challenge
rationality."' 56 Posner reasons that "[i]f a case that has become final through
exhaustion of appellate remedies could have been settled, because the remedy sought
by the plaintiff would cost the defendant more than it would benefit the
plaintiff, the case would have been settled earlier-at the latest after the judgment
in the trial court and before the appeal. '57 We fail to see this reasoning. For
if the defendant thinks there is a good chance a verdict for the plaintiff will be
overturned on appeal, it will have no reason to settle the case prior to appeal,
even if the plaintiffs remedy would cost the defendant more than it would
benefit the plaintiff; the defendant is hoping to have to pay nothing. In any
event, we offer the empirical findings on settlement not to challenge
"rationality," but to suggest that motivations other than material self-interest help to
account for behavior relevant to law-a point to which Posner offers no
objection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-12">
        <title>4. Bureaucratsand debiasing.</title>
        <p>Posner's commentary on our normative analysis is misplaced. We never
suggested that experts would be charged with determining the populace's
"authentic preferences. ' 58 We do not think people have orderly preferences,
so charging anyone with determining them would be a meaningless
assignment. Nor do we suggest that bureaucrats would be immune from bounded
rationality. Indeed, we emphasize precisely the opposite position.5 9</p>
        <p>Posner also faults us for not advocating education and psychiatry to cure
"cognitive quirks and weakness of will. '60 In some circumstances, debiasing
techniques may work for instances of bounded rationality, and this is an
important area for further investigation. We mention several specific
applications in our article. 6 1 Perhaps education and psychiatry can help with
bounded willpower as well, but the problem has been with us at least since the
time of Adam and Eve, and we are not optimistic about a cure any time soon.
In any case, while educators and psychiatrists are doing their best to reduce
the impact of bounded rationality and bounded willpower, we will continue
our efforts to model these phenomena and learn more about how they affect
the economics of the law, and also about how their harmful effects might be
reduced. We hope that no one will attempt to cure bounded self-interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-13">
        <title>Equitypremiumpuzzle.</title>
        <p>Posner suggests that we have succumbed to the hindsight bias; he says we
conclude that people are irrationally risk averse from the fact, known only in
hindsight, that stock returns have been so high.62 We should note that we are
not responsible for declaring the high returns on equities a "puzzle." The
puzzle was declared by rational choice theorists Mehra and Prescott, who
were admirably attempting to make the theory of investment decision-making
falsifiable by asking how large an historical equity premium would be
consistent with reasonable (in their view) levels of risk aversion. 63 They decided
that the returns up to the mid 1980s, when they wrote their article, were too
high. Since their article was written, the equity premium in the United States
58. Id. at 1575.
59. JST, supranote 10, at 1475, 1541, 1543-45.
60. Posner, supranote 1, at 1575.
61. JST, supranote 10, at 1504, 1527, 1544.
62. Posner, supranote 1,at 1572 n.41.</p>
        <p>63. See Siegel &amp; Thaler, supra note 52, at 192, for a discussion. The original article is Rajnish
Mehra &amp; Edward C. Prescott, The EquityPremium:A Puzzle, 15 J. MONETARY ECON. 145 (1985).</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan. L. Rev. 1604 1997-1998
has been even higher than in the past, and a substantial equity premium has
been found in most countries around the world.64 These facts provide
out-ofsample tests of the equity premium puzzle.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>II. KELMAN</title>
      <p>Professor Kelman has considerable sympathy for behavioral economics.
His basic complaint is that far from providing a "fuller, more accurate"
account of human behavior, behavioral economics should recognize that it is
merely one of "a variety of interpretive traditions" engaged in making up
"stories" about social practices. 65 Kelman thinks that behavioral economics
and rational choice theory are "bound together in a form of rhetorical duet or
ritualized dance. '66 In his view, the two therefore stand together in
"irreconcilable mutual dependence. '67 Kelman also contends that behavioral
economics mostly offers "anecdot[es]. '' 68 In Kelman's view, this is not so much
a criticism as a suggestion about the need to avoid "hubris. '69 In light of "the
rich, inexorably overwhelming data with which we have to
deal,...o.pentextured interpretivism" is all that we have.70 His complaint is that behavioral
economists, and the behavioral approach to law and economics, claim to
provide more than that.</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>A. Tropes?</title>
        <p>It is not clear to us why Professor Kelman prefers "interpretive tropes" to
what behavioral economists are trying to do. Kelman does not show that
analysts are unable to develop and to test hypotheses about the relationship
between incentives, including law, and human behavior. We hope to have
suggested a number of promising examples in our article. To be sure, in
many areas we know much less than we should; as we emphasized throughout
the article, one of our most important goals in this project is to outline an
extended research agenda. The solution to this problem is to do more
investigating in order to figure out which hypotheses are true. There is nothing
hubristic about that.</p>
        <p>Kelman thinks that our hope that behavioral economics can supplement
standard economics is wrong because they are in "irreconcilable mutual
dependence. ' 71 We do not understand this objection. While it is surely true that
behavioral economics relies greatly on traditional economic tools (since it is,
indeed, merely an approach to doing economics), behavioral economics is
intended as an improvement because it contains more realistic assumptions
about human behavior.</p>
        <p>Of course Kelman is right to say that some imaginable debates amount to
stylized rhetorical patterns, or "moves," involving those who are not and those
who are committed to traditional rationality assumptions. Psychologists
concerned with bounded rationality may claim to have found hindsight bias; those
committed to unbounded rationality may say that what appears to be hindsight
bias is really not that at all, but rather is a normative judgment about the
appropriate legal regime. Behavioral economists may point to the results of the
ultimatum game as suggesting that people will sacrifice some money to
punish someone who they think has mistreated them; traditional economists may
reply (as Kelman does in their name) that people care about various psychic
goods and are willing to sacrifice their material self-interest to obtain these
goods.72 And so on.</p>
        <p>Some debates may indeed have this form. But taken in this stylized way,
the disagreements between the two camps are awfully tedious. The real task
is to be clear about both the hypothesis being tested and the data, and to go
back and forth between them to see whether the hypothesis in question can be
falsified.</p>
        <p>Consider a few examples. Of course there is nothing to prevent
economists from saying that because people care about "psychic goods," the results
of the ultimatum game are no surprise. But this response has a major defect.
It either makes rational choice theory incapable of generating predictions at
all (because whatever happens can be said to have been a result of the relevant
utility function, constructed ex post), or it converts rational choice theory into
a primitive form of behavioral economics. It is plainly better to do what
behavioral economists are doing, that is, to be explicit about the bounded nature
of self-interest and to see what hypotheses fit the data and might be used to
make predictions, and then test them. Indeed, it is worth remembering that
the ultimatum game was invented precisely to test ideas about resisting unfair
behavior.73</p>
        <p>Or consider Kelman's claim that hindsight bias is not what it appears to
be and the results may well reflect a form of rational Bayesian updating or
normative judgments about liability schemes. 74 This is an intriguing claim
that is difficult to evaluate without seeing the relevant experiments, but
Kelman does not say anything to undermine the central empirical work on
hindsight bias. Consider, for example, Baruch Fischhoff s early study, where
people were asked to say how likely certain events were to happen during
72. Id. at 1585 n.24.</p>
        <p>73. See Werner GUth, Rolf Schmittberger &amp; Bemd Schwairze, An ExperimentalAnalysis
ofUltimatum Bargaining,3 J. ECON. BEHAV. &amp; ORG. 367, 367-68 (1982). Giith, Schmittberger, and
Schwarze, after defining the ultimatum game, proceeded to test people's behavior in the game. See
id. at 373-77.</p>
        <p>74. Kelman, supranote 4, at 1583-84.</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan. L. Rev. 1606 1997-1998
Nixon's trip to China, and then asked to remember their earlier predictions.75
Their remembered probabilities were higher for things that happened. This is
surely a bias. Or consider the work by Colin Camerer and others on the
"curse of knowledge," in which subjects who are told the actual earnings for a
company are unable to give good estimates of what other subjects, who do not
know the outcome, will predict.76 Of course there may be some studies that
attribute some behavior to hindsight bias where some other interpretation is
possible, or even plausible.</p>
        <p>With respect to the equity premium puzzle, Kelman thinks that a
surprisingly high equity premium gives people the profitable opportunity to sell
bonds to unwitting investors and use the proceeds to buy stocks, making a
killing.77 Although this critique is based on standard economic thinking, the
analysis is flawed. The opportunity Kelman identifies is not a true arbitrage
opportunity (meaning without risk); as we suggested in our article, there are
costs to arbitrage in equity markets.78 Investment bankers could try what
Kelman suggests, at their own risk, assuming they could convince investors
that their bonds were risk-free (despite the risks the banks were taking on). If
enough people could do this, then the equity premium might shrink. But this
is precisely the kind of question that behavioral economists have been
successfully addressing, namely, how do the forces of competition and
arbitrageurs interact with quasi rational agents? 79</p>
        <p>Kelman is right to emphasize the importance of sorting out possible
alternative explanations and of understanding what kinds of effects are at work in
different settings. Our basic point is that we have important empirical issues
here, and no reason to think that we are left only with "interpretive tropes" or
"dances." Dancing has its place, but in this context, people should stop
dancing and get to work.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>B. Incompleteness</title>
        <p>Sounding a bit like Posner, Kelman also complains that behavioral
economics is an incomplete theory.80 He objects, for example, that behavioral
economics cannot predict the domain in which quasi rationality will be
important; that we do not know when and how much people will sacrifice their
material interest for the sake of fairness; that the relationship between
legislative behavior and widely shared fairness norms is ambiguous; 81 that the use of
the availability heuristic to explain environmental law leaves many gaps in
understanding the demand for environmental regulation. Generally speaking,
we agree. There is a lot of work to do. To be sure, we already have far more
than "counterstories." Matthew Rabin, for example, has developed a model
of fairness behavior, 82 and there is a good deal of empirical work (cited and
discussed in our article) in this domain. The role of the availability heuristic
in producing regulation has already received considerable attention (again,
examples are cited in our article). This is not to say that all of Kelman's
questions have been answered; as we have repeatedly said, we think there is a
lot more to do.</p>
        <p>Our discussion of the legal examples just mentioned, and the others in our
article, was intended both as an effort to make new progress in behavioral law
and economics, and, equally importantly, an effort to suggest directions for
future research. One of our central points is that behavioral law and
economics is "incomplete" at this extremely early stage. A great deal remains to be
learned about the actual (as opposed to hypothesized) relationship between
law and human behavior. We hope that Posner and Kelman, both occasional
past practitioners of behavioral economics, will join the many people now
engaged in that endeavor.</p>
        <p>81. Kelman misunderstands us when he suggests that we believe that legislators "seek
reelection above all." Kelnan, supra note 4, at 1590. We have only assumed this for purposes ofanalysis.
82. Rabin, supranote 26.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          23.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .at 1559.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          24.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .at 1558.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          25.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .at 1559.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          26. On bounded rationality, see Daniel Kahneman &amp; Amos
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tversky</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Prospect Theory: An Analysis ofDecision UnderRisk, 47 ECONOMETRICA 263</source>
          (
          <year>1979</year>
          ).
          <article-title>On bounded willpower, see Laibson</article-title>
          , supranote
          <volume>20</volume>
          ;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ted O'Donahue &amp; Matthew Rabin</surname>
          </string-name>
          , DoingIt Now orLater (Berkeley Department of Economics Working Paper No.
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>253</lpage>
          , Jan.
          <year>1997</year>
          ); Richard H. Thaler &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>H.M. Shefrin</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>An Economic Theory ofSelf-Control, 89 J. POL. ECON</source>
          .
          <volume>392</volume>
          (
          <year>1981</year>
          ).
          <article-title>(The last two are not cited in our original article</article-title>
          .)
          <article-title>On bounded self-interest, see Matthew Rabin</article-title>
          ,
          <source>IncorporatingFairnessinto Game Theory and Economics</source>
          ,
          <source>83 AM. ECON. REV</source>
          .
          <volume>1281</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
          <article-title>New theoretical work is even emerging that uses psychology to explain the anomalous behavior of stock prices</article-title>
          . See Nicholas Barberis,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Andrei</given-names>
            <surname>Shleifer</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Robert
          <string-name>
            <surname>Vishny</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Model of Investor Sentiment, 49 J. FIN. ECON. (forthcoming Sept</source>
          .
          <year>1998</year>
          ); Kent Daniel, David Hirshleifer &amp;
          <article-title>Avanidhar Subrahmanyam, InvestorPsychology and Securit' Market Under-</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Over-reactions</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>J. FIN</source>
          . (forthcoming
          <year>1998</year>
          )
          <article-title>(manuscript</article-title>
          available at &lt;http://www.cob.ohio-state.edu/dept/fm/joumallabstract.htm#futurearticles&gt;).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. Rev.
          <volume>1597</volume>
          <fpage>1997</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1998</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          51.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          52. See Schlomo Benartzi &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard H. Thaler</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Risk Aversion or Myopia? Choices in Repeated Gambles and Retirement Investments (Nov. 8</source>
          ,
          <year>1997</year>
          )
          <article-title>(unpublished manuscript, on file with the Stanford Law Review); Colin Camerer</article-title>
          , Linda Babcock, George Loewenstein &amp; Richard Thaler, LaborSupply ofNew York City Cabdrivers:
          <source>One Day at a Time</source>
          ,
          <volume>112</volume>
          Q.J. ECON.
          <volume>407</volume>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          );
          <article-title>Jeremy J</article-title>
          . Siegel &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard H. Thaler</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Anomalies: The Equity Premium Puzzle</source>
          ,
          <volume>11</volume>
          J. ECON. PERSP.,
          <source>Winter</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          , at 191.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          53.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Linda</surname>
            <given-names>Babcock</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Xianghong</given-names>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; George
          <string-name>
            <surname>Loewenstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Choosingthe Wrong Pond:
          <article-title>Social Comparisonsin NegotiationthatReflect a Self-Serving Bias, 111 Q</article-title>
          .J. ECON.
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          54.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supranote 1, at 1573.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          55.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Babcock</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>supranote 53</source>
          , at 17-18.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          56.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supranote 1, at 1572.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          57.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          . at 1571-72.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          75.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Baruch</surname>
            <given-names>Fischhoff</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Hindsight --
          <source>Foresight:The Effect ofOutcome Knowledge on Judgment Under Uncertainty, I J. EXPERIMENTAL PSYCHOL</source>
          .
          <source>HUM. PERCEPTION &amp; PERFORMANCE</source>
          <volume>288</volume>
          ,
          <issue>297</issue>
          (
          <year>1975</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          76.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Colin</surname>
            <given-names>Camerer</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , George Loewenstein &amp; Martin
          <string-name>
            <surname>Weber</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Curse ofKnowledge in Economic Settings:An EtperimentalAnalysis</source>
          ,
          <volume>97</volume>
          J. POL. ECON.
          <volume>1232</volume>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          77.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kelman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supranote 4, at 1586-87.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          78. JST, supranote
          <volume>10</volume>
          , at 1485.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          79. See Jeffrey Pontiff, Costly Arbitrage: Evidencefrom
          <string-name>
            <surname>Closed-End</surname>
            <given-names>Funds</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>111</volume>
          Q.J. ECON.
          <volume>1135</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ); Thomas Russell &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard H. Thaler</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Relevance of Quasi RationalBehavior in Competitive Markets</article-title>
          , in RICHARD H. THALER,
          <source>QUASI RATIONAL ECONOMICS 239</source>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ); Andrei Shleifer &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Robert W. Vishny</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Limits ofArbitrage,
          <volume>52</volume>
          J. FIN.
          <volume>35</volume>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          80.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kelman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note 4, at 1580,
          <fpage>1586</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>HeinOnline -- 50 Stan</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. Rev.
          <volume>1607</volume>
          <fpage>1997</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1998</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

