<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Id. at</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cost-Benefit Default Principles</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <email>unbound@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <volume>134</volume>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>46</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics Part of the Law Commons Recommended Citation Cass R. Sunstein, "Cost-Benefit Default Principles" ( John M. Olin Program in Law and Economics Working Paper No. 104, 2000).</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>JOHN M. OLIN LAW &amp; ECONOMICS WORKING PAPER NO. 104 (2D SERIES)</title>
      <p>COST-BENEFIT DEFAULT PRINCIPLES</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein
This paper can be downloaded without charge at:</p>
      <p>The Chicago Working Paper Series Index:
http://www.law.uchicago.edu/Publications/Working/index.html
The Social Science Research Network Electronic Paper Collection:
http://papers.ssrn.com/paper.taf?abstract_id=247884
Preliminary draft 3/6/01
All rights reserved</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Cost-Benefit Default Principles</title>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein* Abstract</title>
        <p>In an important but thus far unnoticed development, federal courts have created a new series of
“default principles” for statutory interpretation, authorizing regulatory agencies, when statutes are unclear,
(a) to exempt trivial risks from regulation and thus to develop a kind of common law of “acceptable risks,”
(b) to take account of substitute risks created by regulation, and thus to engage in “health-health” tradeoffs,
(c) to consider whether compliance with regulation is feasible, (d) to take costs into account, and (e) to
engage in cost-benefit balancing, and thus to develop a kind of common law of cost-benefit analysis. These
cost-benefit default principles are both legitimate and salutary, because they give rationality and sense the
benefit of the doubt. At the same time, they leave many open questions. They do not say whether agencies
are required, and not merely permitted, to go in the direction they indicate; they do not indicate when
agencies might reasonably reject the principles; and they do not say what, specifically, will be counted as an
“acceptable” risk or a sensible form of cost-benefit analysis. Addressing the open questions, this Article
urges that the principles should ordinarily be taken as mandatory, not merely permissive; that agencies may
reject them in certain identifiable circumstances; and that steps should be taken toward quantitative analysis
of the effects of regulation, designed to discipline the relevant inquiries. An understanding of these points
should promote understanding of emerging “second generation” debates, involving not whether to adopt a
presumption in favor of cost-benefit balancing, but when the presumption is rebutted, and what, in
particular, cost-benefit analysis should be taken to entail.</p>
        <p>“Courts should be reluctant to apply the literal terms of a statute to mandate pointless
expenditures of effort. . . . Unless Congress has been extraordinarily rigid, there is likely a basis
for an implication of de minimis authority to provide exemption when the burdens of regulation
yield a gain of trivial or no value.”1</p>
        <p>“It seems bizarre that a statute intended to improve human health would . . . lock the
agency into looking at only one half of a substance’s health effects in determining the maximum
level of that substance.”2
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor, University of Chicago Law School and
Department of Political Science. I am grateful to Elizabeth Garrett, Robert Hahn, Eric Posner, and
Richard Posner for helpful comments on a previous draft.
1 Alabama Power Co. v. Costle, 636 F.2d 323, 360-61 (DC Cir 1979).
2 American Trucking Association v. EPA, 173 F.3d 1027, 1052 (DC Cir 1999).
“It is only where there is ‘clear congressional intent to preclude consideration of cost’
that we find agencies barred from considering costs.”3</p>
        <p>"In order better to achieve regulatory goals - for example, to allocate resources so that
they save more lives or produce a cleaner environment - regulators must often take account of all
of a proposed regulation's adverse effects, at least where those effects clearly threaten serious and
disproportionate public harm. Hence, I believe that, other things being equal, we should read
silences or ambiguities in the language of regulatory statutes as permitting, not forbidding, this
type of rational regulation."4</p>
        <p>“The rule-implicit valuation of a life is high – about $4 million – but not so astronomical,
certainly by regulatory standards, as to call the rationality of the rule seriously into question,
especially when we consider that neither Hepatis B nor AIDS is a disease of old people. These
diseases are no respecters of youth; they cut off people in their working years, and thus in their
prime, and it is natural to set a high value on the lost years.”5</p>
        <p>Risks never exist in isolation. They are part of systems. For that reason,
any effort to reduce a single risk will have a range of consequences, some of them
likely unintended.</p>
        <p>
          If the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) increases security at
airports, so as to make flying safer, it will also make flying less convenient and
more expensive, and thus lead some people to drive instead.6 Flying is much
safer than driving, and hence the FAA’s measures might increase the number of
lives lost on balance. If noise levels are reduced at the Grand Canyon, so that
people can enjoy the area in peace and quiet, air tourism there will have to be
dramatically reduced, so that fewer people can enjoy the area at all.7 If the
Occupational Safety and Health Administration increases regulation of benzene,
a carcinogenic substance, it might lead companies to use an unsafe and perhaps a
less safe substitute; it might also decrease wages of affected workers, and
decrease the number of jobs in the relevant industry. People who have less
money, and who are unemployed, tend to live shorter lives -- and hence
occupational regulation might, under certain circumstances, sacrifice more lives
3 Michigan v. EPA, 213 F.3d 663, 678 (DC Cir 2000).
4 Whitman v. American Trucking Associations (Feb. 27. 2001) (Breyer, J., concurring in part and
concurring in the judgment).
5 American Dental Association v. Martin, 984 F.2d 823, 827 (7th Cir. 1993).
6 See Robert W. Hahn, The Economics of Airline Safety, 20 Harv. . L. &amp; Pub. Policy 791 (1997).
7 Grand Canyon Air Tour Coalition v. FAA, 154 F.3d 4
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">55 (DC Cir 1998</xref>
          ).
than it saves.8 Of course the unintended consequences of risk regulation might be
desirable rather than undesirable – as, for example, where regulation spurs new
pollution control technologies.
        </p>
        <p>Now consider the following cases:
1. The Clean Air Act requires the Environmental Protection Agency
(EPA) to issue standards controlling any substance that “contributes
significantly” to pollution problems in certain areas. EPA issues
regulations governing relevant pollutants, but without considering the
costs of compliance. Industries challenge the regulations on the ground
that cost is a statutorily relevant factor.9
2. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) is
asked to promote fuel economy in automobiles “to the extent feasible.”
NHTSA issues fuel economy standards that are admittedly feasible, in
the sense that no one doubts that they are technologically and
economically possible. But the Coalition for Automobile Safety, a
public interest organization, contends that the effect of the standards
will be to lead manufacturers to produce smaller and more dangerous
cars. The Coalition contends that NHTSA acted unlawfully in failing to
take this effect into account.10
3. A federal statute requires the Occupational Safety and Health</p>
        <p>Administration to regulate toxic substances “to the extent feasible.”11
OSHA interprets this language to require it to consider whether the
regulation is technologically feasible and whether it is “practicable,”
economically speaking, for the industry to comply. OSHA imposes a
regulation that is admittedly “feasible” under this test; but the statute
cannot pass a cost-benefit test, because the benefits are low and the
costs are high. Insisting that costs should be compared with benefits,
industries subject to the regulation complain that it is unlawful.12
8 See Symposium, Risk-Risk Analysis, 8 J Risk and Uncertainty 5 (1994).
9 Cf. Michigan v. EPA, 213 F.3d 663, 678 (DC Cir 2000) (finding cost a permissible factor for the
agency to consider under a similar statute; Lead Industries v. EPA, 647 F.2d 1130 (DC Cir 1980)
(finding cost an irrelevant factor under provisions governing national ambient air quality
standards).
10 See Competitive Enterprise Institute v. NHTSA, 956 F.2d 321 (DC Cir. 1992).
11 29 USC 655(b)(5).
12 ATMI v. Donovan, 452 U.S. 490 (1981).</p>
        <p>In which of these cases has the agency acted unlawfully? The question is
of immense importance, both for regulatory policy and for the relationship
between courts and agencies. One of my main purposes here is to demonstrate
that federal law has now built a novel set of rules for statutory construction: the
cost-benefit default principles. In brief, these principles (1) allow de minimis
exceptions to regulatory requirements; (2) authorize agencies to permit
“acceptable” risks, departing from a requirement of “absolute” safety; (3) permit
agencies to take account of both costs and feasibility; and (4) allow agencies to
balance costs against benefits. Taken as a whole, the cost-benefit default
principles are making a substantial difference to regulatory policy, both because
of their effects in litigated cases and because of their systemic consequences for
regulation.13</p>
        <p>Even when thus specified, however, the default principles raise many
questions. For the most part, the cost-benefit default principles say what agencies
are permitted to do. It is not clear whether the default principles also mean that
where statutes are ambiguous, agencies will be required to do any of these
things. Nor do the principles give much indication of how agencies permitting
”acceptable” risks, or engaging in cost-benefit analysis, might be expected to
proceed. What does it mean to say that agencies are permitted to “consider”
costs? Would it be unlawful for an agency to say that even very high costs are
worth incurring? In what way should the monetary valuation of human life be
constrained? What counts as an acceptable or de minimis risk? How should
agencies deal with the interests of future generations?</p>
        <p>However these questions are resolved, there can be no doubt that the
cost-benefit default principles have emerged as a central part of what amounts to
the federal common law of regulatory policy. Of course most of that common
law, including the incipient federal common law of cost-benefit analysis, will
emerge, and is emerging, from regulatory agencies, which have to decide how
much to regulate, and why.14 Here agencies are the principal architects of what is
13 See Robert Percival et al., Environmental Regulation 425 (4th ed 2000). I discuss the relevance of
the important decision in Whitman v. American Trucking Associations, S. Ct. (Feb. 28, 2001),
below.
14 Hence, for example, different agencies have come up with different dollar figures by which to
value statistical lives; this is a central part of agency-made common law of cost-benefit analysis.
See the table in Matthew Adler and Eric Posner, Implementing Cost-Benefit Analysis When
Preferences Are Distorted, 29 J. Legal Stud. 1105, 1146 (2000). There are also striking variations in
agency selection of discount rate, that is, the treatment of costs and benefits (such as lives saved)
unmistakably a form of common law. But courts will undoubtedly play an
important role,15 and it is in the interaction between agencies and judges that
binding law will emerge. Among my largest purposes here is to understand the
nature of the cost-benefit default principles, their legitimacy, and their future
content.16</p>
        <p>There is a still more general point in the background. The steady
emergence of the cost-benefit default principles signals the impending
conclusion, in all branches of government,17 of a “first generation” debate over
whether cost-benefit analysis is desirable.18 That debate appears to be
terminating with a general victory for its proponents, in the form of a
presumption in favor of their view (signaled above all, perhaps, by President
Clinton’s substantial endorsement of cost-benefit balancing via Executive
Order19). The “second generation” debates raise difficult questions about how
(not whether) to engage in cost-benefit analysis – how to value life and health,
how to deal with the interests of future generations, how to generate rules of
thumb to simplify complex inquiries, how to ensure that agencies do what they
are supposed to do, how and when to diverge from the conclusion
recommended by cost-benefit analysis, how to determine the roles of agencies
and courts in contested cases. My identification and assessment of the
costbenefit default principles is intended as a contribution to these “second
generation” debates. An especially important “second generation” question is
in the future. See Comment, Judicial Review of Discount Rates Used in Regulatory Cost-Benefit
Analysis, 65 U Chi L Rev 1333, 1364-69 (1998) (documenting variations ranging from 2% to 10%).
These issues are treated below.
15 See, e.g., Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (5th Cir. 1991) (striking down agency
regulation of asbestos under statute calling for cost-benefit balancing).
16 It is important to see that many federal agencies do not comply with the apparent requirements
of cost-benefit balancing in existing executive orders. Robert Hahn has shown that compliance is
episodic and that a great deal needs to be done to systematize the process. See Robert W. Hahn et
al., Empirical Analysis: Assessing Regulatory Impact Analysis: The Failure of Agencies To
Comply With Executive Order 12866, 23 Harv J. L &amp; PP 859 (2000). Here as elsewhere, there is a
large difference between law on the books and law in the world. I do not attempt here to address
the important issue of how to ensure compliance with principles that call for attention to costs
and benefits. But judicial review of agency action can serve as a partial corrective at least,
ensuring that in the egregious cases, agency action will be held invalid for failure to comply with
the principles. This point is discussed at several places below.
17 Within Congress, see eg, 5 USC 1532, 1535; within the executive, see note supra.
18 For discussion, see Symposium, 29 J. Legal Stud. 837 (2000); Lisa Heinzerling, Regulatory Costs
of Mythic Proportions, 106 Yale LJ 1981 (1998).
19 See Executive Order 12866, 58 Fed Reg 51735 (1993).
when, if ever, the presumption in favor of cost-benefit balancing is rebutted. I
attempt to make a start in answering that complex question.</p>
        <p>The Article is organized as follows. Part II traces the rise of cost-benefit
default rules in federal law; it begins with the emergence of cost-benefit
principles, outlines statutory formulations, and then elaborates the default rules.
Part III explores the underlying considerations in some detail – what supports
the use of default principles generally and these default principles in particular.
In Part III, I address the general question when the presumption in favor of the
principles might be rebutted. Part IV turns to the question whether agencies
should be required to do what the cost-benefit default principles permit them to
do. Part V deals briefly with a set of issues that an agency must address if it is
going to engage in cost-benefit balancing. Part VI is a brief conclusion.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Considering and Not Considering Costs</title>
      <p>A. From 1970s Environmentalism to the Cost-Benefit State? A Prefatory Note</p>
      <p>I will not attempt to resolve the broad question whether cost-benefit analysis
is a good idea, or whether the many recent initiatives in that direction should be
approved or modified.20 But as background to an understanding of the
costbenefit default principles, a brief discussion is in order.</p>
      <p>The rise of interest in cost-benefit balancing signals a dramatic shift from the
initial stages of national risk regulation. Those stages were undergirded by
might be called “1970s environmentalism,” which placed a high premium on
immediate responses to long-neglected problems, which emphasized the
existence of problems rather than their magnitude, and which was often rooted
in moral indignation directed at the behavior of those who created pollution and
other risks to safety and health.21 Defining aspects of 1970s environmentalism can
be found in the apparently cost-blind national ambient air quality provisions of
the Clean Air Act22 and in statutory provisions requiring “the best available
technology” without an assessment of either costs or benefits.23
20 For a range of perspectives, see Symposium, 29 J. Legal Stud. 837 (2000).
21 See Bruce Ackerman and Richard B. Stewart, Reforming Environmental Law, 13 Colum. J. Env.
L. 171 (1988).
22 42 USC 7409(b).
23 See, eg, 33 USC 1311(b)(1)AA), 42 USC 7411(a)(1), 7412(d)(2), 7475(a)(4), 7502(c)(1).</p>
      <p>No one should deny that 1970s environmentalism has done an enormous
amount of good, helping to produce dramatic improvements in many domains,
above all in the context of air pollution, where ambient air quality has improved
for all major pollutants.24 Indeed, 1970s environmentalism appears, by most
accounts, to survive cost-benefit balancing, producing aggregate benefits in the
trillions of dollars, well in excess of the aggregate costs.25 EPA’s own estimates
suggest that as a result of the Clean Air Act, there were no less than 184,000
fewer premature deaths among people thirty years of age or older in 1990 – and
also that there were 39,000 fewer cases of congestive heart failure, 89,000 fewer
cases of hospital admissions for respiratory problems, 674,000 fewer cases of
chronic bronchitis, and 850,000 fewer asthma attacks.26 EPA finds annual costs of
air pollution control at $32 billion, hardly a trivial number, but less than 4% of
the annual benefits of $1.1 trillion.27 Even if the EPA’s own numbers show an
implausibly high ratio, significant adjustments still reveal benefits far higher
than costs.28</p>
      <p>
        More generally, OMB has, for the last several years, engaged in a full
accounting of the costs and benefits of regulation.29 In general, the report shows
benefits in excess of cost. While the government’s own numbers should be
discounted – agency accounts may well be self-serving – at least they provide a
good place to start.30 In its 2000 report, OMB finds total regulatory benefits
ranging from $254 billion to $1.8 trillion, with total costs ranging from $146
billion to $229 billion, for net benefits ranging from $25 billion to $1.65 trillion.31
A more disaggregated picture is also encouraging. In the transportation sector,
the benefits range from $84 billion to $110 billion, with the costs from $15 billion
to $18 billion, for net benefits of $66 billion to $95 billion.32 In the net benefits
range from $9 billion to $12 billion. Much of the uncertainty stems from
uncertainty about environmental benefits and costs, producing a range from $-73
24 See Economic Analyses at EPA 455-56
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">(Richard Morgenstern ed. 1998)</xref>
        ; Paul Portnoy, Air
Pollution Policy, in Public Policies for Environmental Protection 77, 101-105 (Paul Portnoy and
Robert Stavins eds 2000).
25 Id.
26 Portnoy, supra, at 102-03.
27 Id. at 109.
28 Id. at 113 (showing a benefit-cost ratio of 3 to 1).
29 Available at http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/inforeg/index.html.
30 For a good but sometimes dated overview, see Robert Hahn, What Do The Government’s Own
Numbers Tell Us?, in Risks, Costs, and Lives Saved (Robert Hahn ed 1995).
31 Id.; see 2000 report, charts, table 4.
32 Id.
billion in net benefits to over $1.5 trillion in net benefits.33 For most government
action, however, the benefits seem to exceed the costs.34 As especially good
examples, consider the following regulations, all from recent years:
      </p>
      <p>But even though the overall picture is no cause for alarm, a closer look at
federal regulatory policy shows a wide range of problems. Perhaps foremost is</p>
      <p>260-1900
330-360
50-1,200
110-1200
136-736
0
260-1900
510-580
50-1,200
110-1200
136-736
12,000113,000
260-1900
440-500
50-1,200
110-1200
136-736
-20,00086,000
exceptionally poor priority-setting, with substantial resources sometimes going
to small problems, and with little attention to some serious problems.35 There are
also unnecessarily high costs, with no less than $400 billion being attributable to
compliance costs each year,36 including $130 billion on environmental protection
alone.37 OMB’s own report shows some disturbing numbers: For the next fifteen
years, OSHA’s methylene chloride regulation will have annual costs of $100
million and annual benefits of $40 million38; a regulation calling for roadway
worker protection has benefits of $30 million, but equivalent costs; the
costbenefit ratio for airbag depowering regulation seems bad, though there is
uncertainty in the data39; EPA’s regulation for financial assurance for municipal
solid waste landfills has monetized benefits of $0, but costs of $100 million, and
this is expected for the next fifteen years.40 By way of general illustration,
consider the following table,41 all drawn from recent regulations:
35 This is the theme of Stephen Breyer, Breaking the Vicious Circle (1995).
36 Thomas Hopkins, The Costs of Federal Regulation, 2 J Reg and Soc. Costs 5, 25 tbl. 2 (1992).
37 Paul Portney and Robert Stavins, Regulatory Review of Environmental Policy, 8 J Risk and
Uncertainty 111, 119 n. 1 (1995).
38 Id., table 12.
39 Id.
40 Id.
41 Id.
Pulp and -150 to 0
paper effluent
guidelines
Ozone 0
standards
Child restraint -40 to 40
system
Vessel -220
response
plans
Nitrogen -57 to 29
oxide
emission from
new fossil fuel
fired steam
generating
units
-150 to 0
-150 to 0</p>
      <p>-240 to 0
-235 to 240
-840 to 1190</p>
      <p>-9,200 to -1000
-40 to 40
-220
-40 to 40
-220
-40 to 40
-220
-57 to 29
-57 to 29
-57 to 29</p>
      <p>These figures, drawn from regulations in a single year, show a less than
coherent pattern of regulation, especially when Table 1 is put together with Table
2. According to one study, better allocations of health expenditures could save,
each year, 60,000 additional lives at no additional cost – and such allocations
could maintain the current level of lives saved with $31 billion in annual
savings.42 The point has been dramatized by repeated demonstrations that some
regulations create significant substitute risks43 -- and that with cheaper, more
effective tools, regulation could achieve its basic goals while saving billions of
dollars.44</p>
      <p>In these circumstances, the most attractive parts of the movement for
costbenefit analysis have been rooted not in especially controversial judgments about
what government ought to be doing, but instead in a more mundane search for
pragmatic instruments designed to reduce the three central problems of poor
priority-setting, excessively costly tools, and inattention to the unfortunate
sideeffects of regulation. By drawing attention to costs and benefits, it should be
42 Tammy Tengs et al., Five Hundred Life-Saving Interventions and Their Cost-Effectiveness, 15
Risk Analysis 369 (1995).
43 See John Graham and Jonathan Wiener, Risk vs. Risk (1995).
44 See, e.g., A. Denny Ellerman et al., Markets in Clean Air (2000); Robert Stavins, Market-Based
Environmental Policies, in Public Policies for Environmental Protection, supra, at 31, 35-55.
possible to spur the most obviously desirable regulations, to deter the most
obviously undesirable ones, to encourage a broader view of consequences, and to
promote a search for least-cost methods of achieving regulatory goals.45 Notice
here that so defended, cost-benefit analysis is not only an obstacle to unjustified
regulation; it should be a spur to government as well, showing that it should
attend to neglected problems. If cost-benefit balancing is supported on these
highly pragmatic grounds, the central question is whether that form of balancing
is actually producing what can be taken as policy improvements by people with
diverse views about appropriate policy.</p>
      <p>On these counts, the record of cost-benefit analysis, at least within the EPA, is
generally encouraging.46 Assessments of costs and benefits has, for example,
helped produce more stringent and rapid regulation of lead in gasoline;
promoted more stringent regulation of lead in drinking water; led to stronger
controls on air pollution at the Grand Canyon and the Navaho Generating
Station; and produced a reformulated gasoline rule that promotes stronger
controls on air pollutants.47 In these areas, cost-benefit analysis, far from being
only a check on regulation, has indeed spurred governmental attention to
serious problems.</p>
      <p>
        Cost-benefit analysis has also led to regulations that accomplish statutory
goals at lower cost, or that do not devote limited private and public resources to
areas where they are unlikely to do much good. With respect to asbestos, for
example, an analysis of benefits and costs led the EPA to tie the phase-down
schedules to the costs of substitutes, and also to exempt certain products from a
flat ban.48 With respect to lead in gasoline and control of CFCs (destructive of the
ozone layer), cost-benefit analysis helped promote the use of economic incentives
rather than command-and-control regulation49; economic incentives are much
cheaper and make more stringent regulation possible in the first place. For
regulation of sludge, protection of farmworkers, water pollution regulation for
the Great Lakes, and controls on organic chemicals, cost-benefit analysis helped
regulators produce modifications that significantly reduced costs.50 For modern
government, one of the most serious problems appears to be, not agency use of
45 For many examples, see Economic Analysis at EPA
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15 ref17">(Richard Morgenstern ed. 1996)</xref>
        .
46 See id.
47 See id. at 458.
48 Id. at 458.
49 Id. at 49-86; 131-169.
50 Id. at 458.
cost-benefit analysis, but frequent noncompliance with executive branch
requirements that agencies engage in such analysis.51
      </p>
      <p>Of course cost-benefit analysis is hardly uncontroversial.52 Insofar as both
costs and benefits are being measured by the economic criterion of “private
willingness to pay,” there are many issues. Poor people often have little ability
and hence little willingness to pay; some people will be inadequately informed,
and hence show unwillingness to pay for benefits that would make their lives go
better53; and perhaps regulatory agencies should seek, not private willingness to
pay, but public judgments, as expressed in public arenas.54 Society is not best
taken as some maximizing machine, in which aggregate output is all that
matters. Sometimes a regulation producing $5 million in benefits but $6 million
in costs will be worthwhile, if those who bear the costs (perhaps representing
dollar losses alone?) can do so easily, and if those who receive the benefits
(perhaps representing lives and illnesses averted?) are especially needy.</p>
      <p>In view of these problems, the strongest arguments for cost-benefit balancing
are based, not only on neoclassical economics, but also on an understanding of
human cognition, on democratic considerations, and on an assessment of the
real-world record of such balancing.55 Begin with cognition: People have a hard
time in understanding the systemic consequences of one-shot interventions.56
Unless they are asked to seek a full accounting, they are likely to focus on small
parts of problems, producing inadequate or even counterproductive solutions.57
Cost-benefit analysis is a way of producing that full accounting. Ordinary people
also have difficulty in calculating probabilities, and they tend to rely on rules of
thumb, or heuristics, that can lead them to make systematic errors.58 Cost-benefit
analysis is a natural corrective here. Because of intense emotional reactions to
51 See Hahn, supra note.
52 For a general challenge to quantification, see Lisa Heinzerling, Regulatory Costs of Mythic
Proportions, 106 Yale LJ 1981 (1998).
53 See Adler and Posner, supra note.
54 Many of these points are pressed in Elizabeth Anderson, Value in Ethics and Economics (1993).
55 I attempt to develop this point in Cass R. Sunstein, Cognition and Cost-Benefit Analysis, 29 J.
Legal Stud. 1059 (2000). In the same vein, see Allan Gibbard, Risk and Value, in Values At Risk
94-112 (Douglas MacLean ed 1986).
56 See Dietrich Dorner, The Logic of Failure (1994).
57 Id.
58 Amos Tversky and Daniel Kahneman, Judgment under Uncertainty: Heurisics and Biases, in
Judgment unde Uncertainty: Heuristics and Biases 3, 11 (Daniel Kahneman, Paul Slovic, and
Amos Tversky eds 1982); Roger Noll and James Krier, Some Implications of Cognitive
psychology for Risk regulation, 19 J. Legal Stud. 747 (1990).
particular incidents, people often make mistakes in thinking about the
seriousness of certain risks.59 Cost-benefit balancing should help government
resist demands for regulation that are rooted in misperceptions of facts.</p>
      <p>With respect to democracy, the case for cost-benefit analysis is strengthened
by the fact that interest-groups are often able to use these cognitive problems
strategically, thus fending off regulation that is desirable, or pressing for
regulation when the argument on its behalf is fragile.60 Here cost-benefit analysis,
taken as an input into decisions, can protect democratic processes by exposing an
account of consequences to public view. With respect to pragmatic
considerations, a review of the record suggests that cost-benefit balancing leads
to improvements, not on any controversial view of how to value the goods at
stake, but simply because such balancing leads to more stringent regulation of
serious problems, less costly ways of achieving regulatory goals, and a reduction
in expenditures for problems that are, by any account, relatively minor.61</p>
      <p>
        None of these points suggests that cost-benefit analysis is a panacea for the
problems that I have identified. Everything depends on questions of
implementation, and there are also hard questions about appropriate valuation,
questions to which I shall return. Sometimes respect for rights, or concerns about
irreversibility, justify a rejection of cost-benefit balancing.62 The central point is
that cost-benefit analysis can be seen, not as opposition to some abstraction
called “regulation,” and not as an endorsement of the economic approach to
valuation, but as a real-world instrument, designed to ensure that the
consequences of regulation are placed before relevant officials and the public as a
whole, and intended to spur attention to neglected problems while at the same
time ensuring that limited resources will be devoted to areas where they will do
the most good. So understood, cost-benefit analysis promises to attract support
from a wide range of people with diverse perspectives on contested issues – a
promise realized in the apparently growing bipartisan consensus on some form
of cost-benefit balancing in many domains of regulatory policy.63 An
understanding of this consensus is an indispensable background for approaching
the cost-benefit default principles.
59 See George Loewenstein et al., Risk As Feelings (forthcoming 2001).
60 See Timur Kuran and Cass R. Sunstein, Availability Cascades and Risk Regulation, 51 Stan. L.
Rev. 6
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">83 (1999</xref>
        ).
61 See Economic Analysis at EPA 455-76.
62 TVA v. Hill, 437 US 153 (1978).
63 See Executive Order 12866, 58 Fed Reg 51735 (1993).
      </p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>B. Statutory Terms</title>
        <p>My emphasis here will be on the relationship between these points and
judgemade default rules for statutory interpretation. But judge-made rules have
considerable overlap with approaches taken explicitly by Congress, in statutes
governing health, safety, and the environment. In fact there is undoubtedly an
interaction effect between statutes and judge-made law, with default principles
emerging from statutory formulations and vice-versa. Part of the argument for
the cost-benefit default principles is that they do not reflect purely judicial
polcymakng; those principles fit well with explicit enactments in other areas of
the law. In dealing with the role of benefits and costs, federal statutes tend to fall
in the following categories. I order the statutes roughly in accordance with their
treatment of cost-benefit balancing, beginning with those that most flatly reject it,
and ending with those that unambiguously embrace it.</p>
        <p>1. Flat bans on consideration of costs. Some statutes, exemplifying 1970s
environmentalism, appear to forbid any consideration of cost. Perhaps
the most famous example is the Delaney Clause, which for a long period
prohibited food additives that “induce cancer in man or animal.”64 In the
face of that language, the government sought to permit additives that,
while carcinogenic, created only the most miniscule risks of cancer –
lower risks, in fact than those that would come from eating one peanut
with the FDA-permitted level of aflatoxins every 250 days, and much
lower risks than come from spending about 17 hours every year in Denver
(with its high elevation and radiation levels) rather than the District of
Columbia.65 Nonetheless, the Delaney Clause was taken to forbid any
form of balancing. 66 But a far more important example comes from the
most fundamental provisions of the Clean Air Act, governing national
ambient air quality standards.67 For a long time, the national ambient air
quality standards set under that Act have been understood to be based on
“public health” alone.68 The EPA’s judgment is to be grounded only in
benefits; the cost of compliance is irrelevant.
64 21 USC 376(b)(5)(B).
65 Public Citizen v. Young, 831 F.2d 1108 (DC Cir 1987).
66 Id.
67 42 USC 7409(b).
68 Lead Industries v. EPA, 647 F.2d 1130 (DC Cir 1980). See also Union Electric Company v. EPA,
427 US 246 (1976) (holding that EPA may not consider economic and technological feasibility
when approving or disapproving a state implementation plan). As noted, the issue is currently
before the Supreme Court. See note supra.
2. Significant risk requirements. An alternative formulation is to require the
agency to address only “significant” or “unacceptable” risks. On this
view, risks that do not reach a certain level need not and perhaps may not
be addressed. This is the prevailing interpretation of the Occupational
Safety and Health Act, under both the toxic substance provisions and the
more general provisions of the Act.69 A requirement of a “significant risk”
falls short of cost-benefit analysis in the sense that it is entirely
benefitsbased; costs are irrelevant as such. Once benefits fall below a certain
threshold, regulation is not required and in fact is banned.70 Once benefits
rise above that threshold, regulation is permissible, even if the benefits
seem low in comparison to the costs.
3. Substitute risks and health-health tradeoffs. Some statutes require
agencies to consider whether a regulation controlling one risk would, in so
doing, create a substitute risk. If so, agencies are permitted to decline to
regulate, or to regulate to a different point. These are clear statutory
recognition of health-health tradeoffs, which arise when there are health
concerns on both sides of the equation, from both more and less
regulation.71 Many statutory “consideration” requirements72 have an
unambiguous feature of this sort, for example by requiring agencies
entrusted with reducing air pollution problems to take account as well of
“non-air quality health and environmental impacts.” The Toxic
Substances Control Act similarly requires the EPA to take account of
substitute risks.73
4. Feasibility requirements. Some statutes require agencies to regulate “to
the extent feasible” or “achievable.”74 These expressions are far from
transparent. But as generally understood, such statutes put the focus not
on benefits but solely on costs, and on costs in a particular way: They
forbid an agency from regulating to a point that is neither (a) technically
69 Industrial Union Department, AFL-CIO v. API, 448 US 607 (1980); International Union, UAW v.
OSHA, 37 F.3d 605 (DC Cir 1994).
70 American Trucking Assn. v. EPA, 175 F.3d 1027 (DC Cir 1999), appears to endorse this view for
regulation of air pollutants, on the theory that an interpretation that would allow the EPA to pick
any point it chooses would violate the nondelegation doctrine.
71 See John Graham and Jonathan Wiener, Risk vs. Risk (1995).
72 42 USC 7429 (a) (2) (OSHA); 42 USC 300g-1(b)(4)(B) (Safe Drinking Water Act).
73 Corrosion Proof Fittings v. EPA, 947 F.2d 1201 (5th Cir. 1991).
74 See, eg, 29 USC 655(b)(5).
feasible, because the relevant control technology does not exist, nor (b)
economically feasible, because the industry cannot bear the cost without
significant or massive business failures.75 The line between (a) and (b),
usually treated as crisp and simple, is hardly that; whether a requirement
is technically feasible will usually depend on the level of resources that are
devoted to it. In practice, (a) and (b) therefore overlap in practice, with (b)
serving as a separate category only on those occasions when even with
massive use of existing resources, the technology cannot be brought into
existence. Noteworthy here is the fact that while a significant risk
requirement is entirely benefits-based, a feasibility requirement looks
exclusively at the cost side of the equation. Such a requirement is a
“block” of excessively expensive regulation.
5. “Consideration” requirements. A large number of statutes ask agencies to
“take into consideration” various factors, including cost, in addition to the
principal factor to which the statute draws the agency’s attention (such as
clean air or water). The most common formulation, now standard, asks
the agency to produce the “maximum degree of reduction” that is
“achievable,” after “taking into consideration [1] the cost of achieving
such emission reduction, and [2] any [a] non-air quality health and
environmental impacts and [b] energy requirements.”76 The basic idea
here is that the agency is supposed to qualify the pursuit of the
“maximum” achievable reduction by asking (a) whether the cost is
excessive, (b) whether energy requirements would be adversely affected,
and (c) whether the “maximum” requirement might create health and
environmental harms by, for example, increasing water pollution though
reducing air pollution. Under the Safe Drinking Water Act, EPA is
similarly instructed to back away from the maximum feasible level if the
benefits of the stricter standard “would not justify the costs of complying
with the level.”77
6. Cost-benefit requirements. Several statutes ask agencies to balance costs
against benefits, mostly through a prohibition on “unreasonable risks,”
alongside a definition of “unreasonable” that refers to both costs and
benefits. The most prominent examples are the Toxic Substances Control
75 452 US 490, 508-09 (1976); ADL-CIO v, OSHA. 965 F.2d 962, 980 (11th Cir 1992).
76 42 USC 7429 (a) (2) (OSHA); 42 USC 300g-1(b)(4)(B) (Safe Drinking Water Act).
77 42 USC 300g-1(b)(6).
Act78 and the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act.79 Here
the agency is required to calculate both costs and benefits and to compare
them against each other. If the costs exceed the benefits, regulation is
unacceptable. More recently, cost-benefit analysis is mandated by the Safe
Drinking Water Act Amendments.80 While Congress has thus far resisted
efforts to impose a cost-benefit “supermandate” calling for a general
decision rule based on cost-benefit balancing,81 Congress has enacted
legislation requiring assessment, and public disclosure, of costs and
benefits of major regulations.82 OMB itself has been required to produce
annual accounting of costs and benefits.83</p>
        <p>In the abstract, the distinctions among these kinds of provisions should be
clear enough. A statute that calls for consideration of substitute risks does not
require cost-benefit balancing, because it is more narrowly concerned to ensure
that risks (generally to health) do not increase on balance; under a statute calling
for health-health tradeoffs, it is irrelevant that costs as such exceed benefits. A
statute that requires that regulations be “feasible” is ordinarily taken to entail no
comparison between costs and benefits, but a cost-focused inquiry into what
industry is able to do -- whereas a statute that regulates “significant risks” is
ordinarily taken to entail no comparison between costs and benefits, but a
benefit-centered inquiry into the magnitude of the risk to be addressed.</p>
        <p>Of course many open questions remain, and I will return to those
questions in Part IV. Let us simply take this menu of options as the background
for understanding the nature of the cost-benefit default rules.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>C. The Default Rules Identified: An Overview</title>
        <p>If Congress has been genuinely clear, the legal issue is at an end. But statutory
terms are frequently ambiguous (this is an initial difficulty), and sometimes an
interpretive problem is created by general language that seems not to reflect
78 15 USC 2605 (a).
79 7 USC 136a(a).
80 42 USC 300g-1(b)(3).
81 See Cass R. Sunstein, Congress, Constitutional Moments, and the Cost-Benefit State, 48 Stan. L.
Rev. 247 (1996).
82 5 USC 1532, 1535
83 See, eg, section 625 of the Treasury and General Government Appropriations Act, 1998, PL
10561; section 638(a) of the 1999 Omnibus Consolidated and Emergency Supplemental
Appropriations Act.
anything like congressional consideration of the specific point at issue (this is a
second difficulty). In the face of statutory uncertainty, cases provide support for
each of the following principles. For some of the principles, the law is more
developed than for others; but each of the principles is an identifiable part of
contemporary public law.</p>
        <p>-- Unless Congress has clearly said otherwise, agencies will be permitted to
make de minimis exceptions to statutory requirements, by exempting small
risks from regulatory controls.84
-- Unless Congress has clearly said otherwise, agencies will be permitted to
take costs into account in issuing regulations. In its current form, this
principle means that where statutes are ambiguous, agencies will have the
authority to consider costs as well as benefits.85
-- Unless Congress has clearly said otherwise, agencies will be permitted to
balance the health risks created by regulation against the health benefits
created by regulation.86
-- Unless Congress has clearly said otherwise, agencies will be permitted to
decline to regulate past the point where regulation would be economically or
technologically feasible.87
-- Unless Congress has clearly said otherwise, agencies will be expected to
balance costs against benefits in issuing regulations.88</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>Now let us explore some details.</title>
        <p>D. De Minimis Exceptions</p>
        <p>1. The basic idea. In a series of cases, the D.C. Circuit has developed a
principle authorizing agencies to make de minimis exceptions to regulatory
requirements. The initial case was Monsanto Co. v. Kennedy.89 There the agency
banned acrylonitrile on the ground that it counts as a “food additive,” migrating
in small amounts from bottle into drinks within bottles. The FDA concluded that
the ban was justified on safety grounds, a conclusion that the court found
inadequately justified. But what is more important in the case is the general
language with which the court remanded the case to the FDA. The court stressed
84 See, e.g. Committee on Sensible Transportation, Inc. v. Dole, 826 F.2d 60 (DC Cir 1987).
85 213 F. 2d 663 at XX.
86 This principle appears to underlie American Trucking Association v. EPA, 175 F.3d 1027 (1999).
87 See NRDC v. EPA, 824 F.2d 1146 (DC Cir. 1987).
88 956 F.2d 321 (DC Cir 1992).
89 613 F.2d 947 (DC Cir 1979).
governmental assistance.255 Notwithstanding this risk, there are several possible
grounds for making adjustments. For example, an agency might make a
reasonable upward adjustment if it believes that children are largely at risk
-perhaps because more life-years are at stake, perhaps because children are
unable to protect themselves and hence have a special equitable claim to
government resources.256 A downward adjustment would similarly be lawful if
the agency finds that mostly old people are at risk, so that any extensions of lives
would produce a low level of savings in terms of life-years. Or the agency might
reasonably conclude that special attention should be given to risks faced by poor
people or African-Americans, on the ground that existing injustice is
compounded in a situation in which health and environmental dangers are thus
concentrated.</p>
        <p>Agencies should also be permitted to take into account the fact that people
care about relative economic position, not only absolute economic position, and
thus to adjust market valuations upwards.257 And the agency could reasonably
employ “incidence analysis” to conclude that regulation should go forward
notwithstanding the fact tha benefits exceed costs (see the reference to
distributional considerations in OMB’s “best practices” document, in the
appendix). If, for example, the benefits are $800 million, but enjoyed mostly by
low-income workers, whereas the costs are $900 million, but faced mostly by
consumers generally, it seems reasonable for the agency to go forward, at least if
Congress has not expressly precluded that judgment.</p>
        <p>There is a larger point here. In addition to knowing the benefits and costs
of regulation, it is necessary to know who bears those costs and enjoys those
benefits, and also the particular nature of those costs and benefits. Suppose, for
example, that an occupational safety and health regulation would have a total
cost of $600 million, and that the monetized benefits would be $400 million
(including, let us say, 40 lives saved per year, and hence $200 million in
monetized savings from fatalities averted). Is it clear that this regulation should
not go forward? For various reasons it is not. If the people who are saved are
children or teenagers, the uniform lives saved number might undervalue the
relevant benefits. Equally important: What does the $600 million mean,
concretely? Does it mean that prices will increase, by a little, for many people?
255 See Viscusi, supra note (documenting abuses of this kind).
256 See the acknowledgement of the relevance of life-years in American Dental Association v.
Martin, 984 F.2d 823, 827 (7th Cir. 1993).
257 See Robert Frank and Cass R. Sunstein, Cost-Benefit Analysis and Relative Position, U Chi L
Rev (forthcoming 2001).
That cost might be worth incurring. So too if the consequence of the $600 million
expenditure would be a reduction in annual profits for companies that already
make billions. Or does the cost mean that poor people will lose their jobs? An
ideal cost-benefit analysis would tell us something about the incidence of both
costs and benefits. It makes sense to say that the “bottom line” numbers will not
be decisive when an incidence analysis shows that those numbers should be
adjusted to take account of the identify of the winners and losers. Of course it is
possible to think that we lack the tools to engage in a good incidence analysis, or
that an assessment of distributional issues will be subject to interest-group
manipulation, and hence that the “bottom line” numbers should be used for
pragmatic reasons.258</p>
        <p>While these points give agencies a degree of flexibility, they do not give
them carte blanche, because they operate in limited domains, and because they
come with a duty of reasoned explanation. This duty is procedural, but it is far
more than that. In the Corrosion Proof Fittings case, for example, it is hard to see
how the agency could have justified the extreme cost-benefit ratios that applied
to certain bans on asbestos.259</p>
        <p>3. The discount rate. Perhaps the most difficult issue here, from the
theoretical point of view, involves the selection of the appropriate discount rate.
How should the agency value future gains and losses? In terms of ultimate
outcomes, the choice matters a great deal. If an agency chooses a discount rate of
2%, the outcome will be very different from what it would be an agency chooses
a discount rate of 10%; the benefits calculation will shift dramatically as a result.
If a human life is valued at $8 million, and if an agency chooses a 10% discount
rate, a life saved 100 years from now is worth only $581.260 “At a discount rate of
five pecent, one death next year counts for more than a billion deaths in 500
years.”261 OMB suggests a 7% discount rate (see Appendix); but this is highly
controversial. A key question is therefore: What legal constraints should be
imposed on the agency’s choice?262
258 See Viscusi, Risk Equity, supra note.
259 947 F.2d 1201 (5th Cir. 1991).
260 See Michael Gerrard, Demons and Anegls in Hazardous Waste Regulation, 92 NW L Rev 706,
742-43 (1998).
261 Derek Parfit, Reasons and Persons 357 (1984).
262 Valuable treatments include Richard Revesz, Environmental Regulation, Cost-Benefit
Analysis, and the Discounting of Human Lives, 99 Col L Rev 941 (1999); Comment, Judicial
Review of Discount Rates Used in Regulatory Cost-Benefit Analysis, 65 U Chi L Rev 1333 (1998).</p>
        <p>My basic conclusion is that it is much harder to untangle the theoretical
issue than to identify the appropriate posture of reviewing courts. In this highly
technical area, courts should adopt a posture of deference, requiring agencies
only to produce a reasonable explanation for their choice and to show a degree of
consistency. Part of the reason for deference is the extreme complexity of the
underlying issues. Part of the reason is the risk that an aggressive judicial posture
would contribute to the “ossification” of rulemaking263 -- a particular problem in
this setting, because any particular discount rate will be easy to challenge, with
reasonable arguments suggesting that it is too low or too high.264 To understand
these points, some details are in order.</p>
        <p>Usually statutes are silent on the question of appropriate discount rate. In
fact I have been unable to find any statute that specifies a discount rate for
agencies to follow. On judicial review, the question will therefore involve a claim
that the agency’s choice is arbitrary. Here the national government shows
strikingly (and inexplicably) variable practices. As noted, the Office of
Management and Budget suggests a 7% discount rate,265 departing from a 10%
rate in the 1980s.266 But agencies are not bound by OMB guidelines, and they
have ranged from as low as 3% (Food and Drug Administration, Department of
Housing and Urban development ) to as high as 10% (EPA).267 In fact the same
agency sometimes endorses different discount rates for no apparent reason
-with EPA, for example, selecting a 3% rate for regulation of lead-based paint as
compared to 7% for regulation of drinking water, and 10% rates, respectively,
for regulation of emissions from locomotives.268 Here government practice seems
extremely erratic.</p>
        <p>From the purely economic standpoint, there are serious conundrums
here.269 The impetus for discounting future effects stems from the judgment that
in the context of money, discounting future benefits and losses is entirely
rational, even simple: A dollar today is worth more than a dollar tomorrow.
There are two reasons: investment value (or opportunity cost) and pure time
263 Thomas McGarity, Some Thoughts on “Deossifying” the Rulemaking Process, 1992 Duke LJ
1385.
264 I am therefore disagreeing with the endorsement of “hard look” review in the excellent
Comment, supra note.
265 See OMB, Benefit-Cost Analysis of Federal Programs, 57 Fed Reg at 53520 (1992).
266 See appendix for details; see also Revesz, supra note, at 950.
267 See Comment, supra note, at 1336-37.
268 Id. at 1337.
269 See id. at 1341-1350; see also Appendix for excerpts from OMB’s own account.
preference.270 A dollar today can be invested, and for this reason it is worth more
than a dollar a year from now. An emphasis on the investment value of money
yields a discount rate of roughly 5%-7%. Quite apart from this point, people
generally seem to have a preference for receiving money sooner rather than later.
People value current consumption more than they value future consumption; for
this reason alone, $1000 is worth more today than it is in a decade. An inquiry
into pure time preference produces discount rates of 1%-3%. Though they lead to
different numbers, both points justify discounting future income gains and
losses.</p>
        <p>So far, so good. The problem is that notwithstanding conventional
wisdom among economists, these points are not easily taken to justify a discount
rate for the nonmonetary benefits of regulation (see table 5 for an overview of
such benefits). If a regulation will save ten lives this year, and ten years annually
for the next ten years, it cannot plausibly be urged that the future savings are
worth less than the current savings, on the ground that a current life saved can
be immediately “invested.” The point about investment value, or the
opportunity cost of using capital, seems utterly irrelevant here. With time
preference, things are less clear. Perhaps people would rather save ten lives
today than ten lives in a decade. But it is unclear that this is so; and even if it is,
what moral status would such a time preference have? Almost certainly it makes
sense to say that it would be worse for you to lose your limb now than to lose it
in ten years; in the latter case, you will have ten years of use of the limb. And
probably it makes sense to say that agencies should attend to life-years saved,
not only lives saved. But holding all this constant, the death of a thirty-five year
old in 2004 does not seem worth more than the death of a thirty-five year old in
2044. And since different people are involved, the moral problem is serious: The
preference of the chooser in 2002 is certainly relevant to determining that
chooser’s own fate, and the timing of risks that might come to fruition for that
chooser; but the chooser’s preference cannot easily be used to determine the fate
of someone not yet born.</p>
        <p>These points suggest that, as Richard Revesz suggests, it is important to
distinguish two issues that go under the name of “discounting” and that have yet
to be separated in administrative practice: (a) latent harms, in the form of
exposures whose consequences will occur late in someone’s lifetime; and (b)
harms to future generations.271 It is reasonable to say that latent harms should
count for less than immediate ones, since they remove few years from people’s
lives. Some kind of discount rate is sensible here, although OMB’s 7% figure is
probably too high.272 The case of harms to future generations, or people not yet
born, is altogether different, and in that case the usual grounds for discounting
monetary benefits are quite inapplicable. For this reason some people think that
no discounting is appropriate for the nonmonetary benefits of regulation.273 On
this view, a life-year saved is a life-year saved, and it does not matter, for
purposes of valuation, when the saving occurs.</p>
        <p>But there is a major objection to this way of proceeding: It would appear
to require truly extraordinary sacrifices from the present for the sake of the
(infinite) future. Perhaps the “failure to discount would leave all generations at a
subsistence level of existence, because benefits would be postponed perpetually
for the future.”274 On the other hand, it is not clear that the assumption behind
this objection is convincing. Technological and other advances made by the
current generation benefit future generations as well, and hence impoverishment
of the current generation would inevitably harm those who will come later.275 In
any case there is a hard ethical question here – how much the current generation
should suffer for the benefit of the future – and a judgment against discounting
would not answer that question unless we were sure that as a matter of policy,
we should be engaging in maximizing some aggregate welfare function.276 It is
not at all clear that this form of maximization is the appropriate choice to make.</p>
        <p>At this point it should be clear that these issues are exceedingly complex
and that agencies asked to engage in cost-benefit analysis have no clear path to
an appropriate choice of discount rate. My principal topic, however, is not
regulatory policy, but the implementation of the cost-benefit default principles.
In the face of the underlying conundrums, the most that a reviewing court can
require is a rationale for the agency’s choice that is both articulated and
reasonable. There are several possibilities here,277 suggesting what courts should
and should not do.
272 See id. at 981-87.
273 Id. at 987-1009 (offering a qualified version of this view).
274 See David Pearce and R. Kelly Turner, Economics of Natural Resources and the Environment
223-24 (1990).
275 Revesz, supra note, at 994.
276 Tyler Cowen and Derek Perfit, Against the Social Discount Rate, in Justice Between Age
Groups and Generations 149 (Peter Laslett and James Fishkin eds. 1992).
277 For a good discussion, see Daniel Farber, Ecopragmatism (1999).
! Courts should not require costs and benefits to have the same discount
rate, at least not if costs are to be absorbed in terms of dollars and
benefits will come in terms of fatalities and illnesses averted. It follows
that in Corrosion Proof Fittings case, the court of appeals was quite
wrong to tell EPA to produce an “apples-to-apples comparison, even if
this entails discounting benefits of a non-monetary nature.”278
! Courts should not simply defer to agency decisions as a “policy
choice,” as did one court in an unusually complex setting.279 What is
necessary is some kind of explanation for the choice.
! Courts should acknowledge that good explanations can be given for a
wide range of choices – between, say, a discount rate of 0% (for future
generations, not latent harms) and 7% (OMB’s suggestion). So long as
the agency gives a sensible rationale and departs from it only on the
basis of articulated reasons, courts should respect the choice. The
value judgments here can be reasonably disputed, and they should be
made democratically, not judicially. It follows that in the context of
discount rates, as elsewhere, the common law of cost-benefit analysis is
to be developed at the administrative level, subject only to judicial
review for reasonableness.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this Article I have attempted to identify the cost-benefit default
principles, to defend their use, and to explore their meaning for the future. In the
face of statutory ambiguity, courts are now permitting agencies to refuse to
regulate when a significant risk is not shown; to refuse to regulate beyond the
point where regulation is not feasible; to consider costs; and to engage in a form
of cost-benefit balancing. At their least intrusive, the cost-benefit default rules
allow the agency to go in the suggested direction when the statute is unclear. At
their most intrusive, the principles require the agency to act in the way they
suggest unless Congress has unambiguously said otherwise.</p>
      <p>I have argued on behalf of both the least and most intrusive version of the
cost-benefit default rules, by suggesting that they are likely to give sense and
rationality the benefit of the doubt. At the same time, I have urged that the
argument on their behalf is presumptive only, and that in certain contexts,
agencies have good reasons for embarking on a different course. The question is
278 Corrosion Proof Fittings, supa note, 947 F.2d at 1218.
279 880 F 2d at 465.
whether agencies have been able to suffer a reasonable defense of their decision
to that effect.</p>
      <p>I have also attempted to set out some guidelines for the future, both under
the cost-benefit default principles and under statutes that point in the same
direction. It is necessary for agencies to particularize the idea of “significant”
and “de minimis” risks through quantitative guidelines. A large point here is
that the statistical probability of harm is not all that matters; the size of the
exposed population is important as well. “Feasibility” is not an off-on switch,
and here too agencies should specify what they understand the term to mean,
beginning with the admittedly vague notion that massive dislocations would be
both necessary and sufficient to show that regulation is not feasible. We have
seen that with respect to valuation of life and health, market measures can
provide a good start, from which agencies are entitled to make reasonable
adjustments. We have also seen that the most difficult issue involves selection of
the appropriate discount rate. Reviewing courts should not require agencies to
apply the same discount rate to life and health that they apply to money; with
respect to discounting, there are good reasons to distinguish money from other
goods. The most that courts can do is to impose ceilings and floors on agency
judgments, by requiring a good rationale for whatever discount rate is chosen.</p>
      <p>The most general conclusion, signaled by the rise of the cost-benefit
default principles, is that the nation is nearing the end of a “first generation”
debate about whether to adopt a presumption in favor of cost-benefit balancing,
and rapidly moving into a “second generation” debate about when the
presumption is rebutted, and about what cost-benefit analysis specifically entails.
If cost-benefit analysis is to be defended, it is not because of especially
controversial judgments of value, but because of a belief that regulatory action
should be judged largely in terms of its consequences.280 Suitably specified and
understood, the cost-benefit default principles should be regarded, not as a
technique for stalling desirable regulation, but as a pragmatic effort to ensure
that regulation responds to serious problems rather than to trivial or imaginary
ones. And if they are seen in these terms, the cost-benefit default principles
operate not only a foundation for deterring regulation that promises to do less
280 Of course there is no way of assessing consequences, or even identifying them, that is entirely
neutral on evaluative questions. What I mean to suggest is that agreed-upon understandings can
do the necessary work here. See the outline of the track record of cost-benefit analysis at EPA,
supra.
281 See the account, supra, of instances in which cost-benefit balancing spurred regulatory action.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>Appendix: Excerpts from OMB Guidance on Cost-Benefit Analysis</title>
      <p>The following consists of excerpts from OMB’s “best practices” guidelines
for cost-benefit analysis. Because the understanding of cost-benefit analysis is so
much better developed within OMB than within courts and the legal culture, it is
worth attending, with some care, to OMB’s suggestions. I have challenged some
of OMB’s claims – especially on the appropriate discount rate – but there is no
question that OMB has offered a helpful and thoughful treatment of many of the
underlying problems.</p>
      <p>January 11, 1996</p>
      <p>Economic Analysis of Federal Regulations under Executive Order 12866</p>
      <sec id="sec-5-1">
        <title>III. ANALYSIS OF BENEFITS AND COSTS</title>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>A. General Principles
3. Discounting. One of the problems that arises in developing a
benefitcost analysis is that the benefits and costs often occur in different time periods.
When this occurs, it is not appropriate, when comparing benefits and costs, to
simply add up the benefits and costs accruing over time. Discounting takes
account of the fact that resources (goods or services) that are available in a given
year are worth more than the identical resources available in a later year. One
reason for this is that resources can be invested so as to return more resources
later. In addition, people tend to be impatient and to prefer earlier consumption
over later consumption.</p>
        <p>(a) Basic considerations. Constant-dollar benefits and costs must be
discounted to present values before benefits and costs in different years can be
added together to determine overall net benefits. To obtain constant dollar
estimates, benefit and cost streams in nominal dollars should be adjusted to
correct for inflation. The basic guidance on discount rates for regulatory and
other analyses is provided in OMB Circular A-94. The discount rate specified in
that guidance is intended to be an approximation of the opportunity cost of
capital, which is the before-tax rate of return to incremental private investment.
The Circular A-94 rate, which was revised in 1992 based on an extensive review
and public comment, reflects the rates of return on low yielding forms of capital,
such as housing, as well as the higher rates of returns yielded by corporate
capital. This average rate currently is estimated to be 7 percent in real terms (i.e.,
after adjusting for inflation). . . .</p>
        <p>Even those benefits and costs that are hard to quantify in monetary terms
should be discounted.. . . .</p>
        <p>(b) Additional considerations. Modern research in economic theory has
established a preferred model for discounting, sometimes referred to as the
shadow price approach. The basic concept is that economic welfare is ultimately
determined by consumption; investment affects welfare only to the extent that it
affects current and future consumption. Thus, any effect that a government
program has on public or private investment must be converted to an associated
stream of effects on consumption before being discounted.</p>
        <p>Converting investment-related benefits and costs to their
consumptionequivalents as required by this approach involves calculating the "shadow price
of capital." This shadow price reflects the present value of the future changes in
consumption arising from a marginal change in investment, using the
consumption rate of interest (also termed the rate of time preference) as the
discount rate. . . .</p>
        <p>4. Treatment of Risk and Uncertainty. . . . Often risks, benefits, and costs
are measured imperfectly because key parameters are not known precisely;
instead, the economic analysis must rely upon statistical probability distributions
for the values of parameters. Both the inherent lack of certainty about the
consequences of a potential hazard (for example, the odds of contracting cancer)
and the lack of complete knowledge about parameter values that define risk
relationships (for example, the relationship between presence of a carcinogen in
the food supply and the rate of absorption of the carcinogen) should be
considered.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>(a) Risk assessment. . . . Data relating to effects that can be identified may
be sketchy, incomplete, or subject to measurement error or statistical bias.
Exposures and sensitivities to risks may vary considerably across the affected
population. These difficulties can lead, for example, to a range of quantitative
estimates of risk in health and ecological risk assessments that can span several
orders of magnitude. Uncertainties in cost estimates also can be significant, in
particular because of lack of experience with the adjustments that markets can
make to reduce regulatory burdens, the difficulty of identifying and quantifying
opportunity cost, and the potential for enhanced or retarded technical
innovation. All of these concerns should be reflected in the uncertainties about
outcomes that should be incorporated in the analysis.</p>
        <p>The treatment of uncertainty in developing risk, benefit, and cost
information also must be guided by the principles of full disclosure and
transparency, as with other elements of an EA. Data, models, and their
implications for risk assessment should be identified in the risk characterization.
. . . .</p>
        <p>In order for the EA to evaluate outcomes involving risks, risk assessments
must provide some estimates of the probability distribution of risks with and
without the regulation. Whenever it is possible to quantitatively characterize the
probability distributions, some estimates of central tendency (e.g., mean and
median) must be provided in addition to ranges, variances, specified low-end
and high-end percentile estimates, and other characteristics of the distribution.</p>
        <p>Overall risk estimates cannot be more precise than their most uncertain
component. Thus, risk estimates should be reported in a way that reflects the
degree of uncertainty present in order to prevent creating a false sense of
precision. The accuracy with which quantitative estimates are reported must be
supported by the quality of the data and models used. In all cases, the level of
precision should be stated explicitly.</p>
        <p>Overall uncertainty is typically a consequence of uncertainties about many
different factors. Appropriate statistical techniques should be used to combine
uncertainties about separate factors into an overall probability distribution for a
risk. . . .</p>
        <p>Uncertainty may arise from a variety of fundamentally different sources,
including lack of data, variability in populations or natural conditions,
limitations in fundamental scientific knowledge (both social and natural)
resulting in lack of knowledge about key relationships, or fundamental
unpredictability of various phenomena. The nature of these different sources
may suggest different approaches. For example, when uncertainty is due to lack
of information, one policy alternative may be to defer action pending further
study. One factor that may help determine whether further study is justifiable as
a policy alternative is an evaluation of the potential benefits of the information
relative to the resources needed to acquire it and the potential costs of delaying
action. When uncertainty is due largely to observable variability in populations
or natural conditions, one policy alternative may be to refine targeting, that is, to
differentiate policies across key subgroups. Analysis of such policies should
consider the incremental benefits of improved efficiency from targeting, any
incremental costs of monitoring and enforcement, and changes in the
distribution of benefits and costs. . . .</p>
        <p>7. Nonmonetized Benefits and Costs. Presentation of monetized benefits
and costs is preferred where acceptable estimates are possible. However,
monetization of some of the effects of regulations is often difficult if not
impossible, and even the quantification of some effects may not be easy. Effects
that cannot be fully monetized or otherwise quantified should be described.
Those effects that can be quantified should be presented along with qualitative
information to characterize effects that are not quantified.</p>
        <p>Irrespective of the presentation of monetized benefits and costs, the EA
should present available physical or other quantitative measures of the effects of
the alternative actions to help decisionmakers understand the full effects of
alternative actions. These include the magnitude, timing, and likelihood of
impacts, plus other relevant dimensions (e.g., irreversibility and uniqueness). For
instance, assume the effects of a water quality regulation include increases in fish
populations and habitat over the affected stream segments and that it is not
possible to monetize such effects. It would then be appropriate to describe the
benefits in terms of stream miles of habitat improvement and increases in fish
population by species (as well as to describe the timing and likelihood of such
effects, etc.). . . .</p>
        <p>8. Distributional Effects and Equity. Those who bear the costs of a
regulation and those who enjoy its benefits often are not the same people. The
term "distributional effects" refers to the description of the net effects of a
regulatory alternative across the population and economy, divided up in various
ways (e.g., income groups, race, sex, industrial sector). Benefits and costs of a
regulation may be distributed unevenly over time, perhaps spanning several
generations. Distributional effects may also arise through "transfer payments"
arising from a regulatory action. For example, the revenue collected through a
fee, surcharge, or tax (in excess of the cost of any service provided) is a transfer
payments.</p>
        <p>Where distributive effects are thought to be important, the effects of
various regulatory alternatives should be described quantitatively to the extent
possible, including their magnitude, likelihood, and incidence of effects on
particular groups. Agencies should be alert for situations in which regulatory
alternatives result in significant changes in treatment or outcomes for different
groups. Effects on the distribution of income that are transmitted through
changes in market prices can be important, albeit sometimes difficult to assess.
The EA should also present information on the streams of benefits and costs over
time in order to provide a basis for judging intertemporal distributional
consequences, particularly where intergenerational effects are concerned.</p>
        <p>There are no generally accepted principles for determining when one
distribution of net benefits is more equitable than another. Thus, the EA should
be careful to describe distributional effects without judging their fairness. These
descriptions should be broad, focusing on large groups with small effects per
capita as well as on small groups experiencing large effects per capita. Equity
issues not related to the distribution of policy effects should be noted when
important and described quantitatively to the extent feasible.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-2">
        <title>B. Benefit Estimates</title>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>The calculation of benefits (including benefits of risk reductions) should
reflect the full probability distribution of potential consequences. For example,
extreme safety or health results should be weighted, along with other possible
outcomes, by estimates of their probability of occurrence based on the available
evidence to estimate the expected result of a proposed regulation. To the extent
possible, the probability distributions of benefits should be presented. Extreme
estimates should be presented as complements to central tendency and other
estimates. If fundamental scientific disagreement or lack of knowledge precludes
construction of a scientifically defensible probability distribution, benefits should
be described under plausible alternative assumptions, along with a
characterization of the evidence underlying each alternative view. . . .</p>
        <p>1. General Considerations. The concept of "opportunity cost" is the
appropriate construct for valuing both benefits and costs. The principle of
"willingness-to-pay" captures the notion of opportunity cost by providing an
aggregate measure of what individuals are willing to forgo to enjoy a particular
benefit. Market transactions provide the richest data base for estimating benefits
based on willingness-to-pay, as long as the goods and services affected by a
potential regulation are traded in markets. It is more difficult to estimate benefits
where market transactions are difficult to monitor or markets do not exist.
Regulatory analysts in these cases need to develop appropriate proxies that
simulate market exchange. Indeed, the analytical process of deriving benefit
estimates by simulating markets may suggest alternative regulatory strategies
that create such markets.</p>
        <p>Either willingness-to-pay (WTP) or willingness-to-accept (WTA) can
provide an appropriate measure of benefits, depending on the allocation of
property rights. The common preference for WTP over WTA measures is based
on the empirical difficulties in estimating the latter. . . .</p>
        <p>2. Principles for Valuing Benefits Directly Traded in Markets. Ordinarily,
goods and services are to be valued at their market prices. However, in some
instances, the market value of a good or service may not reflect its true value to
society.</p>
        <p>If a regulatory alternative involves changes in such a good or service, its
monetary value for purposes of benefit-cost analysis should be derived using an
estimate of its true value to society (often called its "shadow price"). For example,
suppose a particular air pollutant damages crops. One of the benefits of
controlling that pollutant will be the value of the crop saved as a result of the
controls. That value would typically be determined by reference to the price of
the crop. If, however, the price of that crop is held above the unregulated market
equilibrium price by a government price-support program, an estimate based on
the support price would overstate the value of the benefit of controlling the
pollutant. . . .</p>
        <p>In other cases, market prices could understate social values, for example
where production of a particular good also provides opportunities for improving
basic knowledge.</p>
        <p>3. Principles for Valuing Benefits That Are Indirectly Traded in Markets. .
. .</p>
        <p>A variety of methods have been developed for estimating indirectly
traded benefits. Generally, these methods apply statistical techniques to distill
from observable market transactions the portion of willingness-to-pay that can
be attributed to the benefit in question. Examples include estimates of the value
of environmental amenities derived from travel-cost studies, hedonic price
models that measure differences or changes in the value of land, and statistical
studies of occupational-risk premiums in wage rates. For all these methods, care
is needed in designing protocols for reliably estimating benefits or in adapting
the results of previous studies to new applications. The use of occupational-risk
premiums can be a source of bias because the risks, when recognized, may be
voluntarily rather than involuntarily assumed, and the sample of individuals
upon which premium estimates are based may be skewed toward more
risktolerant people.</p>
        <p>Contingent-valuation methods have become increasingly common for
estimating indirectly traded benefits, but the reliance of these methods on
hypothetical scenarios and the complexities of the goods being valued by this
technique raise issues about its accuracy in estimating willingness to pay
compared to methods based on (indirect) revealed preferences. Accordingly,
value estimates derived from contingent-valuation studies require greater
analytical care than studies based on observable behavior. For example, the
contingent valuation instrument must portray a realistic choice situation for
respondents -- where the hypothetical choice situation corresponds closely with
the policy context to which the estimates will be applied. The practice of
contingent valuation is rapidly evolving, and agencies relying upon this tool for
valuation should judge the reliability of their benefit estimates using this
technique in light of advances in the state of the art.</p>
        <p>4. Principles and Methods for Valuing Goods That Are Not Traded
Directly or Indirectly in Markets. Some types of goods, such as preserving
environmental or cultural amenities apart from their use and direct enjoyment by
people, are not traded directly or indirectly in markets. The practical obstacles to
accurate measurement are similar to (but generally more severe than) those
arising with respect to indirect benefits, principally because there are few or no
related market transactions to provide data for willingness-to-pay estimates.</p>
        <p>For many of these goods, particularly goods providing "nonuse" values,
contingent-valuation methods may provide the only analytical approaches
currently available for estimating values. The absence of observable and
replicable behavior with respect to the good in question, combined with the
complex and often unfamiliar nature of the goods being valued, argues for great
care in the design and execution of surveys, rigorous analysis of the results, and
a full characterization of the uncertainties in the estimates to meet best practices
in the use of this method.
(b) Fatality risks. . . .</p>
        <p>Reductions in fatality risks as a result of government action are best
monetized according to the willingness-to-pay approach. . . . Another way of
expressing reductions in fatality risks is in terms of the "value of statistical
lifeyears extended" (VSLY). For example, if a regulation protected individuals
whose average remaining life expectancy was 40 years, then a risk reduction of
one fatality would be expressed as 40 life-years extended. This approach allows
distinctions in risk-reduction measures based on their effects on longevity.
However, this does not automatically mean that regulations with greater
numbers of life-years extended will be favored over regulations with fewer
numbers of life-years extended. VSL and VSLY ultimately depend on the
willingness to pay for various forms of mortality risk reduction, not just
longevity considerations.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>To value reductions in more voluntarily incurred risks (e.g., those related
to motorcycling without a helmet) that are "high," agencies should consider
using lower values than those applied to reductions in involuntary risk. When a
higher-risk option is chosen voluntarily, those who assume the risk may be more
risk-tolerant, i.e., they may place a relatively lower value on avoiding risks.
Empirical studies of risk premiums in higher-risk occupations suggest that
reductions in risks for voluntarily assumed high risk jobs (e.g., above 10-4
annually) are valued less than equal risk reductions for lower-risk jobs.
However, when occupational choices are limited, the occupational risks incurred
may be more involuntary in nature.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-3">
        <title>C. Cost Estimates . . .</title>
        <p>As with benefit estimates, the calculation of costs should reflect the full
probability distribution of potential consequences. Extreme values should be
weighted, along with other possible outcomes, by estimates of their probability
of occurrence based on the available evidence to estimate the expected result of a
proposed regulation. If fundamental scientific disagreement or lack of
knowledge precludes construction of a scientifically defensible probability
distribution, costs should be described under plausible alternative assumptions,
along with a characterization of the evidence underlying each alternative view. .
. .</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-4">
        <title>Readers with comments should address them to:</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-5">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein</title>
        <p>Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor
University of Chicago Law School
1111 East 60th Street
Chicago, IL 60637</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-5-6">
        <title>Chicago Working Papers in Law and Economics</title>
        <p>(Second Series)
1. William M. Landes, Copyright Protection of Letters, Diaries and Other</p>
        <p>Unpublished Works: An Economic Approach (July 1991).
2. Richard A. Epstein, The Path to The T. J. Hooper: The Theory and History of</p>
        <p>Custom in the Law of Tort (August 1991).
3. Cass R. Sunstein, On Property and Constitutionalism (September 1991).
4. Richard A. Posner, Blackmail, Privacy, and Freedom of Contract (February
1992).
5. Randal C. Picker, Security Interests, Misbehavior, and Common Pools
(February 1992).
6. Tomas J. Philipson &amp; Richard A. Posner, Optimal Regulation of AIDS (April
1992).
7. Douglas G. Baird, Revisiting Auctions in Chapter 11 (April 1992).
8. William M. Landes, Sequential versus Unitary Trials: An Economic Analysis
(July 1992).
9. William M. Landes &amp; Richard A. Posner, The Influence of Economics on</p>
        <p>Law: A Quantitative Study (August 1992).
10. Alan O. Sykes, The Welfare Economics of Immigration Law: A Theoretical</p>
        <p>Survey With An Analysis of U.S. Policy (September 1992).
11. Douglas G. Baird, 1992 Katz Lecture: Reconstructing Contracts (November
1992).
12. Gary S. Becker, The Economic Way of Looking at Life (January 1993).
13. J. Mark Ramseyer, Credibly Committing to Efficiency Wages: Cotton</p>
        <p>Spinning Cartels in Imperial Japan (March 1993).
14. Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law (April 1993).
15. Richard A. Posner, What Do Judges and Justices Maximize? (The Same Thing</p>
        <p>Everyone Else Does) (April 1993).
16. Lucian Arye Bebchuk and Randal C. Picker, Bankruptcy Rules, Managerial</p>
        <p>Entrenchment, and Firm-Specific Human Capital (August 1993).
17. J. Mark Ramseyer, Explicit Reasons for Implicit Contracts: The Legal Logic to
the Japanese Main Bank System (August 1993).
18. William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, The Economics of Anticipatory</p>
        <p>Adjudication (September 1993).
19. Kenneth W. Dam, The Economic Underpinnings of Patent Law (September
1993).
20. Alan O. Sykes, An Introduction to Regression Analysis (October 1993).
21. Richard A. Epstein, The Ubiquity of the Benefit Principle (March 1994).
22. Randal C. Picker, An Introduction to Game Theory and the Law (June 1994).
23. William M. Landes, Counterclaims: An Economic Analysis (June 1994).
86. Douglas G. Baird and Edward R. Morrison, Optimal Timing and Legal
Decisionmaking: The Case of the Liquidation Decision in Bankruptcy
(October 1999)
87. Gertrud M. Fremling and Richard A. Posner, Market Signaling of Personal</p>
        <p>Characteristics (November 1999)
88. Matthew D. Adler and Eric A. Posner, Implementing Cost-Benefit Analysis</p>
        <p>When Preferences Are Distorted (November 1999)
89. Richard A. Posner, Orwell versus Huxley: Economics, Technology, Privacy,
and Satire (November 1999)
90. David A. Weisbach, Should the Tax Law Require Current Accrual of Interest
on Derivative Financial Instruments? (December 1999)
91. Cass R. Sunstein, The Law of Group Polarization (December 1999)
92. Eric A. Posner, Agency Models in Law and Economics (January 2000)
93. Karen Eggleston, Eric A. Posner, and Richard Zeckhauser, Simplicity and</p>
        <p>Complexity in Contracts (January 2000)
94. Douglas G. Baird and Robert K. Rasmussen, Boyd’s Legacy and Blackstone’s</p>
        <p>Ghost (February 2000)
95. David Schkade, Cass R. Sunstein, Daniel Kahneman, Deliberating about</p>
        <p>Dollars: The Severity Shift (February 2000)
96. Richard A. Posner and Eric B. Rasmusen, Creating and Enforcing Norms,
with Special Reference to Sanctions (March 2000)
97. Douglas Lichtman, Property Rights in Emerging Platform Technologies
(April 2000)
98. Cass R. Sunstein and Edna Ullmann-Margalit, Solidarity in Consumption
(May 2000)
99. David A. Weisbach, An Economic Analysis of Anti-Tax Avoidance Laws
(May 2000)
100. Cass R. Sunstein, Human Behavior and the Law of Work (June 2000)
101. William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, Harmless Error (June 2000)
102. Robert H. Frank and Cass R. Sunstein, Cost-Benefit Analysis and Relative</p>
        <p>Position (August 2000)
103. Eric A. Posner, Law and the Emotions (September 2000)
104. Cass R. Sunstein, Cost-Benefit Default Principles (October 2000)</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          24.
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. Mark</surname>
            <given-names>Ramseyer</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Market for Children: Evidence from Early Modern Japan</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          25.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Robert</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gertner</surname>
            and
            <given-names>Geoffrey P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>Settlement Escrows</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>August 1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          26.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kenneth</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dam</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Some Economic Considerations in the Intellectual Property Protection of Software (August</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          27.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Rules and Rulelessness, (
          <year>October 1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          28. David Friedman,
          <article-title>More Justice for Less Money: A Step Beyond Cimino</article-title>
          (
          <year>December 1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          29. Daniel Shaviro,
          <article-title>Budget Deficits and the Intergenerational Distribution of Lifetime Consumption</article-title>
          (
          <year>January 1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          30.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Baird,
          <source>The Law and Economics of Contract Damages (February</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          31. Daniel Kessler, Thomas Meites, and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Geoffrey P.</given-names>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Explaining Deviations from the Fifty Percent Rule: A Multimodal Approach to the Selection of Cases for Litigation (March</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          32.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Geoffrey</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Das Kapital: Solvency Regulation of the American Business Enterprise (April</article-title>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          33. Richard Craswell, Freedom of Contract (
          <year>August 1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          34.
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. Mark</surname>
            <given-names>Ramseyer</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Public
          <string-name>
            <surname>Choice</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>November 1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          35.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kenneth</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dam</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Intellectual Property in an Age of Software and Biotechnology (November</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          36.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Social Norms and Social
          <string-name>
            <surname>Roles</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>January 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          37.
          <string-name>
            <surname>J. Mark</surname>
          </string-name>
          Ramseyer and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Eric B. Rasmusen</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Judicial Independence in Civil Law Regimes: Econometrics from Japan (
          <year>January 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          38.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Epstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Transaction Costs and Property Rights: Or Do Good Fences Make Good Neighbors? (March</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          39.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , The Cost-Benefit
          <string-name>
            <surname>State</surname>
          </string-name>
          (May
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          40.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Landes and Richard A. Posner, The Economics of Legal Disputes Over the Ownership of Works of Art</article-title>
          and Other
          <string-name>
            <surname>Collectibles</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>July 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          41.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr. and
          <string-name>
            <surname>David</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Mustard</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Crime, Deterrence, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Right-toCarry Concealed Handguns</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>August 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          42.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Health-Health Tradeoffs</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>September 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          43. G.
          <article-title>Baird, The Hidden Virtues of Chapter 11: An Overview of the Law and Economics of Financially Distressed Firms (March</article-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          44. Richard A. Posner, Community, Wealth, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Equality</surname>
          </string-name>
          (March
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          45.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William M. Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Art of Law and Economics: An Autobiographical Essay (March</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          46.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Behavioral Analysis of Law (April</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          47.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr. and Kermit Daniel, Term Limits and
          <article-title>Electoral Competitiveness: Evidence from California's State Legislative Races</article-title>
          (May
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          48.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Randal</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picker</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Simple Games in a Complex World: A Generative Approach to the Adoption of Norms (June</article-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          49.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Epstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Contracts Small and Contracts Large: Contract Law through the Lens of Laissez-Faire</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          50.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Daniel Kahneman, and David Schkade,
          <article-title>Assessing Punitive Damages (with Notes on Cognition and Valuation in Law)</article-title>
          (
          <year>December 1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          51.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William M. Landes</surname>
            , Lawrence Lessig, and
            <given-names>Michael E.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Solimine</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Judicial Influence:
          <article-title>A Citation Analysis of Federal Courts of Appeals Judges</article-title>
          (
          <year>January 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          52.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jr.</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>A Simple Explanation for Why Campaign Expenditures are Increasing: The Government is Getting Bigger (</article-title>
          <year>February 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          53.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A. Posner, Values and Consequences: An Introduction to Economic Analysis of Law (March</article-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          54.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Denise DiPasquale and Edward L. Glaeser</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Incentives and Social Capital: Are Homeowners Better Citizens? (
          <year>April 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          55.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Christine</surname>
            <given-names>Jolls</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
            , and Richard Thaler,
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </string-name>
          Behavioral Approach to Law and Economics (May
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          56.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr.,
          <source>Does a Helping Hand Put Others</source>
          At Risk?: Affirmative Action, Police Departments, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Crime</surname>
          </string-name>
          (May
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          57.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
            and
            <given-names>Edna</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ullmann-Margalit</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Second-Order
          <string-name>
            <surname>Decisions</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>June 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          58.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jonathan</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Karpoff and John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr., Punitive Damages:
          <article-title>Their Determinants, Effects on Firm Value, and the Impact of Supreme Court and Congressional Attempts to Limit Awards (</article-title>
          <year>July 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          59.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kenneth</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dam</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Self-Help in the Digital Jungle</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          60.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr.,
          <article-title>How Dramatically Did Women's Suffrage Change the Size and Scope of Government?</article-title>
          (
          <year>September 1998</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          61.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kevin</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A. Kordana and Eric A</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Positive Theory of Chapter</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          (
          <year>October 1998</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          62.
          <string-name>
            <surname>David</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Weisbach</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Line Drawing, Doctrine, and
          <article-title>Efficiency in the Tax Law (November</article-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          63. Jack L.
          <article-title>Goldsmith and Eric A</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Theory of Customary International Law (November</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          64.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Public</surname>
            <given-names>Schooling</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Indoctrination, and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Totalitarianism</surname>
          </string-name>
          (December
          <year>1998</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          65.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Private Broadcasters and the Public Interest: Notes Toward A “Third Way”</article-title>
          (
          <year>January 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          66.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>An Economic Approach to the Law of Evidence (February</article-title>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          67.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Yannis</surname>
            <given-names>Bakos</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Erik Brynjolfsson, Douglas Lichtman, Shared Information Goods (
          <year>February 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          68.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kenneth</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Dam</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Intellectual Property and the Academic Enterprise (February</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          69.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gertrud</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Fremling and Richard A. Posner, Status Signaling and the Law, with Particular Application to Sexual Harassment (March</article-title>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          70.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Must Formalism Be Defended Empirically? (
          <year>March 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          71.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jonathan M. Karpoff</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr., and Graeme Rankine, Environmental Violations,
          <source>Legal Penalties, and Reputation Costs (March</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref49">
        <mixed-citation>
          72.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Matthew</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Adler</surname>
            and
            <given-names>Eric A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Rethinking
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cost-Benefit Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>April 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <mixed-citation>
          73.
          <string-name>
            <surname>John R. Lott</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Jr. and
          <string-name>
            <surname>William M. Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Multiple Victim Public Shooting, Bombings, and
          <article-title>Right-to-Carry Concealed Handgun Laws: Contrasting Private and Public Law Enforcement (April</article-title>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <mixed-citation>
          74.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lisa</surname>
            <given-names>Bernstein</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Questionable Empirical Basis of Article 2's Incorporation Strategy: A Preliminary Study</article-title>
          (May
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <mixed-citation>
          75.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Epstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Deconstructing Privacy: and Putting It Back Together Again (May
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <mixed-citation>
          76.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William M. Landes</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Winning the Art Lottery: The Economic Returns to the Ganz Collection</article-title>
          (May
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <mixed-citation>
          77.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , David Schkade, and Daniel Kahneman, Do People Want Optimal Deterrence? (
          <year>June 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <mixed-citation>
          78.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tomas</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </string-name>
          .
          <article-title>Philipson and Richard A. Posner, The Long-Run Growth in Obesity as a Function of Technological Change (</article-title>
          <year>June 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <mixed-citation>
          79.
          <string-name>
            <surname>David</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Weisbach</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Ironing Out the Flat Tax</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <mixed-citation>
          80.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Eric</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>A Theory of Contract Law under Conditions of Radical Judicial Error</article-title>
          (
          <year>August 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref58">
        <mixed-citation>
          81. David Schkade,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and Daniel Kahneman, Are Juries Less Erratic than Individuals? Deliberation, Polarization, and Punitive Damages (
          <year>September 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref59">
        <mixed-citation>
          82.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Nondelegation
          <string-name>
            <surname>Canons</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>September 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref60">
        <mixed-citation>
          83.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A. Posner, The Theory and Practice of Citations Analysis, with Special Reference to Law and Economics (September</article-title>
          <year>1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref61">
        <mixed-citation>
          84.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Randal</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Picker</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Regulating Network Industries: A Look at Intel (
          <year>October 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref62">
        <mixed-citation>
          85.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Cognition and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cost-Benefit Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>October 1999</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

