<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>" 90 Georgetown Law Journal 2379 (2001).</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <fpage>2001</fpage>
      <lpage>2002</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>The legal culture contains countless discussions of the vices and virtues of
cost-benefit analysis.' But it has hardly any explorations of the real world of
cost-benefit analysis-of what agencies do, concretely, when they do
costbenefit analysis. We know very little about the interactions among law, science,
and economics in the actual, rather than theoretical, world of cost-benefit
balancing.</p>
      <p>The Arithmetic of Arsenic2 represents a modest effort to begin to fill this gap.
My goal was to explore not whether cost-benefit is a good idea in the abstract,
but what it means in practice. In fact my major purposes were descriptive and
conceptual, not normative. I wanted to highlight a topic about which lawyers
and judges know too little: the specific questions whose answers can drive
"benefits numbers" in one or another direction. For low levels of arsenic, we
lack clear knowledge of the likely health benefits, and any extrapolation from
the data will depend on some disputable judgments, involving above all: (1) the
dose-response curve, (2) the use of data from other nations, and (3) the decision
whether to quantify certain risks on the basis of highly speculative evidence.
Monetization of benefits raises further problems involving the valuation of both
life and health and the appropriate discount rate for cancers to be averted in the
future. With an understanding of these problems, we can see exactly why there
are reasonable disputes about both nonmonetized and monetized benefits-why
some estimates are high and others are lower. We can also isolate the issues on
which more progress, both conceptual and empirical, might be made in the
future.</p>
      <p>In identifying those issues, I did not seek to resolve them, much less say how
the arsenic controversy should be handled (though in a few places I offered
some tentative judgments). I meant instead to provide a kind of lawyer's primer
on the real world of cost-benefit analysis, in the process showing where legal
objections might be raised, explaining why a deferential judicial role might
make sense, and indicating why a "benefits range," and a wide one at that, is
sometimes the most that can be offered.</p>
      <p>I am extremely grateful to Lisa Heinzerling and Thomas McGarity for their
valuable comments and criticisms. Their objections seem to me to fall into two
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, Law School and Department
of Political Science, University of Chicago.</p>
      <p>1. For a valuable collection, see COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS: LEGAL, ECONOMIC, AND PHILOSOPHICAL
PERSPECTIVES (Matthew D. Adler &amp; Eric A. Posner eds., 2001).</p>
      <p>2. Cass R. Sunstein, The Arithmetic ofArsenic, 90 GEO. L.J. 2255 (2002).</p>
      <p>3. McGarity's title is therefore fitting, though the fuzziness seems to me inescapable in light of gaps
in knowledge. Thomas 0. McGarity, ProfessorSunstein's Fuzzy Math, 90 GEO. L.J. 2341 (2002).</p>
      <p>2379
categories-the first involving the assessment of benefits (my major theme, and
a topic emphasized by Heinzerling), the second involving the assessment of
cost-benefit analysis itself (which both of them dislike). In this brief reply, I take
up these two kinds of criticisms in sequence.</p>
      <p>I. ASSESSING BENEFITS</p>
      <p>Much of Heinzerling's response urges that the EPA should have placed a
higher monetary value on life. She emphasizes, for example, that the
value-oflife data is quite old (from the 1970s). In her view, per capita growth in
economic activity requires a significant upward adjustment.4 She also contends
that the EPA should have used a cancer premium on the ground that cancer risks
receive a higher willingness to pay than other deaths. These are entirely
plausible claims and well worth further investigation.</p>
      <p>But some of Heinzerling's other suggestions seem to me more doubtful. She
contends, for example, that because cancer is involved, the EPA was wrong to
have concluded that the benefits of the arsenic rule should be discounted
because cancer arises decades after exposure to its cause.6 To be sure, it is hard
to know how the discounting problem should be handled. But isn't it much
worse to get cancer tomorrow than to get cancer twenty years from tomorrow?
Isn't it much worse to die in a plane crash tomorrow than to die from cancer
twenty years from tomorrow? Heinzerling is right to emphasize the existence of
a cancer premium. But even with that premium, it seems reasonable to discount
risks that will not turn into harms for many decades. 7</p>
      <p>I also wonder about Heinzerling's suggestion that the EPA should have
4. Lisa Heinzerling, Markets for Arsenic, 90 GEo. L.J. 2311, 2320 (2002). With respect to wealth
adjustments, I agree with Heinzerling that poor people's lives should not be valued less than the lives of
wealthy people. The complexity here is that poor people are willing, because of their poverty, to spend
less to reduce a statistical risk than wealthy people and that it is not clear that government does poor
people any favor by forcing them to spend more than they are willing to pay. (This assumes that people
are adequately informed and that individuals are being required to pay for risk reduction, which is true
in the case of arsenic but not, fortunately, in every case.).</p>
      <p>5. Id. at 2317-18.</p>
      <p>6. The Scientific Advisory Board raises another issue, not discussed by the EPA: the "cessation lag,"
meaning the lag between a reduction in exposure and a reduction in risk. See ARSENIC RULE BENEFITS
REVIEW PANEL, U.S. ENVTL. PROT. AGENCY, ARSENIC RULE BENEFITS ANALYSIS: AN SAB REVIEW 6-7
(2001), available at http://www.epa.gov.sab/ecO1008.pdf. Imagine that those now being exposed to 45
parts-per-billion (ppb) of arsenic are exposed in 2006 to 10 ppb. If so, it will take a while until cancer
risks will be equivalent to what they would be if everyone, all of the time, was exposed to 10 ppb or
less. Because the EPA did not take account of the cessation lag, the Science Advisory Board suggests
that it presented an upper bound on mortality and morbidity savings. Id. at 5.</p>
      <p>7. I am not sure that I understand Heinzerling's objection to the idea that risks that are run
involuntarily should be valued especially highly. See Heinzerling, supra note 4 at 2327. To be sure, the
line between voluntarily and involuntarily run risks is one of degree, not of kind. See Cass R. Sunstein,
The Laws of Fear, 115 HARv. L. REV. 1119, 1154-55 (2002) (book review). When we say that a risk is
involuntarily run, we typically mean that those who run it are unaware of it, or that it is very costly for
people to avoid it. See id. at 1154. But when the costs of risk-avoidance are especially high, it makes
sense to devote extra resources to reducing it. Of course Heinzerling is right to say that there is no
market for risks that are involuntarily run in the strong sense.
assessed the benefits of reducing arsenic in drinking water by examining the
market for bottled water.8 As Heinzerling notes, many people buy bottled water
for the taste, not for the increase in safety. In any case, most people do not buy
bottled water. It would be extremely odd for government to use the Safe
Drinking Water Act to do the equivalent of forcing people to buy bottled water
when this option is rejected by most people. (Should the National Highway
Safety Traffic Administration require all car manufacturers to spend the amount
spent on safety by Volvo owners?)</p>
      <p>Heinzerling also suggests that instead of using a number for statistical lives,
the EPA might have done better to survey consumers, asking them how much
they would be willing to pay to reduce arsenic levels in drinking water.9 She
thinks that such a survey would reveal that people would be willing to pay more
than enough for significant reductions. As it happens, I conducted just such a
survey with University of Chicago law students. The survey produced a median
willingness to pay $100 to eliminate a 1/100,000 risk and a median willingness
to pay $50 to eliminate a 1/1,000,000 risk.' ° These numbers, among a fairly
affluent group, do not suggest that the EPA's choice was as easy as Heinzerling
indicates, because the mean cost per household, for the 10 ppb standard, ranged
from under $1 to over $300.11 Of course there are serious doubts about the
meaningfulness of people's answers to survey questions of this kind, especially
when low probabilities are involved. 12 Hence it was reasonable, it seems to me,
for the EPA (assuming that it was interested in willingness to pay) to use its
standard dollar amount per life saved, rather than to rely on surveys.</p>
      <p>McGarity emphasizes the EPA's legitimate difficulties in handling adverse
effects that it considered nonquantifiable, including certain cancers,
hypertension, diabetes, and reproductive effects. He is concerned that these effects "fade
in and out of' my analysis "like an aircraft warning beacon"-and also that
8. Heinzerling, supra note 4, at 2324-27.
9. Id. at 2325.</p>
      <p>10. For a full discussion, see Cass R. Sunstein, ProbabilityNeglect: Emotions, Worst Cases, and the
Law, 112 YALE L.J. 61 (2002).</p>
      <p>11. Note that this was true at the time that the EPA made its initial decision; subsequent data and
analysis have strengthened the case for reduction below 20 ppb. See SUMCOMM. ON ARSENIC IN DRINKING
WATER, NAT'L RESEARCH COUNCIL, ARSENIC IN DRINKING WATER: 2001 UPDATE (2001).</p>
      <p>Heinzerling engages in some clever framing to make the issue seem easy. She compares a 20 ppb
standard to the more protective alternatives-an illuminating exercise to be sure, but one that does not
adequately describe the EPA's choice, which was whether and how to depart from the 50 ppb standard.
She also calculates the amount that consumers would be willing to spend per day, finding the very low
number conclusive on the question. But this kind of framing proves too much. See Sunstein, supra note
2, at 2295. There are countless worthy causes that might reasonably ask Americans to spend, say, a
dollar a day. Assuming that 250 million Americans participate, each dollar-a-day program could raise
$91.5 billion. Is it worth spending $91.5 billion to clean up hazardous waste dumps? To reduce benzene
emissions? To reduce greenhouse gases? To immunize children? To improve education in poor
neighborhoods? To house people who need housing? To improve national defense? To increase the
number of police officers on the streets? To do all of these eight dollar-a-day programs, raising over
$720 billion? To do more?
12. See Sunstein, supranote 10.
once all of them are included, my low-end estimates "are too low" and my
high-end estimates "may only be slightly too high or perhaps not high enough."13
All of these points are reasonable. My basic suggestion is that benefits should
be quantified if this is at all possible.' 4 In general, the EPA should assign
numbers to adverse effects whenever it can, if only to provide a range, and it
should have done more in this vein here. In this case, as in many others, efforts
at quantification illuminate the analysis, even when there is uncertainty.' 5</p>
      <p>Heinzerling dislikes the willingness-to-pay criterion. Her most interesting
claim is that market behavior is likely to be inadequately informed, not least
because people are "intuitive toxicologists," acting in the market domain as they
do in politics. 16 For this reason she doubts that market evidence reveals people's
informed tradeoffs between dollars and statistical risks. Heinzerling is right to
say that cognitive problems and simple ignorance play a role in the market
domain; her Perrier example might well be a case in point. The real question, an
empirical one, is whether some correctives might not be provided by the sheer
number of people involved in market decisions. Many of us do not know
whether products we buy will do what they are supposed to do; yet the
knowledge of some is enough to ensure, most of the time at least, that there is a
correlation between quality and cost. In the domain of risks, it is possible that
market processes will work in the same way, ensuring, much of the time, that
risky products will cost more than less risky ones, and that other things being
equal, employers will have to pay people a wage premium for higher risks. The
evidence here is suggestive if not conclusive, indicating that in markets, at least,
people will not pay infinite or even huge amounts to eliminate low-level cancer
risks. Indeed the amounts they are willing to pay fall within a certain range, one
that is wide but far from unbounded.' 7 Of course, Heinzerling is right to
question whether an examination of market behavior can uncover informed
judgments about the price of a statistical life.</p>
      <p>II. ASSESSING COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS</p>
      <p>To say the least, Heinzerling and McGarity are skeptics about cost-benefit
analysis. I do not share their skepticism. In my view, cost-benefit analysis
should be seen as a valuable tool, partly as a way to counteract the errors that
we all make in thinking about risk, partly as a mechanism for ensuring that
government addresses serious problems rather than trivial ones, partly as a way
13. McGarity, supra note 3, at 2351-52.</p>
      <p>14. The point is emphasized by the Science Advisory Board, asking for more quantification from the
EPA. See ARSENIC RULE BENEFITS REVIEW PANEL, supra note 6, at 3.</p>
      <p>15. McGarity also objects to my very tentative suggestion that if we include an appropriate discount
rate, $4.5 million is a sensible value for statistical lives in this context. McGarity, supra note 3, at
2355-56. While discounting seems to me sensible here, I am not at all wedded to the $4.5 million
number and would welcome alternative suggestions.</p>
      <p>16. Heinzerling, supra note 4, at 2330.
17. See W. Kip Viscusi, FATAL TRADEOFFS: PUBLIC &amp; PRIVATE RESPONSIBILITIES FOR RISK (1992).
of getting a sense of the consequences in front of decisionmakers before they
act. 8 Is this so terribly controversial? Is it not revealing that President Clinton,
no less than Presidents Reagan and Bush, required agencies to produce
costbenefit analyses of major rules? 9</p>
      <p>To be sure, cost-benefit analysis may be unhelpful or misused in practice,
simply because of the indeterminacy in the data. A lurking question, pressed by
both Heinzerling and McGarity, is whether the arsenic controversy supports or
undermines the argument for cost-benefit analysis. 20 I think that the analysis
was helpful, simply because it showed the range of potential effects from low
levels of arsenic exposure. The analysis greatly weakened the efforts of interest
groups and others to treat the old 50 ppb standard as unexceptionable. After the
EPA did its work, no one could responsibly contend that it would be silly to
rethink the old standard. Indeed, the analysis--especially taken in light of the
2001 report from the National Research Council 2 '-helped show that the 10
ppb standard would not be exceedingly costly and likely would be a real
improvement, in terms of public health, over the 50 ppb standard. At the same
time, the analysis showed why reasonable people might be uncertain whether
there would be very large public health gains from a standard below (say) 20
ppb. (Note in this regard that Canada, a nation not unconcerned with the health
of its citizens, has a standard of 25 ppb.2 2 )</p>
      <p>Heinzerling's attack on cost-benefit analysis seems to be based not on a belief
that costs and benefits are irrelevant, but on the willingness-to-pay criterion,
which she identifies with cost-benefit analysis. The identification is
understandable: Those who do cost-benefit analysis generally use that criterion. But to
engage in cost-benefit analysis, we can value benefits however we like. In the
1960s and 1970s, it was popular to use the "human capital" approach, which
values life by looking at lost earnings.23 This method, still popular within the
courts, produced amounts that were a mere fraction of those elicited by
willingness-to-pay methods. Or suppose that a contemporary analyst rejected
willingness to pay and instead chose, for her own reasons, $15 million as the
presumptive amount to spend per statistical life-with the presumptive amount
subject to increase or decrease if the circumstances warranted either.24 Such an
analyst could still compare costs and benefits. We might even start with the
amounts that emerge from labor market studies, not because we have a deep
18. See Matthew D. Adler &amp; Eric A. Posner, Rethinking Cost-Benefit Analysis, 109 YALE L.J. 165,
179 (1999); CASS R. SUNSTEIN, RISK AND REASON (forthcoming 2002).</p>
      <p>19. Exec. Order No. 12,866, 58 Fed. Reg. 51,735 (Sept. 30, 1993).
20. Heinzerling, supra note 4, at 2313; McGarity, supra note 3, at 2364-65.
21. See SUMCOMM. ON ARSENIC IN DRINKING WATER, supra note 11.
22. ROBERT PERCIVAL ET AL., ENVIRONMENTAL REGULATION 122 (3d ed. 2000).
23. See Viscusi, supra note 17, at 17-18.</p>
      <p>24. An increase may occur if, for example, children were mostly at risk, or a decrease if elderly
people were mostly at risk. Of course the life-years criterion could automatically incorporate this
variable. Note that the Science Advisory Board sensibly asked the EPA to consider the "age distribution
of cases avoided whenever possible." See ARSENIC RULE BENEFITS REVIEW PANEL, supra note 6, at 5.
commitment to willingness to pay, but because of a democratic judgment that
those amounts provide a reasonable place to begin. What seems to me most
important is not to be dogmatic about willingness to pay, but to ensure against
uninformed stabs in the dark and to promote coherence and sense in
regulation-so that we are not spending small sums on large problems and large sums
on small problems.</p>
      <p>McGarity thinks that the largest lesson of the arsenic controversy involves the
"daunting scientific uncertainties" that plague cost-benefit analysis.25 In view of
these uncertainties, he thinks that cost-benefit analysis is a matter of "frequently
preposterous and always manipulable number spinning.' 26 He has a point. But
it need not be a matter of "spinning." We might try instead to identify the likely
range of effects, and when the range is large, we might want to know why the
benefits might be small and why they might be big. 27 If we are choosing among
several levels of protection, what should we do instead? Guess? Flip a coin?
Does it really make sense to conclude (as both Heinzerling and McGarity seem
to do) that whenever people are being exposed to a carcinogen (any
carcinogen?), the government should regulate to the point that is "feasible" for
industry28-- even if the cost is (say) $900 billion and the health benefits are likely.to
29
be trivial?</p>
      <p>I suspect that both Heinzerling and McGarity think that cost-benefit analysis
fails cost-benefit analysis. They believe that all things considered, we would be
better off with some other standard-for example, basing standards on
feasibility. They might be right! If cost-benefit analysis simply makes it harder for
agencies to protect the public, and mostly increases the power of regulated
groups to block desirable regulation, it is hard to celebrate cost-benefit analysis.
But there are reasons to believe that cost-benefit analysis is not simply an
antiregulatory tool. Indeed cost-benefit analysis helped spur the removal of lead
from gasoline and dramatic steps, pushed by the United States, to eliminate
25. McGarity, supra note 3, at 2344.
26. Id. at 2366.</p>
      <p>27. One possibility is to create a margin of safety, an idea supported by McGarity and often found in
federal law. See, e.g., Clean Air Act § 108, 42 U.S.C. § 7408 (2000). Often a margin of safety makes
sense to prevent risks that are possible but not demonstrable. But sometimes there are risks and costs on
all sides of the equation, and when a margin of safety itself creates risks and costs, a high margin of
safety can be a bad idea. See INDUR M. GOKLANY, THE PRECAUTIONARY PRINCIPLE: A CRITICAL APPRAISAL
OF RISK ASSESSMENT (2001).</p>
      <p>28. McGarity approves of the technology-based approach on the ground that it "says that we ought
to do 'the best we can' to protect human health from environmental contaminants, especially those that
result from profit-making human activities." McGarity, supra note 3, at 2374. The difficulty arises if the
costs imposed on "profit-making human activities" turn out to be significant human costs, in the form of
lower wages, decreased employment, higher prices, or even poverty. If the costs merely mean reduced
profits, there is much less to worry about.</p>
      <p>29. Heinzerling and McGarity are correct to say that costs play some rule under statutory provisions
that are based on an inquiry into technology. See, e.g., 33 U.S.C. § 1314(b)(2)(B) (2000). The problem
is that benefits are not assessed and that there is no direct balancing of costs and benefits.
chlorofluorocarbons, which contribute to depletion of the ozone layer.30 More
recently, the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs (OIRA) has
pioneered the idea of a "prompt letter"-letters designed to promote agencies to act
in cases in which the benefits of action seem to outweigh the coStS. 3 ' Inspired
by tentative cost-benefit analysis, OIRA has asked the Occupational Safety and
Health Administration to consider requiring the placement of automatic
defibrillators in workplaces, has urged the Food and Drug Administration to issue a
final rule requiring disclosure of the level of trans fatty acids in foods, and has
asked the Department of Transportation to take steps to improve automobile
safety by establishing a high-speed, frontal offset crash test. In any case,
cost-benefit analysis has often driven policy in more sensible directions, by
showing the best means of achieving regulatory goals.3 2</p>
      <p>It remains important to ask whether cost-benefit analysis can be defended on
normative grounds. But for better or for worse, cost-benefit analysis is here to
stay. We need to be asking a number of more concrete questions. Where does
science leave gaps, and what gaps does it leave? What are the sources of high
benefit judgments and low benefit judgments? How does the dose-response
curve matter? How should we think about harms that will not occur for
decades? Are there systematic distortions on the cost side, and if so why? An
investigation of the arsenic controversy casts light on these questions. But there
is a lot more to do.</p>
      <p>30. See ECONOMIC ANALYSES AT EPA: ASSESSING REGULATORY IMPACT (Richard D. Morgenstern ed.,
1997).</p>
      <p>31. See http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/inforeg/prompt-letter.html.
32. See ECONOMIc ANALYSES AT EPA, supra note 30.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list />
  </back>
</article>

