<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Correspondence</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Wilson Quarterly and Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars are collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to The Wilson Quarterly</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>1976-</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>26</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at http://www.jstor.org/page/ info/about/policies/terms.jsp JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org. http://www.jstor.org</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>This content downloaded from 128.240.233.146 on Tue, 15 Mar 2016 21:01:19 UTC</p>
      <p>All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions
Letters may be mailed to One Woodrow Wilson Plaza, 1300 Pennsylvania Avenue, N.W., Washington, D.C.</p>
      <p>20004-3027, or sent via facsimile, to (202) 691-4036, ore-mail, to wq@wwic.si.edu.</p>
      <p>The writer's telephone number and postal address should be included. For reasons of space, letters are usually
edited for publication. Some letters are received in response to the editors' requests for comment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Taking Issue</title>
      <p>According to Peter Berkowitz and Benjamin
Wittes ["The Professors and Bush v. Gore" WQ,
Autumn '01 ], my "work dripped with disdain for the
conservative majority" of the Supreme Court long
before Bush v. Gore. This is simply not true.</p>
      <p>In fact, a forthcoming book of mine goes out of
its way to defend the Supreme Court's decisions
in the area of campaign finance. In contrast to the
harsh judgments of Buckley v. Valeo (1976) and its
progeny that generally prevail in the academy, I
defend the basic principles of the Court's
jurisprudence. In contrast, I challenge the
authors to point to a single essay or book of mine
that engages in disdainful criticism of a major
area of the Rehnquist Court's work.</p>
      <p>I leave it to your readers to compare my essay
in the London Review of Books with the
Berkowitz/Wittes characterization of my
arguments concerning the 2000 election. This can be
done by searching www.lrb.co.uk. But it is harder
to check on their broad-brush
mischaracterizations, and so it seems appropriate to set this part of
the record straight.</p>
      <p>Bruce Ackerman
Yale University Law School</p>
      <p>New Haven, Conn.</p>
      <p>Peter Berkowitz and Benjamin Wittes are
certainly right to say that "scholars who assume the
office of public intellectual must exercise a
heightened degree of care and restraint in their
public pronouncements." But they do not live up to
their own standards.</p>
      <p>As Berkowitz and Wittes well know, my little
piece in the Chronicle of Higher Education was a
response to the editors' somewhat whimsical
request for a very brief essay on how historians in
the far distant future would regard Bush v. Gore.
I chose to accept the invitation with an
obviously whimsical piece from an imaginary historian.
The piece was not intended to reflect my own
considered views on the subject. (Anyone who doubts
the element of whimsy should consult the piece
itself, with its multiple references to made-up
events in the first half of the 21st century.) By
contrast, my comments on National Public Radio
did reflect my own views, indeed, the same view
that I have elaborated in my academic writing: On
the one hand, the Court, with its decision on
Bush v. Gore, might well have done the nation a
big favor, and no one should accuse the justices
of partisan motives. (In his strident book on Bush
v. Gore, Alan Dershowitz sharply criticizes me
for saying this.) On the other hand, the Court s
reasoning was embarrassingly weak as a matter of
law, and for this reason it has serious problems from
the standpoint of legitimacy.</p>
      <p>Berkowitz and Wittes take the hilarious step of
juxtaposing my comments on NPR with my
science-fictional piece in the Chronicle, thus
manufacturing a conflict between "two seemingly
irreconcilable views" and lumping me together
with scholars making "flamboyant assertions
supported only by their authority." Berkowitz and
Wittes are certainly entitled to defend Bush v.
Gore against its critics. But they should be more
careful about converting disagreements on the
merits into attacks on the good faith of their fellow
citizens. They should exercise a heightened
degree of care in their public pronouncements.</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein
University of Chicago Law School</p>
      <p>Chicago, III.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Teaching History</title>
      <p>Wilfred M McClay has written a perceptive and
poignant essay ["History for a Democracy," WQ,
Autumn '01] advocating a long-needed great
awakening for the place of history in American life.
Endorsing his plea, I add a few words.</p>
      <p>When Lincoln said we must "disenthrall
ourselves," it was from the "dogmas" of the past and
not from the past itself, for in the same speech he
declared, "We cannot escape history." Similarly,
John Adams stated that we must "disabuse" ourselves
of the past. "The dogma of Aristotle is the most
unphilosophical of the world, the most inhuman
and cruel. Until this wicked position, which is
worse than the slavery of the ancient republics, or</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list/>
  </back>
</article>