<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Jack L. Goldsmith</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein &amp; Jack L. Goldsmith, "Military Tribunals and Legal Culture: What a Difference Sixty Years</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2002</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <fpage>260</fpage>
      <lpage>290</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>President Bush's Military Order of November 13, 2001
established a legal framework to enable military commissions to
try terrorists associated with the attacks of September 11, 2001
on Washington, DC, and New York City.1 This Military Order
was greeted with impassioned criticism in the press, the legal
academy, and Congress. But it hardly lacked precedent. Sixty
years earlier, in the midst of World War II, President Franklin
Delano Roosevelt (FDR) established a Military Commission to
try eight Nazi agents who had covertly entered the United States
to commit acts of sabotage and terrorism. Although the Nazis
failed in their mission, their aims were similar to those of the
9/11 terrorists. And yet Roosevelt's creation of the Commission,
and the subsequent secret trial of the Nazi saboteurs, received
widespread praise from the same institutions that protested
Bush's action.</p>
      <p>* Professor of Law, University of Chicago
** Karl N. Llewellyn Dist. Service Professor of Jurisprudence, University of
Chicago. We thank Ryan Goodman, Dennis Hutchinson, Bernard Meltzer, Eric Posner,
Richard Posner, Peter Spiro, Laurence Tribe, Detlav Vagts, Adrian Vermeule, G.E.
White, and Ben Wittes for helpful comments, and Sarah Rispin for outstanding research
assistance.</p>
      <p>This article was completed before Professor Goldsmith took a leave of absence to
serve as Special Counsel to the General Counsel of the U.S. Department of Defense.
The views expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not reflect the official
policy or position of the Department of Defense or the United States Government.</p>
      <p>1. Technically the reach of the Military Order was somewhat broader than this,
see note 92, but the defining cases clearly involved those associated with the September
11 attacks.</p>
      <p>Our purpose here is not to investigate, except in passing,
issues of law and policy.2 We instead explore three other
questions: What explains the dramatically different reactions? What
lessons do the different reactions offer about changes, over time,
in the legal culture and in culture in general? What lessons do
they offer about the evolution of protections for civil liberties in
general and during wartime in particular?</p>
      <p>The most tempting, and common, explanation for the
different reactions is that there is a significant difference in
lawthat President Roosevelt's Order stands on much firmer legal
ground than President Bush's Order. We show that this and
related explanations are weak. The different reactions are instead
best explained in terms of two large differences between the
United States of 1942 and the United States of 2001. In 1942,
the nation perceived a far greater threat to its own survival; for
this reason Americans were far less solicitous of the interests of
defendants thought to have participated in a war effort against
the United States. But this explanation is inadequate by itself.
It must be supplemented with an understanding of the
largescale, post-1960s shift in American attitudes, involving decreased
trust of executive and military authority, and a strengthened
commitment to individual rights in the legal system and broader
culture. Our general claim is that with respect to these issues,
the legal culture is fundamentally different from what it was
before, so much so that many previous practices are barely
recognizable. We use the different reactions to the Bush and
Roosevelt Military Orders as a way of obtaining a window on this shift.</p>
      <p>After making out these claims, we conclude with some
general reflections on the evolution of civil liberties protections
during wartime. In particular, we identify a mechanism behind the
trend toward greater protection for civil liberties during
wartime, namely: A judgment, in hindsight, that past civil liberty
intrusions were unnecessary or excessive. We also suggest that
this trend is, in a way, an accident of America's distinctive
history.</p>
      <p>2. The relevant legal issues have been discussed in many places. See, e.g., Neal K.
Katyal and Laurence H. Tribe, Waging War, Deciding Guilt: Trying the Military
Tribunals, 111 Yale L.J. 1259 (2002); George P. Fletcher, War and the Constitution: Bush's
Military Tribunals Haven't Got a Legal Leg to Stand On, The American Prospect 26,
(Jan. 1, 2002); Curtis A. Bradley and Jack L. Goldsmith, The ConstitutionalValidity of
MilitaryCommissions,5 Green Bag (2d) 249 (2002).
I. THE NAZI SABOTEURS AND THE REACTION TO</p>
      <p>ROOSEVELT'S ORDER</p>
      <p>
        On June
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">12, 1942</xref>
        , six months after Hitler declared war
against the United States, four Nazi agents who had traveled by
submarine from France landed in darkness on a beach in Long
Island, New York.' A few days later, four more Nazi agents
landed on the north Atlantic coast of Florida. The eight men
had all lived in America before returning to Germany after
Hitler rose to power; two of them, Herbert Haupt and Ernest
Burger, were naturalized American citizens.4 The saboteurs'
mission was the brainchild of Hitler himself, who wanted to cripple
U.S. military production capacities and demoralize the
American civilian population. Their task was to blow up aluminum
plants, railroad lines, canal locks, hydroelectric plants, and
bridges. They also had plans for "nuisance bombings" of
railroad terminals and Jewish-owned department stores.5
      </p>
      <p>Soon after their arrival in the United States, two of the
saboteurs, Dasch and Burger, decided to betray their mission to
the U.S. government. It is unclear why they turned. Most
historians believe they were motivated by fear of betrayal by the
other saboteurs, or by fear of detection by U.S. officials.
Whatever their reason, Dasch and Burger telephoned the FBI office
in New York to announce their plot. When they were dismissed
as cranks, Dasch traveled to Washington, where FBI agents took
his story more seriously. The FBI interviewed Dasch for five
days about the saboteurs' plans, and then rounded up his seven
accomplices.</p>
      <p>FBI Director J. Edgar Hoover announced the capture of the
eight Nazi Saboteurs on June 27, 1942. Hoover insinuated that
the arrests resulted from the FBI's infiltration of the Nazi
system. But he revealed little actual information beyond the names
of those involved, how they landed, the weapons they possessed,
and their sabotage aims. Nonetheless, the nation reacted to the
news with enormous joy. "The little that [Hoover] told was
enough to make headlines of a size that had hitherto been
reserved for the war's major battles.... With no information
about how the success had been achieved, the public took the
fnoerwAsmaseruicnadnenGia-bmleenp.r'6oof that Nazi fiendishness was no match</p>
      <p>The newspaper reports of the saboteurs' capture insisted
that the eight men would face the death penalty. Within the
government, however, there was considerable uncertainty about
how to prosecute and punish the saboteurs. One complicating
factor was that the laws applicable in civilian trials did not
permit the death penalty for the non-U.S. citizen defendants.
Another was a concern that Article III of the Constitution required
the government to try the American citizens for treason.</p>
      <p>"If there was doubt in the Justice Department, there was
none among politicians, the press and most of the public."7
Almost everyone seemed to call for the saboteurs' execution-the
sooner the better. The Washington Post reported that
"[d]emands immediately arose among members of Congress for
swift justice to the saboteurs-for the death penalty if the law
permits it."8 The general public favored death for the saboteurs
by a 10-1 margin. A Newsweek essay entitled Death for the
Saboteurs argued that "[w]e ought to meet this threat with the
most swift and the most ruthless punishment which the law
permits."' "Life Magazine headlined its story of the capture: The
Eight Nazi Saboteurs Should Be Put To Death."'1</p>
      <p>President Roosevelt agreed. "Offenses such as... these are
probably more serious than any offense in criminal law," he
wrote to Attorney General Biddle on June 30. "The death
penalty is called for by usage and by the extreme gravity of the war
aim and the very existence of our American government. [The
saboteurs] should be tried by court martial."' 2 Biddle concurred
that a military commission is preferable because of greater
flexibility, its traditional use in cases of this character and its clear
power to impose the death penalty. 3</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>MILITARY</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>TRIBUNALS</title>
      <p>&amp; LEGAL CULTURE</p>
      <p>On July 2, Roosevelt issued two proclamations that together
established a Military Commission to try the eight saboteurs.
One proclamation established the jurisdiction of the Military
Commission and purported to preclude judicial review of its
decisions. 14</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>The other named the eight defendants as well as the</title>
        <p>judges, prosecutors, and defense counsel. It also outlined the
structure of the Commission in very general terms."i</p>
        <p>Roosevelt's announcement that a Military Commission
would try the saboteurs "met with general satisfaction in
Washington, as it will throughout the country,"
wrote Lewis Wood,
the New York Times Washington correspondent. 6 "The
Presidential action calmed the fears of many who realized the delays
and technicalities incident to civil trials."' 7</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>A few days later,</title>
        <p>Wood wrote: "Expectation.., that the Administration
would
seek the death penalty for the Hitler spies before the military
commission chosen by the President sounded a heartening note
at a moment when indignant Americans everywhere
were
demanding this extreme punishment for the audacious criminals.
Americans wanted to hear the roar of rifles in the hands of a
firing squad, and the government has apparently agreed that this is
the proper course." s8
14. The proclamation provided that:
[a]ll persons who are subjects, citizens, or residents of any nation at war with
the United States or who give obedience to or act under the direction of any
such nation, and who during time of war enter or attempt to enter the United
States or any territory or possession thereof, through coastal or boundary
defenses, and are charged with committing or attempting or preparing to commit
sabotage, espionage, hostile or warlike acts, or violations of the law or war, shall
be subject to the law of war and to the jurisdiction of military tribunals; and that
such persons shall not be privileged to seek any remedy or maintain any
proceeding directly or indirectly, or to have any such remedy or proceeding sought
on their behalf, in the courts of the United States, or of its States, territories,
and possessions, except under such regulations as the Attorney General, with
the approval of the Secretary of War, may from time to time prescribe.
7 Fed. Reg. 5101 (July 2, 1942).</p>
        <p>15. See 7 Fed. Reg. 5103 (July 2, 1942) ("The Commission shall have power to and
shall, as occasion requires, make such rules for the conduct of the proceeding, consistent
with the powers of military commissions under the Articles of War, as it shall deem
necessary for a full and fair trial of the matters before it. Such evidence shall be admitted as
would, in the opinion of the President of the Commission, have probative value to a
reasonable man. The concurrence of at least two-thirds of the Members of the Commission
present shall be necessary for a conviction or sentence. The record of the trial including
any judgment or sentence, shall be transmitted directly to me for my action thereon.").</p>
        <p>The saboteurs' trial began on July 8 on the fifth floor of the
Justice Department in a room whose windows were covered in
heavy black curtains to block all daylight. Major General Frank
McCoy, the Commission's presiding officer, closed the trial to
the press and public due to the nature of the testimony, which
involves the security of the United States and the lives of its
soldiers, sailors and citizens. 19 McCoy released "communiqu6s"
about the trial that contained adjournment times and other
meaningless bits of information. He also let reporters view the
empty trial chamber, and he released photographs of the trial
and the defendants. But other than this, the trial process took
place in complete secrecy.</p>
        <p>Although the Washington press corps complained about
this secrecy,' ° many, and perhaps most, commentators did not
object to it. Arthur Krock of the New York Times dismisse'd
claims for open press coverage of the trial as "thoughtless."'
The Nation noted that "[a]lien sabotage trials are obviously rich
in information that can be of value to the enemy, particularly to
other saboteurs still on the loose. '22 In this light, it viewed the
''meaningless communiques" emerging from the trial as a
"victory" for the press.23</p>
        <p>The next piece of real public information about the
Commission came three weeks later, when the Supreme Court
announced that it would convene a special summer session to
entertain the saboteurs' habeas corpus petitions challenging the
legality of the military commission. Congress and the public
were outraged by the Court's intervention. "The decision to
seek recourse in the Supreme Court did not meet popular
approval in Washington," reported the New York Times. "On the
contrary, there is great dissatisfaction here with the length to
which the [three-week military trial] has already proceeded....
On all sides hope was expressed that the Supreme Court would
make short work of the move., 24 The Los Angeles Times
believed that "[s]uch a hearing was totally uncalled for.... The
Supreme Court should never have been dragged into this
wartime military matter., 25 The DetroitFreePress agreed: "Realism
calls for a stone wall and a firing squad, and not a lot of
holierthan-thou eyewash about extending the protection of civil rights
to a group that came among us to blast, burn, and kill.",26 So too
did the Communist Daily Worker. "The unprecedented action,"
it said, "is in itself a victory for the enemies of America and the
United States., 2 7</p>
        <p>Some newspapers were more supportive. Arthur Krock,
who had earlier claimed that the secret military trial was
legitimate and fair, saw the Supreme Court's intervention as a fine
service to democracy at war. "Whatever disposition the Court
shall make of the grave issues presented to it, the fact.. .will
brighten the American history of a time when Cicero's
apothegm-'inter anna silent leges'21-is the rule in almost every
other land."2 9 The Washington Post,also a supporter of the
military commission, defended Supreme Court review, noting that
"the very circumstances that the Court is meeting to hear the
petition-this after a long and exhaustive trial of the men by a
military commission- shows that the saboteurs are being given their
day in court." The Post added that "in a time when in so many
parts of the world law has become a mockery and justice an
obscenity, it will hearten freemen everywhere that here in this
citadofelthoofselibwehrtoy sluawrreapntidti ojuusstliyceinsvtialldefdunocutriolann-devteondofours tihnejubrye.ne30fit</p>
        <p>
          On July
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">31, 1942</xref>
          , the Supreme Court announced in a
unanimous per curiam order that the Military Commission was
legally constituted and thus that the petitioners' were lawfully
detained. The Court did not provide reasons for its conclusion,
but indicated that it would do so at a later time.
        </p>
        <p>Most commentators viewed the Court's hurried review of
the Commission approvingly. The New York Herald Tribune
described the Court's action as a victory for civil liberties:
The action of the Supreme Court was of real importance to
the American people as a whole... [The Court] affirmed the
right of the President to deny the civil courts of this country to
those acting under enemy orders who... [violate] the laws of
war. In other words, it gave no comfort to the guilty. But by
the fact of their intercession the justices of America's highest
court reaffirmed to innocent Americans that the law still
stands as a shield over them, against malicious usurpation or
the quick tempers and brash judgments of war time.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>In all this court drama, American was showing the world that</title>
        <p>its judicial system could give even an enemy invader a
sporting chance to prove his innocence; even in war time we
regarded as important the rights of the individual and
shoot him offhand, as Nazi Germany would have done.d32id not</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-3-1">
          <title>The Washington Postsimilarly stated:</title>
          <p>In denying civil justice to the eight Nazi saboteurs, the
Supreme Court did the expected thing.... To handle [the
saboteurs] in the civil courts would be to help Hitler immensely,
and that would be intolerable. We cannot afford to give our
enemy, in our present pass, the slightest assistance. At the
same time we are engaged in delivering the world from a
tyranny in which the rights of the individual have no place.
Those rights are enshrined in our reign of law. If we simply
disregard the law, even in our treatment of our enemies, we
shall be in danger of coming out of the war as Hitlerian as
Hitler. That is why the admittance of the petitions for writs of
habeas corpus to the Supreme Court was widely approved. 33
The Nation was also Supportive, though somewhat more
impatient:</p>
          <p>A touch of the ludicrous is a small price to pay for
maintaining the traditions of American judicial procedure.
Whatever the fate of the Nazi invaders who landed on our beaches
in the middle of June we need not begrudge them a few extra
weeks of life involved in giving them a more fair trial. The
niceties of jurisprudence, however, can be carried too far, and in
this case the procedure was beginning to take on such
overtones of fantasy that the Supreme Court's refusal to give the
defendants standing in the civil courts came in the nick of
time. . . . Had the Supreme Court granted [the saboteurs']
petitions, American soldiers would have to go into battle with
John Doe summonses in place of rifles and a round of
subpoenas in their cartridge belts. But the Supreme Court held
firm, and Ringling Brothers need not worry
turn Gargantua loose on a writ of habeas corpuasb.o34ut having to
Unbenkownst to the public, the Military Commission trial
ended three days after the Supreme Court announcement, on
August 3, 1942. The Commission found all eight defendants
guilty, recommended that they all be executed, and sent the
3,000-page record to the President for review. On August 8,
President Roosevelt publicly announced that he had approved
the commission's judgments but had commuted the sentences of
Burger and Dasch (the turncoats) to life and thirty years
imprisonment, respectively. By the time of the public announcement,
the executions had been carried out.</p>
          <p>In their post-mortems, the major news organizations praised
the Military Commission for its fairness and integrity, the
Supreme Court for its quick review and approval of the
Commission's legali3tyV,- and the entire process as a victory for democracy
and justice. The Washington Post's analysis was typical:</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>Americans will read with grim satisfaction the news that six of</title>
        <p>the eight Nazi saboteurs have been executed. [... ] It was
hardly surprising, under the circumstances, that many an
impatient voice was raised regarding the seeming laggardness of
the procedure that was being followed and many an impatient
demand was made that the culprits be summarily executed.
That certainly was what would have occurred in Germany
under similar circumstances. But drum-head trials and summary
executions are not the American way. The very enormity of
the crime these eight saboteurs had committed made it all the
more essential, not for their sake but for ours, that their guilt
be established beyond peradventure of a doubt, that they be
given the benefit of able counsel, that all the facts be fully
reviewed. All this was done. It was bound to take time. Yet,
actually, justice was swift and sure. A month after the
military commission first convened the verdict of this
distinguished tribunal was carried out. Nothing was lost by this
punctilious procedure. But Americans can have the
satisfaction of knowing that even in a time of great national peril we
did not stoop to the practices of our enemies. And those who
may seek to follow in the steps of the eight will be under no
illusion as to what is in store for them if they are caught. 3 6
The New Republic stated that the process revealed that "even in
wartime and even toward the enemy we do not abandon our
basic protection of individual rights. 3'7 The New York Herald
Tribune, in an editorial entitled "Justice has Been Done,"
asserted:</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-4-1">
          <title>No one can suggest that these men, [...] despite the tension of</title>
          <p>a terrible war, did not receive a full and fair trial. Nor, on the
other hand, can it be said that the issue of the trial has
jeoptaircdeizheadvethbeeesnafveitnydoicfattheed innattihoen.eyeAsmoefrtihceanwoprrlidn.c3i8ples of
jusEven the condemned Nazis acknowledged that they had "been
given a fair trial" and that their military lawyers had
"represented our case as American officers unbiased, better that we
could39expect and probably risking the indignation of public
opinion.</p>
          <p>Almost three months after the saboteurs were executed, the
Supreme Court released its unanimous opinion-Ex Parte
Quirin40-explaining why the Military Commission was
constitutionally valid. The Court first interpreted Roosevelt's preclusion
of judicial review to permit review on habeas corpus. It then
reasoned that Congress had authorized the use of military
commissions to try violations of the laws of war, and that at least
some of the acts allegedly committed by the defendants
constituted such violations. 2 The Court distinguished a leading Civil
War precedent, Ex ParteMilligan4,3 which had held that a U.S.
civilian charged with conspiracy against the federal government
could not be tried by a military commission when federal courts
were "open to hear criminal accusations and redress
grievances."44 Quirin held that Milligan involved an individual who
was 4n5ot an enemy belligerent and thus not subject to the laws of
war.</p>
          <p>36.
37.</p>
          <p>
            3
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">8.
1942</xref>
            ).
          </p>
          <p>39. See Rachlis, They Came to Kill at 297-98 (cited in note 3).
40. 317 U.S. 1 (1942).
41. Id. at 24-25.
42. Id. at 26-29.
43. 71 U.S. 2 (1866).
44. Id. at 121-22.
45. Ex Parte Quirin,317 U.S. 1, 45 (1942).</p>
          <p>
            Editorial, Justiceis Done, Wash. Post, Sec. B, 6 (Aug
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">9, 1942</xref>
            ).
          </p>
          <p>
            Editorial, The Saboteursand the Court, New Republic 159 (Aug
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">10, 1942</xref>
            ).
Editorial, Justice Has Been Done, N.Y. Herald Tribune, Section II, 8 (Aug 9,
          </p>
          <p>The announcement of the Court's opinion in Quirin was
reported with little fanfare. We found no editorial commentary
about the opinion in any of the mainstream periodicals
mentioned above. The ACLU's Wartime Civil Liberties Reports
covering the years 1942 and 1943, which contained lists of
"deplored" and "regretted" civil liberties violations by government
officials (including the Supreme Court), failed even to mention
Quirin4.6 Moreover, the legal commentary that emerged in the
law reviews in the years following Quirin,generally "applauded"
the decision. 47 "Because most legal commentators agreed with
what the Chief Justice was trying to accomplish, they found
unobjectionable both the Quirin ruling and the way which he had
justified it."'48 In the context of the events of late 1942, the
decision in Quirin to limit Milligan and to uphold the validity of
Roosevelt's Military Commission was not viewed as a big deal.</p>
          <p>II. 9/11 AND THE REACTION TO THE BUSH</p>
          <p>MILITARY ORDER</p>
          <p>The reaction to President Bush's Order to establish Military
Commissions was much different from the reaction to
Roosevelt's. The public supported the Bush Military Commission
proposal by a greater than 2-1 margin.4 ' Though significant, this
support is more ambiguous and less enthusiastic than the public
support Roosevelt received in 1942. But the real differences in
reaction were in Congress and especially the mainstream press
and members of the legal academy. These institutions reacted
with vehement, and sometimes strident, opposition. The New
York Times typified the reaction of many newspapers:
46. See ACLU, The Bill of Rights in War (1942); ACLU, Freedom in Wartime
(1943).</p>
          <p>47. Belknap, 89 Mil. L. Rev. at 88 (cited in note 25). In support of Belknap's
conclusion, see, for example, Cyrus Bernstein, The Saboteur Trial: A Case History, 11 Geo.
Wash. L. Rev. 131 (1943); Robert E. Cushman, Ex Pane Quirin et al-The Nazi Saboteur
Case, 28 Cornell L.Q. 54 (1942); George Schilling, Saboteurs and the Jurisdictionof
Military Commissions, 41 Mich. L. Rev. 481 (1942); Note, 17 Tulane L. Rev. 475 (1943);
Note, 31 Geo. L.J. 90 (1942). For more critical contemporary perspectives, see Edward
S. Corwin, Total War and the Constitution 118 (Alfred Knopf, 1947); Charles Barber,
Trialof Unlawful Enemy Belligerents,29 Cornell L.Q. 53 (1944).</p>
          <p>48. Belknap, 89 Mil. L. Rev. at 88 (cited in note 25).</p>
          <p>49. In a survey conducted by NPR News, the Kaiser Family Foundation and
Harvard University's Kennedy School, 64% answered "'yes," and 26% answered "no," to the
question "Do you favor or oppose military tribunals for non-citizens suspected of
terrorism who are captured outside the United States or arrested inside the nation's borders?"
See NPRIKaiser/KennedySchool Poll on Civil Liberties, as reported in NPR, Poll:
Security Trumps Civil Liberties (Nov 30, 2001), available at &lt;http://www.npr.org/news/
specials/civillibe rtiespoll/01 1130. poll.html&gt;.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-4-2">
          <title>President Bush's plan to use secret military tribunals to try</title>
          <p>terrorists is a dangerous idea .... In his effort to defend
America from terrorists, Mr. Bush is eroding the very values
and principles he seeks to protect, including the rule of law.
The administration's action.. .do[es] an end run around the
Constitution.... [B]y ruling that terrorists fall outside the
norms of civilian and military justice, Mr. Bush has taken it
upon himself to establish a prosecutorial channel that answers
only to him. The decision is an insult to the exquisite
balancing of executive, legislative and judicial powers that the
framers incorporated into the Constitution. With the flick of a pen,
in this case, Mr. Bush has essentially discarded the rulebook
of American justice painstakingly assembled over the course
of more than two centuries. In the place of fair trials and due
process he has substituted a crude and unaccountable system
that any dictator would admire.... Using secretive military
tribunals would ultimately undermine American interests in
the Islamic world by casting doubt on the credibility of a
verdict against Osama bin Laden and his aides. No amount of
spinning by Mr. Bush's public relations team could overcome
the impression that the verdict had been dictated before the
trial began. Reliance on tribunals would also signal a lack of
confidence in the case a~ainst the terrorists and in the nation's
democratic institutions.</p>
          <p>The New York Times dismissed the Roosevelt precedent for
military tribunals as "an embarrassing skirting of the legal
process." Other prominent newspapers reacted in a similar
fashion. 2</p>
          <p>Many members of Congress also reacted critically to the
Order. Democratic representative Conyers, the ranking
member of the House Judiciary Committee, called the order "a civil
liberties calamity" that puts "the executive branch in the
unattainable role of legislator, prosecutor, judge and jury., 53
Representative Kucinich described the Bush Order as "Kafka's The
Trial writ large," and added that "we should not let the actions
of terrorists cause us to reject our American system of justice.,1 4
Representative Bob Barr, the conservative republican from
Georgia, stated the "executive order takes your breath away, if
you read the details of it."55 Democratic Senator Leahy accused
the Bush administration of ignoring "the checks and balances
that make up our constitutional framework," adding that it
improperly "cut out Congress in determining the appropriate
tribunal and procedures to try terrorists," and "sends a terrible
message to the world that, when confronted with a serious
challenge, we lack confidence in the very institutions we are fighting
for.1156</p>
          <p>Finally, the legal academy came out strongly against
military commissions. Most strikingly, a letter to Senator Leahy,
drafted by Yale Law School professors and students, and signed
by over 700 law professors and lawyers, claimed that Bush's
Order authorized the creation of institutions that were "legally
deficient, unnecessary, and unwise." It added that Bush's Military
Order "undermines the tradition of [s]eparation of [p]owers"
because, in contrast to Roosevelt's Commission, which was
based on an "express[] grant[]" of legislative authorization, the
Bush Order was "without congressional approval." The letter
added that "the use of military commissions would be unwise, as
it could endanger American lives and complicate American
foreign policy." The letter concluded: "The proposal to abandon
our existing legal institutions in favor of such a constitutionally
questionable endeavor is misguided. Our democracy is at its
most resolute when we meet crises with out bedrock ideals intact
and unyielding."5 7 Many law professors echoed the same themes
in editorials across the country. 8</p>
          <p>III. WHY THE DIFFERENT REACTIONS?</p>
          <p>The reaction to President Bush's Military Order presents
the following puzzle. In 1942, FDR's creation and use of a
military commission was widely viewed as legitimate, appropriate,
constitutionally valid, authorized by Congress, consistent with
American democratic and rule-of-law values, protective of civil
liberties, and helpful to the war effort. In 2001, Bush's Order to
establish military commissions was widely viewed (at least
among elites) to be illegitimate, inappropriate, unprecedented,
unauthorized, unconstitutional, undemocratic, violative of basic
civil liberties, harmful to the war effort, and self-defeating. Why
were the seemingly similar Military Orders greeted with such
different elite reactions?</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-4-3">
          <title>A. UNPERSUASIVE EXPLANATIONS</title>
          <p>We begin with four explanations that have some surface
appeal but that cannot, we believe, explain the different reactions
to the Roosevelt and Bush Orders.</p>
          <p>1. Domestic Legality</p>
          <p>Many people, including some distinguished professors of
law, have argued that Congress granted Roosevelt the authority
to establish military commissions to try Nazi saboteurs, while
President Bush's Order lacked congressional approval.59 On this
view, the reason for the different reactions lies in significant
differences in the legal basis for the two orders. But there are no
such differences. The Bush Order was premised on 10 U.S.C.
§821, which states that the creation of statutory jurisdiction for
court martials does not "deprive military commissions.., of
concurrent jurisdiction with respect to offenders or offenses
that.., by the law of war may be tried by military
commissions. 6 ° Roosevelt's Order was premised on the
identicallyworded predecessor to this statute, Article 15 of the Articles of
War-the very statute that a unanimous Supreme Court in
Quirin held was "explicit[]" congressional authorization for the
President to establish military commissions.6'</p>
          <p>Far from being on more tenuous ground than the Roosevelt
Order, one could plausibly argue that the Bush Order is on
firmer legal ground in light of the relevant precedents. When
Roosevelt created his Military Commission, the leading
precedent was Milligan. Bush's military commissions, by contrast,
could rely on the more recent, more supportive, and probably
more relevant Quirin precedent. Because Quirin was on the
books when Bush created his commissions but not when
Roosevelt created his, Bush's commissions have stronger grounding in
Supreme Court precedent.</p>
          <p>In addition, although Quirin held that Congress had
affirmatively authorized military commissions in Article 15 of the
Articles of War, Article 15 is probably best read merely as a
congressional refusal to abroate a prior non-statutory
jurisdiction for military commissions. . The Quirin Court thus may have
erred in concluding that Congress had, at the time of the Quirin
decision, authorized the President to establish military
commissions. But Congress re-enacted Article 15 in 1950, recodifying it
at 10 U.S.C. §821 against the background of the
Quirininterpretation. The legislative history to this reenacted provision
suggests that Congress was aware of, and accepted, Quirin's
interpretation of the provision.63 And this, in turn, makes it more
plausible today than at the time of Quirin that Congress has in
fact authorized the President to establish military commissions.
Hence the Bush Order has two bases of support that the
Roosevelt Order lacked: Quirin itself and a clearer congressional
authorization.64
offenses against the law of war before such commissions.").</p>
          <p>62. See In re Yamashita, 327 U.S. 1, 7 (1946); Madsen v. Kinsella, 343 U.S. 341,
35055 (1952); see also statement of the Judge Advocate General of the Army, Brig. Gen.
Enoch H. Crowder, S. Rep. No. 130, 64th Cong. 1st Sess. 53, 40-41 (1916) (in context of
Article 15, asserting that military commission "has not been formally authorized by
statute," but noting that Article 15 was designed to make clear that the "common law of war
jurisdiction was not ousted"); Madsen, 343 U.S. at 353 (referring to General Crowder's
testimony concerning Article 15 as "authoritative").</p>
          <p>63. See Sen. Rpt. 486, Establishing a Uniform Code of Military Justice, 81st Cong.,
1st Sess. at 13 (June 10, 1949) ("The language of [Article of War] 15 has been preserved
because it has been construed by the Supreme Court. (Ex Parte Quirin, 317 U.S. 1
(1942))."); H. Rept. 491, Uniform Code of Military Justice, 81st Cong., 1st Sess. at 17
(April 28, 1949) (same).</p>
          <p>64. Some have sought to limit the Quirin holding by arguing that it rested not only
on Article 15 concerning a law of war violation, but also on Articles 81 (relieving the
enemy) and 82 (spying). See Katyal and Tribe, 111 Yale L.J. at 1281-90 (cited in note 2). It
is true that charges were brought against the saboteurs under Articles 15, 81, and 82. But
three passages in Quirin suggest that the Court thought-rightly or wrongly-that
Article 15 itself authorized military commission trials for violations of the law of war:
A. "By the Articles of War, and especially by Article 15, Congress has
explic</p>
          <p>Our point here is not to argue that Bush's Order was in fact
on firmer legal ground than Roosevelt's. There are other issues
that may affect the legality of the two commissions in different
ways. 61 Our point is simply to show that differences in the
legality of the two commissions simply cannot explain the differences
in reaction to them. In fact, we believe that far from explaining
the different reactions to the Roosevelt and Bush orders, the
perceived legal differences between the two orders are a product
of those different reactions. During World War II, the weaker
points in the Executive's position did not receive thorough
critical scrutiny, to say the least. By contrast, skepticism about the
Bush Order resulted in intense concern with the legal
technicalities and a high degree of doubt about plausible legal arguments.
The very fact that some people now doubt and seek to confine
the reasoning of Quirin66 attests to our basic claim: A decision of
a unanimous Supreme Court, welcomed at the time, is now seen,
in many quarters, as an alarming and even dangerous precedent.
2. International Legality</p>
          <p>Another potentially relevant difference between 1942 and
2001 can be found in international law. In 1955, the United
States ratified the 1949 Geneva Conventions on the Protection
of Prisoners of War, and in 1992 the United States ratified the
International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights ("ICCPR").
Neither of these treaties was in force in 1942; both of them
potentially affect the legality of the Bush Military Order under
international law. Can the Bush Order's possible illegality under
international law explain the differences in reaction?</p>
          <p>We doubt it. The main reason is that the severest reactions
to the Bush Order, in November and December 2001, were
premised on violations of American constitutional and civil
liberties traditions, and not on violations of international law. For
the most part, the people who criticized Bush's Order did not
invoke the Order's potential international law difficulties. When
complaints based on international law arose in early 2002, they
did so mostly in connection with the treatment of "detainees" in
Guantanamo, not with respect to military commissions.
International law arguments have remained at the periphery of the
debate within the United States about the legality of military
commissions.</p>
          <p>Moreover, it is hard to see how the international law
changes affect the validity of the military commissions, as
opposed to the proceduresthe commissions must employ.
Assuming that the Geneva Convention applies to the al Qaeda and
Taliban detainees (a contested point), the Convention
contemplates the use of military commissions, and thus does not call
their legality per se into question." Thus a broad-scale dismissal
of military commissions (as opposed to commission-related
complaints about access to counsel and federal appellate review)
could not be based on the Geneva Convention. As for the
ICCPR, it says nothing about military commissions. While it
does guarantee certain basic procedural rights such as the right
to choose counsel and be presumed innocent,68 it also recognizes
that a state party to the treaty may "derogate" from these
obligations if it certifies that an emergency affecting the safety of the
nation so requires.6 9
67. See Geneva Convention III, Article 84.
68. See ICCPR, Article 14.</p>
          <p>69. See id., Article 4. As of this writing, the United States had neither used a
military commission nor attempted to derogate from the ICCPR.</p>
          <p>Once again our point is not to argue that the Bush Order
was in fact legal under international law, for this claim raises
many complicated issues that are far beyond our concern here.
Our point is simply that whatever the validity of the
international law objections to military commissions, differences in
international law in 1942 and 2001 do not adequately explain the
different reaction of elites in the United States.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>3. FDR v. Bush, Biddle v. Ashcroft</title>
      <p>In 1940 FDR was elected to his third term in a landslide in
1940; in 2000 Bush won controversially and lost the popular
vote. Attorney General Biddle was a well-respected
establishment figure; he was also a member of the ACLU and NAACP,
and was in general "revered by liberals."7° Attorney General
Ashcroft, while an establishment figure in many ways, is viewed
with suspicion by the civil liberties left and some on the
libertarian right. In the 1940s, actions by the Executive branch met with
a much greater presumption of approval, at least within elite
circles. Perhaps there is a kind of heuristic at work in the
contemporary reaction. If Bush and Ashcroft are in favor of doing
something that might be objectionable from the standpoint of
civil liberties, some people might think it reasonable to assume
that the action is, in fact, objectionable from that standpoint. A
similar heuristic may have been at work in the 1940s. If
Roosevelt and Biddle were in favor of doing something that might be
objectionable from the standpoint of civil liberties, many people
thought it reasonable to assume that the action is not, in fact,
objectionable from that standpoint. The heuristic does the work of
a more fine-grained analysis.</p>
      <p>We think that this difference has some explanatory value.
Distrust of Bush and Ashcroft by some elites was hardly
irrelevant. But the point is insufficient by itself. Counterfactuals are
notoriously hazardous, but imagine, for example, if a President
Gore and his Attorney General (Reno? Tribe?) were
responsible for a military order akin to that issued by President Bush.
The critical reaction would have been diminished in some circles,
but it would have been increased in others. We strongly suspect
that it would have been far closer to the reaction to the Bush
Order than to the Roosevelt Order.
4. The Question of Guilt or Innocence.</p>
      <p>There were many salient differences between the
authorizations for the Roosevelt and Bush military commissions.
Roosevelt's was much briefer than Bush's. Unlike Bush's, Roosevelt's
applied to U.S. citizens. But Roosevelt's had a far narrower
scope. It applied only to persons who entered the United States
to commit sabotage and related acts. Perhaps most important,
Roosevelt's authorization specifically named the eight saboteurs
who would be tried by Military Commission. The Bush Order,
by contrast, applied not just to al Qaeda members and others
who committed terrorist acts against the United States, but also
to anyone who "aided or abetted" the commission of terrorist
acts or "knowingly harbored" terrorists. And it did not include
the names of any persons who would be tried before military
commissions.</p>
      <p>The important point is that it was clear from the beginning
who would be tried before the Roosevelt Military Commission.
The defendants were in hand and widely known to be saboteurs;
there was no real doubt about their guilt; and their names were
included in the set of proclamations establishing the
Commission. By contrast, the persons to whom the Bush Order might
apply, and their factual guilt, remain uncertain. We speculate
that the critical reaction to the Bush Order would have been
radically diminished if it applied only to people who were
already under arrest for helping to plan the September 11 attack.
One of the palpable concerns of the critics is that military
commissions might convict the innocent. 71 There was no serious
question about the essential guilt of those tried before
Roosevelt's Commission. And there is a psychological point as well: A
vivid sense of the identity of the perpetrators could well heighten
the sense that an expeditious proceeding is appropriate, and
under the right conditions, such a sense could also weaken the
protests of those who insist on what they see as procedural
requirements.</p>
      <p>But again, this cannot be the whole picture. Here as
elsewhere, counterfactuals are notoriously hard to assess. But is it
plausible to think that military commissions would have been
uncontroversial in 2001 and 2002 if the defendants were
identified, were in custody, and were widely viewed to be guilty? It
71. See, for example, Editorial, Military Justice (continued), Wash. Post (cited in
note 52) (urging that under military tribunals "innocent people likely will be convicted
and punished" because "[t]he nature of the rules almost guarantees mistakes").
might well be that the identification of the perpetrators would, in
many circles, have fortified the insistence on the need for an
ordinary civil trial. We think that the most important and
instructive differences lie elsewhere.</p>
      <sec id="sec-4-1">
        <title>B. BETrER EXPLANATIONS</title>
        <p>We now turn to two explanations that we think better
account for the differences in reaction in 1942 and 2001.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-2">
        <title>1. Differences in War Context</title>
        <p>The capture of the Nazi saboteurs was one of the first pieces
of good news in an unprecedentedly large-scale war that had not
gone well during the first half of 1942. The future of the Nation
was at serious risk, and everyone was aware of that fact. World
War II was a "total war" that mobilized the entire Nation.
Nearly everyone had relatives or acquaintances involved in the
fighting, and tens of thousands of Americans had been killed or
captured by the summer of 1942. On the home front, there were
daily reminders of the war, including rubber shortages, gas
rationing, and wage and price controls. Most people had a genuine
fear of invasion by the Japanese on the west coast; and on the
east coast German submarines had sunk hundreds of ships.
Everything was disrupted; all of life was changed. There was no
ambiguity about whether the Nation was at war, or about whether
the nation's survival was at stake.</p>
        <p>The events following 9/11 are much different- certainly
thus far. 9/11 has required relatively few sacrifices or changes in
American life. There is a general (though diminishing) fear
among the population. And there have been (relatively minor)
disruptions at airports. But we have seen none of the
mobilization and sacrifice (or call to sacrifice) that characterized World
War II, and the United States has suffered only a comparatively
small number of military casualties. The main imperative to the
civilian population following 9/11 was not "sacrifice," but rather
"spend." Many continue to question whether military action is
an appropriate response to 9/11, whether we can truly be at
"war" against non-state actors like al Qaeda, and whether the
9/11 attacks represent a true threat to the Nation's survival.</p>
        <p>These radical differences in war contexts unquestionably
help explain the different reactions to the 1942 and 2001 Order
establishing military commissions. For those who view the
stakes to be lower now than they were perceived to be in 1942, it
is altogether natural to question the wisdom of military
commissions. Of course it would be extreme to suggest that the Nation's
prospects for success in World War II would have been seriously
compromised by the use of ordinary civil courts. But in 1942, the
widespread perception of a threat to national survival made it far
harder for people to insist on the use of those courts. For better
or for worse, solicitude for the interests of accused belligerents
will diminish when the risks to the Nation seem most serious and
tangible. If the current situation does not seem like a genuine
war, then civilian rather than military trials seem more
appropriate. If the stakes of the conflict are relatively low, then the
justification for diminishing civil liberties and protecting secrets is
relatively weak. If 9/11 is not a genuine threat to the nation's
survival, then the usual tradeoffs of ordinary civilian trials-in
which erroneous acquittals are the price we pay for procedures
that diminish the risk of erroneous convictions -seem
appropriate.</p>
        <p>Some platitudes are worth repeating: When a nation
believes that its future is at risk, it will not be so careful about the
protecting the perceived interests of those who are, or who
might well be, involving in creating the relevant threat. But here
too a cautionary note is appropriate. Suppose that the threat
posed by the events of 9/11 were thought to be far greater than
they now are. Would military commissions be widely approved?
As widely as in 1942? This is doubtful. To be sure, the reaction
to military commissions would be more muted if, for example,
terrorists exploded a nuclear suitcase bomb, killing 100,000
people. Hence the perception of a lesser threat, in 2001 and 2002, is
a contributing factor to the public reaction. But it is hardly all of
the picture.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-3">
        <title>2. Evolving Social Attitudes: Government, the Military, and Law</title>
        <p>It is not possible to account for the different reactions to the
Roosevelt and Bush Orders without emphasizing large social
and related legal changes within the last sixty years. President
Roosevelt acted before Vietnam, before the revelations of
Hoover's domestic espionage, and before Watergate. To say the
least, this was a time when the press, Congress, and intellectuals
had a much higher regard for the Executive branch and the
Military.</p>
        <p>In July 1942, Arthur Krock defended the elaborate secrecy
of the Nazi saboteur trial on the following terms: "The FBI
vouches for the need of secrecy and the administration's lawyers
support the legality of the procedure. Unless these lead to clear
abuses, neither is likely to be called into broad question., 72 A
passage of this sort in the New York Times is unimaginable in
2002. In large part as a result of the disclosures and rebellions of
the 1960s and 1970s, Executive branch officers -Democrat or
Republican, liberal or conservative -receive diminished levels of
trust, at least when there is a plausible claim that civil liberties
are at risk. Compare in this regard the frequent suggestion that
President Bush's Order called for "secret military trials"-a
claim that was not supported by the Order itself, which did not
mandate secrecy.</p>
        <p>But the cultural difference is not adequately described as
involving a mere reduction in trust. It involved at the same time
a massively strengthened commitment to individual rights, not
only within the culture but within the legal system itself. Begin
with culture: In 1942, "neither the country, nor its political and
intellectual leaders, nor such organizations as the American Civil
Liberties Union, were truly libertarian in their outlook. 7 3 In
1942, restrictions on free speech did not produce a firestorm of
public protest. Libelous speech was commonly regulated,
without discernible public objection. Commercial speech received no
protection at all, while sexually explicit speech was heavily
controlled, and there was little organized cultural opposition to
these practices. Of course this was an era of racial segregation,
and public opposition to discrimination was far more tepid than
it is today. Nor did the public insist on what we now take to be
minimal procedural safeguards for the accused. There is a large
question about why, exactly, the culture has shifted in the
direction of more solicitude for civil liberties and civil liberties.
Undoubtedly World War II itself played a role, encouraging
American culture to attempt to distinguish itself radically from those of
regimes that did not respect freedom. We cannot fully address
the causal question here; but it is clear that the shift has been
massive.</p>
        <p>
          Turn now to law: In 1942, federal constitutional law was
fundamentally different from what it is today. The Court that
72. Arthur Krock, In the Nation: Civil Rights in the Saboteurs' Trial, N.Y. Times 18
(July
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">21, 1942</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>73. See Belknap, 89 Mil. L. Rev. at 89 (cited in note 25), see also Francis Biddle, In
BriefAuthority 234-35 (Doubleday, 1962).
wrote Quirin was the same Court that supported the Japanese
exclusion in Korematsu. Indigent defendants did not yet have a
right to counsel.7 4 Within the states, the exclusionary rule was
yet to be created.75 Police abuses had not yet been held to be
generally violative of the Due Process clause of the Fourteenth
Amendment.76 In fact the criminal procedure revolution was
decades away. 17</p>
        <p>In addition, habeas corpus review has changed significantly
since 1942. Beginning a few months after Quirin was decided,
the Supreme Court began its dramatic extension of habeas
corpus from a review of jurisdictional defects in prior judicial
proceedings to something closer to post-conviction federal review of
the merits of defendants' federal constitutional and statutory
claims.78 This expanded conception of habeas was the
procedural mechanism that made possible the extraordinary growth,
in the late 1950s and 1960s, of constitutional protections for
defendants in criminal cases. Although the Rehnquist Court has
cut back on the scope of habeas corpus, the writ in its modern
guise remains available for properly raised claims of
constitutional deprivation. Moreover, the expansion of habeas was not
limited to civilian trials. It has also extended to military trials of
U.S. service members, even ones held abroad.7 9</p>
        <p>Finally, military justice itself has undergone a fundamental
transformation since 1942. Congress's enactment of the
Uniform Code of Military Justice ("UCMJ") in 1950 marked "the
most important development in military justice since our
country's founding." 80 The Articles of War regime that governed
during World War II was a "command-dominated system...
designed to secure obedience to the commander, and to serve the
commander's will."'" Military justice during this period
contained few of the procedural protections of the civilian criminal
system, and was widely criticized as "harsh and arbitrary. ' 82
Following World War II, in which the U.S. military fought to
preserve American freedoms, it was widely believed that these
freedoms should extend to the military itself.</p>
        <p>The UCMJ applied the civilian concept of procedural justice
in a way that was consistent with the special circumstances of the
military.83 The UCMJ and its successor statutes (such as the
Military Justice Act of 1968)84 established a powerful Court of
Military Appeals, independent of command structures, that
would eventually extend most conceptions of civilian due
process to military courts. The Military Justice Act of 1983
continued this trend by authorizing Supreme Court review of the Court
of Military Appeals. Today military justice remains different
from civilian justice in important respects. But as Justice
Ginsburg correctly noted in Weiss v. United States, "men and women
in the Armed Forces do not leave constitutional safeguards
behind.., when they enter military service," for the present system
of military justice is "notably more sensitive to due process
concerns than the one prevailing through most of our country's
history."85</p>
        <p>In the past 60 years, in sum, the Nation has become far
more committed to the independence of the federal judiciary
and to a high degree of civil liberties and criminal procedural
protections. The legal and social world of 2001 is radically
different from the legal and social world of 1942. In this new world,
it was much more natural to think that the displacement of
civilian courts in favor of a more expeditious military procedure
would offend constitutional values.</p>
        <sec id="sec-4-3-1">
          <title>IV. ON THE EVOLUTION OF CIVIL LIBERTIES</title>
          <p>DURING WARTIME</p>
          <p>The different reactions to the Roosevelt and Bush military
commissions exemplify a persistent theme in the historical
evolution of civil liberties during wartime in the United States.
Dur81. Id. at3.
82. Id. at6.</p>
          <p>
            83. See generally Jonathan Lurie, Military Justice in America: The US. Court of
Appealsfor The Armed Forces,1775-1980
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32 ref36">(U Press of Kansas, rev ed.2001)</xref>
            .
84. Pub. L. No. 90-632,82 Stat. 1335 (1968).
85. 510 U.S. 163, 194 (1994) (Ginsburg, J., concurring).
ing every serious war in our nation's history, civil liberties have
been curtailed. Following (usually not during) each war, elites
regret these restrictions on civil liberties because the restrictions
often seem-from the ex post perspective when the danger of
war has passed and the true extent of the threats become
known-to be unwarranted or extreme. During the next war,
the perceived abuses during the last war are used as the baseline
for determining which civil liberties restrictions are appropriate.
This dialectic produces a ratchet effect, over time, in favor of
more expansive civil liberties during wartime. Of course there is
nothing inevitable to this process. We could imagine an opposite
effect, in which a failure to provide adequate security was
recognized as such, in hindsight, and in which the ratchet effect
worked in the opposite direction. But in the American context,
with a remarkable record of military success, the historical trend
has been toward increasing suspicion of intrusions on civil liberty
and civil rights, even when national security seems to be at risk.
          </p>
          <p>Arthur Krock of the New York Times again illustrates the
point. In a column on July 14, 1942, Krock recalled a bill
proposed by Senator Chamberlin during World War I to punish
spies and disloyalists by court martial. The proposal, Krock
noted, came in 1918, when "a wave of hysteria about spies and
sabotage has swept the country.,1 6 The bill died after President
Wilson opposed it on the ground that it was unconstitutional,
inconsistent "with the spirit and practice of America," and in any
event unnecessary in light of the Espionage Act and Sabotage
Act.</p>
          <p>Krock recounted this episode in order to show, in the midst
of the saboteurs trial, that "the country seems to have grown up"
since 1918 with respect to civil liberties. "No such proposal [like
Chamberlin's] or anything remotely like it has been responsibly
put forth in Congress or among the public," he noted. He
continued:</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-4-4">
        <title>The chapter from past history confers even greater dignity on</title>
        <p>the proceedings of the military commission [for the Nazi
saboteurs]. The contrast is very great between this deliberate
search for truth and justice in a case where more summary
methods might easily have been invoked and what Mr.</p>
        <p>Chamberlain would have done to anyone merely charged with
86. Arthur Krock, When MartialLaw Was Proposedfor Everybody, N.Y. Times 18
(July 14, 1942).
far lesser crimes twenty-four years ago. 87</p>
        <p>From today's perspective, much of Krock's piece seems
peculiar. Wilson's favorable invocation in 1918 of the Espionage
Act in an argument protective of civil liberties appears ironic,
even weird, to the modern observer. For the Espionage Act was
amended in May 1918 to include the Sedition Act, a statute that
formed the basis of some of the most notorious, and widely
regretted, anti-free speech prosecutions in U.S. history.8" But the
contemporary supporters of the Sedition Act, many of whom
viewed themselves as "enlightened liberals" protective of the
First Amendment, 9 were no doubt implicitly comparing their
acts to the last great war, in which Lincoln suspended the writ of
habeas corpus, arrested civilians and tried them in military
commissions, seized newspapers and suspended their mailing
privileges, and much more.9 Similarly, many today have difficulty
understanding how Krock could view a (literally) secret military
commission as a dignified and deliberate search for truth. But
Krock's claim seemed natural in 1942, for his implicit baseline of
comparison was the World War I experience.91</p>
        <p>The Krock episode illustrates what Chief Justice Rehnquist
has described as a "generally ameliorative trend" in civil liberties
during wartime. 92 Rehnquist notes that World Wars I and II
were each, by comparison to the prior war, characterized by
increased congressional and judicial involvement in the protection
of civil liberties, and diminished governmental attempts to
suppress criticism of the war effort. 93 To Rehnquist's catalogue we
add the more general point that restrictions of civil liberties that
came to be regretted after the war were never again repeated.
No President has ever repeated Lincoln's suspension of the writ
of habeas corpus, his military trials for civilians in the United
States, or his brutal suppression of newspapers. We have never
again seen loyalty prosecutions as in World War I, and we are
unlikely to do so. The same is true of the World War II
exclusion of Japanese-Americans.</p>
        <p>This brings us back to the Bush Military Order. Following
World War II, many criticized the use of some military
commissions during the War, especially the ones in Japan. But the
commissions were not condemned with the same vehemence,
and were not looked back upon with the same sense of shame, as
Lincoln's suspension of the writ, or the World War I speech
prosecutions, or the World War II Japanese exclusion Order. In
the post-war period, military commissions were not generally
viewed as a horrible "mistake" never to be repeated again. As
we noted above, in 1950 Congress recodified the statute that
supported the military trial of the Nazis, and in the process
appeared to embrace Quirin's interpretation of affirmative
congressional authorization for military commissions. And in sharp
contrast to, say, Korematsu, Quirinhas often been cited without
embarrassment by the Supreme Court as good law.94 In this
light, it is perhaps not surprising that the Bush military
commissions, though subject to criticism, was not unthinkable in 2001,
and indeed attracted some support among some elites.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen whether the President will use military
commissions to prosecute those connected to the 9/11 attacks. If
he does not, one important reason will be the changed
circumstances -including changed legal and cultural
circumstanceswe have outlined. If he does, the commissions will look far more
like civilian courts than past commissions. Department of
Defense regulations provide that commission trials are open except
when necessary to protect national security or the safety of
participants. The regulations also presume the innocence of the
accused, require proof beyond a reasonable doubt, require the
prosecutor to provide the accused with access to all evidence to
be introduced at trial, including exculpatory evidence, forbid
adverse inferences to be drawn from the accused's failure to testify,
94. See, e.g., Hohn v. UnitedStates, 524 U.S. 236, 246 (1998); Middendorfv. Henry,
425 U.S. 25, 34 (1976); Parkerv. Levy, 417 U.S. 733, 768 (1974) (Douglas, J., dissenting);
Gosa v. Mayden, 413 U.S. 665,685-686 (1972); United States v. O'Brien, 391 U.S. 367, 377
(1968); Reid v. Covert, 354 U.S. 1, 37 n. 68 (1957). By contrast, compare the treatment of
Korematsuin, for example, Stenberg v. Carhart,530 U.S. 914, 953 (2000) (Scalia, J.,
concurring); Skinner v. Railway LaborExecutives' Ass'n, 489 U.S. 602, 635 (1989) (Marshall,
J., dissenting); Richmond v. J.A. Croson Co., 488 U.S. 469, 501 (1989). We should note
that there was one dimension along which Quirin was deeply regretted ex post, namely,
the haste in which the decision was reached, and the unfortunate circumstance of writing
and releasing the opinion after six of the eight saboteurs had been executed. See
Danelski, 1 J. S. Ct. Hist. 61 (cited in note 3).
provide the accused with a military attorney and allow him to
choose another attorney, require a 2/3 vote for conviction and a
unanimous vote for a death sentence, and require at least two
levels of review, including one level that can (but need not)
contain civilian judges.95 While these procedures fall short of
civilian standards (especially with respect to evidence rules, the jury,
and judicial review), they are in most respects like military trials
under the Uniform Code of Military Justice, and they provide
far greater procedural safeguards than any previous military
commission, including Nuremberg. These procedural advances
can be seen as a result of the factors we have discussed. In short,
changes in the use and structure of military commissions fit the
general trend described here:</p>
        <p>So too do the other restrictions that the Bush administration
has placed on civil liberties. Civil libertarians have condemned
the Bush administration's monitoring of attorney-client phone
calls, its treatment of the Guantanamo prisoners, its detention of
alleged "dirty bomber" Jose Padilla as an "enemy belligerent,"
and its detentions of Muslims on technical immigration
violations. We do not express a view on these practices; nothing said
here is meant to approve of them, for approval would require a
detailed analysis of each. But compared to past wars led by
Lincoln, Wilson, and Roosevelt, the Bush administration has, thus
far, diminished relatively few civil liberties. Even a conservative
Executive branch, it seems, is influenced by the general trend
towards protections of civil liberties during wartime.</p>
        <p>There is a potential danger here. The danger is that in an
age of anthrax, nuclear suitcases, and other easy-to-conceal
weapons of mass destruction, the threat posed by al Qaeda and
other terrorists might warrant tradeoffs between liberty and
security that are inconsistent with ordinary respect for civil
liberties. It is always difficult to gauge the seriousness of wartime
threats to security in the midst of the war. The problem is
significantly exacerbated in the context of asymmetrical warfare
involving suicidal terrorists. Whether the government has made
the proper tradeoff between liberty and order can be known
only ex post. The ameliorative trend in civil liberties is a
testament to our extraordinary constitutional traditions and legal
culture-and perhaps above all to the post-World War II shift in
legal understandings. It is customary, and sensible, to fear that an
95. See Department of Defense March 21, 2002, available at &lt;http://www.
dfenselink.mil/news/Mar2002/d20020321ord.pdf.&gt;.
overestimation of the current threat will lead us to abridge civil
liberties in unjustifiable ways. But it is not senseless to fear as
well that the gravitational pull of this trend might, in this or
other circumstances, lead some to underestimate the threat we
actually face.</p>
        <p>V. CONCLUSION</p>
        <p>The different reactions to the Roosevelt and Bush Orders
illuminate a great deal about the relationship between war and
civil liberties, and about cultural and legal change over time. We
have argued that perceived legal differences between the
Orders, far from explaining the different reactions, are a product of
those different reactions. The enthusiasm for the Roosevelt
Order, and the critical reaction to the Bush Order, can be explained
partly by the much greater perception of threat in 1942 than in
2001. But the most powerful and instructive explanation, we
think, lies in the fact that with respect to actions of the Executive
branch that might endanger civil liberties, the Nation is now far
less trusting of government, and far more solicitous of the
accused, than it was sixty years ago. This change counts as a
genuine revolution not only in law but also in cultural attitudes. An
exploration of the radically different attitudes toward essentially
identical legal acts is a remarkable illustration of this revolution.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          3.
          <article-title>Unless otherwise indicated, the following account of the Nazi saboteur ordeal is based on Eugene Rachlis, They Came to Kill: The Story of Eight Nazi Saboteursin America 3</article-title>
          (
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Random</given-names>
            <surname>House</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1961</year>
          )
          <article-title>;</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>David J.</given-names>
            <surname>Danelski</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Saboteurs'Case, 1 J. S.Ct. Hist</source>
          .
          <volume>61</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          4.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Rachlis</surname>
          </string-name>
          , They Came to Killat
          <volume>22</volume>
          ,
          <issue>57</issue>
          (cited in note 3).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>5. Id.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>6. Id. at 169-70.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>7. Id. at 173.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          8.
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Felix</given-names>
            <surname>Cotton</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Death PenaltyAsked for 8 CapturedSpies, Wash</article-title>
          .
          <source>Post</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          (
          <issue>June</issue>
          29,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          9.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Contemporary</surname>
            <given-names>polls</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , American Institute of Public Opinion, as reported in Week in Review, N.Y. Times,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Section</surname>
            <given-names>IV</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>2</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug 2</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          10.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Raymond</surname>
            <given-names>Moley</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Perspective: Death for the Saboteurs</article-title>
          ,
          <source>Newsweek</source>
          <volume>64</volume>
          (
          <issue>July 6</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          11.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rachlis</surname>
          </string-name>
          , They Came to Kill at 173 (cited in note 3).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          12. FDR Memorandum to Biddle, (June 30,
          <year>1942</year>
          ), cited in Danelski, 1
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Hist. at 65 (cited in note 3).</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          13.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Biddle</surname>
            <given-names>Memorandum to FDR</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (June 30,
          <year>1942</year>
          ), cited in Danelski, 1
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Hist. at 66 (cited in note 3).</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          16.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>Wood</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Army Court to Try 8 Nazi Saboteurs</article-title>
          ,
          <source>N.Y. Times</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <issue>3</issue>
          (
          <issue>July 3</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          17.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          18.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>Wood</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Nazi Saboteurs Face Stern Army Justice: Order For a Military Trial Comes as National Anger at Invasion Rises</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>N.Y.</given-names>
            <surname>Times</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Section</surname>
            <given-names>IV</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>6</volume>
          (
          <issue>July 5</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          19,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          20.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>Rachlis</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , They Came to Kill at 177 (cited in note 3).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          21.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Arthur</surname>
            <given-names>Krock</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Editorial, In the Nation:
          <article-title>When Martial Law Was Proposedfor Everybody</article-title>
          ,
          <source>N.Y. Times</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          (
          <issue>July</issue>
          14,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          22. In Shape of Things,
          <source>The Nation 41 (July</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          23.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          24.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>Wood</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Supreme Court is Called in UnprecedentedSession to HearPlea of Nazi Spies,
          <source>N.Y. Times</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <issue>10</issue>
          (
          <issue>July</issue>
          28,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          25.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Michal</surname>
            <given-names>Belknap</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>The Supreme Court Goes to War: The Meaning and Implications of the Nazi SaboteurCase, 89</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Mil. L.</given-names>
            <surname>Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>59</volume>
          ,
          <issue>69</issue>
          (
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          26.
          <article-title>As quoted in Rachlis, They Came to Kill at 249 (cited in note 3).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          27.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>
          28.
          <article-title>"In the time of war, the laws are silent"</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          29.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Arthur</surname>
            <given-names>Krock</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>In the Nation: The Issues of Law and Factin Sabotage Case, N.Y. Times (July</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          30.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Editorial</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Habeus Corpus,
          <source>Wash. Post</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          (
          <issue>July</issue>
          31,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          31.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Editorial</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A Welcome</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Opinion</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>N.Y. Herald Tribune</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug 1</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          32.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Week</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>'s Editorial News Events: America's Judicial System Tested</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>N.Y.</given-names>
            <surname>Herald Tribune</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Section</surname>
            <given-names>II</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>3</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug</issue>
          . 2,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          33.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Editorial</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Saboteur's Case, Wash. Post</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug 1</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          34. The Shape of Things, The Nation,
          <volume>103</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug 8</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          35.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Some</surname>
          </string-name>
          , to be sure, were critical.
          <article-title>Norman Cousins, for example, viewed the trial as "an ostentation out of democratic procedure" that made a "farce out of justice." Norman Cousins, The Saboteurs,The Sat</article-title>
          .
          <source>Rev. of Lit</source>
          .
          <volume>8</volume>
          (
          <issue>Aug 8</issue>
          ,
          <year>1942</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          50.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Editorial</surname>
          </string-name>
          , A Travesty of Justice, N.Y. Times
          <source>A24 (Nov. 16</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          51. See also Editorial, Justice Deformed:
          <article-title>War and the Constitution</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>N.Y.</given-names>
            <surname>Times</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Week in Review,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Section</surname>
            <given-names>IV</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>14</volume>
          (
          <issue>Dec 2</issue>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          52.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Editorial</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>An</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Un-American Secrecy</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Times</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Section</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>24</volume>
          (Nov. 17,
          <year>2001</year>
          ); Editorial,
          <string-name>
            <surname>MilitaryJustice</surname>
          </string-name>
          (Continued),
          <source>Wash. Post A24 (Nov. 26</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          53.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Lawmakers Criticize Bush's Order for Military Tribunals</article-title>
          ,
          <volume>11</volume>
          /16/02, available at &lt;http://www.cnn.com/2001/US/1/1 6/inv.tribunals&gt;.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          54. Press Release of Representative Kucinich,
          <source>November</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          , available at &lt;http://www.house.gov/Kucinich/press/pr-011115-tribunals.htm&gt;.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          55. Joyce Howard Price,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Unlikely Allies Fight Federal Anti-Terror</surname>
            <given-names>Initiatives</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Washington Times (Nov. 11,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          56.
          <string-name>
            <surname>George</surname>
            <given-names>Lardner</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Jr.,
          <source>Democrats Blast Order on Tribunals: Senators Told Military Trials Fall Under President's Power, Wash. Post A22 (Nov. 29</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          57. See Yale Letter dated
          <volume>12</volume>
          /5/2001, at &lt;http://www.law.yale.edu/outside/html/ PublicAffairs/152/Leahy.pdf.&gt;
          <article-title>(last visited</article-title>
          <volume>7</volume>
          /23/02).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          58.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Bruce</surname>
            <given-names>Ackerman</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Bush Can't Operate as a One-</article-title>
          Man
          <string-name>
            <surname>Act</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Times</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>M5 (Dec</article-title>
          . 16,
          <year>2001</year>
          );
          <article-title>George Fletcher, War and the Constitution: Bush's Military Tribunals Haven't Got a Legal Leg to Stand On</article-title>
          ,
          <source>The American Prospect</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          (
          <issue>Jan</issue>
          . 1,
          <year>2002</year>
          );
          <article-title>Patricia Williams, War and the Law: The Dangerous Patriot's Game</article-title>
          ,
          <source>The Observer 26 (Dec. 2</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          );
          <string-name>
            <surname>Anne-Marie</surname>
            <given-names>Slaughter</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Al Qaeda Should be Tried Before the World, N.Y. Times A23 (Nov. 17</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          );
          <article-title>Harold Hongju Koh, We Have the Right Courts for Bin Laden</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>N.Y.</given-names>
            <surname>Times</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A39 (Nov</article-title>
          . 23,
          <year>2001</year>
          );
          <article-title>Judith Resnick, Invading the Courts: We Don't Need Military Tribunals to Sort Out the Guilty, Legal Times: Law and Lobbying In the Nations Capital 34 (Jan</article-title>
          . 14,
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>59. See Yale Letter to SenatorPatrickLeahy (cited in note 57).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          60. 10 U.S.C. §
          <volume>821</volume>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          61. See Ex Parte Quirin,317 U.S.
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          (
          <year>1942</year>
          )
          <article-title>("By the Articles of War, and especially Article 15, Congress has explicitly provided, so far as it may constitutionally do so, that military tribunals shall have jurisdiction to try offenders or offenses against the law of war in appropriate cases."); id. ("Congress [in Article 15] has authorized trial of 70</article-title>
          . Geoffrey Perrett, Days of Sadness, Years of Triumph, The American People,
          <fpage>1939</fpage>
          -1945 at 358 (Coward,
          <string-name>
            <surname>McCann</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Geoghegan,
          <year>1985</year>
          ). See also Richard W. Steele,
          <article-title>Free Speech in the Good War 119 (St</article-title>
          . Martin's Press,
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          74. Gideon v.
          <source>Wainright</source>
          , 372 U.S.
          <volume>335</volume>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          75. Mapp v.
          <source>Ohio</source>
          , 367 U.S.
          <volume>643</volume>
          (
          <year>1961</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          76. See Rochin v.
          <source>California</source>
          ,342 U.S.
          <volume>165</volume>
          (
          <year>1952</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          77.
          <article-title>The largest symbol here is Mirandav</article-title>
          . Arizona, 384 U.S.
          <volume>436</volume>
          (
          <year>1966</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          78. See Wainwright v.
          <source>Sykes</source>
          , 433 U.S.
          <volume>72</volume>
          ,
          <issue>79</issue>
          (
          <year>1977</year>
          )
          <article-title>(noting that the Court in Waley v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Johnston</source>
          , 316 U.S.
          <volume>101</volume>
          (
          <year>1942</year>
          ),
          <article-title>"openly discarded the concept of jurisdiction.., as a touchstone of the availability of federal habeas review, and acknowledged that such review is available for claims of 'disregard of the constitutional rights of the accused, and where the writ is the only effective means of preserving his rights</article-title>
          .
          <source>"')</source>
          .
          <article-title>Other important decisions in this line were Brown v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Allen</source>
          , 344 U.S.
          <volume>443</volume>
          (
          <year>1953</year>
          );
          <article-title>Sanders v</article-title>
          .
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>373</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          );
          <article-title>Fay v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Noia</source>
          , 372 U.S.
          <volume>391</volume>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          )
          <article-title>; and Townsend v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Sain</source>
          , 372 U.S.
          <volume>293</volume>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          )
          <article-title>; see generally Paul M. Bator, Finality in Criminal Law</article-title>
          and FederalHabeasCorpus forState Prisoners,
          <volume>76</volume>
          Harv. L. Rev.
          <volume>441</volume>
          (
          <year>1963</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref49">
        <mixed-citation>
          79.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <article-title>Braden v</article-title>
          . 30th
          <source>JudicialCircuitCourt of Kentucky</source>
          , 410 U.S.
          <volume>484</volume>
          (
          <year>1973</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <mixed-citation>
          80.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Brigadier</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>General (retired) John Cooke</article-title>
          ,
          <source>Introduction: Fiftieth Anniversary of the Uniform Code of MilitaryJustice,Symposium Edition</source>
          ,
          <volume>165</volume>
          Mil. L. Rev.
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1</issue>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <mixed-citation>
          87.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <mixed-citation>
          88.
          <article-title>See for example, Frohwerk v</article-title>
          .
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>249</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>204</volume>
          (
          <year>1919</year>
          );
          <article-title>Debs v</article-title>
          .
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>249</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>211</volume>
          (
          <year>1919</year>
          );
          <article-title>Abrams v</article-title>
          .
          <source>UnitedStates</source>
          , 250 U.S.
          <volume>616</volume>
          (
          <year>1919</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <mixed-citation>
          89. See Richard Polenberg,
          <source>FightingFaiths:The Abrams Case, The Supreme Court, and Free Speech</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          -36 (Viking Penguin,
          <year>1987</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <mixed-citation>
          90.
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>generally</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , Mark E. Neely, Jr.,
          <source>The Fate of Liberty: Abraham Lincoln and Civil Liberties</source>
          (Oxford U. Press,
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <mixed-citation>
          91. On this general point see Richard Polenberg, War and Society: The United States,
          <fpage>1941</fpage>
          -1945 at 37 (
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.P. Lippincott</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <year>1972</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <mixed-citation>
          92.
          <string-name>
            <surname>William H. Rehnquist</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>All the Laws But One: Civil Liberties in Wartime 221 (Alfred A Knopf</source>
          ,
          <year>1998</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <mixed-citation>
          93.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Id</surname>
          </string-name>
          . at 219-21.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>