<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>W hat Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy, Desuetude, Sexuality, and Marriage</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <email>unbound@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "What Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>Desuetude, Sexuality, and Marriage"</addr-line>
          ,
          <institution>John M. Olin Program in Law and Economics Working Paper No.</institution>
          <addr-line>196, 2003</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">
          <label>2</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <fpage>3</fpage>
      <lpage>44</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics Part of the Law Commons Recommended Citation</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>JOHN M. OLIN LAW &amp; ECONOMICS WORKING PAPER NO. 196
(2D SERIES)
What Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy, Desuetude,
Sexuality, and Marriage</p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>What Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy, Desuetude, Sexuality, and Marriage</title>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein*</p>
      <p>The Supreme Court’s decision in Lawrence v. Texas is best seen as a cousin to
Griswold v. Connecticut, invalidating a ban on the use of contraception within marriage,
and Reed v. Reed, invalidating a preference for men over women in the administration of
estates. In both cases, the Court struck down an anachronistic law palpably out of step
with existing public convictions. Lawrence should be understood in the same terms, as
rooted in a distinctly American-style doctrine of desuetude. The central principle is that
at least if certain interests are involved, criminal statutes may not be invoked against
citizens when the underlying moral judgments have become anachronistic, as
demonstrated by a pattern of nonenforcement. A key problem here is procedural; it
involves an absence of fair notice and arbitrary exercise of discretion. This
understanding of the decision has implications for the many imaginable constitutional
challenges to other laws involving sex and sexual orientation. After Lawrence, states are
certainly prohibited from banning fornication; they are almost certainly forbidden to ban
use of sexual devices. Bans on prostitution, incest, and adultery stand on firmer grounds,
though even here responsible challenges can be imagined. After Lawrence, the
Constitution almost certainly forbids public discrimination against those who have
engaged in homosexual conduct, at least outside of certain specialized contexts (most
notably the military). The hardest cases involve the failure to recognize same-sex
marriages. The ban on same-sex marriages cannot be said to be an anachronism, even
though it is not easy, in principle, to reject the law struck down in Lawrence while
permitting states to deny gays and lesbians the right to marry. One general lesson,
underlined by Lawrence, is that political and social change is usually a precondition for
changed interpretation of the Constitution.
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor, Law School and Department of Political Science,
University of Chicago. I am grateful to Mary Anne Case, Carolyn Frantz, Richard A. Posner, Geoffrey
Stone, and Adrian Vermeule for valuable comments; special thanks to Case, Frantz, and Vermeule for
discussions. I am also grateful to Sarah A. Sulkowski for superb research assistance.</p>
      <p>In 1900, Mr. Dooley famously said that “[n]o matter whether th’ constitution
follows th’ flag or not, th’ supreme court follows th ‘ilection returns.”1 The Court doesn’t
really do that. But members of the Supreme Court live in society, and they are inevitably
influenced by what society appears to think.2 My principal suggestion here is that the
Court’s remarkable decision in Lawrence v. Texas3 is best seen as a successor to
Griswold v. Connecticut45: judicial invalidation of a law that had become hopelessly out
of touch with existing social convictions. So understood, Lawrence, like Griswold,
reflects an American variation on the old English idea of desuetude. Put too simply, the
basic idea is that when constitutionally important interests are at stake, due process
principles requiring fair notice, and banning arbitrary action, are violated when criminal
prosecution is brought on the basis of moral judgments lacking public support, as
exemplified by exceedingly rare enforcement activity.6</p>
      <p>In Griswold, it will be recalled, the Court invalidated a Connecticut law
forbidding married people to use contraceptives—a law that was ludicrously inconsistent
with public convictions in Connecticut and throughout the nation.7 Griswold was decided
in the midst of a substantial national rethinking of issues of sex and morality. Whatever
the outcome of that rethinking, it was clear, by 1965, that reasonable people would no
longer support bans on the use of contraceptives within marriage. In this respect,
Griswold was quite similar to Reed v. Reed.8 There the Court struck down an Idaho
statute giving a preference to men over women in the administration of estates of
decedents who had died intestate—a law that was unquestionably a holdover from views
about sex roles that were widely regarded as obsolete. Reed was decided in the midst of a
substantial rethinking of gender roles; whatever the outcome of that rethinking, it was
clear, by 1971, that a flat presumption in favor of men over women in employment would
no longer be acceptable in principle.9 Lawrence belongs in the same family. In the area of</p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>1Peter Dunne, The Supreme Court’s Decisions, in Mr. Dooley’s Opinions 26 (1900).</title>
        <p>2 Robert Dahl made this argument nearly a half-century ago, before much of the work of the Warren Court.
Notwithstanding the passage of decades, his argument stands up well. See Robert Dahl, Decision-Making in
a Democracy: The Supreme Court as a National Policy-Maker, 6 Journal of Public Law 279 (1957).
3 123 S. Ct. 2472 (2003).
4 381 U.S. 479 (1965).
5 404 U.S. 71 (1971).
6 I specify this brief statement below.
7 381 U.S. 479 (1965).
8 404 U.S. 71 (1971).
9 The Court has shown special sensitivity to changing public convictions in the death penalty context.
Furman v. Georgia, 408 US 238 (1972), invalidated certain capital sentences, in a complex set of opinions
that seemed to presage the end of capital punishment in the United States. At least in retrospect, Furman is
best seen as a kind of “remand” to state legislatures, asking for a new assessment of whether capital
punishment was consistent with contemporary values. The result of the “remand” was a new affirmation of
public support for capital punishment, to which the Court subsequently deferred, see Gregg v. Georgia, 428
US 153 (1976). In Coker v. Georgia, 433 U.S. 584 (1977), and Enmund v. Florida, 458 U.S. 782, 789-793
(1982), the Court relied heavily on contemporary practices in striking down death sentences for rape and
for a defendant who did not take or intend to take life.More recently, the Court ruled that the Constitution
forbids application to capital punishment to the mentally retarded, see Atkins v. Virginia, 536 US 304
(2002); in so ruling, the Court relied heavily on what it saw as changing social values. In a theme echoed in
Lawrence, the Court wrote, A claim that punishment is excessive is judged not by the standards that
prevailed in 1685 when Lord Jeffreys presided over the ‘Bloody Assizes’ or when the Bill of Rights was
sexual orientation, America is in the midst of a civil rights revolution -- one that has
moved, in an extraordinarily short time, toward delegitimating prejudice against and
hatred for homosexuals. Lawrence was made possible by that revolution, of which it is
now a part.</p>
        <p>In making this argument, my principal goal is not to evaluate Lawrence, but
instead to obtain an understanding of its scope and of its relationship to other apparently
dramatic decisions in the Court’s past. But even if my argument is correct, it must be
acknowledged that the Court’s remarkably opaque opinion has three principal strands.10
Each of those strands supports a different understanding of the Court’s holding and the
principle that supports it.
1. Autonomy. A tempting reading of Lawrence is straightforward: A criminal
prohibition on sodomy is unconstitutional because it intrudes on private sexual
conduct that does not harm third parties. On this view, the Court has endorsed a quite
general principle: Without a compelling justification, the state cannot interfere with
consensual sexual behavior, at least if that behavior is noncommercial. On this view,
consensual sexual behavior counts as a fundamental right for purposes of the due
process clause. The state is forbidden to intrude into the domain of consensual sexual
behavior unless it can show that its intrusion is the least restrictive means of
achieving a compelling state interest—a showing that will be impossible to make, at
least most of the time.
2. Rational basis. An alternative reading of Lawrence, also quite broad, would take the
Court to have held, not that sexual behavior counts as a fundamental right requiring
compelling justification, but that the criminal prohibition on sodomy is
unconstitutional because it is not supported by a legitimate state interest. The
principle here is that the government cannot interfere with consensual sexual behavior
if it is attempting to do so for only moral reasons, unaccompanied by a risk of actual
harm. The implications of this reading are not so different from those of the first; both
are Millian in nature.11 But the two readings are nonetheless different, because the
second depends not on the fundamental nature of the right to engage in sexual
activity, but instead on the absence of even plausibly legitimate grounds for
interfering with that right in the context of consensual sodomy. On this reading,
adopted, but rather by those that currently prevail.” Id. at 311. In a key passage, the Court suggested: “It is
not so much the number of these States [abolishing the death penalty for the mentally retarded] that is
significant, but the consistency of the direction of change. Given the well-known fact that anticrime
legislation is far more popular than legislation providing protections for persons guilty of violent crime, the
large number of States prohibiting the execution of mentally retarded persons (and the complete absence of
States passing legislation reinstating the power to conduct such executions) provides powerful evidence
that today our society views mentally retarded offenders as categorically less culpable than the average
criminal.” Id. at 315. Note also that the Court emphasized that even in states that authorized the death
penalty to those with mental retardation, few were actually willing to impose that punishment, an idea with
clear links to the rationale in Lawrence.
10 In this respect, the decision is akin to Plyler v. Doe, 457 US 202 (1982), in which the Court struck down
a law requiring children of illegal aliens to pay for public education; there too the Court’s opinion was an
amalgam of considerations, without a clear doctrinal foundation.
11 John Stuart Mill, On Liberty (Currin V. Shields ed., Liberal Arts Press 1956) (1859).
Lawrence is rooted in a form of “rational basis” review, one that dooms a great deal
of legislation.</p>
        <p>Desuetude, American-style. A narrower reading of Lawrence, my emphasis here,
would take the following form: The criminal prohibition on sodomy is
unconstitutional because it intrudes on private sexual conduct without having a strong
or even legitimate moral grounding in existing public commitments. If this is the
Court’s holding, it is undergirded by a more general principle: Without a strong
justification, the state cannot bring the criminal law to bear on consensual sexual
behavior if enforcement of the relevant law can no longer claim to have strong moral
support in the enforcing state or the nation as a whole. This aspect of the opinion is
rooted in the old idea of desuetude. It suggests that, at least in some circumstances,
involving certain kinds of interests, a criminal law cannot be enforced if it has lost
public support.</p>
        <p>It should be clear that while all three principles are potentially broad, the first and
the second are the most far-reaching. And there is actually a fourth understanding of the
opinion, one that cannot be characterized as the Court’s holding, but one that is perhaps a
subtext:
4. Equality. Sodomy laws are unconstitutional because they demean the lives of gays
and lesbians and thus offend the Constitution’s equality principle. The underlying
principle is that as a general rule, there is no legitimate basis for treating homosexuals
differently than heterosexuals. On this view, Lawrence is really a case about the
social subordination of gays and lesbians, whatever the rhetoric about sexual freedom
in general. Lawrence’s words sound in due process, but much of its music involves
equal protection.</p>
        <p>Each of the four ideas can be found in Lawrence, a claim that I hope to establish
here. But I want to draw special attention to the third, which is, I believe, central to the
Court’s own analysis, and a key to the development of substantive due process over the
past decades. In fact something like a desuetude principle is part and parcel of the
Lawrence Court’s treatment of the state’s interest, showing why that interest counts as
illegitimate, and also of the Court’s explanation of why the case cannot be distinguished
from Griswold and its successors. When the Court asserts the absence of a “legitimate
state interest which can justify its intrusion into the personal and private life of an
individual,”12 it is best understood to be saying that the moral claim that underlies the
intrusion has become hopelessly anachronistic. And the anachronistic nature of that moral
claim has everything to do with the Court’s rejection, not of moral claims in general, but
of the particular moral claim that underlies criminal prohibitions on same-sex sodomy.</p>
        <p>Lawrence might be read broadly as an effort to enact some version of John Stuart
Mill’s On Liberty13, requiring respect for individual choices (at least with respect to sex)
unless there is some kind of harm to others. But it is reasonable to understand the Court’s
12 123 S. Ct. at 2484.
13 John Stuart Mill, On Liberty (Currin V. Shields ed., Liberal Arts Press 1956) (1859).
decision more narrowly, as a ruling that forbids invocation of generally unenforced
criminal law on the basis of a moral justification that has become anachronistic -- at least
when a constitutionally important interest is involved and when the absence of significant
enforcement activity can be explained only by reference to the anachronistic nature of the
relevant moral justification. This reading also helps clarify what made the decision
possible and its future fate. If I am correct, Lawrence was possible not because the Court
reached, all on its own, an ambitious and novel view of the nature of constitutional
liberty, or because it attempted to read a controversial view of autonomy into the due
process clause. The decision was possible only because of the ludicrously poor fit
between the sodomy prohibition and the society in which the justices live. And if I am
correct, Lawrence will have broad implications only if and to the extent that those broad
implications receive general public support. For example, the Supreme Court may or may
not read Lawrence to require state to recognize gay and lesbian marriages. But if it does
so, it will be following public opinion, not leading it. Political and social change was a
precondition for Lawrence, whose future reach will depend on the nature and extent of
that change.</p>
        <p>While I will spend most of my time on the Court’s due process ruling, my own
view is that the proper course in Lawrence was sketched by Justice O’Connor in her
concurring opinion.14 Rather than invalidating the Texas statute on grounds of substantive
due process, the Court should have invoked the equal protection clause to strike down, as
irrational, the state’s decision to ban homosexual sodomy but not heterosexual sodomy.
This approach would have been more cautious than the Court’s own. It would have had
the large advantage of making it unnecessary to overrule any precedent.15 At the same
time, an equal protection ruling would have recognized the fact, established by the
Court’s opinions, that the equal protection clause does not build on longstanding
traditions, but instead rejects them insofar as they attempt to devalue or humiliate certain
social groups.16 The problem in Lawrence is not adequately understood without reference
to the social subordination of gays and lesbians, not least through the use of the criminal
law. Hence Justice O’Connor’s approach suggests, lightly to be sure, the plausibility of
rationale (4) above, a rationale that seems to me essentially correct. And if states are
required to punish heterosexual sodomy if they are attempting to punish homosexual
sodomy, I believe that it is quite implausible to think that any form of sodomy would be
subject to criminal prosecution; political safeguards are far too strong to permit
significant numbers of arrests and prosecutions of heterosexuals for engaging in conduct
that is quite widespread.
14 123 S. Ct. at 2485 (O’Connor, J., concurring).
15 I do not engage here the debate over whether principles of stare decisis required the Court to refuse to
overrule Bowers v. Hardwick. My only suggestion is that the Court should not have overruled that decision
when it was unnecessary to do so in order to decide Lawrence. A possible objection to the equal protection
approach, one that I also cannot engage here, is that this approach is actually broader than that taken by the
majority, above all because it would seem to require states to recognize same-sex marriages. It is true that
an equal protection ruling would raise questions about bans on such marriages. But as we shall see, a due
process ruling has the same effect.
16 See, e.g., City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Center, Inc., 473 U.S. 432 (1985); Romer v. Evans, 517
U.S. 620 (1996).</p>
        <p>For all these reasons, invalidation on equal protection grounds would have been
preferable to the substantive due process route. But if the due process clause is to be
invoked, the idea of desuetude provides a method for understanding, disciplining, and
narrowing what the Court did. This reading of Lawrence prevents the opinion from being
a simple invocation of “liberty”; it also helps explain what made the Lawrence decision
possible from a generally conservative Supreme Court. Best of all, it has considerable
independent appeal.17</p>
        <p>This Article comes in four parts. The first explores the Court’s dilemma in
Lawrence—the state of pre-Lawrence law, the available options, and the difficulties with
those options. The second discusses Lawrence itself, emphasizing the various strands to
which I have referred. The third discusses possible readings of the decision and tries to
unpack them. Here I draw attention to the more narrow reading of the opinion, suggesting
that if understood in a way that emphasizes the anachronistic and almost never enforced
nature of the Texas statute, the Lawrence decision can claim a strong foundation in both
democratic values and the rule of law. The fourth explores the implications of the
Lawrence decision for constitutional attacks on laws regulating sexual relationships,
constitutional attacks on government discrimination against gays and lesbians, and
constitutional attacks on laws refusing to recognize same-sex marriages.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>I. The Court’s Dilemma</title>
      <p>The facts of Lawrence were exceedingly simple. Police officers in Houston,
Texas responded to a private report of a weapons disturbance in a private residence. They
entered the residence, owned by John Geddes Lawrence. On entering, they did not see
any weapons. But they did see Lawrence, engaging in a sexual act with Tyron Garner.
Lawrence and Garner were arrested, held in custody, and convicted of the crime of
“deviate sexual intercourse, namely anal sex, with a member of the same sex (man).”18
They were each fined $200.19 Deviate sexual intercourse is defined to include “any
contact between any part of the genitals of one person and the mouth or anus of another
person” or “the penetration of the genitals or the anus of another person with an object.”20
The Texas law was challenged on equal protection and due process grounds.21</p>
      <p>The Lawrence Court had three options. It could have invalidated the Texas statute
on equal protection grounds. It could have invalidated that law on due process grounds.
Or it could have upheld the law against both challenges. As we will see, the Court faced a
serious difficulty in Lawrence: a majority believed, in my view correctly, that the Texas
statute had to be invalidated -- but any rationale for invalidation would inevitably raise
serious doubts about practices, including the ban on same-sex marriages, that the majority
did not want to question. For the majority, a central problem was to develop a rationale
17 See Guido Calabresi, Foreword: Antidiscrimination and Constitutional Accountability (What the
BorkBrennan Debate Ignores), 105 Harv. L. 80 (1991); Cass R. Sunstein, One Case At A Time (1999).
18 123 S. Ct. at 2475-76.
19 41 S.W.3d at 349.
20 Id. at 2476 (citing Tex. Penal Code Ann. § 21.01(1)).
21 Id.
that would strike down the Texas statute without producing an unintended revolution in
the law. Let us investigate the Court’s options in light of preexisting law.
A. Equal Protection</p>
      <p>1. Heightened scrutiny. The Equal Protection Clause might have been used to
strike down the Texas law under decisions calling for “heightened scrutiny” of laws that
discriminate against traditionally disadvantaged groups. The paradigm examples of such
groups are, of course, African-Americans and women.22 Perhaps laws discriminating
against gays and lesbians should be subject to similarly skeptical judicial scrutiny.23 To
say the least, the Court has not laid down a clear test for deciding when such scrutiny will
be applied; instead it has pointed to a series of considerations, including a history of
discrimination, a circumstance of immutability, and political powerlessness.24 Probably
the best way of making sense of the doctrine is to say that heightened scrutiny is applied
when the relevant discrimination is peculiarly likely to reflect prejudice and hostility
rather than legitimate interests. In the context of race, for example, the problem is not that
skin color is immutable, but that discrimination against African-Americans is usually
based on illicit considerations; heightened scrutiny is a way of testing whether other,
public-spirited justifications can actually be brought forward in defense of the relevant
law. Discrimination against homosexuals can be understood in analogous terms. Suppose,
for example, that a school forbids homosexuals from becoming teachers,25 or that a police
department refuses to hire gays them.26 If heightened scrutiny were applied, a ban on
same-sex sodomy would be extremely difficult to defend.</p>
      <p>As a matter of precedent, the problem is that the Court has never suggested that
gays and lesbians are entitled to heightened scrutiny. In fact it has been extremely
reluctant to expand the class of groups so entitled—ruling, for example, that rational
basis review applies to discrimination against handicapped people27 and elderly people.28
These are not decisive problems, to be sure; a ruling that required heightened scrutiny is
not foreclosed by existing decisions. But such a ruling would certainly be an innovation.</p>
      <p>An alternative route to heightened scrutiny would be to contend that
discrimination against homosexuals is a kind of discrimination on the basis of sex.29 Here
it might be suggested that if a law punishes same-sex sodomy, it is punishing people who
would not be punished if their gender were different. But this view raises a number of
22 See, e.g., United States v. Virginia, 518 U.S. 515 (1996); Loving v. Virginia, 388 U.S. 1 (1967).
23 See David Richards, Sexual Preference as a Suspect (Religious) Classification, 55 Ohio St. L.J. 491
(1994); Cass R. Sunstein, Homosexuality and the Constitution, 70 Ind. L.J. 1, 8 (1994).
24 See, e.g., Frontiero v. Richardson, 411 US 677 (1973) (plurality opinion).
25 Glover v. Williamsburg Local School District Board of Education, 20 F.Supp.2d 1160 (U.S. District
Court, S.D.Ohio, 1998).
26 See, e.g., Childers v. Dallas Police Department, 513 F.Supp. 134 (U.S. District Court, N.D. Texas, 1981)
27 City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Center, Inc., 473 U.S. 432 (1985).
28 Massachusetts v. Murgia, 427 U.S. 307 (1981).
29 See Andrew Koppelman, Why Discrimination Against Lesbians and Gay Men Is Sex Discrimination, 69
N.Y.U. L. Rev. 197 (1994).
complexities.30 It would also seem to have broad implications, essentially treating all
discrimination against gays and lesbians as indistinguishable from, because literally
identical to, discrimination against women.31</p>
      <p>2. Rationality review. When rational basis review is applied, statutes are almost
always upheld under the equal protection clause.32 But three cases provided a plausible
backdrop for the plaintiffs’ challenge in Lawrence. Taken together, the three cases
suggest that a bare “desire to harm a politically unpopular group”33 is constitutionally
unacceptable. Texas’ prohibition of homosexual sodomy, not affecting heterosexual
sodomy, could be challenged as reflecting such a bare desire.</p>
      <p>The problem in United States Department of Agriculture v. Moreno arose from
Congress’ decision to exclude from the food stamp program any household containing an
individual who was unrelated to any other member of the household. 34 Thus the statute
required that any household receiving food stamps must consist solely of “related”
individuals.35 The Court invalidated the statute. The Court noted that the legislative
history suggested a congressional desire to exclude "hippies" and "hippie communes."36
To this the Court said: "[I]f the constitutional conception of 'equal protection of the laws'
means anything, it must at the very least mean that a bare congressional desire to harm a
politically unpopular group cannot constitute a legitimate governmental interest . . . ."37
This idea was extended in the Cleburne case, in which the plaintiffs challenged a city’s
denial of a special use permit for the operation of a group home for the mentally
retarded.38 Applying rational basis review, the Court admonished that "mere negative
attitudes, or fear, unsubstantiated by factors which are properly cognizable in a zoning
proceeding, are not permissible bases for"39 unequal treatment. Thus the Court concluded
that the discriminatory action under review was based "on an irrational prejudice."40 And
in Romer v. Evans, the Court struck down a Colorado law forbidding localities from
including gays and lesbians within the protection of laws prohibiting discrimination.41
The Court held that the law violated rational basis review because it was based not on a
legitimate public purpose but on a form of “animus”—with the apparent suggestion that
statutes rooted in “animus” represent core offenses of the equal protection guarantee. The
Court said that the law stands (and falls) as "a status-based classification of persons
undertaken for its own sake."42</p>
      <p>An equal protection ruling in Lawrence, based on these cases, would have had a
great deal of appeal. It would have made it unnecessary for the Court to reconsider
Bowers v. Hardwick43. It would have built carefully on Romer v. Evans. In these ways,
such a ruling would have been narrow, converting the Moreno-Cleburne-Romer trilogy
into the Moreno-Cleburne-Romer-Lawrence quartet. On the other hand, it is not clear that
such a ruling would have had more limited consequences than a due process ruling. An
invalidation of the line between homosexual and heterosexual sodomy would have raised
questions about a host of other discriminatory practices. Is the state permitted not to
recognize gay marriages? To discriminate against homosexuals in its employment
practices? If the Court wanted to cabin the reach of its ruling, and not to create anything
like a revolution in the law, these were important (and difficult) questions to answer.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>B. Due Process</title>
      <p>The modern story of substantive due process begins in 1965, when the Court
invalidated a Connecticut law forbidding the use of contraceptives by married people.44
After that decision, the Court decided a set of cases protecting certain decisions involving
sex, reproduction, the family, and other areas that appeared to be intimate and private.45
The cases turned out to be quite unruly, and there was no clear line between what was
protected and what was not.46</p>
      <p>A possible view would be that since Bowers, or at least since Washington v.
Glucksberg,47 the Court has said something like this: “Thus far, but no further!” Since
1985, the Court has been extremely reluctant to use the idea of substantive due process to
strike down legislation, and before Lawrence, the Court seemed unwilling to add to the
list even if the logic of the prior cases suggested that it ought to do so.48 On this view, the
Court’s refusal to overrule Roe v. Wade49 reflects not approval of that decision, and much
less a willingness to extend its logic, but a kind of temporal dividing line between
permissible and prohibited uses of substantive due process.50 In other words, the
continuing validity of Roe suggests not that the Court will try to follow the logic of the
privacy cases, but that the Court will refuse to overrule its precedents while also failing to
build on their logic.</p>
      <p>If we sought to bring more principled order to the Court’s decisions, we might
invoke the Court’s own words and insist that any asserted right must have a strong
foundation in Anglo-American traditions. This was the limiting principle invoked in both
Bowers and Glucksberg. In Bowers, the Court, quoting Justice Powell, emphasized the
43 478 U.S. 186 (1986) (holding that there is no fundamental right to engage in homosexual sodomy).
44 Griswold, 381 U.S. 479.
45 See, e.g., Eisenstadt v. Baird, 405 U.S. 438 (1972); Carey v. Population Services International, 431 U.S.
678 (1977); Roe v. Wade, 410 U.S. 113 (1973).
46 For a general discussion, see Cass R. Sunstein, The Right to Die, 106 Yale L.J. 1123 (1997)
47 521 U.S. 702 (1997) (holding that there is no fundamental right to assistance in committing suicide).
48 The most obvious example here is Glucksberg, id.
49 410 U.S. 113.
50 See Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey, 505 U.S. 833 (1992) (upholding some state
restrictions on abortion).
need to ask whether the relevant liberties “are ‘deeply rooted in this Nation’s history and
tradition.’”51 In Glucksberg, the Court said that “the development of this Court’s
substantive-due-process jurisprudence . . . has been…carefully refined by concrete
examples involving fundamental rights found to be deeply rooted in our legal tradition.”52
The Court stressed that this historical test tended “to rein in the subjective elements”53
and to avoid “the need for complex balancing of competing interests in every case.”54
The historical approach might have the advantage of disciplining judicial discretion, but
it has the disadvantage of fitting extremely poorly with some of the cases. It is not at all
clear, for example, that the right to choose abortion has a strong foundation in tradition.
Nonetheless, it would hardly be implausible, before Lawrence v. Texas, to argue that
henceforth, the line between protected and unprotected interests would turn largely on
history.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>II. What the Court Did</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>A. Substantive Due Process Reborn</title>
      <p>The heart of the Court’s opinion in Lawrence began with a dramatic reading of
precedent, stating, for the first time in the Court’s history, that the Constitution
recognizes a right to make sexual choices free from state control. Putting Griswold
together with Eisenstadt, the Court said that “the right to make certain decisions
regarding sexual conduct extends beyond the marital relationship.”55 Taken by itself, this
statement equivocates between two readings: the state may not punish sexual activity
through the particular means of the threatening unwanted pregnancy56; or the state may
not punish sexual activity at all. But the Court clearly endorsed the broader reading. In
speaking of homosexual activity in particular, the Court said that the government was
seeking “to control a personal relationship that, whether or not entitled to formal
recognition in the law, is within the liberty of persons to choose without being punished
as criminals.”57 Thus the Court suggested that the state could not intrude on sexual liberty
“absent injury to a person or abuse of an institution the law protects.”58 Here, then, is the
foundation for a reading of Lawrence as rooted in a general principle of sexual autonomy.
51 478 U.S. at 194.
52 521 U.S. at 722.
53 Id.
54 Id.
55 123 S. Ct. at 2477.
56 Thus it would have been possible to read the contraception cases as holding, not that the state may not
punish consensual sexual activity, but that it cannot do so through the indirect and discriminatory means of
threatening childbirth. The early privacy cases did not involve bans on sexual activity; instead they
involved efforts to control such activity by prohibiting the use of contraception. A narrow reading of the
cases would suggest that there is no right to immunity from state regulation of sex, but instead a right not to
be subject to regulation through the indirect method of risking unwanted pregnancy. See Cass R. Sunstein,
Designing Democracy (2002).
57 123 S. Ct. at 2478.
58 Id.</p>
      <p>The Court then turned from its precedents to an investigation of the suggestion in
Bowers that prohibitions on same-sex sodomy “have ancient roots.”59 Rejecting that
conclusion, the Court emphasized the complexity of American traditions on this count. In
a lengthy discussion, the Court undermined the suggestion that there has been an
unbroken path of hostility to same-sex sodomy. But the Court freely conceded that there
is no history of accepting that practice; it did not contend that traditions affirmatively
support a constitutional right to sexual freedom in that domain. On the contrary, and in a
dramatic departure from both Bowers and Glucksberg, the Court said that longstanding
traditions were not decisive. What were important were current convictions, not old ones.
“[W]e think that our laws and traditions in the past half century are of most relevance
here.”60 Hence the Court stressed an “emerging recognition that liberty gives substantial
protection to adult persons in deciding how to conduct their private lives in matters
pertaining to sex.”61</p>
      <p>The emerging recognition could be seen in many places. First, the Model Penal
Code did not endorse criminal penalties on consensual sexual activities conducted in
private; and several states specifically changed their laws in response to the Model Penal
Code.62 Second, fewer than half the states (24) outlawed sodomy even in 1986, and the
statutory prohibition went largely unenforced even in those states.63 Third, the practices
of Western nations were increasingly opposed to the criminal punishment of homosexual
conduct. Britain repealed its law forbidding homosexual conduct in 1967,64 and the
European Court of Human Rights concluded that laws banning consensual homosexual
conduct are invalid under the European Convention on Human Rights.65 Fourth, only
thirteen states now forbid such conduct, and of these just four have laws that discriminate
only against homosexual conduct.66 “In those states where sodomy is still proscribed,
whether for same-sex or heterosexual conduct, there is a pattern of nonenforcement with
respect to consenting adults acting in private.”67</p>
      <p>The Court added that it had issued two decisions casting the holding of Hardwick
“into even more doubt.”68 In Casey, the Court had reaffirmed not only Roe but also its
commitment to substantive due process, emphasizing “that our laws and traditions afford
constitutional protection to personal decisions relating to marriage, procreation,
contraception, family relationships, child rearing, and education.”69 Thus the Court read
Casey as an endorsement of the ideas underlying Roe, and not simply as a refusal to
reject a decision on which the nation had come to rely. And in Romer v. Evans, the Court
59 478 U.S. at 192.
60 123 S. Ct. at 2480.
61 Id.
62 Id. at 2480-81.
63 Id. at 2481 (citing Bowers, 478 U.S. at 192-93).
64 Id. (citing Sexual Offences Act, 1967, c. 60, § 1).
65 Id. (citing Dudgeon v. United Kingdom, 45 Eur. Ct. H.R. (1981)). The use of materials from other
nations, for the interpretation of the United States Constitution, raises many complexities, which I cannot
explore here.
66 Id.
67 Id.
68 Id.
69 Id. (citing Casey, 505 U.S. at 851).
struck down a law “born of animosity toward the class of persons affected.”70 These
decisions made Bowers decreasingly plausible.</p>
      <p>The Court acknowledged that the plaintiff’s equal protection challenge, based on
Romer, was “tenable.”71 But the Court said that “the instant case requires us to address
whether Bowers itself has continuing validity.”72 (This is remarkable because the instant
case “required” no such thing; it would have been fully possible to resolve the case
without addressing Bowers.) The Court explained that if the Texas statute were
invalidated on equal protection grounds, it would remain unclear whether a statute could
forbid both same-sex and different-sex sodomy.73 The Court added that when
“homosexual conduct is made criminal by the law of the State, that declaration in and of
itself is an invitation to subject homosexual persons to discrimination both in the public
and in the private spheres.”74 In the Court’s view, the continued validity of Bowers
“demeans the lives of homosexual persons.”75 Here the Court emphasized the stigma
imposed by the law, coming not only from the fact that the act is a misdemeanor but also
because of “all that imports for the dignity of the persons charged.”76 The collateral
consequences of the criminal conviction could not be avoided.</p>
      <p>At this point the Court emphasized that Bowers had been eroded not only by
Casey and Romer, but also by independent sources. Academics had widely criticized the
decision.77 Five different state courts had refused to follow it in interpreting their own
state constitutions.78 The European Court of Human Rights, along with other nations, had
rejected the Bowers approach, a relevant fact “to the extent that Bowers relied on values
we share with a wider civilization.”79 Stare decisis was relevant but not conclusive, for
the Bowers decision did not produce detrimental reliance “comparable to some instances
where recognized individual rights are involved.”80 The Court concluded that “Bowers
was not correct when it was decided, and it is not correct today.”81</p>
      <p>The Court was aware of the potential breadth of its ruling, and it took steps to
clarify its scope. “The present case does not involve minors. It does not involve persons
who might be injured or coerced or who are situated in relationships where consent might
not easily be refused. It does not involve public conduct or prostitution. It does not
involve whether the government must give formal recognition to any relationship that
homosexual persons seek to enter.”82 What was involved instead was “full and mutual
consent” to engage in “sexual practices common to a homosexual lifestyle. . . . The State
cannot demean their existence or control their destiny by making their private sexual
conduct a crime.”83 In a closing word, the Court said that the Texas law “furthers no
legitimate state interest which can justify its intrusion into the personal and private life of
the individual.”84</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>B. Other Voices</title>
      <p>I will return to the complexities in the opinion shortly. For the moment, let us
explore the views of the three other justices who wrote in Lawrence.</p>
      <p>1. Equal protection and Justice O’Connor. Justice O’Connor rejected the Court’s
due process holding and urged the equal protection route. Building on the
MorenoCleburne-Romer trilogy, she contended that when a law is based on “a desire to harm a
politically unpopular group,” the Court has applied “a more searching form of rational
basis review.”85 She added that invalidation, via rational basis review, is more likely
when the challenged legislation “inhibits personal relationships.”86</p>
      <p>To be sure, Texas had justified its law as a means of promoting morality, and that
kind of justification had been found sufficient in Bowers, which Justice O’Connor did not
seek to disturb. But Bowers was decided under the due process clause. Lawrence was
different, because it presented the not-yet-decided question “whether, under the Equal
Protection Clause, moral disapproval is a legitimate state interest to justify by itself a
statute that bans homosexual sodomy, but not heterosexual sodomy.”87 She concluded
that it is not. Under rational basis review, moral disapproval is not a sufficient basis for
discriminating among groups of persons. “Texas’ invocation of moral disapproval as a
legitimate state interest proves nothing more than Texas’ desire to criminalize
homosexual sodomy.”88 And because the law is enforced so infrequently, “the law serves
more as a statement of dislike and disapproval than as a tool to stop criminal behavior.”89</p>
      <p>Aware of the potentially broad implications of the equal protection argument,
Justice O’Connor urged that her analysis would not doom all distinctions between
homosexuals and heterosexuals. With her eye firmly on the military and on family law,
she said that “Texas cannot assert any legitimate state interest here, such as national
security or preserving the traditional institution of marriage.”90 In the latter context,
82 Id.
83 Id.
84 Id.
85 Id. at 2485 (O’Connor, J., concurring).
86 Id. (O’Connor, J., concurring).
87 Id. at 2486 (O’Connor, J., concurring).
88 Id. (O’Connor, J., concurring).
89 Id. (O’Connor, J., concurring).
90 Id. at 2487-88 (O’Connor, J., concurring).
“other reasons exist to promote the institution of marriage beyond mere moral
disapproval of an excluded group.”91</p>
      <p>2. Scalia, the slippery slope, and “a massive disruption of the current social
order.” Justice Scalia’s argument had three elements. First, he chastised the Court for
what he saw as its palpable inconsistency on the issue of stare decisis. Invoking stare
decisis, the Court had refused to overrule Roe, a nineteen-year-old ruling, in its Casey
decision in 1992.92 The same Court was now willing to overrule Bowers, decided
seventeen years previously. Justice Scalia saw no justification for the differential
treatment. Second, Justice Scalia urged that the Court’s ruling would have extremely
large implications. “State laws against bigamy, same-sex marriage, adult incest,
prostitution, masturbation, adultery, fornication, bestiality, and obscenity” can be upheld
“only in light of Bowers’ validation of laws based on moral choices. Every single one of
these laws is called into question by today’s decision.”93 The Court’s decision therefore
entails “a massive disruption of the current social order”94 (something that could not have
been said about a decision to overrule Roe). Thus Justice Scalia urged that the Court’s
opinion “dismantles the structure of constitutional law that has permitted a distinction to
be made between heterosexual and homosexual unions, insofar as formal recognition in
marriage is concerned.”95</p>
      <p>Justice Scalia’s third argument involved the proper interpretation of the
Constitution in principle. After doubting that the due process clause is a substantive
safeguard at all, he urged that as it has developed, the idea of substantive due process has
been disciplined by asking whether the relevant rights are “deeply rooted in this Nation’s
history and tradition.”96 Justice Scalia questioned the idea that there is an “emerging
awareness”97 that consensual homosexual activity should be protected; but his more basic
objection was that any emerging awareness was irrelevant. “Constitutional entitlements
do not spring into existence because some States choose to lessen or eliminate criminal
sanctions on certain behavior.”98 Justice Scalia saw the Court as holding that the moral
views underlying the Texas statute did not provide a legitimate basis for it. Here his
objection was exceedingly simple: “This effectively decrees the end of all morals
legislation.”99 With respect to equal protection, Justice Scalia urged that a rational basis
was what was required, and that as for due process purposes, “the enforcement of
traditional notions of sexual morality” provided the rational basis.100</p>
      <p>3. Thomas and the uncommonly silly law. Justice Thomas’ short dissenting
opinion emphasizes that as a member of the Texas legislature, he would vote to repeal the
91 Id. at 2488 (O’Connor, J., concurring).
92 Id. (Scalia, J., dissenting) (citing Casey, 505 U.S. at 844).
93 Id. at 2490 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
94 Id. at 2491 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
95 Id. at 2498 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
96 Id. at 2492 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
97 Id. at 2494 (Scalia, J., dissenting) (internal citation omitted).
98 Id. (Scalia, J., dissenting).
99 Id. at 2495 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
100 Id. at 2496 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
relevant law. “Punishing someone for expressing his sexual preference through
noncommercial consensual conduct with another adult does not appear to be a worthy
way to expend valuable law enforcement resources.”101 Invoking Justice Stewart’s
concurrence in Griswold, he contended that the law is “uncommonly silly,”102 but that
nothing in the Constitution forbids it.103</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>III. Interpretive Puzzles</title>
      <p>I will suggest that Lawrence is best understood as responsive to what the Court
saw as an emerging national awareness, reflected in a pattern of nonenforcement, that it is
illegitimate to punish people because of homosexual conduct -- and that the decision
therefore embodies a kind of American-style desuetude. But to support this suggestion, it
will be necessary to unpack the Court’s opaque opinion, which raises a number of
puzzles. Let us begin with the simplest.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>A. A Fundamental Right or Rational Basis Review?</title>
      <p>Was Lawrence based on rational basis review, or instead on something else? It is
astonishing but true that this question is exceedingly difficult to answer.</p>
      <p>If the Court had attempted to write a conventional due process opinion, it would
have taken one of two routes. First, the Court might have said that the right to engage in
consensual sexual activity qualifies as fundamental, so that the government may not
interfere with that right unless it has a compelling justification.104 Second, the Court
might have said that whether or not the relevant right qualifies as fundamental, the state
cannot interfere with it, simply because it lacks a legitimate reason to justify the
interference. But the Court said neither, at least not in plain terms. The Court did not
unambiguously identify any “fundamental interest” on the part of the plaintiffs that would
support its ruling. In fact it did not use the “fundamental interest” formulation at any
point in its analysis. Moreover, the Court did not say that the Texas statute lacked a
“rational basis.” In fact it did not use the “rational basis” formulation at any point in its
analysis. Much of the opacity of the Court’s opinion stems from its failure to specify
what kind of review it was applying to the Texas statute.</p>
      <p>To be sure, the Court did end its opinion with a reference to the absence of any
“legitimate interest” on the state’s part.105 Justice Scalia seized on this point to urge that
the Court issued a rational basis opinion after all106—a characterization to which the
Court (revealingly?) does not specifically object. Thus Justice Scalia contends that much
of the Court’s opinion “has no relevance to its actual holding,”107 which was that the
statute failed rational basis review. Justice Scalia’s reading cannot be said to be senseless;
101 Id. at 2498 (Thomas, J., dissenting).
102 Id. (Thomas, J., dissenting) (quoting Griswold, 381 U.S. at 527 (Stewart, J., concurring)).
103 Id. (Thomas, J., dissenting).
104 See, e.g., Roe, 410 U.S. 113.
105 123 S. Ct. at 2484.
106 Id. at 2488 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
107 Id. (Scalia, J., dissenting).
it is not demonstrably wrong. But I believe that it is incorrect, and that in the end the
Court’s opinion treats the relevant right as a fundamental one. Begin with the most
relevant part of the Court’s opinion:</p>
      <p>“The petitioners are entitled to respect for their private lives. The State cannot
demean their existence or control their destiny by making their private sexual conduct a
crime. Their right to liberty under the Due Process Clause gives them the full right to
engage in their conduct without intervention of the government. ‘It is a promise of the
Constitution that there is a realm of personal liberty which the government may not
enter.’ The Texas statute furthers no legitimate state interest which can justify its
intrusion into the personal and private life of the individual.”108</p>
      <p>The Court immediately follows its reference to “no legitimate state interest”109
with the phrase, “which can justify its intrusion into the personal and private life of the
individual.”110 The Court’s emphasis on “respect for their private lives,”111 on “control
[of] their destiny”112, and on “personal and private life”113 suggests that the interest
involved is not an ordinary one -- and that the Court is demanding something more than a
rational basis. The same point is strongly suggested by the Court’s reference, in this
paragraph, to Casey114, which of course involved a fundamental right, not a rational basis
test.</p>
      <p>But there is a more basic reason for seeing the Court’s opinion as finding the
relevant interest to be fundamental. The Court begins with an effort to assimilate the
issue in Lawrence to the issues in Griswold, Eisenstadt, Roe, Carey, and Casey -- all of
which are now taken, by the Court, to suggest a fundamental right in the domain of sex
and reproduction. Hence the Court refers to “the right to make certain decisions regarding
sexual conduct,”115 to the individual’s interest in making “certain fundamental decisions
affecting her destiny,”116 and to the “emerging awareness that liberty gives substantial
protection to adult persons in deciding how to conduct their private lives in matters
pertaining to sex.”117 These statements would be unintelligible if Lawrence were based
solely on rational basis review. Indeed, much of the Court’s opinion would be dicta. In
the end, Lawrence is not plausibly a rational basis decision.</p>
      <p>An alternative reading is that the Court deliberately refused to specify its “tier” of
analysis because it was rejecting the idea of tiers altogether. Perhaps the Court was
signaling its adoption of a kind of sliding scale, matching the strength of the interest to
the demand for state justification, without formally requiring identification of a
108 Id. at 2484 (quoting Casey, 505 U.S. at 847) (internal citation omitted).
109 Id.
110 Id.
111 Id.
112 Id.
113 Id.
114 Id. (citing Casey, 505 U.S. at 847).
115 Id. at 2477.
116 Id.
117 Id. at 2480.
fundamental right. And indeed, some of the Court’s decisions do suggest a partial
collapse of the traditional tiers approach to judicial review.118 For many years, Justice
Marshall complained of the rigidity of the usual tiers, urging a more open-ended form of
balancing.119 Justice Marshall’s views appeared to fall on deaf ears. But perhaps
Lawrence reflects some appreciation of the difficulties in fitting all cases within the
traditional framework. This is not a wholly implausible reading, but it would be quite
surprising if the Court meant to adopt a sliding-scale of analysis without saying so. The
more natural interpretation is simpler: The Court’s assimilation of the Lawrence problem
to that in Griswold and its successors suggests that a fundamental right was involved.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>B. Autonomy Simpliciter, or Desuetude-Informed Autonomy?</title>
      <p>But why, exactly, does the relevant interest count as a fundamental one? There are
two possibilities. The first is that the right to engage in consensual sex counts, simply as a
matter of principle, as part of the liberty that the due process clause substantively
protects. On this view, in Lawrence the Court accepted, to this extent, John Stuart Mill’s
view in On Liberty,120 holding that the government may not interfere with (certain)
private choices unless there is harm to others. The second and narrower idea is that this
particular kind of sex—homosexual sex between consenting adults—counts as
fundamental. It does so because of major changes in social values in the last half-century.
On this view, Lawrence finds a fundamental right as a result of existing public
convictions, with which the Texas statute cannot be squared, simply because sodomy
prosecutions are so hopelessly out of step with them.</p>
      <p>Lawrence could be read in either way. But the second interpretation is far more
plausible. A simple autonomy reading would have consequences that the Court did not
likely intend. As Justice Scalia suggests, it would raise serious questions about
prohibitions on adult incest, prostitution, adultery, fornication, bestiality, and
obscenity.121 (I do not mention his suggestion that the Court has questioned laws
forbidding masturbation,122 for one reason: There are no laws forbidding masturbation!)
Now it might be possible, even under the autonomy reading, to justify most or all of those
prohibitions on the ground that they counteract concrete harms, sufficient to support the
intrusion on a presumptively protected right. (I return to this question below.) And cases
involving commercial activity probably must be analyzed in a way that gives the
government more room to maneuver. But it would be remarkable if Lawrence were
understood to require a careful inquiry into the adequacy of government justifications for
banning (say) adult incest and bestiality.
118 See, e.g., the heightened approach to rational basis review in Romer, 517 U.S. 620, and Cleburne, 473
U.S. 432, and the softened approach to strict scrutiny in Grutter v. Bollinger, 123 S. Ct. 2325 (2003).
119 See Dandridge v. Williams, 397 U.S. 471 (1970) (Marshall, J., dissenting); San Antonio Independent
School District v. Rodriguez, 411 U.S. 1 (Marshall, J., dissenting).
120 See Mill, supra note 11.
121 123 S. Ct. at 2490 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
122 Id. (Scalia, J., dissenting). There are of course laws forbidding public masturbation, but that is a
different matter. Nothing in Lawrence suggests that states are banned from regulating sexual conduct that
occurs in public view.</p>
      <p>In any case, a simple autonomy reading would make the Court’s apparently
pivotal discussion of “emerging awareness” into an irrelevancy. Recall that the Court
rejected Bowers in large part by pointing to a range of indications that bans on
homosexual sodomy were out of step with existing values.123 Hence two factors were
emphasized in the Court’s ruling: only thirteen states prohibited sodomy; and the sodomy
laws were rarely enforced, through criminal prosecution, even in those states.124 It does
appear that the Court was responding to, and requiring, an evolution in public opinion—
something like a broad consensus that the practice at issue should not be punished.</p>
      <p>These points suggest that the Court’s decision was less about sexual autonomy,
as a freestanding idea, and closer to a kind of due process variation on the old common
law idea of desuetude.125 According to that concept, laws that are hardly ever enforced
are said, by courts, to have lapsed, simply because they lack public support.126 The
rationale here is that unenforced laws lack support in public convictions, and may not be
brought to bear, in an unpredictable and essentially arbitrary way, against private
citizens.127 Most American courts do not accept that idea in express terms.128 But long
ago, Alexander Bickel invoked the notion of desuetude to help account for Griswold.129
The simple idea is that the ban on use of contraceptives by married people had become
hopelessly out of touch with existing convictions—so much so that the ban could rarely
if ever be invoked as a basis for actual prosecutions. The public would not accept a
situation in which married people were actually convicted of that crime. In those
circumstances, the statutory ban was a recipe for arbitrary and even discriminatory
action, in a way that does violence to democratic ideals and even the rule of law. It does
violence to democratic ideals because a law plainly lacking public support is nonetheless
invoked to regulate private conduct. It violates the rule of law because a measure of this
kind lacks, in practice, the kind of generality and predictability on which the rule of law
depends.130</p>
      <p>If anything, a ban on sodomy is even worse than the Connecticut law struck down
in Griswold. Such a ban is used, not for frequent arrests or convictions, but for rare and
unpredictable harassment by the police. An advantage of this reading is that it mutes the
apparent roots of Lawrence in substantive due process. The idea of desuetude is, in a
sense, a procedural one. There is a procedural problem: a lack of fair notice combined
with denial of equal treatment, a problem that is inevitable in a system in which criminal
prosecutions are rare and episodic. In fact, the idea of desuetude forbids criminal
123 Id. at 2479-2482.
124 Id. at 2481.
125 See, e.g., J.R. Philip, Some Reflections on Desuetude, 43 Juridical Review 260 (1931); Linda Rogers and
William Rogers, Desuetude as a Defense, 52 Iowa Law Review 1 (1966).
126 Mortimer Kadish and Sanford Kadish, Discretion to Disobey: A Study of Lawful Departures From
Legal Rules 129-31 (1973).
127 Poe v. Ullman, 367 U.S. 497, 502 (1961) (quoting Nashville, C. &amp; St. L.R. Co. v. Browning, 310 U.S.
362, 369 (1940)).
128 For discussion, see Kadish and Kadish, supra note 116, at 127-140; John Chipman Gray, Desuetude of
Statutes in the United States, in The Nature and Sources of Law 189-97, 329-34, (2nd ed. 1921); Arthur E.
Bonfield, The Abrogation of Penal Statutes by Nonenforcement, 49 Iowa Law Review 389 (1964).
129 See Alexander Bickel, The Least Dangerous Branch 155 (1965).
130 See Lon Fuller, The Morality of Law (1962).
hopes to promote. To be sure, these points are cautionary notes and no more. But at the
very least, they suggest that where the Court is in a position to choose, a desuetude-type
ruling, building on widespread convictions, has considerable advantages over a ruling
that is based on the Court’s own conception of autonomy.</p>
      <p>3. Too much? Of course Lawrence, read in the way I have suggested, might be
criticized from other directions. Perhaps a better alternative is Thayerism: An approach
that would uphold any intrusion on liberty unless it lacks even a minimally rational
basis.147 This approach might be defended on the ground that a judicial judgment about
emerging public convictions is not very reliable, and certainly less so than the evidence
provided by actual legislation. If there is a serious risk in judicial effort, why not require
people to resort to their political remedies? I believe that the idea of desuetude provides a
partial answer. If legislation is infrequently enforced, most citizens can treat it as
effectively dead. They have nothing to worry about. At least in clear cases, it seems
plausible, and inoffensive to democratic values, to use the Due Process Clause to forbid
criminal prosecutions in cases of this kind. Both Griswold and Lawrence are defining
examples.</p>
      <p>But perhaps the Court would have done better, in Lawrence, to continue on the
path marked out by Bowers and Glucksberg, and hence to uphold any intrusion on liberty
unless it runs afoul of Anglo-American traditions. Due process traditionalism might be
supported on the ground that federal judges are not especially good at evaluating our
practices, and that if a practice has endured there is good reason to support it, if only
because many people have endorsed it, or at least not seen fit to change it. Constitutional
traditionalism therefore makes decisions simpler at the same time that it makes them less
likely to go wrong. If economic terminology is thought to be helpful here, the use of
traditions by imperfect human beings might not be perfect, but it is the best way to go
because it minimizes both “decision costs,” taken as the burdens of deciding what to do,
and “error costs,” taken as the problems introduced by making mistakes.</p>
      <p>A central question is whether tradition-bound judges will make more or fewer
errors than judges who depart from traditions and pay a great deal of attention to
conventional morality. At least some of those who are skeptical about substantive due
process might endorse traditionalism as a possible source of law, but also conclude that it
is proper for the Court to strike down statutes that lack support in popular convictions. In
other words, the desuetude-type approach of the Lawrence Court might be a supplement
to due process traditionalism, rooted in similar concerns. Indeed, a desuetude-type
approach has the advantage of underlining the procedural features of procedural due
process. As we have seen, a statute like that invalidated in Lawrence fails to provide
predictability, and it is a recipe for arbitrary enforcement. The Court’s refusal to permit
criminal convictions, under these circumstances, is not radically inconsistent with
democratic ideals. In a sense, it helps to vindicate them.
147 See James Bradley Thayer, The Origin and Scope of the American Doctrine of Constitutional Law, 7
Harv. L. Rev. 129 (1893).
4. Coherence, optimal deterrence, and expressive condemnation. Another
response is possible, one that would raise questions about the coherence of any approach
that draws on the idea of desuetude. For governments, there is a tradeoff between the
magnitude and the frequency of punishment. A government might decide to lessen the
deterrent signal simply by scaling back enforcement. In the context of conduct that a state
would like to deter, but not greatly, the sensible strategy might be to maintain a
prohibition but to enforce it rarely. It is easy to imagine a city taking this approach with
respect to non-flagrant speeding (driving, say, ten miles over the speed limit), or certain
parking offenses (giving tickets rarely in certain places, for example), or certain alcohol
or drug offenses (rarely arresting or convicting teenagers for use of alcohol, or
infrequently arresting or convicting people for marijuana use). In fact many prohibitions
are rarely enforced. Is this situation unconstitutional? Why is a state banned from making
this particular tradeoff between severity and probability of sanction? In any case the ex
ante deterrent effect of a rarely enforced law, including the sodomy law in Texas, applies
equally to all those subject to it. Isn’t this ex ante equality a sufficient response to the
objection of unpredictability?</p>
      <p>To answer this objection, it is necessary to narrow the due process ruling in
Lawrence. The problem with the sodomy law was not only the fact that it was enforced
rarely; infrequent enforcement stemmed from the particular fact that the moral claim that
underlay it could no longer claim public support. The same cannot be said in the
examples just described; in those cases, there is public ambivalence about arrest and
conviction, but not because of a widespread belief that the prohibition is itself outmoded.
But Lawrence does not depend on this factor alone. It is also important that the interest at
stake is similar, in principle, to those protected by earlier cases. In these circumstances,
the state is required to produce, by way of justification, something other than a moral
position that no longer fits with public convictions. To be sure, the effect of a
rarelyenforced law is similar to that of a lottery, and in that respect there is a degree of ex ante
equality. But people are punished ex post, not ex ante, and it is the ex post randomness
that supports the Court’s ruling, at least in the light of the particular interest involved.</p>
      <p>Consider a final argument. One purpose of the criminal law is to permit
expressive condemnation. For some conduct, the social judgment is in favor of such
condemnation but opposed to much in the way of actual prosecution. As examples,
consider laws forbidding adultery or the consumption of alcohol by sixteen-year-olds.
Rare enforcement reflects a belief that the law, operating in conjunction with social
norms, will deter misconduct optimally—and that criminal prosecution would be too
heavy-handed, at least in most cases. Does it follow, from Lawrence, that states are
forbidding from adopting the strategy of expressive condemnation with rare prosecution?
Why isn’t that strategy the most sensible one in some circumstances? The answer is that
when certain interests are involved,148 states are indeed forbidden from following that
strategy, and the reason has to do with the lack of fair notice and the inevitability of
randomness. As I have emphasized, these are the conventional (procedural) concerns of
the due process clause.
148 Consumption of liquor does not fall within the category of protected interests; on adultery, see below,</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-11">
      <title>IV. Implications</title>
      <p>What are the implications of Lawrence? Because of the opacity of the Court’s
opinion, this is not an easy question to answer. In the fullness of time, it is imaginable
that Lawrence will be a sport, a decision with no descendents, one in which the Court
struck down a law that shocked its conscience but that proved unable to generate further
doctrine. But it is no less imaginable that Lawrence will turn out to have broad
consequences for regulation of sexual relationships, in a way that vindicates a quite
general interest in sexual autonomy. Bowers had stopped a number of potential doctrinal
innovations here; Bowers is no longer good law. And it is wholly imaginable that
Lawrence will draw into question many forms of discrimination against gays and
lesbians. If my basic argument is correct, the eventual path of the law will have a great
deal to do with public convictions over time. I am concerned in this section with the logic
of the Court’s opinion and with its bearing on issues that the Court did not resolve.
A. Sex</p>
      <p>Justice Scalia urged that Lawrence decrees an end to “morals” legislation149, and
in the aftermath of the decision, it is natural to wonder about the constitutionality of laws
forbidding sexual harassment, prostitution, adultery, fornication, obscenity, polygamy,
and incest. Before Lawrence, such laws seemed quite secure. The Court had made clear
that substantive due process would be used only to protect rights well-recognized by
tradition150; and in any event the privacy cases had originally been defined with close
reference to reproduction and its control, not to sex itself.151 But after Lawrence, it would
be possible to contend that many statutory restrictions impose unconstitutional barriers to
consensual sexual activity. And in each of these cases, it would be possible to urge both
that the relevant right is a fundamental one and that the state lacks a legitimate basis for
interfering with consensual activity. Let us see how the underlying issues might be
assessed.</p>
      <p>1. Coercion. The easiest cases involve coercion. In such cases, the predicate for
Lawrence—consent—is absent. If consensual sex is not involved, there is no fundamental
right that would require the state to provide a compelling justification. And for the same
reason, the state has a perfectly legitimate, even compelling, reason to impose a
restriction. In cases of sexual harassment, coercion of one or another sort is generally
involved152, and hence a legal ban is perfectly acceptable. The same is true for many and
149 123 S. Ct. at 2495 (Scalia, J., dissenting).
150 This was the key point in lower court decisions rejecting constitutional challenges to decisions to punish
(for example) adultery, see Mercure v. Van Buren Township, 81 F.Supp.2d 814 (E.D. Mich. 2000);
Commonwealth v. Stowell, 449 N.E.2d 357 (Mass. 1983); City of Sherman v. Henry, 928 S.W.2d 464
(Tex. 1996); and incest, see Smith v. State, 6 S.W.3d 512 (Tenn. Crim. App. 1999); State v. Buck, 757 P.2d
861 (Or. Ct. App. 1988).
151 See, e.g., Griswold, 381 U.S. 479; Roe, 410 U.S. 113.
152 See, e.g., Franklin v. Gwinnett County Pub. Schs., 503 U.S. 60 (1992).
perhaps most cases involving incest, which involve minors unable to give legal
consent.153 The interest in preventing coerced sex is sufficient.</p>
      <p>But somewhat harder cases are imaginable even here. Suppose, for example, that
under a public university’s sexual harassment policy, a teacher and a graduate student are
banned from having a consensual relationship, even though the teacher is not (and will
not be) in a supervisory position over the student. Or suppose that the incestuous relations
are between adults—first cousins, let us say. If an “as applied” challenge were product,
these would be genuinely difficult after Lawrence. If real consent is found in either case,
a fundamental right might well be involved. But it would be possible to defend the broad
sexual harassment prohibition as a way of reducing risks and introducing clarity for all.
And it would be possible to defend the ban on incest among adults as a way of
eliminating certain psychological pressures and protecting any children who might result
from medical risk.154 In neither case can it be said that the prohibitions run afoul of some
emerging national awareness. These are far weaker cases for invalidation than Lawrence,
but some of the underlying logic of the case seems to raise doubts in imaginable
applications.</p>
      <p>2. Commerce. Other easy cases involve commerce. In the case of prostitution, it is
hard to urge that a fundamental right is involved.155 Under Lawrence, commercial sex is
to be treated differently.156 The outcome is easy; but the analysis is not. Why the sharp
distinction between commercial and noncommercial sex? Why are sexual relations
unprotected, or less protected, if dollars are exchanged? Books, after all, are protected,
whether they are given away or sold. Part of the analysis here might be that commercial
sex should not be treated more protectively than any other kind of commercial
interaction, now subject to rational basis review.157 But if sexual relationships have a
special constitutional status, this distinction is far from obvious. The more basic claim
must be that special constitutional status attaches to sexual intimacy, not to sexual
relationships,158 and that intimacy in the relevant sense is not involved when sex is
exchanged for cash.159 Hence no fundamental right is involved. To be sure, this argument
is not entirely convincing. Many sexual relationships (including many that fall within the
category protected by Lawrence) do not involve intimacy (except by definition). But
perhaps the Court can be said to be suggesting that noncommercial sex involves intimacy
frequently enough to justify protection of the overall class, whereas the opposite is true of
sex-for-money.
153 See, e.g., Richardson v. State, 353 S.E.2d 342 (Ga. 1987); Commonwealth v. Arnold, 514 A.2d 890 (Pa.
Super. Ct. 1986).
154 See, e.g., In re Tiffany Nicole M., 571 N.W.2d 872 (Wis. Ct. App. 1997); but see In re Termination of
Parental Rights to Zachary B., 662 N.W.2d 360 (Wis. Ct. App. 2003).
155 See, e.g., J.B.K., Inc. v. Caron, 600 F.2d 710 (8th Cir. 1979); Morgan v. Detroit, 389 F.Supp. 922 (E.D.
Mich. 1975); State v. Allen, 424 A.2d 651 (Conn. Super. Ct. 1980); Blyther v. United States, 577 A.2d
1154 (D.C. 1990).
156 123 S. Ct. at 2484.
157 See, e.g., Heart of Atlanta Motel, Inc. v. United States, 379 U.S. 241 (1964).
158 The case of bestiality should be understood similarly. It would be frivolous to argue that bans on
bestiality eliminate the kind of intimate relationship protected by Lawrence.
159 See Commonwealth v. Walter, 446 N.E.2d 707, 710 (Mass. 1983); State v. Price, 446 N.W.2d 813, 818
(Iowa 1976).</p>
      <p>But what justification does the state have for forbidding prostitution? It is
probably sufficient here to point to the adverse effects of prostitution on the lives of
prostitutes; the risk of exploitation (and worse) is real and serious.160 Nor are moral
justifications, pointing to the corrosive effects of prostitution on sexuality and sex
equality,161 ruled off-limits by Lawrence. I am not taking a position on the complex and
disputed question whether and how prostitution should be outlawed. My suggestion is
only that under rational basis review, restrictions on prostitution are easily defensible.
The ban on the sale of obscenity should be understood in similar terms162; the use of
obscenity raises different issues.163</p>
      <p>3. Without coercion and without commerce. For the state, the most serious
problems, post-Lawrence, come in cases challenging restrictions on genuinely consensual
and noncommercial practices. Begin with what might seem an intermediate case: bans on
sexual devices.164 Following the previous discussion, we should distinguish here between
sale on the one hand and use on the other. Perhaps the state could ban the sale itself,
urging that it is attempting to regulate a commercial enterprise, and that it is permitted to
do so in light of the commercial-noncommercial distinction just made. Even this is not
entirely clear.165 And could the state make it a crime for people to use such devices? The
right to do so might well fall within the protection of fundamental interests. In any case
what is the state’s justification for banning such use? It is easy to imagine an as-applied
challenge, in which a married couple attacks a ban on either the sale or the use of sexual
devices with reference to Griswold itself.166 The difference is that in Griswold, the ban on
use of contraceptives was an effort to prevent non-procreative sex, whereas in the
hypothetical case, the state is banning devices that are designed to increase sexual
pleasure. But why, exactly, would it seek to do that? Is there something wrong with
certain sources of sexual pleasure within constitutionally protected relationships? Perhaps
the answer would be affirmative if real harms were involved, as for example through
sadomasochistic practices. Almost certainly the state could justify a prohibition on the
public display of such devices. But we are not now speaking of these questions. At first
160 See, e.g., People v. Mason, 642 P.2d 8, 12 (Colo. 1982); People v. Johnson, 376 N.E.2d 381, 386 (Ill.
App. Ct. 1978). Of course some of the risk stems from the very fact that prostitution is unlawful.
161 See Bell v. United States, 349 U.S. 81, 84 (1955) (Minton, J., dissenting); People v. Warren, 535
N.W.2d 173, 177 (Mich. 1995) (Levin, J., dissenting); State v. Wright, 561 A.2d 659, 662 (N.J. Super. Ct.
App. Div. 1989).
162 See, e.g., Paris Adult Theatre I v. Slayton, 413 U.S. 49, 58-59 (1973).
163 The use can be banned under Miller, by reference to moral objections, though Stanley v. Georgia, US,
protects the use of obscenity within the home. A different and in my view better analysis would point to
actual harms, see Catharine MacKinnon, Feminism Unmodified (1986); Cass R. Sunstein, Pornography and
the First Amendment, Duke LJ (1996).
164 See, e.g., Williams v. Pryor, 240 F.3d 944 (11th Cir. 2001); Pleasureland Museum, Inc. v. Beutter, 288
F.3d 988 (7th Cir. 2002) (remanding for consideration of whether a ban on sexual devices violated a
fundamental right to privacy).
165 Recall that the constitutional protection given to the use of contraceptives was extended to the sale of
contraceptives. See Carey, supra. If a ban on the sale of contraceptives cannot be justified, it is not clear,
after Lawrence, how the state can justify a ban on the sale of sexual devices. Before Lawrence, it might
have been said that the privacy cases did not protect sexual activity as such, but merely banned the state
from punishing that activity through the indirect and discriminatory means of risking unwanted pregnancy.
But Lawrence forbids this narrow reading of the cases.
166 See Williams, id. at 952-53 (suggesting that an as-applied challenge is plausible).
glance, individuals have a fundamental interest here, and the state seems to lack a
legitimate basis for intruding on that interest.</p>
      <p>If there were laws forbidding masturbation, Lawrence would indeed raise
extremely serious questions about them. Fortunately, there are no such laws.167 What
about laws forbidding fornication, understood to mean non-adulterous sex outside of
marriage?168 Lawrence creates serious doubts, simply because coercion and consent are
not present. In any case, there seems to be an emerging social awareness that fornication
is not a proper basis for criminal punishment.169 And with respect to consenting adults, it
is not easy to produce a legitimate ground for interfering with non-adulterous sex.170 As I
have noted, fully consensual incest is a somewhat harder case. In the case of adult
brothers and sisters, it might be urged that the goal is to prevent harms to any children
who might result, or psychological difficulties that would predictably produce and
accompany any such relationships. Certainly the ban on sexual relations within the family
cannot be said to be anachronistic. There is no “emerging public awareness” that such
relations should be accepted. But imagine, for example, that sex is banned among first
cousins, in circumstances in which any harms are highly speculative. Rational basis
review would be satisfied. But Lawrence does not apply rational basis review, and in
some applications, the ruling would seem to throw legal prohibitions on incest into
considerable doubt.</p>
      <p>The most difficult cases involve laws forbidding adultery.171 We could imagine
actual adultery prosecutions172; we could also imagine cases in which government takes
adverse employment action against those involved in adulterous relationships.173 Here as
in other contexts, it would be possible to urge that a consensual relationship is involved,
one with which the state may not interfere on purely moral grounds. On the other hand, it
is possible to justify prohibitions on adultery by reference to harms to third parties:
children, in many cases, and the betrayed spouse, in many more cases. The adultery laws
can be seen as an effort to protect the marital relationship, involving persons and
interests, including those of children, that are harmed if adultery occurs.174 Marriage can
and often is understood as an exchange of commitments, which have individual and
social value; and a prohibition on adultery, moral and legal, operates in the service of
167 As I have noted, Lawrence raises no questions about laws forbidding public masturbation. The most
plausible objection would be that mere offense is not a legitimate basis for regulating noncoercive sex; and
indeed Justice Scalia seems to read the Court’s opinion to have that implication. But the Court’s rejection
of the moral basis of the ban on sodomy should not be taken to forbid governments from protecting people
from unwanted viewing of other people’s sex lives.
168 See, e.g., Jarrett v. Jarrett, 449 U.S. 927, 929 n. 2 (citing Ill. Rev. Stat. ch. 38, § 11-8 (1977)).
169 See, e.g., id.; In re J.M., 575 S.E.2d 441, 444 (Ga. 2003); State v. Saunders, 381 A.2d 333, 339 (N.J.
1977).
170 Admittedly, rational basis review might be satisfied if, for example, the state urged that it was
attempting to reduce the risks of unwanted pregnancy and venereal disease. But after Lawrence, rational
basis review is unlikely to be applied here.
171 See Marcum v. MacWharter, 308 U.S. 635 (2002).
172 See Commonwealth v. Stowell, 449 N.E.2d 357 (Mass. 1983).
173 See Oliverson v. West Valley City, 875 F.Supp. 1465 (D. Utah 1995); City of Sherman v. Henry, 928
S.W.2d 464 (Tex. 1996).
174 See Oliverson, id., at 1477.
those commitments. If rational basis review is involved, prohibitions on adultery should
certainly be acceptable—except, perhaps, in cases in which the married couple has agreed
to non-exclusivity (in which case criminal prosecution would be especially surprising).</p>
      <p>The difficulty here is that in the context of adultery, criminal prosecutions are
extremely unusual, at least as rare as criminal prosecutions for sodomy. There is a good
argument that criminal prosecutions, in this context, are inconsistent with emerging social
values. This is not because adultery is thought to be morally acceptable; it is not. It is
because adultery is not thought to be a proper basis for the use of the criminal law.
Perhaps it could be said that Lawrence turned at least in part on the Court’s evident desire
to ensure against practices that would “demean[] the lives of homosexual persons.”175 It
is not plausible to say that the Court should take special steps to ensure against practices
that would “demean the lives of” adulterers. But in the end, it is not so easy to distinguish
an adultery prosecution from the sodomy prosecution forbidden in Lawrence.176</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-12">
      <title>B. Sexual Orientation, Employment, and Marriage</title>
      <p>1. Employment. May a public employer discharge or punish an employee because
of his sexual orientation? Before Lawrence, the lower courts were divided on the issue.177
The logic of Bowers supported the decisions upholding such discharges, at least against
due process challenges. And it was possible to urge that because homosexual activity is
not protected by the Constitution, government employees are permitted to discriminate
against those who engage in that activity. At first glance, however, Lawrence resolves
that question the other way. A public employer is not permitted to discharge an employee
because she has exercised a constitutional right (an oversimplification to which I shall
return). If an employee has converted to Catholicism, or voted for a Republican, she may
not be adversely affected for that reason. So too if an employee has exercised a right
protected by the due process clause. A state may not refuse to hire a secretary who has
used contraception or had an abortion. Under Lawrence, government may not refuse to
hire people who have engaged in same-sex relations. It could perhaps be argued that a
criminal punishment is worse than a civil disability, and hence that the prohibition on
175 123 S. Ct. at 2482.
176 Employment discrimination by the state against adulterers raises further complexities. On a standard
analysis, protection against criminal prosecution, if it exists, is conclusive on the issue of public
employment, forbidding discrimination against people who have engaged in constitutionally protected
activity. One exception would apply when the government can invoke distinctive employment-related
grounds for the discrimination. A public university’s admissions office need not hire, as director of
admissions, people who speak out in favor of race discrimination; perhaps discrimination againstadulterers
can, in some contexts, be similarly justified. In any case everything turns on the reason for a due process
ruling. If adultery prosecutions were banned on the basis of a rationale tied to the illegitimacy of using the
criminal law, perhaps civil disabilities, as through employment discrimination, would be permissible.
177 See DeSantis v. Pacific Tel. &amp; Tel. Co., Inc., 608 F.2d 327 (9th Cir. 1979) (holding that homosexuals
are not a protected class under Title VII); Childers v. Dallas Police Dep’t, 513 F.Supp. 134 (N.D. Tex.
1981) (holding that a police department could refuse to hire a gay activist because of doubts about his
character). Compare Glover v. Williamsburg Local Sch. Dist. Bd. of Educ., 20 F.Supp.2d 1160 (S.D. Ohio
1998) (finding no rational basis for a decision not to renew the contract of a homosexual teacher); Weaver
v. Nebo Sch. Dist., 29 F.Supp.2d 1279 (D. Utah 1998) (to the same effect).
criminal prosecution does not entail an equivalent prohibition on adverse employment
actions. But the cases just described should be sufficient response to that argument.</p>
      <p>Most cases of adverse employment action, prompted by homosexual activity, are
easy after Lawrence. But there are some possible responses. One would emphasize the
reading I have emphasized here: Lawrence turned not simply on a finding of a
fundamental right, but more importantly on the Court’s conclusion that the Texas law
was no longer supported by public convictions. If desuetude is involved, then perhaps
employment discrimination is permitted even if criminal prosecution is not. This
argument is not implausible or incoherent; if we emphasize the idea of desuetude, then a
moral judgment might be permissible in the employment context even if it cannot be
invoked as a basis for criminal prosecution. But this approach reads Lawrence a bit too
finely. The Court is best read to have found a fundamental interest, whatever its reason
for doing so; and if so, states may not refuse to hire people who have engaged in the
relevant behavior.</p>
      <p>Another response would emphasize that the government sometimes may indeed
refuse to hire people for engaging in constitutionally protected activity. The President is
permitted to fail to employ, as Secretary of State, someone who has publicly criticized his
policies; so too, a public university is allowed not to hire, or even to fire, an admissions
officer who has said that women should not go to college, or that it is best for
AfricanAmericans to attend vocational school. In such cases, the university can claim, plausibly,
that it is not trying to censor anyone, or to punish them for exercising constitutional right,
but instead to accomplish the substantive task that it has set for itself.178 Might
discrimination against gays and lesbians be similarly justified? This is not entirely
unimaginable, but it is hard to see. Unless the state is to capitulate to private prejudice, as
it is generally forbidden from doing,179 it cannot easily invoke a distinct,
employmentrelated reason to discriminate on the basis of sexual orientation.</p>
      <p>It also follows that the “don’t ask, don’t tell” policy, in the military setting, is
under new pressure. It is no longer possible to defend that policy simply by citing
Bowers. If the policy is to be upheld, it is because courts should give great deference to
military judgments, applying a form of rational basis review to them. I believe that
federal courts are not likely to interfere with military judgments here, and that there is
good reason for a general posture of deference to such judgments. In principle, however,
it is extremely difficult to defend “don’t ask, don’t tell” against constitutional challenge,
and this appears to be one of the exceedingly rare settings in which judicial interference
with military judgments would be justified.180</p>
      <p>2. Marriage. Of course the largest issue is the fate of same-sex marriage. Under
Lawrence, must states recognize such marriages? I have suggested that Lawrence is akin
to Griswold; but Griswold led to Roe. Perhaps Lawrence will lead to its own Roe, in the
178 See Pickering v. Board of Educ., 391 US 563 (1968), for the basic framework.
179 See Palmore v. Sidoti, 466 US 429 (1984).
180 For an argument to this effect before Lawrence was decided, see Cass R. Sunstein, Designing
Democracy (2002).
form of a requirement that states allow gays and lesbians, not less than heterosexuals, to
marry.</p>
      <p>The issue is exceedingly complex. At first glance, Lawrence has nothing at all to
do with same-sex marriage. It involved sodomy prosecutions, brought under
anachronistic laws, and the due process challenge to those prosecutions need not draw
into doubt the still-universal practice of defining marriage to involve one man and one
woman. In any case, the most natural challenge to laws rejecting such marriages is rooted
in the equal protection clause; and Lawrence said nothing about the equal protection
clause (perhaps because it sought to avoid the marriage issue). To the extent that the
Court was emphasizing an “emerging awareness,” its decision does not touch
prohibitions on same-sex marriage—and will not do so unless and until such prohibitions
seem as outmoded as bans on homosexual sodomy do today. Existing practice suggests
universal opposition to same-sex marriage,181 and polling evidence suggests that most
Americans support existing practice.182</p>
      <p>But under existing law, the issue cannot be disposed of so readily. In Loving v.
Virginia183 (probably the best-named case in all of constitutional law), the Court struck
down a ban on racial intermarriage on two grounds. The first is the familiar equal
protection ground, seeing that ban as a form of racial discrimination. But in a separate
ruling, the Court also held that the ban violated the due process clause. In the Court’s
words, “the freedom to marry has long been recognized as one of the vital personal rights
essential to the orderly pursuit of happiness by free men.”184 It added that “[m]arriage is
one of the ‘basic civil rights of man,’ fundamental to our very existence and survival.”185
The Loving Court’s due process ruling was not free from ambiguity; the problem of racial
discrimination played a large role. But subsequent cases confirm that the right to marry
counts as fundamental for due process purposes—and is sufficient by itself to take the
analysis into the domain of heightened scrutiny.</p>
      <p>In Zablocki v. Redhail, the Court struck down a Wisconsin law forbidding people
under child support obligations to remarry unless they had obtained a judicial
determination that they had met those obligations and that their children were not likely
to become public charges. 186 The Court insisted that “the right to marry is of fundamental
importance for all individuals,”187 and that “the decision to marry has been placed on the
same level of importance as decisions relating to procreation, childbirth, child rearing,
and family relationships.”188 The Court said that it would uphold “reasonable regulations
that do not significantly interfere with decisions to enter into the marital relationship.”189
But any direct and substantial interference with the right to marry would be strictly
181 Civil unions are a different matter, but they hardly can claim even strong minority support.
182 See the summary at http://www.bpnews.org/bpnews.asp?ID=16337.
183 388 U.S. 1 (1968).
184 Id. at 12.
185 Id. (quoting Skinner v. Oklahoma ex rel. Williamson, 316 U.S. 535, 541 (1942)).
186 434 U.S. 374 (1978).
187 Id. at 384.
188 Id. at 386.
189 Id. at 386-87 (citing Califano v. Jobst, 434 U.S. 47 (1977)).
scrutinized. In a concurring opinion, Justice Stevens underlined the point, urging that the
Constitution would cast serious doubt on any “classification which determines who may
lawfully enter into the marriage relationship.”190</p>
      <p>In this light a prohibition on same-sex marriage is not so easy to defend in the
aftermath of Lawrence. Under the Court’s decisions, a fundamental right does seem to be
involved, one with which the state can defend only by pointing to a countervailing
interest that is not merely legitimate but also compelling. In the context of same-sex
marriage, what might that interest be? What sorts of social harms would follow from
recognizing marriages between people of the same sex? It is conventional to argue that
the refusal to recognize same-sex marriage is a way of protecting the marital institution
itself. But this is very puzzling; how do same-sex marriages threaten the institution of
marriage? Or perhaps the state can legitimately reserve the idea of marriage to men and
women for expressive reasons. Perhaps the state can urge that it does not want to give the
same expressive support to same-sex unions as to opposite-sex unions. But why not? As
compared to a ban on same-sex marriages, a prohibition on adultery seems easy to justify.
Such a prohibition is likely, in numerous cases, to protect one or even both spouses, and
to protect children besides. If, as I have suggested, Lawrence draws prohibitions on
adultery into some doubt, it would seem to raise extremely serious questions about
prohibitions on same-sex marriage.</p>
      <p>But perhaps criminal punishment is special. Perhaps such punishment is quite
different from, and to be assessed more skeptically than, a statute that confers the benefits
of marriage to some but not to all. Perhaps Lawrence forbids the state from using the
heavy artillery of the criminal law—but without raising questions about civil rights and
civil duties. It would not be at all implausible to say that the Lawrence Court was
responsive to the assortment of disabilities associated with criminal punishment—a set of
disabilities that might be thought unique. But Loving and Zablocki themselves raise
questions for this kind of distinction. Neither case involved a criminal prohibition. Both
applied careful judicial scrutiny to laws saying that certain people could not enter into the
marital relationship.</p>
      <p>Perhaps we could read Loving and Zablocki more narrowly.191 Notwithstanding
the Court’s rhetoric, it is quite doubtful that the Court really meant to raise serious
questions about all state laws dictating who may enter into a marital relationship. People
are not permitted to marry dogs or cats. They are banned from marrying their first cousins
or their aunts. They cannot marry two people, or three, or twenty. Must these restrictions
be justified by showing that they are the least restrictive means of achieving a compelling
state interest? If so, at least some of them would be in serious trouble. Perhaps the ban on
incestuous marriages could be defended by pointing to the risk of coercion and the danger
to any children who would result. But as we have seen, it is easy to imagine some cases
in which any such defense would be weak—as, for example, where the would-be spouses
190 Id. at 404.
191 It would also be possible to deny that the right to marry has a constitutional status—to urge that Loving
and Zablocki were really equal protection cases. This view would have some appeal, especially to skeptics
about substantive due process; but it does not fit with current law.
are both adults and do not plan to have children. Perhaps bans on polygamy could be
defended by pointing to the risk of exploitation, especially of the women involved. But
we might doubt whether Loving and Zablocki should be read to require a careful judicial
inquiry into that question.</p>
      <p>A possible opinion would urge that by deeming the right to marry fundamental,
the Court did not mean to suggest that it would strictly scrutinize any law that departed
from the traditional idea that a marriage is between (one) woman and (one) man. It meant
only to say that when a man and a woman seek to marry, the state must have good
reasons for putting significant barriers in their path. This rationale has the advantage of
fitting with both Loving and Zablocki. The problem is that it seems somewhat arbitrary
and opportunistic. Why, exactly, should a marriage be defined in this way? Why, in any
case, should the definition be such as to allow the state not to recognize same-sex
marriages?</p>
      <p>It is not at all easy to answer this question. In my view, the only difference
between Lawrence and a ban on same-sex marriage is that the sodomy law no longer fits
with widespread public convictions, whereas the public does not (yet) support same-sex
marriages. If we rely heavily on the desuetude-type passages of the Court’s opinion, then
it would be possible to sketch an opinion upholding the ban on same-sex marriages while
also invalidating any state law that punishes consensual sodomy. Such an opinion would
read Loving and Zablocki in the narrow way just suggested, with reference to slippery
slope problems, and conclude that a rational basis is all that is required for a law that
restricts the institution of marriage to one woman and one man. This opinion would
certainly be plausible. The problem is a general one with any approach that relies on
public convictions: they might not be principled. The public might have gone this far, and
no further; but there may be no good reason for it not to have gone further. I cannot see a
principled distinction, aside from public convictions, between what the Court did in
Lawrence and what a court would do in striking down a state’s failure to recognize
samesex marriages.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-13">
      <title>C. A Summary</title>
      <p>The discussion thus far has gone briskly over a considerable amount of territory.
For those who find tabular summaries useful, consider the following:</p>
      <p>Invalid</p>
      <p>Valid
Sexual Harassment X (coercive)
Prostitution</p>
      <p>X (commercial)
Incest
Adultery
Fornication
Use of sexual
devices
Polygamy
Employment
discrimination
against gays and
lesbians
Bans on same-sex
marriage
X
(military)
X (for now?)</p>
      <p>X
(but perhaps
defensible by
reference to harms
to third parties)
X
X
X
(except for
military)</p>
      <p>The Lawrence decision is susceptible to two broad readings. The Court’s ruling
could easily be seen as a recognition of the constitutionally fundamental character of
sexual liberty, disabling the state from controlling the acts of consenting adults without
an extremely powerful justification. Alternatively, it could be seen as a rational basis
holding with a strong Millian foundation—a holding that invalidates “morals” legislation,
requiring harm to third parties whenever government is regulating private sexual conduct.
In practice, these two readings would not be terribly far apart; they would use different
doctrinal avenues to similar results.</p>
      <p>I have suggested the possibility of a third and narrower reading, one that stresses,
as the Court did, that a criminal ban on sodomy is hopelessly out of accord with
contemporary convictions. Thus understood, the due process principle of Lawrence
asserts a constitutional objection to statutes that are rarely enforced and that interfere with
important human interests without anything like a justification in contemporary values.
Such statutes are a recipe for unpredictable and discriminatory enforcement practices;
they do violence to both democratic values and the rule of law. I have stressed the roots
of Lawrence in a narrow, American-style version of the idea of desuetude -- not because
the broader readings are entirely implausible, but because the Court would have been
extremely unlikely to rule as it did if not for its perception that the Texas law could not
claim a plausible foundation in widely shared moral commitments. I believe that an equal
protection ruling, of the sort sketched by Justice O’Connor, would have been preferable,
not least because it would have emphasized what should be clear to all: The problem in
Lawrence had everything to with the social subordination of gays and lesbians. But a due
process ruling, understood in the relatively narrow terms outlined here, has considerable
appeal.</p>
      <p>What is the reach of Lawrence? Restrictions on sex that is nonconsensual or
commercial are surely valid. By contrast, laws forbidding fornication (defined as
extramarital but non-adulterous sex) are surely invalid. The Constitution probably forbids
government from punishing, either criminally or civilly, those who have used sexual
devices. The state is almost certainly banned from discriminating against those who have
engaged in homosexual conduct, at least outside of certain specialized contexts (most
notably the military). In some applications, bans on incest and adultery could be subject
to serious constitutional challenge.</p>
      <p>The hardest cases involve the failure to recognize same-sex marriages. If
Lawrence is put together with Loving and Zablocki, it would seem clear that the
government would have to produce a compelling justification for refusing to recognize
such marriages, and compelling justifications are not easy to find. If we emphasize an
equality rationale, the subtext of Lawrence, then bans on same-sex marriages are in
serious constitutional trouble. On the other hand, the ban on same-sex marriages cannot,
at this point in time, be regarded as an anachronism, or as conspicuously out of touch
with emerging social values; and there are strong prudential reasons for the Court to
hesitate in this domain. The marriage issue, more than any other, will test the question
whether Lawrence is this generation’s Griswold—or the start of something far more
ambitious.</p>
      <sec id="sec-13-1">
        <title>Readers with comments should address them to:</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-13-2">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein</title>
        <p>University of Chicago Law School
1111 East 60th Street
Chicago, IL 60637
csunstei@midway.uchicago.edu
10.
28.
53.</p>
        <p>Richard A. Posner, Values and Consequences: An Introduction to Economic
Analysis of Law (March 1998)
Denise DiPasquale and Edward L. Glaeser, Incentives and Social Capital: Are
Homeowners Better Citizens? (April 1998)
Christine Jolls, Cass R. Sunstein, and Richard Thaler, A Behavioral Approach to
Law and Economics (May 1998)
John R. Lott, Jr., Does a Helping Hand Put Others At Risk?: Affirmative Action,
Police Departments, and Crime (May 1998)
Cass R. Sunstein and Edna Ullmann-Margalit, Second-Order Decisions (June
1998)
Jonathan M. Karpoff and John R. Lott, Jr., Punitive Damages: Their Determinants,
Effects on Firm Value, and the Impact of Supreme Court and Congressional
Attempts to Limit Awards (July 1998)
Kenneth W. Dam, Self-Help in the Digital Jungle (August 1998)
John R. Lott, Jr., How Dramatically Did Women=s Suffrage Change the Size and
Scope of Government? (September 1998)
Kevin A. Kordana and Eric A. Posner, A Positive Theory of Chapter 11 (October
1998)
David A. Weisbach, Line Drawing, Doctrine, and Efficiency in the Tax Law
(November 1998)
Jack L. Goldsmith and Eric A. Posner, A Theory of Customary International Law
(November 1998)
John R. Lott, Jr., Public Schooling, Indoctrination, and Totalitarianism (December
1998)
Cass R. Sunstein, Private Broadcasters and the Public Interest: Notes Toward A
AThird Way@ (January 1999)
Richard A. Posner, An Economic Approach to the Law of Evidence (February
1999)
Yannis Bakos, Erik Brynjolfsson, Douglas Lichtman, Shared Information Goods
(February 1999)
Kenneth W. Dam, Intellectual Property and the Academic Enterprise (February
1999)
Gertrud M. Fremling and Richard A. Posner, Status Signaling and the Law, with
Particular Application to Sexual Harassment (March 1999)
Cass R. Sunstein, Must Formalism Be Defended Empirically? (March 1999)
Jonathan M. Karpoff, John R. Lott, Jr., and Graeme Rankine, Environmental
Violations, Legal Penalties, and Reputation Costs (March 1999)
Matthew D. Adler and Eric A. Posner, Rethinking Cost-Benefit Analysis (April
1999)
John R. Lott, Jr. and William M. Landes, Multiple Victim Public Shooting,
Bombings, and Right-to-Carry Concealed Handgun Laws: Contrasting Private
and Public Law Enforcement (April 1999)
74.</p>
        <p>Lisa Bernstein, The Questionable Empirical Basis of Article 2=s Incorporation
Strategy: A Preliminary Study (May 1999)
Richard A. Epstein, Deconstructing Privacy: and Putting It Back Together Again
(May 1999)
William M. Landes, Winning the Art Lottery: The Economic Returns to the Ganz
Collection (May 1999)
Cass R. Sunstein, David Schkade, and Daniel Kahneman, Do People Want
Optimal Deterrence? (June 1999)
Tomas J. Philipson and Richard A. Posner, The Long-Run Growth in Obesity as a
Function of Technological Change (June 1999)
David A. Weisbach, Ironing Out the Flat Tax (August 1999)
Eric A. Posner, A Theory of Contract Law under Conditions of Radical Judicial
Error (August 1999)
David Schkade, Cass R. Sunstein, and Daniel Kahneman, Are Juries Less Erratic
than Individuals? Deliberation, Polarization, and Punitive Damages (September
1999)
Cass R. Sunstein, Nondelegation Canons (September 1999)
Richard A. Posner, The Theory and Practice of Citations Analysis, with Special
Reference to Law and Economics (September 1999)
Randal C. Picker, Regulating Network Industries: A Look at Intel (October 1999)
Cass R. Sunstein, Cognition and Cost-Benefit Analysis (October 1999)
Douglas G. Baird and Edward R. Morrison, Optimal Timing and Legal
Decisionmaking: The Case of the Liquidation Decision in Bankruptcy (October
1999)
Gertrud M. Fremling and Richard A. Posner, Market Signaling of Personal
Characteristics (November 1999)
Matthew D. Adler and Eric A. Posner, Implementing Cost-Benefit Analysis When
Preferences Are Distorted (November 1999)
Richard A. Posner, Orwell versus Huxley: Economics, Technology, Privacy, and
Satire (November 1999)
David A. Weisbach, Should the Tax Law Require Current Accrual of Interest on
Derivative Financial Instruments? (December 1999)
Cass R. Sunstein, The Law of Group Polarization (December 1999)
Eric A. Posner, Agency Models in Law and Economics (January 2000)
Karen Eggleston, Eric A. Posner, and Richard Zeckhauser, Simplicity and
Complexity in Contracts (January 2000)
Douglas G. Baird and Robert K. Rasmussen, Boyd=s Legacy and Blackstone=s
Ghost (February 2000)
David Schkade, Cass R. Sunstein, Daniel Kahneman, Deliberating about Dollars:
The Severity Shift (February 2000)
Richard A. Posner and Eric B. Rasmusen, Creating and Enforcing Norms, with
Special Reference to Sanctions (March 2000)
97. Douglas Lichtman, Property Rights in Emerging Platform Technologies (April
2000)
98. Cass R. Sunstein and Edna Ullmann-Margalit, Solidarity in Consumption (May
2000)
99. David A. Weisbach, An Economic Analysis of Anti-Tax Avoidance Laws (May
2000, revised May 2002)
100. Cass R. Sunstein, Human Behavior and the Law of Work (June 2000)
101. William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, Harmless Error (June 2000)
102. Robert H. Frank and Cass R. Sunstein, Cost-Benefit Analysis and Relative</p>
        <p>Position (August 2000)
103. Eric A. Posner, Law and the Emotions (September 2000)
104. Cass R. Sunstein, Cost-Benefit Default Principles (October 2000)
105. Jack Goldsmith and Alan Sykes, The Dormant Commerce Clause and the Internet
(November 2000)
106. Richard A. Posner, Antitrust in the New Economy (November 2000)
107. Douglas Lichtman, Scott Baker, and Kate Kraus, Strategic Disclosure in the Patent</p>
        <p>System (November 2000)
108. Jack L. Goldsmith and Eric A. Posner, Moral and Legal Rhetoric in International</p>
        <p>Relations: A Rational Choice Perspective (November 2000)
109. William Meadow and Cass R. Sunstein, Statistics, Not Experts (December 2000)
110. Saul Levmore, Conjunction and Aggregation (December 2000)
111. Saul Levmore, Puzzling Stock Options and Compensation Norms (December
2000)
112. Richard A. Epstein and Alan O. Sykes, The Assault on Managed Care: Vicarious</p>
        <p>Liability, Class Actions and the Patient=s Bill of Rights (December 2000)
113. William M. Landes, Copyright, Borrowed Images and Appropriation Art: An</p>
        <p>Economic Approach (December 2000)
114. Cass R. Sunstein, Switching the Default Rule (January 2001)
115. George G. Triantis, Financial Contract Design in the World of Venture Capital
(January 2001)
116. Jack Goldsmith, Statutory Foreign Affairs Preemption (February 2001)
117. Richard Hynes and Eric A. Posner, The Law and Economics of Consumer</p>
        <p>Finance (February 2001)
118. Cass R. Sunstein, Academic Fads and Fashions (with Special Reference to Law)
(March 2001)
119. Eric A. Posner, Controlling Agencies with Cost-Benefit Analysis: A Positive</p>
        <p>Political Theory Perspective (April 2001)
120. Douglas G. Baird, Does Bogart Still Get Scale? Rights of Publicity in the Digital</p>
        <p>Age (April 2001)
121. Douglas G. Baird and Robert K. Rasmussen, Control Rights, Priority Rights and
the Conceptual Foundations of Corporate Reorganization (April 2001)
122. David A. Weisbach, Ten Truths about Tax Shelters (May 2001)
123.
145.</p>
        <p>David A. Weisbach, Thinking Ouside the Little Boxes (March 2002, Texas Law
Review)
Eric A. Posner, Economic Analysis of Contract Law after Three Decades: Success
or Failure (March 2002)
Randal C. Picker, Copyright as Entry Policy: The Case of Digital Distribution
(April 2002, The Antitrust Bulletin)
David A. Weisbach, Taxes and Torts in the Redistribution of Income (April 2002,
Coase Lecture February 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein, Beyond the Precautionary Principle (April 2002)
Robert W. Hahn and Cass R. Sunstein, A New Executive Order for Improving
Federal Regulation? Deeper and Wider Cost-Benefit Analysis (April 2002)
Douglas Lichtman, Copyright as a Rule of Evidence (May 2002, updated January
2003)
Richard A. Epstein, Steady the Course: Property Rights in Genetic Material (May
2002)
Jack Goldsmith and Cass R. Sunstein, Military Tribunals and Legal Culture: What
a Difference Sixty Years Makes (June 2002)
William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, Indefinitely Renewable Copyright
(July 2002)
Anne Gron and Alan O. Sykes, Terrorism and Insurance Markets: A Role for the
Government as Insurer? (July 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein and Adrian Vermeule, Interpretation and Institutions (July 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein, The Rights of Animals: A Very Short Primer (August 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein, Avoiding Absurdity? A New Canon in Regulatory Law (with
Notes on Interpretive Theory) (August 2002)
Randal C. Picker, From Edison to the Broadcast Flag: Mechanisms of Consent
and Refusal and the Propertization of Copyright (September 2002)
Eric A. Posner, A Theory of the Laws of War (September 2002)
Eric A. Posner, Probability Errors: Some Positive and Normative Implications for
Tort and Contract Law (September 2002)
Lior Jacob Strahilevitz, Charismatic Code, Social Norms, and the Emergence of
Cooperation on the File-Swapping Networks (September 2002)
David A. Weisbach, Does the X-Tax Mark the Spot? (September 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein, Conformity and Dissent (September 2002)
Cass R. Sunstein, Hazardous Heuristics (October 2002)
Douglas Lichtman, Uncertainty and the Standard for Preliminary Relief (October
2002)
Edward T. Swaine, Rational Custom (November 2002)
Julie Roin, Truth in Government: Beyond the Tax Expenditure Budget
(November 2002)
Avraham D. Tabbach, Criminal Behavior, Sanctions, and Income Taxation: An
Economic Analysis (November 2002)
170.</p>
        <p>William L. Meadow, Anthony Bell, and Cass R. Sunstein, Statistics, Not
Memories: What Was the Standard of Care for Administering Antenatal Steroids
to Women in Preterm Labor between 1985 and 2000? (September 2003)
Cass R. Sunstein, What Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy, Desuetude, Sexuality,
and Marriage (September 2003)</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list/>
  </back>
</article>