<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Libertarian Paternalism
Author(s): Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein
Source: The American Economic Review</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <contrib-group>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Thaler:Departmentof Economics andBehavioralScience, University of Chicago GraduateSchool of Business</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>1101 E. 58th Street, Chicago, IL 60637</addr-line>
          ,
          <country country="US">USA</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>93</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>3</fpage>
      <lpage>5</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at http://www.jstor.org/page/ info/about/policies/terms.jsp JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>American Economic Association is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to The American Economic
Review.
http://www.jstor.org</p>
      <p>This content downloaded from 132.211.1.50 on Thu, 20 Aug 2015 22:44:55 UTC</p>
      <p>All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions
BEHAVIORAELCONOMICSP,UBLICPOLICYA,ND PATERNALISMt</p>
      <p>LibertarianPaternalism</p>
      <p>By RICHARDH. THALERANDCASSR. SUNSTEIN*</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Many economists are libertariansand con</title>
      <p>sider the term "paternalistic"to be derogatory.
Most would think that the phrase libertarian
paternalismis an oxymoron.The modestgoal of
this essay is to encourageeconomists to rethink
their views on paternalism.We believe thatthe
anti-paternalistic fervor expressed by many
economists is based on a combinationof a false
assumption and at least two misconceptions.
The false assumptionis thatpeople always
(usually?) make choices that are in theirbest
interest. This claim is either tautological, and
therefore uninteresting,or testable. We claim
that it is testable and false-indeed, obviously
false.</p>
      <p>The first misconceptionis that there are
viable alternativesto paternalism.In many
situations, some organizationor agent must make a
choice thatwill affect the choices of some other
people. The point applies to both private and
public actors. Considerthe problem facing the
directorof a company cafeteria who discovers
that the order in which food is
arrangedinfluences the choices people make. To simplify,
consider three alternative strategies: (1) she
could make choices thatshe thinkswould make
the customers best off; (2) she could make
choices at random;or (3) she could maliciously
choose those items that she thinks would make
the customers as obese as possible. Option 1
*Discussants: RobertE. Hall, StanfordUniversity;Gary
Becker, Universityof
Chicago;RobertBarro,HarvardUniversity.
175
appears to be paternalistic, which it is, but
would anyone advocate options 2 or 3?</p>
      <p>The second misconceptionis thatpaternalism
always involves coercion. As the cafeteria
example illustrates,the choice of which order to
presentfood items does not coerce anyoneto do
anything, yet one might prefer some orders to
others on paternalisticgrounds. Would many
object to puttingthe fruitbefore the desserts at
an elementary school cafeteria if the outcome
were to increasethe consumptionratioof apples
to Twinkies?Is this
questionfundamentallydifferentif the customersareadults?If no coercion
is involved, we think that some types of
paternalism should be acceptable to even the most
ardentlibertarianW.e call such actions
libertarian paternalism.</p>
      <p>In our understandinga, policy counts as
"paternalistic" if it is selected with the goal of
influencing the choices of affected parties in a
way that will make those partiesbetteroff. We
intend"betteroff' to be measuredas objectively
as possible, andwe clearlydo not always equate
revealed preference with welfare. That is, we
emphasize the possibility that in some cases
individuals make inferior choices, choices that
they would change if they had complete
information, unlimited cognitive abilities, and no
lack of willpower. Once it is understoodthat
some organizational decisions are inevitable,
that a form of paternalismcannot be avoided,
and thatthe alternativesto paternalism(such as
choosing options to make people sick, obese, or
generally worse off) are unattractive,we can
abandonthe less interestingquestionof whether
to be paternalisticor not and turn to the more
constructivequestion of how to choose among
paternalisticoptions.1</p>
      <p>
        1Readers interested in this topic should also consult
Colin
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">Camereret al. (2001</xref>
        ) for an illuminatingdiscussionof
related issues. That paper shares with the papers in this
AEA PAPERSAND PROCEEDINGS
      </p>
      <p>I. Are ChoicesRational?</p>
      <p>
        The presumption that individual choices
should be free from interference is usually
based on the assumptionthat people do a good
job of makingchoices, or at least thatthey do a
far betterjob thanthirdpartiescould do. As far
as we can tell, there is little empirical support
for this claim. Research by psychologists and
economists over the past three decades has
raised questions about the rationality of the
judgmentsand decisions thatindividualsmake.
People do not exhibit rationalexpectations,fail
to make forecasts that are consistent with
Bayes' rule, use heuristics that lead them to
make systematic blunders, exhibit preference
reversals(thatis, they preferA to B and B to A)
and make different choices depending on the
wording of the problem
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5 ref7">(for many examples,
see the two recent collections of papers by
Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky [2000]
andby ThomasGilovich et al. [2002])</xref>
        .
Furthermore, in the context of intertemporalchoice,
people exhibit dynamic inconsistency, valuing
present consumption much more than future
consumption.In other words, people have
selfcontrol problems
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11 ref9">(see the other papers in this
session [James Choi et al., 2003b; Ted
O'DonoghueandMatthewRabin,2003] for
details and references)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>Many economists are skeptical of some of
these findings, thinking that people may do a
betterjob of choosing in the "realworld"than
they do in the laboratory.However, studies of
actual choices for high stakes reveal many of
the same problems. For example, the Surgeon
General reports that 61 percent of Americans
are either overweight or obese. Given the
adverse effects obesity has on health, it is hardto
claim that Americansare eating optimal diets.</p>
      <p>
        Another illustrationcomes from the domain
of savings behavior.Shlomo
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">Benartziand
Thaler (2002</xref>
        ) investigate how much investors like
the portfolios they have selected in their
defined-contributionsavings plans. Employees
volunteeredto sharetheirportfoliochoices with
the investigators (by bringing a copy of their
session the commongoal of devisingpolicies thathelp some
agentswho aremakingsome mistake,while minimizingthe
costs imposed on others.
most recent statementto the lab). They were
then shown the probabilitydistributionsof
expected retirementincome for three investment
portfolios just labeled A, B, and C.
Unbeknownst to the subjects, the three portfolios
were their own and portfolios mimicking the
averageand medianchoices of theirfellow
employees. The distributionsof expected returns
were computedusing the softwareof Financial
Engines, the financial information company
founded by William Sharpe. On average, the
subjectsratedthe averageportfolioequallywith
theirown portfolio,andtheyjudged the median
portfolioto be significantlymore attractivethan
their own. Indeed, only 20 percent of the
subjects preferredtheir own portfolio to the
median portfolio. Apparently,people do not gain
much by choosing investment portfolios for
themselves.
      </p>
      <p>II. Is PaternalismInevitable?</p>
      <p>
        As the cafeterialine examplediscussedabove
illustrates, planners are forced to make some
design choices. A simple and
importantexample is the selection of a "default option" to
determine what happens if an agent fails to
choose for himself. In a fully rational world
such design choices would have little effect (at
least in high-stakes situations) because agents
would simply choose the best option for them
regardless of the default. However, numerous
experimentsillustratethatthereis a very strong
"statusquo" bias
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10 ref6">(see William Samuelson and
Richard Zeckhauser, 1988; Kahneman et al.,
1991)</xref>
        . The existing arrangement,whether set
out by private institutions or by government,
tends to stick.
      </p>
      <p>
        One illustrationof this phenomenon comes
from studies of automaticenrollmentin 401(k)
employee savings plans. Most 401(k) plans use
an opt-in design. When employees firstbecome
eligible to participatein the 401(k) plan, they
receive some plan informationand an
enrollment form that must be completed in order to
join. Under the alternativeof
automaticenrollment, employees receive the same information
but aretold thatunless they opt out, they will be
enrolled in the plan (with some default options
for savings rates and asset allocation). In
companies that offer a "match" (the employer
matches the employee's
contributionsaccording to some formula, often a 50-percentmatch
up to some cap), most employees eventuallydo
join the plan, but enrollments occur much
sooner under automaticenrollment.For
example, Brigitte
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">Madrianand Dennis Shea (2001</xref>
        )
found that initial enrollmentsjumped from 49
percentto 86 percent,and
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">Choi et al. (2002)</xref>
        find
similarresults for other companies.
      </p>
      <p>Should the adoptionof automaticenrollment
be consideredpaternalistic?And, if so, shouldit
therefore be seen as a kind of officious
meddling with employee preferences?We answer
these questions yes and no respectively. If the
employer thinks (correctly, we believe) that
most employees would preferto join the 401(k)
plan if they took the time to think about it and
did not lose the enrollmentform,thenby
choosing automaticenrollmentthey are acting
paternalistically. They are attempting to steer
employees' choices in directions that will
promote employees' welfare. But since no one is
forced to do anything, we think this steering
should be considered unobjectionableto
libertarians.The employer must choose some set of
rules, and either plan affects employees'
choices. No law of nature says that, in the
absence of an affirmativeelection by
employees, zero percent of earnings will go into a
retirement plan. Because both plans alter
choices, neitherone can be said, more than the
other, to count as a form of objectionable
meddling.</p>
      <p>Quick-mindedreaders might be tempted to
think that there is a way out of this dilemma.
Employers could avoid choosing a default if
they requiredemployees to make a choice,
eitherin or out. But some thoughtreveals thatthis
is not at all a way out of the dilemma;rather,it
is simply anotheroption among many that the
employer can elect. In fact, Choi et al. (2003a)
findthatthis ruleincreasesenrollments(relative
to the opt-in rule) though by not as much as
automaticenrollment.Furthermoret,he very
requirementthat employees make a choice has a
paternalisticelement. Many employees do not
want to have to make a choice (and would
choose not to have to do so). Should employers
really force them to choose?</p>
      <p>Why, exactly, does the setting of defaults
have such large effects? With respect to
savings, the designateddefaultplan
apparentlycarries a certain legitimacy for many employees,
perhapsbecause it seems to have resultedfrom
some conscious thoughtaboutwhat makesmost
sense for most people. But there is a separate
explanation, involving inertia. For any
employee, a change from any status quo entails
time andeffort, andmanypeople seem to prefer
to avoid both of these, especially if they are
proneto procrastinationW.hen defaultrules are
"sticky" and affect choices as a result, inertia
might be the majorreason.</p>
      <p>Forpresentpurposes,the choice amongthese
variousexplanationsdoes not muchmatter.The
point is only that paternalism,in the form of
effects on individualchoices, is often
unavoidable. When paternalismseems absent,it is
usually becausethe startingpointappearsso natural
and obvious that its preference-shapingeffects
are invisible to most observers. But those
effects are nonetheless there. Of course it is
usually good not to block choices, and we do not
mean to defend non-libertarian paternalism
here. But in an important respect, the
antipaternalisticposition is incoherent.</p>
      <p>III. Beyondthe Inevitable(but Still Libertarian)</p>
      <p>The inevitabilityof paternalismis most clear
when the plannerhas to choose defaultrules. It
is reasonableto ask whetherthe plannershould
go beyond the inevitable. Take the cafeteria
example discussed above. Putting the fruit
before the dessertsis a fairly mild intervention.A
more intrusive step would be to place the
desserts in anotherlocation altogether,so that
diners have to get up and get a dessert after they
have finished the rest of their meal. This step
raises the transactionscosts of eating dessert,
and accordingto a standardeconomic analysis
the proposal is unattractive:it seems to make
dessert-eatersworse off and no one better off.
But once self-controlcosts are incorporated,we
can see that some diners would prefer this
arrangement,namely, those who would eat a
dessert if it were put in front of them but would
resist temptationif given a little help. To the
extent that the dessert location is not hard to
find, and no choice is forbidden,this approach
meets libertarianmuster.</p>
      <p>In the domain of employee savings, Thaler
andBenartzi(2003) have proposeda methodof
increasing contributions to 401(k) plans that
also meets the libertariantest. Under this plan,
AEAPAPERSAND PROCEEDINGS
called Save More Tomorrow, employees are
invited to sign up for a programin which their
contributionsto the savings plan are increased
annuallywhenever they get a raise. Once
employees join the plan, they stay in until they opt
out or reach the maximum savings rate in the
plan. In the first company to use this plan, the
employees who joined increased their savings
rates from 3.5 percentto 11.6 percentin a little
over two years (three raises). Very few of the
employees who join the plan drop out. This is
successful libertarianpaternalismin action.</p>
      <p>IV. How to Choose:The Toolbox</p>
      <p>of the LibertarianPaternalist</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>How should sensible planners(a categorywe</title>
      <p>mean to include anyone who must design plans
for others, from human-resourcedirectors to
bureaucratsto kings) choose among possible
systems, given that some choice is necessary?
We suggest two approachesto this problem.</p>
      <p>If feasible, a comparison of possible rules
should be done using a form of cost-benefit
analysis.The goal of a cost-benefit studywould
be to measurethe full ramificationsof any
design choice. To illustrate,take the example of
automaticenrollment.Under
automaticenrollment some employees will join the plan who
otherwise would not. Presumably, some are
made better off (especially if there is an
employer match), but some may be made worse
off (e.g., those who are highly
liquidityconstrained).If the issue were just enrollment,
we would guess thatthe gains would exceed the
losses. We base this guess partly on revealed
choices. Most employees do join the plan
eventually, and very few who are
automaticallyenrolled opt out when they figure out what has
happenedto them. We also judge thatthe costs
of having too little saved up for retirementare
typically greaterthanthe costs of having saved
too much.</p>
      <p>In many cases, however, the plannerwill be
unable to make a direct inquiry into welfare,
eitherbecause too little informationis available
or because the costs of doing the analysis are
not warranted.The committed anti-paternalist
might say, in such cases, that people should
simply be permittedto choose as they see fit.
We hope thatwe have said enoughto show why
this response is unhelpful.Whatpeople choose
often depends on the startingpoint, and hence
the startingpoint cannot be selected by asking
whatpeople choose. In these circumstances,the
libertarianpaternalistwould seek
indirectproxies for welfare:methodsthattest whetherone or
anotherapproachis welfare-promotingwithout
relying on unreliable guesswork about that
question. We suggest three possible methods.</p>
      <p>First, the libertarianpaternalistmight select
the approachthat the majoritywould choose if
explicit choices were required and revealed.
Useful though it is, this
market-mimickingapproach raises its own problems. Perhaps the
majority's choices would be insufficiently
informed. Perhaps those choices, in fact, would
not promotethe majority'swelfare.At least as a
presumption,however, it makes sense to follow
those choices, if the planner knows what they
would be. A deeper problem is that the
majority's choices might themselves be a functionof
the startingpoint or the default rule. If so, the
problem of circularity dooms the
marketmimicking approach. But in some cases, at
least, the majorityis likely to go one way or the
otherregardlessof the startingpoint;andto that
extent, the market-mimickingstrategy seems
quite workable.</p>
      <p>Second, the libertarianpaternalistmight
select the approachthat would force people to
make their choices explicit. This approach
might be chosen if the
market-mimickingstrategy fails, eitherbecause of the
circularityproblem or because the planner does not know
which approachwould in fact be chosen by the
majority.We have seen the possibilityof forced
choices in the context of retirementplans; it
would be easy to findotherexamples.Here too,
however, thereis a risk thatthe choices thatare
actually elicited will be inadequatelyinformed
or will not promote welfare. In the case of
retirementplans, for example, forced choices
have been found to produce higher
participation rates than requiring opt-ins, but lower
rates than requiringopt-outs. If it is likely that
automatic enrollment is welfare-promoting,
perhaps automatic enrollment should be
preferred over forced choices. The only
suggestion is that, where the social planneris unsure
how to handle the welfare question, he might
devise a strategythatrequirespeople to choose.</p>
      <p>Third,the libertarianpaternalistmight select
the approachthat minimizesthe numberof
optouts. For example, very few employees opt out
of the 401(k) plan when they are automatically
enrolled,thoughmany opt in underthe standard
enrollmentprocedure.This is an ex post inquiry
into people's preferences,in contrastto the ex
ante approachfavoredby the market-mimicking
strategy.With those numbers,thereis reasonto
thinkthatautomaticenrollmentis better,if only
because morepeople are sufficientlysatisfiedto
leave it in place.</p>
      <p>V. Conclusion</p>
      <p>Our goal here has been to defend libertarian
paternalism, an approach that preserves
freedom of choice but that authorizesboth private
and public institutionsto steer people in
directions thatwill promotetheirwelfare. Some kind
of paternalismis likely whenever such
institutions set out arrangementsthat will prevail
unless people affirmativelychoose otherwise. In
these circumstances,the goal shouldbe to avoid
random, arbitrary,or harmful effects and to
produce a situation that is likely to promote
people's welfare, suitably defined.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Benartzi</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Shlomoand Thaler,
          <source>RichardH. "How Much Is Investor Autonomy Worth?"Journal of Finance</source>
          ,
          <year>August 2002</year>
          ,
          <volume>57</volume>
          (
          <issue>4</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>1593</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1616</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Camerer</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Colin; Issacharoff,Samuel; Loewenstein,
          <string-name>
            <surname>George; O'Donoghue</surname>
            ,Ted and Rabin,
            <given-names>Matthew.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>"Regulation for Conservatives: Behavioral Economics and the Case for Asymmetric Paternalism."Working paper</article-title>
          ,
          <source>CaliforniaInstituteof Technology</source>
          ,
          <year>2001</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,James;Laibson,David;Madrian,BrigitteC. and Metrick,Andrew.
          <article-title>"DefinedContribution Pensions: Plan Rules, ParticipantDecisions, and the Path of Least Resistance,"</article-title>
          in James M. Poterba,ed.,
          <source>Taxpolicy and the economy</source>
          , Vol.
          <volume>16</volume>
          . Cambridge,MA: MIT Press,
          <year>2002</year>
          , pp.
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>113</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>. "BenignPaternalismand Active Decisions: A NaturalExperiment."</surname>
          </string-name>
          Working paper, University of Chicago, GraduateSchool of Business,
          <year>2003a</year>
          . .
          <article-title>"Optimal Defaults." American Economic Review</article-title>
          ,
          <source>May 2003b (Papers and Proceedings)</source>
          ,
          <volume>93</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>180</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Gilovich</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Thomas;Griffin,Dale and Kahneman, Daniel, eds. Heuristics and
          <article-title>biases: The psychology of intuitive judgment</article-title>
          . Cambridge, U.K.: CambridgeUniversity Press,
          <year>2002</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kahneman</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Daniel;Knetsch,Jack L. and Thaler, Richard H.
          <article-title>"The Endowment Effect</article-title>
          ,
          <source>Loss Aversion, and Status Quo Bias." Journal of Economic Perspectives, Winter</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          ,
          <volume>5</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>206</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kahneman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Daniel and Tversky, Amos, eds. Choices, values, and frames. Cambridge, U.K.: CambridgeUniversity Press,
          <year>2000</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Madrian</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Brigitteand Shea,Dennis.
          <article-title>"ThePower of Suggestion:Inertiain 401(k) Participation</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Savings</given-names>
            <surname>Behavior</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <article-title>"QuarterlyJournal of Economics</article-title>
          ,
          <year>November 2001</year>
          ,
          <volume>116</volume>
          (
          <issue>4</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>1149</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>87</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>O'Donoghue</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Ted and Rabin,Matthew.
          <article-title>"Studying Optimal Paternalism, Illustrated by a Model of Sin Taxes</article-title>
          .
          <article-title>" American Economic Review</article-title>
          ,
          <article-title>May 2003 (Papers</article-title>
          and Proceedings),
          <volume>93</volume>
          (
          <issue>2</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Samuelson</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Williamand Zeckhauser,RichardJ.
          <article-title>"StatusQuo Bias in Decision Making."</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Risk and Uncertainty,March</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          ,
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          ), pp.
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Thaler</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,RichardH. and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Benartzi</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,Shlomo.
          <article-title>"Save More Tomorrow:Using BehavioralEconomics to IncreaseEmployee Saving."Journalof Political Economy,2003 (forthcoming</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>