<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>U. Chi. L. Rev.</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Libertarian Paternalism Is Not an Oxymoron</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Richard H. Thaler</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein &amp; Richard H. Thaler, "Libertarian Paternalism Is Not an Oxymoron," 70 University of</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>1159</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2003</volume>
      <fpage>90</fpage>
      <lpage>91</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>companies cannot be liable for failing to inform people about the risks
of smoking because people already have sufficient information,
indeed usually overestimating the risks. If he is right about this latter
point, then one would expect his reforms to increase the amount of
smoking as people learn that smoking is less risky than they had
believed.</p>
      <p>But Viscusi fails to grapple with the public health community's
fundamental concern with smoking: that it is addictive. Many people
start smoking when they are still children, and others who start as
adults do not have adequate information about the dangers of
smoking. They might know that smoking causes a high risk of lung cancer
and other diseases, but they do not understand the power of nicotine
addiction, and they believe that they will quit before they do
significant damage to their bodies. They also have trouble resisting peer
pressure and the glamorous image of smoking fed by highly effective
tobacco advertising. These individuals try to quit later in life, but are
unable to, and high numbers succumb to smoking-related illnesses.</p>
      <p>Viscusi's view about addiction is not clear. On the one hand, he
says that cigarettes are addictive. On the other hand, he stresses that
smoking is a matter of choice. He cites the -0.4 to -0.7 elasticity of
demand for cigarettes as evidence that they are not addictive (pp
17172), but the elasticity just tells us that some people will stop or reduce
smoking when the price rises, not that everyone will, and the evidence
suggests that for a core group even large price increases will not affect
their behavior. The two views can be reconciled with the rational
addiction model, which Viscusi cites.26 This model assumes that when a
person begins to smoke he takes account of the cost of being able to
stop. By contrast to the public health model, which assumes that a
person starts smoking without thinking about addiction, and then finds
himself trapped by the addiction when further information about the
risks persuades him that it is time to stop, the rational addiction model
assumes that a person chooses the whole package of cigarette-related
benefits and afflictions -the pleasure of the smoke, the glamorous
image, the approval of friends, the possibility of addiction, and the
remote but devastating health consequences.</p>
      <p>The rational addiction view has been criticized in ways that go
beyond the scope of this Review.27 It is sufficient, however, to point out
that even if one accepts its behavioral assumptions, it does not have
strong normative implications. Usually, when a person makes a choice</p>
      <p>The Universityof Chicago Law Review
at time 1 that he regrets at time 2, we do not allow him to escape the
consequences of his decision. Otherwise, it would be difficult for
people to commit themselves, and the power to commit oneself is
extremely valuable in a range of social and economic relationships. But
there is a philosophical objection to holding the welfare of the person
at time 2 hostage to the preferences of the person at time 1: There is
no obvious reason for thinking that welfare at time 1 is more
important than welfare at time 2, while it is clear that individuals discount
benefits flowing to their future selves. These concerns are relatively
minor for most transactions, but they loom large when the early
choice has significant negative consequences in the distant future, as is
the case for smoking and the consumption of other dangerous and
addictive drugs.</p>
      <p>Viscusi is more persuasive when he criticizes the regulatory
package established by the MSA, and in particular the high de facto excise
taxes that it establishes.2 High excise taxes are troublesome regardless
of whether one takes Viscusi's choice view, or the public health
community's addiction view. If smoking is a matter of choice, then excise
taxes should be used to deter harms to others; however, these harms
appear to be relatively small, justifying only low excise taxes. If
smoking is a matter of addiction, then excise taxes will deter some people
from smoking but leave unaffected a large group of people who will
pay more for smoking, and carry a larger part of the tax burden than
nonsmokers.29 (In theory, these distributive burdens could be
eliminated by adjusting the income tax but the politics of such adjustments
are complex.) A moderate excise tax might be justified, but at a time
when the drug war is under intense criticism, a prohibitively high tax
or an outright ban hardly seems appropriate.</p>
      <p>Other policy instruments also have moderate value. Educational
efforts, advertising limitations, and regulation of public spaces show
promise but have clear limits0 One problem with these strategies,
which is frequently overlooked, is that their quasi-intended effect of
stigmatizing smoking may do more harm than good. Stigma is an
inefficient way of helping addicts; stigma harms the addicts just like excise
taxes, but unlike excise taxes does not raise revenues. In addition,
selfconscious efforts by authorities to create and reinforce stigma can
28 This is a point made by many other authors. See, for example, Frank J. Chaloupka, et al,
Taxing Tobacco:The Impact of Tobacco Taxes on CigaretteSmoking and OtherTobacco Use, in
Rabin and Sugarman, eds, Regulating Tobacco at 63-464 (cited in note 1) (describing the
disproportionate impact of tobacco excise taxes on low-income smokers). But there are complications,
as noted in this Review.</p>
      <p>29 See id.</p>
      <p>30 For discussions of these proposals, see the essays in Rabin and Sugarman, eds,
Regulating Tobacco (cited in note 1).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Tobacco Regulationor Litigation?</title>
      <p>backfire and make the forbidden activity all the more alluring to
young people and others who regard themselves as nonconformists
not easily cowed by officially endorsed public sentiment.</p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>III. REGULATION BY LITIGATION</title>
        <p>Viscusi sees the MSA as but one element in a class of cases that
reflect a disturbing new trend that he calls "regulation by litigation" (p
217). The vast fees earned by tort lawyers in the Medicaid litigation
have stimulated similar lawsuits against gun manufacturers, the paint
and fast food industries, and HMOs. Viscusi argues that litigation
generates bad regulation that favors lawyers and interest groups, and that
legislation and agency regulation (he does not distinguish the two) are
the more appropriate vehicles for reining in industry, if such reining-in
is needed (p 217). He faults the MSA for its role in encouraging this
new litigation (p 4).</p>
        <p>This claim that there is a special class of troubling "regulation by
litigation" cases" will strike lawyers as odd. Tort law is a form of
regulation, and always has been. Manufacturers know that when they
design products they will be held liable under tort law if they choose an
unreasonably dangerous design. Judicial decisions ex post will often
have the effect of creating regulation-like commands -for instance, do
not design a car that explodes if rear-ended at low speeds-but the
policy here is to give manufacturers an ex ante incentive to invest in
safety. There is nothing new about regulation by litigation, and one
suspects that Viscusi does not understand this basic point.'</p>
        <p>Viscusi argues that regulation is superior to litigation because of
the traditional values of transparency and accountability. Affected
parties have the opportunity to lobby legislators and regulators prior
to the creation of rules. If the public does not like the rules, they can
vote the politicians out of office. Viscusi thinks that the tort system, by
contrast, has been corrupted by well-financed tort lawyers,
pusillanimous judges, and populist juries.</p>
        <p>This view turns traditional public-choice thinking on its head.
If there is any interest group with dominant influence, one would
think it the tobacco industry -rich, highly concentrated, very
sophisticated- and not so much the tort lawyers, who are much more
numerous and varying in their goals and, for all their new wealth, not nearly
as rich. The public health community- another one of Viscusi's betes
31 See W. Kip Viscusi, ed, Regulation through Litigation v (Brookings 2002) (contending
that large-scale lawsuits over tobacco, guns, and other products represent a new genre of
litigation that confront broad policy problems better left to legislatures).</p>
        <p>32 See also Randall Lutter and Elizabeth Mader, LitigatingLead-Based PaintHazards,in
Viscusi, ed, Regulation through Litigation at 125-26 (cited in note 31) (calling the tort system's
normal retroactive determination of liability "Kafkaesque").
noires-is a loose conglomeration of different interests, including
doctors, hospitals, insurance companies, universities, and health advocates.
The fact is that all these groups influence legislative and regulatory
outcomes, transparency and accountability notwithstanding. The
tobacco industry subverted the effort to incorporate a predecessor to
the MSA in federal legislation when the proposed bills went beyond
the restrictions to which the industry had initially agreed. The tort
lawyers persuaded state legislatures to enact statutes that would
facilitate their Medicaid litigation. And the public health community has
influenced countless smoking-related laws and regulations. Indeed, all
the things that Viscusi deplores in the MSA, like the excise taxes and
the advertising restrictions, can be found in countless laws and
regulations that existed long before the MSA was negotiated. "Regulation
by regulation" has produced outcomes every bit as bad from Viscusi's
perspective as those produced by "regulation by litigation.33</p>
        <p>By contrast, the tort system has long been thought to be relatively
immune to public choice pressures. Although this view has come
under increasing scrutiny, the evidence provides little support for
Viscusi's negative view about tobacco litigation. If Viscusi is right about
the weakness of the smokers' cases, the tort system has performed
admirably until recently, resulting in few awards against the tobacco
industry. Although the tort lawyers won some important early
victories in the Medicaid litigation, they also lost some important cases, and
never obtained a final judgment against a tobacco company. Viscusi's
own theory-that the cartel arrangement benefited the tobacco
industry and hurt smokers-suggests that the MSA can't be blamed on the
tort system. On Viscusi's theory, the tobacco industry would have
agreed to the MSA, or some similar version of it, even if the industry
had thought it would do well in court.</p>
        <p>One of Viscusi's strongest grounds for complaint is the
extraordinary legal fees won by the tort lawyers, but the blame for these fees
lies on the shoulders of the states and the tobacco industry. When the
tort lawyers offered to represent states in the Medicaid litigation,
many states turned them down and relied on the staffs of their
attorneys general. Other states preferred to use outside counsel and agreed
to pay a percentage of any damages recovered, or what in other
contexts would be called a normal contingency fee arrangement. The
MSA contained a vague "reasonable" fees provision, to be determined
by arbitration, and the arbitrators used the contracts between the
states and the lawyers as a guide. Because the states won hundreds of
billions of dollars, the contingency percentages yielded very high
dol33 For a detailed discussion of the politics of tobacco litigation and legislation, see Martha
A. Derthick, Up in Smoke (Congressional Quarterly 2002).
lar values. The political outcry was muted because under the MSA the
tobacco industry had to pay the fees, though of course the payment
could only come from money that would otherwise be available for
the states. However, the outcry was still significant enough to create
resistance in some legislatures and stimulate concessions by some
tobacco lawyers. So if the fees were unreasonable, the responsibility can
be traced to the voluntary arrangements between attorneys general,
legislatures, tobacco executives, and the tort lawyers. Judges, the
guardians of the tort system, could not be expected to interfere with
these arrangements. Nor could juries.</p>
        <p>The significant role of state legislatures and attorneys general in
the Medicaid litigation suggests that this litigation should not be the
prime exhibit for the case against "regulation by litigation," which is
probably best used to refer to class actions involving private
individuals, not governments, as the plaintiffs. Because the states were the
plaintiffs in the Medicaid litigation, it is hard to draw a clean
distinction between a virtuous political process and a corrupt legal process.
Viscusi complains that the de facto excise taxes in the MSA are
perverse because they are regressive, and as a result of them states
benefit when tobacco sales rise. States' reluctance to finance antismoking
advertisements with their tobacco money, as they had promised, is
taken as evidence that they regard tobacco sales as a money pump.
But if legislatures are politically responsible, why did they consent to
the excise taxes in the first place? And if they were presented with
them as a fait accompli,why didn't the legislatures fix the regressive
impact by adjusting income taxes, and why would they put revenues
over their concern for public health? No one argues that the excise tax
on gasoline should be repealed because it gives the government an
incentive to encourage people to drive.</p>
        <p>What is most noteworthy about the tobacco litigation is not its
exposure of a new form of ex post regulation; the tort system is far
older than the regulatory system that Viscusi champions. What is
noteworthy is the significant role in the litigation of a group of
wealthy and successful tort lawyer-entrepreneurs. Viscusi thinks that
these people are bad guys (pp 5,53-54, 134,219-20), and perhaps they
are, but like the tobacco industry executives their sin was their
exploitation of a permissive legal environment in order to make money. So
that this legal environment may be changed, understanding the
emergence and incentives of the tort lawyers is an important task, for which
the crude opposition between litigation and regulation is not helpful.
There are smoke-filled rooms in state capitols, just as there are in the
pricey hotels where the MSA was hammered out.</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 1163 2003</p>
        <p>HeinOnline -- 70 U. Chi. L. Rev. 1164 2003</p>
        <sec id="sec-2-1-1">
          <title>EricA. Posner&amp;</title>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Adrian Vermeule 1331</title>
      <p>COMMENTS
The Illegitimacy of Protective Jurisdiction
over Foreign Affairs ..........................................</p>
      <p>Andrew C. Baak 1487
The Philosophical Dimensions of the</p>
      <p>Doctrine of Unconscionability ........................... Philip Bridwell 1513
State Income Taxation of Out-of-State</p>
      <p>Trademark Holding Companies ....................... Tun-Jen Chiang 1533
Viewpoint Restrictions and</p>
      <p>School-Sponsored Student Speech:</p>
      <p>Avenues for Heightened Protection .............. Samuel P Jordan 1555
An Antitrust Challenge to the</p>
      <p>NCAA Transfer Rules ..................................... Sarah M. Konsky 1581
The Power to Declare</p>
      <p>Peace Unilaterally ..............................................</p>
      <p>Cooperative Federalism and</p>
      <p>Constructive Waiver of
State Sovereign Immunity .................................</p>
      <p>Mark W M osier 1609</p>
      <p>Sarah C. Rispin 1639</p>
      <p>REVIEW
The Many Meanings of Separation</p>
      <p>Separationof Church and State
Philip Hamburger ............................................</p>
      <p>DouglasLaycock 1667
Volume 70
© 2003 by The University of Chicago
Libertarian Paternalism Is Not an Oxymoron</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunsteint</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>RichardH. Thalertt</title>
        <p>The idea of libertarianpaternalismmight seem to be an oxymoron, but it is both possible
and desirablefor private and public institutions to influence behavior while also
respectingfreedom of choice. Often people's preferences are unclearand ill-formed,and their choices will
inevitably be influenced by default rules,framing effects and startingpoints.In these circumstances,a
form of paternalismcannotbe avoided. Equipped with an understandingof behavioralfindings of
bounded rationalityand bounded self-control,libertarianpaternalistsshould attempt to steer
people's choices in welfare-promotingdirections without eliminatingfreedom of choice. It is
alsopossible to show how a libertarianpaternalistmight select among the possible options and to assess
how much choice to offer.Examples are given from many areas,including savings behavior,labor
law, and consumerprotection.</p>
        <p>INTRODUCrION
Consider two studies of savings behavior:
o Hoping to increase savings by workers, several employers have
adopted a simple strategy. Instead of asking workers to elect to
t Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor, Law School and Department of
Political Science, The University of Chicago.</p>
        <p>tt Robert P. Gwinn Professor of Economics and Behavioral Science, The University of
Chicago Graduate School of Business.</p>
        <p>We are grateful to Gary Becker, Bryan Caplan, Richard Epstein, Carolyn Frantz, Daniel
Gilbert, Robert Hahn, J.B. Heaton, Christine Jolls, Howard Kunrenther, Owen Lamont, Brigitte
Madrian, Jane Mansbridge, Eric Posner, Richard Posner, Matthew Rabin, and David Strauss for
valuable comments on a previous draft. We are also grateful to Caryn Campbell for excellent
research assistance and to participants in discussions at the John F Kennedy School of
Government at Harvard University, the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, and a
workin-progress lunch at the University of Chicago Law School. Finally, thanks to discussants on a
panel in which an early version of this Article was presented at the 2003 meetings of the
American Economic Association.</p>
        <p>1159
participate in a 401(k) plan, workers will be assumed to want
to participate in such a plan, and hence they will be enrolled
automatically unless they specifically choose otherwise. This
simple change in the default rule has produced dramatic
increases in enrollment.'
* Rather than changing the default rule, some employers have
provided their employees with a novel option: Allocate a
portion offuture wage increasesto savings. Employees who choose
this plan are free to opt out at any time. A large number of
employees have agreed to try the plan, and only a few have
opted out. The result has been significant increases in savings
rates</p>
        <p>Libertarians embrace freedom of choice, and so they deplore
paternalism.' Paternalists are thought to be skeptical of unfettered
freedom of choice and to deplore libertarianism.4 According to the
conventional wisdom, libertarians cannot possibly embrace paternalism,
and paternalists abhor libertarianism. The idea of libertarian
paternalism seems to be a contradiction in terms.</p>
        <p>Generalizing from the two studies just described, we intend to
unsettle the conventional wisdom here. We propose a form of
paternalism, libertarian in spirit, that should be acceptable to those who are
firmly committed to freedom of choice on grounds of either autonomy
or welfare.' Indeed, we urge that libertarian paternalism provides a
basis for both understanding and rethinking a number of areas of
contemporary law, including those aspects that deal with worker welfare,
consumer protection, and the family.6 In the process of defending
these claims, we intend to make some objections to widely held beliefs
about both freedom of choice and paternalism.7 Our emphasis is on
the fact that in many domains, people lack clear, stable, or
wellordered preferences. What they choose is strongly influenced by
details of the context in which they make their choice, for example
default rules, framing effects (that is, the wording of possible options),
and starting points. These contextual influences render the very
meaning of the term "preferences" unclear.</p>
        <p>Consider the question whether to undergo a risky medical
procedure. When people are told, "Of those who undergo this procedure, 90
percent are still alive after five years," they are far more likely to
agree to the procedure than when they are told, "Of those who
undergo this procedure, 10 percent are dead after five years." What,
then, are the patient's "preferences" with respect to this procedure?
Repeated experiences with such problems might be expected to
eliminate this framing effect, but doctors too are vulnerable to it.' Or
return to the question of savings for retirement. It is now clear that if
an employer requires employees to make an affirmative election in
favor of savings, with the default rule devoting 100 percent of wages to
current income, the level of savings will be far lower than if the
employer adopts an automatic enrollment program from which
employees are freely permitted to opt out.' Can workers then be said to have
well-defined preferences about how much to save? This simple
example can be extended to many situations involving the behavior of
workers and consumers.</p>
        <p>As the savings problem illustrates, the design features of both
legal and organizational rules have surprisingly powerful influences on
people's choices. We urge that such rules should be chosen with the
explicit goal of improving the welfare of the people affected by them.
The libertarian aspect of our strategies lies in the straightforward
insistence that, in general, people should be free to opt out of specified
arrangements if they choose to do so. To borrow a phrase, libertarian
paternalists urge that people should be "free to choose."" Hence we
do not aim to defend any approach that blocks individual choices.</p>
        <p>The paternalistic aspect consists in the claim that it is legitimate
for private and public institutions to attempt to influence people's
behavior even when third-party effects are absent. In other words, we
argue for self-conscious efforts, by private and public institutions, to
steer people's choices in directions that will improve the choosers'
own welfare. In our understanding, a policy therefore counts as
"paternalistic" if it attempts to influence the choices of affected parties in
a way that will make choosers better off.'2 Drawing on some
wellestablished findings in behavioral economics and cognitive
psychology, we emphasize the possibility that in some cases individuals make
inferior decisions in terms of their own welfare-decisions that they
would change if they had complete information, unlimited cognitive
abilities, and no lack of self-control." In addition, the notion of
libertarian paternalism can be complemented by that of
libertarianbenevolence, by which plan design features such as default rules, framing
effects, and starting points are enlisted in the interest of vulnerable third
parties. We shall devote some discussion to this possibility.</p>
        <p>Libertarian paternalism is a relatively weak and nonintrusive
type of paternalism, because choices are not blocked or fenced off. In
its most cautious forms, libertarian paternalism imposes trivial costs
on those who seek to depart from the planner's preferred option. But
the approach we recommend nonetheless counts as paternalistic,
because private and public planners" are not trying to track people's
anticipated choices, but are self-consciously attempting to move people
in welfare-promoting directions. Some libertarians are likely to have
little or no trouble with our endorsement of paternalism for private
institutions; their chief objection is to paternalistic law and
government. But as we shall show, the same points that support
welfarepromoting private paternalism apply to government as well. It follows
standing of libertarianism, one that attempts to minimize influences on free choice, or to
maximize unfettered liberty of choice. We suggest below that influences on freedom of choice are
often impossible to avoid. We also offer reasons to believe that more choices are not always better
than fewer. A policy of requiring active choices, we shall show, does promote a form of choice,
but it has problems of its own. We hope not to have any real quarrels with libertarians here,
simply because our approach allows people to opt out of any specified arrangements.</p>
        <p>12 For a similar definition, see Donald VanDeVeer, PaternalisticIntervention: The Moral
Bounds on Benevolence 22 (Princeton 1986).</p>
        <p>13 Bounded rationality and bounded self-control are described in Christine Jolls, Cass R.
Sunstein, and Richard Thaler, A BehavioralApproach to Law and Economics, 50 Stan L Rev
1471, 1477-79 (1998).</p>
        <p>14 When we use the word "planner" in this Article, we mean anyone who faces the job of
designing institutional features such as rules, procedures, information packages, and the like. A
large firm will typically have many employees who are serving as "planners" in this sense, from
the human resources manager who chooses the set of health insurance options to the CEO who
decides whether to pay the match in the 401(k) plan in shares of company stock. For most of our
examples, planners are not government officials, though the arguments apply to this class of
planners as well.
that one of our principal targets is the dogmatic anti-paternalism of
numerous analysts of law, including many economists and
economically oriented lawyers." We believe that this dogmatism is 6based on a
combination of a false assumption and two misconceptions.</p>
        <p>The false assumption is that almost all people, almost all of the
time, make choices that are in their best interest or at the very least
are better, by their own lights, than the choices that would be made by
third parties. This claim is either tautological, and therefore
uninteresting, or testable. We claim that it is testable and false, indeed obviously
false. In fact, we do not think that anyone believes it on reflection.
Suppose that a chess novice were to play against an experienced
player. Predictably the novice would lose precisely because he made
inferior choices-choices that could easily be improved by some
helpful hints. More generally, how well people choose is an empirical
question, one whose answer is likely to vary across domains." As a first
approximation, it seems reasonable to say that people make better
choices in contexts in which they have experience and good
information (say, choosing ice cream flavors) than in contexts in which they
are inexperienced and poorly informed (say, choosing among medical
treatments or investment options). So long as people are not choosing
perfectly, it is at least possible that some policy could make them
better off by improving their decisions.
[B]y explicitly addressing when and how people do and do not pursue their own best
interests, economists will be better able to contribute to policy debates.To contribute to debates
over regulating private financial decisions, we must study whether financial decisions are
based on fallacious statistical reasoning and whether self-control problems lead people to
borrow too heavily; to contribute to debates over teenage smoking, we must study whether
teenagers become smokers against their long-run best interest. Economists will and should
be ignored if we continue to insist that it is axiomatic that constantly trading stocks or
accumulating consumer debt or becoming a heroin addict must be optimal for the people
doing these things merely because they have chosen to do it.</p>
        <p>17 In some areas, of course, it will be difficult to reach uncontroversial conclusions on the
basis of empirical study alone, because contested judgments of value are in the background. Do
people choose well if they choose to marry young, or do they choose better if they cohabit for a
long time before marrying? Do young, unmarried women choose well if they choose abortion?
Empirical issues are highly relevant here, but they will hardly resolve all social disputes on these
questions. We are not attempting to say anything controversial about welfare, or to take sides in
reasonable disputes about how to understand that term. For discussion of these normative issues,
see Amartya Sen, Development as Freedom 74-76 (Knopf 1999) (maintaining that welfare should
be seen in terms of the substantive freedoms of people to choose a life that they have reason to
value); Daniel Kahneman, Ed Diener, and Norbert Schwarz, Preface, in Daniel Kahneman, Ed
Diener, and Norbert Schwarz, eds, Well-Being: The Foundations of Hedonic Psychology ix, xi-xii
(Russell Sage 1999) (urging a view of human welfare that extends beyond traditional economic
indicators to include "desirable goods such as love, mental challenge, and stress").</p>
        <p>The first misconception is that there are viable alternatives to
paternalism. In many situations, some organization or agent must make a
choice that will affect the behavior of some other people. There is, in
those situations, no alternative to a kind of paternalism-at least in
the form of an intervention that affects what people choose. We are
emphasizing, then, the possibility that people's preferences, in certain
domains and across a certain range, are influenced by the choices
made by planners.' The point applies to both private and public actors,
and hence to those who design legal rules as well as to those who
serve consumers. As a simple example, consider the cafeteria at some
organization. The cafeteria must make a multitude of decisions,
including which foods to serve, which ingredients to use, and in what order
to arrange the choices. Suppose that the director of the cafeteria
notices that customers have a tendency to choose more of the items that
are presented earlier in the line. How should the director decide in
what order to present the items? To simplify, consider some
alternative strategies that the director might adopt in deciding which items to
place early in the line:
1. She could make choices that she thinks would make the
customers best off, all things considered.
2. She could make choices at random.
3. She could choose those items that she thinks would make the
customers as obese as possible.
4. She could give customers what she thinks they would choose
on their own.</p>
        <p>Option 1 appears to be paternalistic, but would anyone advocate
options 2 or 3? Option 4 is what many anti-paternalists would favor,
but it is much harder to implement than it might seem. Across a
certain domain of possibilities, consumers will often lack well-formed
preferences, in the sense of preferences that are firmly held and
preexist the director's own choices about how to order the relevant items. If
the arrangement of the alternatives has a significant effect on the
selections the customers make, then their true "preferences" do not
formally exist.</p>
        <p>18 For claims to this effect, see Russell Korobkin, The Status Quo Bias and Contract
Default Rules, 83 Cornell L Rev 608,675 (1998) (asserting that "the preference exogeneity
assumption, implicit in all law-and-economics theories of efficient contract default rule selection, is
probably false"); Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law,22 J Leg Stud
217, 224 (1993) (arguing that the demand for environmental regulation is affected by the initial
allocation of rights by government planners). Important qualifications come from Robert C.
Ellickson, Orderwithout Law: How Neighbors Settle Disputes (Harvard 1991) (discussing settings
in which people organize their affairs without reference to law). But even with those
qualifications, there is no objection to libertarian paternalism; in the contexts explored by Ellickson, the
default rule is irrelevant, not harmful.</p>
        <p>Of course, market pressures will impose a discipline on the
selfinterested choices of those cafeteria directors who face competition.
To that extent, those directors must indeed provide people with
options they are willing to buy. A cafeteria that faces competition and
offers healthy but terrible-tasting food is unlikely to do well.
Marketoriented libertarians might urge that the cafeteria should attempt to
maximize profits, selecting menus in a way that will increase net
revenues. But profit maximization is not the appropriate goal for cafeterias
granted a degree of monopoly power-for example, those in schools,
dormitories, or some companies. Furthermore, even those cafeterias
that face competition will find that some of the time, market success
will come not from tracking people's ex ante preferences, but from
providing goods and services that turn out, in practice, to promote
their welfare, all things considered. Consumers might be surprised by
what they end up liking; indeed, their preferences might change as a
result of consumption." And in some cases, the discipline imposed by
market pressures will nonetheless allow the director a great deal of
room to maneuver, because people's preferences are not well-formed
across the relevant domains.</p>
        <p>While some libertarians will happily accept this point for private
institutions, they will object to government efforts to influence choice
in the name of welfare. Skepticism about government might be based
on the fact that governments are disciplined less or perhaps not at all
by market pressures. Or such skepticism might be based on the fear
that parochial interests will drive government planners in their own
preferred directions (the public choice problem).2' We agree that for
government, the risks of mistake and overreaching are real and
sometimes serious. But governments, no less than cafeterias (which
governments frequently run), have to provide starting points of one or
another kind; this is not avoidable. As we shall emphasize, they do so
every day through the rules of contract and tort, in a way that
inevitably affects some preferences and choices.2' In this respect, the
antipaternalist position is unhelpful-a literal nonstarter.</p>
        <p>The second misconception is that paternalism always involves
coercion. As the cafeteria example illustrates, the choice of the order in
which to present food items does not coerce anyone to do anything,
yet one might prefer some orders to others on grounds that are
paternalistic in the sense that we use the term. Would anyone object to
putting the fruit and salad before the desserts at an elementary school
cafeteria if the result were to increase the consumption ratio of apples
to Twinkies? Is this question fundamentally different if the customers
are adults? Since no coercion is involved, we think that some types of
paternalism should be acceptable to even the most ardent libertarian.
In the important domain of savings behavior, we shall offer a number
of illustrations. To those anti-libertarians who are suspicious of
freedom of choice and would prefer to embrace welfare instead, we urge
that it is often possible for paternalistic planners to make common
cause with their libertarian adversaries by adopting policies that
promise to promote welfare but that also make room for freedom of
choice. To confident planners, we suggest that the risks of confused or
ill-motivated plans are reduced if people are given the opportunity to
reject the planner's preferred solutions.</p>
        <p>The thrust of our argument is that the term "paternalistic" should
not be considered pejorative, just descriptive. Once it is understood
that some organizational decisions are inevitable, that a form of
paternalism cannot be avoided, and that the alternatives to paternalism
(such as choosing options to make people worse off) are unattractive,
we can abandon the less interesting question of whether to be
paternalistic or not, and turn to the more constructive question of how to
choose among the possible choice-influencing options. To this end we
make two general suggestions. First, programs should be designed
using a type of welfare analysis, one in which a serious attempt is made
to measure the costs and benefits of outcomes (rather than relying on
estimates of willingness to pay). Choosers should be given more
choices if the welfare benefits exceed the welfare costs. Second, some
results from the psychology of decisionmaking should be used to
provide ex ante guidelines to support reasonable judgments about when
consumers and workers will gain most by increasing options. We argue
that those who are generally inclined to oppose paternalism should
consider these suggestions uncontroversial.</p>
        <p>The remainder of this Article is organized as follows. In Part I, we
briefly support the claim that people's choices might not promote
their own welfare. Part II, in some ways the conceptual heart of the
Article, asks whether a form of paternalism is inevitable. We suggest
that because of the likely effects of default rules, framing effects, and
starting points on choices and preferences, paternalism, at least in a
weak sense, is impossible to avoid. To be sure, planners can try to
avoid paternalism by requiring people to make active choices, but
sometimes people will resist any such requirement (which is along one
dimension paternalistic too, simply because people sometimes do not
want to choose). Part III investigates how a libertarian paternalist
1.167
might select among the major options, including minimal paternalism,
required active choices, procedural constraints, and substantive
constraints. Part IV explores a large question: How much choice should
be offered? We identify a set of questions that must be answered in
order to know whether people's welfare is likely to be promoted or
undermined by a large option set. Part V explores objections.</p>
        <p>I. THE RATIONALITY OF CHOICES</p>
        <p>The presumption that individual choices should be respected is
usually based on the claim that people do an excellent job of making
choices, or at least that they do a far better job than third parties could
possibly do.22 As far as we can tell, there is little empirical support for
this claim, at least if it is offered in this general form. Consider the
issue of obesity. Rates of obesity in the United States are now
approaching 20 percent, and over 60 percent of Americans are
considered either obese or overweight." There is overwhelming evidence
that obesity causes serious health risks, frequently leading to
premature death.24 It is quite fantastic to suggest that everyone is choosing
22 It is usually, but not always, based on this claim. Some of the standard arguments against
paternalism rest not on consequences but on autonomy-on a belief that people are entitled to
make their own choices even if they err. Thus John Stuart Mill, On Liberty (1859), reprinted in
Utilitarianism,On Liberty, Considerationson Representative Government 69 (Dent 1972) (H.B.
Acton, ed), is a mix of autonomy-based and consequentialist claims. Our principal concern here
is with welfare rnd consequences, though as we suggest below, freedom of choice is sometimes
an ingredient in welfare. We do not disagree with the view that autonomy has claims of its own,
but we believe that it would be fanatical, in the settings that we discuss, to treat autonomy, in the
form of freedom of choice, as a kind of trump not to be overridden on consequentialist grounds.
In any case, the autonomy argument is undermined by the fact, discussed in Part I, that
sometimes preferences and choices are a function of given arrangements. Most importantly, we think
that respect for autonomy is adequately accommodated by the libertarian aspect of libertarian
paternalism, as discussed below.</p>
        <p>We note as well that the complex relationship among preferences, choices, and autonomy is a
large theme in the liberal tradition. See Don Herzog, Happy Slaves: A Critiqueof Consent
Theory 229 (Chicago 1989) (challenging consent theory on the ground that some individuals may not
really be capable of choice, or that the preexisting social roles people occupy do not provide
them with real choice); Jon Elster, Sour Grapes:Studies in the Subversion of Rationality 109
(Cambridge 1983) (discussing adaptation of preferences to existing opportunities). Sometimes it
is emphasized that preferences and choices are a product of unjust background conditions,
jeopardizing autonomy, and that when choices are a product of background injustice, respect for
those choices may not promote autonomy. See Amartya Sen, Commodities and Capabilities
(North-Holland 1985). Our discussion does not engage these issues, but there is a clear
connection between such arguments and claims about "adaptive preferences," see Elster, Sour Grapes
at 109-10, and our emphasis on status quo bias and the endowment effect in Part II.C.</p>
        <p>23 See Center for Disease Control data, online at http://www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/dnpa/
obesity/trend/prev-char.htm (visited May 10, 2003). This represents a 61 percent increase in
obesity between 1991 and 2000; 38.8 million Americans qualify as obese. See id. See also Ali H.
Mokdad, et al, The Continuing Epidemics of Obesity and Diabetes in the United States, 286
JAMA 1195 (2001).</p>
        <p>24 See, for example, Eugenia E. Calle, et al, Body-Mass Index and Mortality in a Prospective
Cohort of US. Adults, 341 New Eng J Med 1097 (1999) (discussing increased risk of death from
the optimal diet, or a diet that is preferable to what might be
produced with third-party guidance. Of course, rational people care about
the taste of food, not simply about health, and we do not claim that
everyone who is overweight is necessarily failing to act rationally. It is
the strong claim that all or almost all Americans are choosing their
diet optimally that we reject as untenable. What is true for diets is true
as well for much other risk-related behavior, including smoking and
drinking, which produce over 500,000 premature deaths each year." In
these circumstances, people's choices cannot reasonably be thought, in
all domains, to be the best means of promoting their well-being.
Indeed, many smokers, drinkers, and overeaters are willing to pay for
third parties to help them choose better consumption sets.</p>
        <p>On a more scientific level, research by psychologists and
economists over the past three decades has raised questions about the
rationality of many judgments and decisions that individuals make.
People fail to make forecasts that are consistent with Bayes's rule," use
heuristics that can lead them to make systematic blunders,27 exhibit
preference reversals (that is, they prefer A to B and B to A)," suffer
from problems of self-control, " and make different choices depending
on the framing of the problem.' It is possible to raise questions about
all causes among the obese). See also National Institute of Diabetes &amp; Digestive &amp; Kidney
Diseases, Understanding Adult Obesity, NIH Pub No 01-3680 (Oct 2001), online at
http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health/nutrit/pubs/unders.htm#Healthrisks (visited May 10, 2003)
(noting links between obesity and cancer, diabetes, heart disease, high blood pressure, and stroke).</p>
        <p>
          25 See Cass R. Sunstein, Risk and Reason: Safety, Law, and the Environment 8-9
(Cambridge 2002), relying on J. Michael McGinnis and William H. Foege, Actual Causes of Death in
the United States, 270 JAMA 2207 (1993). For an interesting discussion, see Jonathan Gruber,
Smoking's 'Internalities,' 25 Regulation 52, 54-55 (Winter 200
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">2/2003</xref>
          ) (finding a disconnect
between smokers' short-term desire for self-gratification and their long-term desire for good
health, and suggesting that cigarette taxation can help smokers exercise the self-control needed
to act on behalf of their long-term interests).
        </p>
        <p>26 See David M. Grether, Bayes Rule as a Descriptive Model: The Representativeness
Heuristic, 95 Q J Econ 537 (1980). Bayes's rule explains how to change existing beliefs as to the
probability of a particular hypothesis in the light of new evidence. See Jonathan Baron, Thinking
and Deciding 109-15 (Cambridge 3d ed 2000) (giving a mathematical explanation and examples
of the rule's application).</p>
        <p>27 See, for example, Daniel Kahneman and Shane Frederick, Representativeness Revisited:
Attribute Substitution in Intuitive Judgment, in Thomas Gilovich, Dale Griffin, and Daniel
Kahneman, eds, Heuristics and Biases: The Psychology of Intuitive Judgment 49,53 (Cambridge 2002);
Amos Tversky and Daniel Kahneman, Judgment under Uncertainty: Heuristics and Biases, 185
Science 1124 (1974); Amos Tversky and Daniel Kahneman, Availability: A Heuristic for Judging
Frequency and Probability, 5 Cognitive Psych 207 (1973).</p>
        <p>28 See Richard H. Thaler, The Winner's Curse: Paradoxes and Anomalies of Economic Life
79-91 (Free Press 1992). In the legal context, see Cass R. Sunstein, et al, Predictably Incoherent
Judgments, 54 Stan L Rev 1153 (2002).</p>
        <p>29 See Shane Frederick, George Loewenstein, and Ted O'Donoghue, Time Discounting and
Time Preference: A Critical Review, 40 J Econ Lit 351,367-68 (2002).</p>
        <p>30 See Colin F. Camerer, Prospect Theory in the Wild: Evidence from the Field, in Daniel
Kahneman and Amos Tversky, eds, Choices, Values, and Frames 288, 294-95 (Cambridge 2000);
Eric J.Johnson, et al, Framing, Probability Distortions, and Insurance Decisions, in id at 224,238.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>LibertarianPaternalism</title>
        <p>some of these findings and to think that people may do a better job of
choosing in the real world than they do in the laboratory." But studies
of actual choices reveal many of the same problems, even when the
stakes are high."</p>
        <p>We do not intend to outline all of the relevant evidence here, but
consider an illustration from the domain of savings behavior. Benartzi
and Thaler have investigated how much investors like the portfolios
they have selected in their defined contribution savings plans."
Employees volunteered to share their portfolio choices with the
investigators by bringing a copy of their most recent statement to the lab. They
were then shown the probability distributions of expected retirement
income for three investment portfolios simply labeled A, B, and C.
Unbeknownst to the subjects, the three portfolios were their own and
portfolios mimicking the average and median choices of their fellow
employees. The distributions of expected returns were computed using
the software of Financial Engines, the financial information company
founded by William Sharpe. On average, the subjects rated the
average portfolio equally with their own portfolio, and judged the median
portfolio to be significantly more attractive than their own. Indeed,
only 20 percent of the subjects preferred their own portfolio to the
Note also the emerging literature on people's inability to predict their own emotional reactions
to events, a literature that might well bear on the uses of libertarian paternalism. See Timothy D.
Wilson and Daniel T.Gilbert, Affective Forecasting,35 Advances in Experimental Soc Psych 345
(2003).</p>
        <p>31 For some evidence in favor of consumer sovereignty, see Joel Waldfogel, Does Consumer
Irrationality Trump Consumer Sovereignty?: Evidence from Gifts and Own Purchases (Feb
2003), online at http://papers.ssrn.com/abstractid=337261 (visited May 10, 2003). Waldfogel finds
that people value their own purchases more highly than they value gifts from third parties-a
finding that, in his view, provides support for the idea that consumers are the best judges of what
goods will promote their welfare. We do not doubt the finding. Note, however, that Waldfogel is
studying the context of ordinary consumer purchases, in which people are in an especially good
position to know what they like. We are focusing on less familiar situations, which present special
puzzles.</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>
          For evidence that heuristics and biases operate in the real world, even when dollars are
involved, see Werner F.M. De Bondt and Richard H. Thaler, Do Security Analysts Overreact?,80
Am Econ Rev 52 (1990) (demonstrating that security analysts overreact to market data and
produce forecasts that are either too optimistic or too pessimistic); Robert J. Shiller,
IrrationalExuberance 135-47 (Princeton 2000) (discussing anchoring and overconfidence in market behavior);
Colin F. Camerer and Robin M. Hogarth, The Effects of FinancialIncentives in Experiments:A
Review and Capital-Labor-ProductionFramework, 19 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty 7 (1999) (finding
that financial incentives have never eliminated anomalies or persistent irrationalities). See also
Colin F. Camerer, BehavioralGame Theory: Experiments in Strategic Interaction 60-6
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">2
(Princeton 2003</xref>
          ) (finding little effect from increased stakes in ultimatum games designed to test the
hypothesis that people are self-interested, and adding, "If I had a dollar for every time an
economist claimed that raising the stakes would drive ultimatum behavior toward self-interest, I'd
have a private jet on standby all day").
        </p>
        <p>33 See Shlomo Benartzi and Richard H. Thaler, How Much Is Investor Autonomy Worth?,
57 J Fin 1593 (2002).</p>
        <p>34 Id at 1598.
think about it and did not lose the enrollment form, then by choosing
automatic enrollment, they are acting paternalistically by our
definition of the term. They are not attempting to protect against harms to
third parties, but to steer employees' choices in directions that will, in
the view of employers, promote employees' welfare. Since no one is
forced to do anything, we think that this steering should be considered
unobjectionable even to committed libertarians. The employer must
choose some set of rules, and either plan affects employees' choices.
No law of nature says that in the absence of an affirmative election by
employees, 0 percent of earnings will go into a retirement plan.
Because both plans alter choices, neither one can be said, more than the
other, to count as a form of objectionable meddling.</p>
        <p>2. Skeptics.</p>
        <p>Skeptical readers, insistent on freedom of choice, might be
tempted to think that there is a way out of this dilemma. Employers
could avoid choosing a default if they requiredemployees to make an
active choice, either in or out. Call this option requiredactive choosing.
Undoubtedly required active choosing is attractive in some settings,
but a little thought reveals that this is not at all a way out of the
dilemma. On the contrary, required active choosing is simply another
option among many that the employer can elect. In fact the very
requirement that employees make a choice has a strong paternalistic
element. Some employees may not want to have to make a choice
(and might make a second-order choice not to have to do so). Why
should employers force them to choose?</p>
        <p>Required active choosing honors freedom of choice in a certain
respect; but it does not appeal to those who would choose not to
choose, and indeed it will seem irritating and perhaps unacceptably
coercive by their lights. In some circumstances, required choosing will
not even be feasible." In any case, an empirical question remains:
What is the effect of forced choosing? Choi, et al, find that required
active choosing increases enrollments relative to the opt-in rule,
though not by as much as automatic enrollment (opt-out).' Our
dis47 Consider the cafeteria example: Any menu has to predate choosing. The same is true in
any context, such as social security privatization, in which planners must provide a menu of
options. Perhaps it will be responded that planners might ask choosers to select "any option at all,"
but this is unlikely to be feasible.</p>
        <p>48 Compare Choi, et al, Defined Contribution Pensions at 86 (cited in note 1) (noting that
78 percent of employees offered enrollment in a program committing to savings from future
raises accepted, and 62 percent accepted and stayed in through three pay raises), with id at 77
(showing enrollment rates in opt-out savings plans at three companies six months after hire at
93.4 percent, 85.9 percent, and 96.0 percent).
cussion in Part III below offers some suggestions about the
circumstances in which it makes most sense to force people to choose.</p>
        <p>Other skeptics might think that employers should avoid
paternalism by doing what most employees would want employers to do. On
this approach, a default rule can successfully avoid paternalism if it
tracks employees' preferences. Sometimes this is a plausible solution.
But what if many or most employees do not have stable or
wellformed preferences, and what if employee choices are inevitably a
product of the default rule? In such cases, it is meaningless to ask what
most employees would do. The choices employees will make depend
on the way the employer frames those choices. Employee
"preferences," as such, do not exist in those circumstances.</p>
        <p>We think that savings is a good example of a domain in which
preferences are likely to be ill-defined. Few households have either
the knowledge or inclination to calculate their optimal life-cycle
savings rate, and even if they were to make such a calculation, its results
would be highly dependent on assumptions about rates of return and
life expectancies. In light of this, actual behavior is highly sensitive to
plan design features.</p>
        <p>Government</p>
        <p>Some enthusiasts for free choice might be willing to acknowledge
these points and hence to accept private efforts to steer people's
choices in what seem to be the right directions. Market pressures, and
the frequently wide range of possible options, might be thought to
impose sufficient protection against objectionable steering. But our
emphasis has been on the inevitability of paternalism, and on this count,
the same points apply to some choices made by governments in
establishing legal rules.</p>
        <p>1. Default rules.</p>
        <p>Default rules of some kind are inevitable, and much of the time
those rules will affect preferences and choices." In the neglected words
of a classic article:
[A] minimum of state intervention is always necessary.... When
a loss is left where it falls in an auto accident, it is not because
God so ordained it. Rather it is because the state has granted the
injurer an entitlement to be free of liability and will intervene to
49 See Cass R. Sunstein, Switching the Default Rule, 77 NYU L Rev 106 (2002) (showing
that employees sometimes value certain rights simply because they have been granted such
rights in the first instance); Korobkin, 83 Cornell L Rev 608 (cited in note 18) (arguing that
evidence of status quo bias belies the standard law-and-economics assumption that preferences are
exogenous to the default rule).
prevent the victim's friendSs,• i5f0 they are stronger, from taking
compensation from the injurer.</p>
        <p>If the entitlement-granting rules seem invisible, and seem to be a
simple way of protecting freedom of choice, it is because they appear
so sensible and natural that they are not taken to be a legal allocation
at all. But this is a mistake. What we add here is'that when a default
rule affects preferences and behavior, it has the same effect as
employer presumptions about savings plans. This effect is often both
unavoidable and significant. So long as people can contract around the
default rule, it is fair to say that the legal system is protecting freedom
of choice, and in that sense complying with libertarian goals.</p>
        <p>Consumers, workers, and married people,' for example, are
surrounded by a network of legal allocations that provide the
background against which agreements are made. As a matter of
employment law, and consistent with freedom of contract, workers might be
presumed subject to discharge "at will," or they might be presumed
protected by an implied right to be discharged only "for cause." They
might be presumed to have a right to vacation time, or not. They might
be presumed protected by safety requirements, or the employer might
be free to invest in safety as he wishes, subject to market pressures. In
all cases, the law must establish whether workers have to "buy" certain
rights from employers or vice versa." Legal intervention, in this
important sense, cannot be avoided. The same is true for consumers, spouses,
and all others who are involved in legal relationships. Much of the
time, the legal background matters, even if transaction costs are zero,
because it affects choices and preferences.0" Here, as in the private
context, a form of paternalism is unavoidable.</p>
        <p>In the context of insurance, an unplanned, natural experiment
showed that the default rule can be very "sticky."" New Jersey created
a system in which the default insurance program for motorists
included a relatively low premium and no right to sue; purchasers were
allowed to deviate from the default program and to purchase the right
to sue by choosing a program with that right and also a higher
premium. By contrast, Pennsylvania offered a default program containing
a full right to sue and a relatively high premium; purchasers could
elect to switch to a new plan by "selling" the more ample right to sue
and paying a lower premium. In both cases, the default rule tended to
stick. A strong majority accepted the default rule in both states, with
only about 20 percent of New Jersey drivers acquiring the full right to
sue, and 75 percent of Pennsylvanians retaining that right." There is no
reason to think that the citizens of Pennsylvania have systematically
different preferences from the citizens of New Jersey. The default plan
is what produced the ultimate effects. Indeed, controlled experiments
find the same results, showing that the value of the right to sue is
much higher when it is presented as part of the default package."</p>
        <p>In another example, a substantial effect from the legal default
rule was found in a study of law student reactions to different state
law provisions governing vacation time from firms.7 The study was
intended to be reasonably realistic, involving as it did a pool of subjects
to whom the underlying issues were hardly foreign. Most law students
have devoted a good deal of time to thinking about salaries, vacation
time, and the tradeoffs between them. The study involved two
conditions. In the first, state law guaranteed two weeks of vacation time, and
students were asked to state their median willingness to pay (in
reduced salary) for two extra weeks of vacation. In this condition, the
median willingness to pay was $6,000.,, In the second condition, state
law provided a mandatory, non-waivable two-week vacation
guarantee, but it also provided employees (including associates at law firms)
with the right to two additional weeks of vacation, a right that could
be "knowingly and voluntarily waived." Hence the second condition
was precisely the same as the first, except that the default rule
provided the two extra weeks of vacation. In the second condition,
students were asked how much employers would have to pay them to
give up their right to the two extra weeks. All by itself, the switch in
the default rule more than doubled the students' responses, producing
a median willingness to accept of $13,000."</p>
        <p>We can imagine countless variations on these experiments. For
example, the law might authorize a situation in which employees have
to opt into retirement plans, or it might require employers to provide
automatic enrollment and allow employees to opt out. Both systems
would respect the freedom of employees to choose, and either system
would be libertarian in that sense. In the same vein, the law might
as55 See Johnson, et al, Framing, Probability Distortions, InsuranceDecisions at 238 (cited in
note 30).</p>
        <p>56 Id at 235-38.
57 See Sunstein, 77 NYU L Rev at 113-14 (cited in note 49).</p>
        <p>58 The question asked students to assume that no adverse employment consequences could
come from asking for, and receiving, those two extra weeks in vacation. See id at 113.
59 See id.
sume that there is no right to be free from age discrimination in
employment, permitting employees (through individual negotiation or
collective bargaining) to contract for that right. Alternatively, it might
give employees a nondiscrimination guarantee, subject to waiver via
contract. Our suggestion here is that one or another approach is likely
to have effects on the choices of employees. This is the sense in which
paternalism is inevitable, from government no less than from private
institutions.</p>
        <p>In emphasizing the absence of well-formed preferences, we are
not speaking only of default rules. Consider the crucial role of
"anchors," or starting points, in contingent valuation studies, an influential
method of valuing regulatory goods such as increased safety and
environmental protection.' Such studies, used when market valuations are
unavailable, attempt to ask people their "willingness to pay" for
various regulatory benefits.' Contingent valuation has become prominent
in regulatory theory and practice. "2 Because the goal is to determine
what people actually want, contingent valuation studies are an effort
to elicit, rather than to affect, people's values. Paternalism, in the sense
of effects on preferences and choices, is not supposed to be part of the
picture. But it is extremely difficult for contingent valuation studies to
avoid constructing the very values that they are supposed to discover."
The reason is that in the contexts in which such studies are used,
people do not have clear or well-formed preferences, and hence it is
unclear that people have straightforward "values" that can actually be
found. Hence some form of paternalism verges on the inevitable:
Stated values will often be affected, at least across a range, by how the
questions are set up.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most striking evidence to this effect comes from a
study of willingness to pay to reduce annual risks of death and injury
in motor vehicles." The authors of that study attempted to elicit both
maximum and minimum willingness to pay for safety improvements.
People were presented with a statistical risk and an initial monetary
amount, and asked whether they were definitely willing or definitely
unwilling to pay that amount to eliminate the risk, or if they were "not
sure." If they were definitely willing, the amount displayed was
increased until they said that they were definitely unwilling. If they were
unsure, the number was moved up and down until people could
identify the minimum and maximum.</p>
        <p>The authors were not attempting to test the effects of anchors; on
the contrary, they were alert to anchoring only because they "had
been warned" of a possible problem with their procedure, in which
people "might be unduly influenced by the first amount of money that
they saw displayed."6 To solve that problem, the study allocated
people randomly to two subsamples, one with an initial display of 25
pounds, the other with an initial display of 75 pounds. The authors
hoped that the anchoring effect would be small, with no significant
consequences for minimum and maximum values. But their hope was
dashed. For every level of risk, the minimum willingness to pay was
higher with the 75 pound startingpoint than the maximum willingness
to pay with the 25 pound startingpoint!67 For example, a reduction in
the annual risk of death by 4 in 100,000 produced a maximum
willingness to pay of 149 pounds with the 25 pound starting value, but a
minimum willingness to pay of 232 pounds with the 75 pound starting
value (and a maximum, in that case, of 350 pounds)." The most
sensible conclusion is that people are sometimes uncertain about
appropriate values, and whenever they are, anchors have an effect-sometimes
a startlingly large one.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how those interested in eliciting (rather than
affecting) values might respond to this problem." What is clear is that in the
domains in which contingent valuation studies are used, people often
lack well-formed preferences, and starting points have important
consequences for behavior and choice.</p>
        <p>65 See Michael Jones-Lee and Graham Loomes, Private Values and Public Policy,in Elke
U.Weber, Jonathan Baron, and Graham Loomes, eds, Conflict and Tradeoffs in DecisionMaking
205,208-12 (Cambridge 2001).</p>
        <p>66 Id at 210.
67 ldat211.
68 Id.</p>
        <p>69 For a general discussion, see Payne, Bettman, and Schkade, 19 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty 243
(cited in note 63).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>LibertarianPaternalm</title>
        <p>We have suggested that in the important context of medical
decisions, framing effects are substantial." Apparently, most people do not
have clear preferences about how to evaluate a procedure that leaves
90 percent of people alive (and 10 percent of people dead) after a
period of years. A similar effect has been demonstrated in the area of
obligations to future generations,7' a much-disputed policy question. 2
This question does not directly involve paternalism, because those
interested in the valuation of future generations are not attempting to
protect people from their own errors. But a regulatory system that
attempts to track people's preferences would try to measure
intergenerational time preferences, that is, to elicit people's judgments about
how to trade off the protection of current lives and future lives.7</p>
        <p>Hence an important question, asked in many debates about the
issue, is whether people actually make such judgments and whether
they can be elicited. And indeed, an influential set of studies finds that
people value the lives of those in the current generation far more than
the lives of those in future generations.7 From a series of surveys,
Maureen Cropper and her coauthors suggest that people are
indifferent between saving 1 life today and saving 44 lives in 100 years. 7 They
make this suggestion on the basis of questions asking people whether
they would choose a program that saves "100 lives now" or a program
that saves a substantially larger number "100 years from now."6</p>
        <p>But it turns out that other descriptions of the same problem yield
significantly different results.71 Here, as in other contexts, it is unclear
whether people actually have well-formed preferences with which the
legal system can work. For example, most people consider "equally
bad" a single death from pollution next year and a single death from
pollution in 100 years"-implying no preference for members of the
current generation. In another finding of no strong preference for the
current generation, people are equally divided between two programs:
one that will save 55 lives now and 105 more lives in 20 years; and one
that will save 100 lives now and 50 lives 25 years from now. " It is even
possible to frame the question in such a way as to find that future lives
are valued more, not less, highly than current lives. The most sensible
conclusion is that people do not have robust, well-ordered
intergenerational time preferences. If so, it is not possible for government to
track those preferences, because they are an artifact of how the
question is put. The point applies in many contexts. For example, people
are unlikely to have context-free judgments about whether
government should focus on statistical lives or statistical life-years in
regulatory policy; their judgments will be much affected by the framing of
the question."</p>
        <p>Why Effects on Choice Can Be Hard to Avoid
1. Explanations.</p>
        <p>Why, exactly, do default rules, starting points, and framing effects
have such large effects? To answer this question, it is important to
make some distinctions.</p>
        <p>a) Suggestion. In the face of uncertainty about what should be
done, people might rely on one of two related heuristics: do what most
people do, or do what informed people do.8 Choosers might think that
the default plan or value captures one or the other. In many settings,
any starting point will carry some informational content and will thus
affect choices. When a default rule affects behavior, it might well be
because it is taken to carry information about how sensible people
78 Id at 43.
79 Id at 44.</p>
        <p>8t See id at 45. Frederick asked subjects to choose between two programs. The first would
become more effective over time, saving 100 lives this decade, 200 lives in the following decade,
and 300 lives in the decade after that. The second would become less effective over time, saving
300 lives this decade, 200 lives in the following decade, and 100 lives in the decade after that.
Most people preferred the first program, apparently suggesting that future lives are valued more
highly. Id.</p>
        <p>81 See Cass R. Sunstein, Lives, Life-Years, and Willingness to Pay, Colum L Rev
(forthcoming 2004).</p>
        <p>82 See the discussion of imitation as a fast and frugal heuristic in Joseph Henrich, et al,
What Is the Role of Culture in Bounded Rationality?, in Gerd Gigerenzer and Reinhard Selten,
eds, Bounded Rationality:The Adaptive Toolbox 343,344 (MIT 2001) ("Cultural transmission
capacities allow individuals to shortcut the costs of search, experimentation, and data processing
algorithms, and instead benefit from the cumulative experience stored in the minds (and
observed in the behavior) of others.").
usually organize their affairs. Notice that in the context of savings,
people might have a mild preference for one or another course, but
the preference might be overcome by evidence that most people do
not take that course. Some workers might think, for example, that they
should not enroll in a 401(k) plan and have a preference not to do so;
but the thought and the preference might shift with evidence that the
employer has made enrollment automatic.</p>
        <p>With respect to savings, the designated default plan apparently
carries a certain legitimacy for many employees, perhaps because it
seems to have resulted from some conscious thought about what
makes most sense for most people."3This interpretation is supported
by the finding that the largest effects from the new default rule are
shown by women and African-Americans." We might speculate that
members of such groups tend to be less confident in their judgments
in this domain and may have less experience in assessing different
savings plans.</p>
        <p>b) Inertia. A separate explanation points to inertia." Any
change from the default rule or starting value is likely to require some
action. Even a trivial action, such as filling in some form and returning
it, can leave room for failures due to memory lapses, sloth, and
procrastination. Many people wait until the last minute to file their tax
return, even when they are assured of getting a refund. The power of
inertia should be seen as a form of bounded rationality. Although the
costs of switching from the default rule or the starting point can be
counted as transaction costs, the fact that large behavioral changes are
observed even when such costs are tiny suggests that a purely rational
explanation is difficult to accept.</p>
        <p>c) Endowment effect. A default rule might create a "pure"
endowment effect. It is well known that people tend to value goods more
highly if those goods have been initially allocated to them than if
those goods have been initially allocated elsewhere." And it is well
known that, in many cases, the default rule will create an endowment
effect. When an endowment effect is involved, the initial allocation,
by private or public institutions, affects people's choices simply
because it affects their valuations.</p>
        <p>d) Ill-formed preferences. In the cases we have discussed,
people's preferences are ill-formed and murky. Suppose, for example,
83 See Madrian and Shea, 116 Q J Econ at 1177-78 (cited in note 1).
84 See id at 1160-61.</p>
        <p>85 See id at 1171 (noting that, under automatic enrollment, individuals become "passive
savers" and "do nothing to move away from the default contribution rate").</p>
        <p>86 See generally Korobkin, 83 Cornell L Rev 608 (cited in note 18); Richard H. Thaler,
QuasiRational Economics (Russell Sage 1991).</p>
        <p>87 See note 43.
that people are presented with various payouts and risk levels for
various pension plans. They might be able to understand the
presentation; there might be no confusion. But people might not have
a well-defined preference for, or against, a slightly riskier plan with a
slightly higher expected value. In these circumstances, their
preferences might be endogenous to the default plan simply because
they lack well-formed desires that can be accessed to overrule the
default starting points. In unfamiliar situations, it is especially unlikely
that well-formed preferences will exist. The range of values in the
highway safety study is likely a consequence of the unfamiliarity of
the context, which leaves people without clear preferences from which
to generate numbers. The effects of framing on intergenerational time
preferences attest to the fact that people do not have unambiguous
judgments about how to trade off the interests of future generations
with those of people now living.m
2. The inevitability of paternalism.</p>
        <p>For present purposes, the choice among these various
explanations does not greatly matter. The central point is that effects on
individual choices are often unavoidable. Of course it is usually good not
to block choices, and we do not mean to defend non-libertarian
paternalism here. But in an important respect the anti-paternalist position
is incoherent, simply because there is no way to avoid effects on
behavior and choices. The task for the committed libertarian is, in the
midst of such effects, to preserve freedom of choice.</p>
        <p>Because framing effects are inevitable, it is hopelessly inadequate
to say that when people lack relevant information the best response is
to provide it. In order to be effective, any effort to inform people must
be rooted in an understanding of how people actually think.
Presentation makes a great deal of difference: The behavioral consequences of
otherwise identical pieces of information depend on how they are
framed.</p>
        <p>Consider one example from the realm of retirement savings.
Benartzi and Thaler asked participants in a defined contribution
savings plan to imagine that they had only two investment options, Fund
A and Fund B, and asked them how they would allocate their
investments between these two funds." (The two funds were, in fact, a
diversified stock fund and an intermediate term bond fund.) All subjects
were given information about the historic returns on these funds.
However, one group was shown the distribution of annual rates of
re88 See notes 75-80 and accompanying text.</p>
        <p>89 See Shlomo Benartzi and Richard H. Thaler, Risk Aversion or Myopia? Choices in
Repeated Gamblesand Retirement Investments, 45 Mgmt Sci 364,375 (1999).
turn, whereas another group was shown simulated thirty-year rates of
return. " The long-term rates of return were derived from the annual
rates of return (by drawing years at random from history), and so the
two sets of information were, strictly speaking, identical. Nevertheless,
participants elected to invest about 40 percent of their money in
equities when shown the annual returns and 90 percent when shown the
long-term rates of return.' The lesson from this example is that plan
sponsors cannot avoid influencing the choices their participants make
simply by providing information. The way they display the
information will, in some situations, strongly alter the choices people make.</p>
        <p>The point that the presentation of information influences choice
is a general one. In the face of health risks, for example, some
presentations of accurate information might actually be counterproductive,
because people might attempt to control their fear by refusing to
think about the risk at all. In empirical studies, "some messages
conveying identical information seemed to work better than others, and
[ ] some even appeared to backfire."'" When information campaigns
fail altogether, it is often because those efforts "result in
counterproductive defensive measures.""' Hence the most effective approaches go
far beyond mere disclosure and combine "a frightening message about
the consequences of inaction with an upbeat message about the
efficacy of a proposed program of prevention. "4</p>
        <p>There are complex and interesting questions here about how to
promote welfare. If information greatly increases people's fear, it will
to that extent reduce welfare-in part because fear is unpleasant, in
part because fear has a range of ripple effects producing social costs.
We do not speak to the welfare issue here. Our only suggestions are
that if people lack information, a great deal of attention needs to be
paid to information processing, and that without such attention,
information disclosure might well prove futile or counterproductive.
And to the extent that those who design informational strategies are
taking account of how people think and are attempting to steer people
in desirable directions, their efforts will inevitably have a paternalistic
dimension.</p>
        <p>90 See id.
91 Id at 377.</p>
        <p>92 Andrew Caplin, Fearas a Policy Instrument, in George Loewenstein, Daniel Read, and
Roy Baumeister, eds, Time and Decision:Economic and PsychologicalPerspectives on
IntertemporalChoice 441,443 (Russell Sage 2003).</p>
        <p>93 Id at 442.
94 Id at 443.
D. Beyond the Inevitable (But Still Libertarian)</p>
        <p>The inevitability of paternalism is most clear when the planner
has to choose starting points or default rules. But if the focus is on
welfare, it is reasonable to ask whether the planner should go beyond
the inevitable, and whether such a planner can also claim to be
libertarian. To illustrate the problem, return to the simple cafeteria
example discussed above. Putting the: fruit before the desserts is a fairly
mild intervention. A more intrusive step would be to place the
desserts in another location altogether, so that diners have to get up and
get a dessert after they have finished the rest of their meal. This step
raises the transaction costs of eating dessert, and according to a
standard economic analysis the proposal is quite unattractive-it seems to
make dessert eaters worse off and no one better off. But many people
face problems of self-control, and the results include illness and
disease, small and large." Once the costs of self-control are incorporated
into the analysis, we can see that some diners would prefer this
arrangement, namely those who would eat a dessert if it were put in
front of them but would resist temptation if given a little help. To fit
with libertarian principles, the planner could arrange two lines in the
cafeteria: the tempting line and the non-tempting line. The tempting
line would include everything, whereas the non-tempting line would
make unhealthy foods less available. Since people could choose either
line, this passes the libertarian test. (As a solution to the self-control
problem, it might not be entirely adequate, because people would be
tempted to join the tempting line.) Hence it is possible to preserve
freedom of choice, and to allow opt-outs, but also to favor
selfconscious efforts to promote welfare by helping people to solve
problems of bounded rationality and bounded self-control. Efforts of this
kind need not attempt to give people what they would choose ex ante,
even in cases in which preferences exist; but such efforts would
nonetheless allow people to move in their preferred directions.</p>
        <p>In the domain of employee behavior, there are many imaginable
illustrations. Employees might be automatically enrolled in a 401(k)
plan, with a right to opt out, but employers might require a waiting
period, and perhaps a consultation with an adviser, before the opt-out
could be effective." Thaler and Benartzi have proposed a method of
95 See O'Donoghue and Rabin, 93 Am Econ Rev at 187 (cited in note 16) (arguing that
"imposing seemingly large sin taxes on unhealthy items while lowering taxes on other items may
not hurt rational consumers by much," and may "create significant benefits for those who
overconsume the unhealthy items due to self-control problems"); Jolls, Sunstein, and Thaler, 50 Stan
L Rev at 1479 (cited in note 13).</p>
        <p>96 Note that some committed libertarians might be uncomfortable with waiting periods,
separate cafeteria lines, and the like, especially if these are defended as a way of changing
preferences. Our main goal here, however, is to help people to solve their self-control problems, and
increasing contributions to 401(k) plans that also meets the libertarian
test."7 Under the Save More Tomorrow plan, briefly described in the
Introduction, employees are invited to sign up for a program in which
their contributions to the savings plan are increased annually
whenever they get a raise. Once employees join the plan, they stay in until
they opt out or reach the maximum savings rate. In the first company
to use this plan, the employees who joined increased their savings
rates from 3.5 percent to 11.6 percent in a little over two years (three
raises).98 Very few of the employees who join the plan drop out. We
believe that this is successful libertarian paternalism in action. In fact,
the ideas of automatic enrollment and Save More Tomorrow provide
quite promising models for increasing saving; they might well be more
effective than imaginable economic incentives, as for example through
decreased taxes on savings.</p>
        <p>The same sort of strategy might be used in many domains.
Moving from paternalism to protection of third parties, employers (or the
state) might seek to increase charitable giving from workers. Is it
possible to produce a form of libertarian benevolence, and if so, how
might this be done? Moral suasion may or may not succeed, but
compare a system of Give More Tomorrow. Because workers appear quite
willing to part with a fraction of their future raises, such a system, like
Save More Tomorrow, would be highly appealing to many people. In
fact the ideas explored here might well be used to produce significant
increases in charitable donations (of course, there are obvious
complexities about institutional design and appropriate default
beneficiaries').</p>
        <p>It should now be clear that the difference between libertarian and
non-libertarian paternalism is not simple and rigid. The libertarian
paternalist insists on preserving choice, whereas the non-libertarian
paternalist is willing to foreclose choice. But in all cases, a real question
is the cost of exercising choice, and here there is a continuum rather
than a sharp dichotomy. A libertarian paternalist who is especially
enthusiastic about free choice would be inclined to make it relatively
costless for people to obtain their preferred outcomes. (Call this a
libertarianpaternalist.) By contrast, a libertarian paternalist who is
espefor this reason the objection, from the standpoint of liberty, seems weak, at least if freedom of
choice is preserved.</p>
        <p>97 See Thaler and Benartzi, J Polit Econ (forthcoming) (cited in note 2).
98 Id.</p>
        <p>99 We acknowledge that a Give More Tomorrow program is more easily abused than one
involving Save More Tomorrow. In the latter case, the resources remain with the employee,
whereas in the former, the resources go elsewhere, and perhaps to those whom employers favor.
Any development of a Give More Tomorrow plan should have safeguards against employer
favoritism or self-dealing, just as one would want safeguards to prevent self-dealing in the choice
of mutual funds to include in the 401(k) plan.
cially confident of his welfare judgments would be willing to impose
real costs on workers and consumers who seek to do what, in the
paternalist's view, would not be in their best interests. (Call this a
libertarian paternalist.)</p>
        <p>Rejecting both routes, a non-libertarian paternalist would
attempt to block certain choices. But notice that almost any such
attempt will amount, in practice, to an effort to impose high costs on
those who try to make those choices. Consider a law requiring drivers
to wear seat belts. If the law is enforced, and a large fine is imposed,
the law is non-libertarian even though determined violators can
exercise their freedom of choice-at the expense of the fine. But as the
expected fine approaches zero, the law approaches libertarianism. The
libertarian paternalism that we are describing and defending here
attempts to ensure, as a general rule, that people can easily avoid the
paternalist's suggested option.""
E. Illustrations and Generalizations</p>
        <p>Many actual and proposed legal provisions embody libertarian
paternalism. Some of those provisions require disclosure of
information; some of them shift the default rule; some of them preserve
freedom of contract but impose procedural or substantive restrictions on
those who seek to move in directions that seem, to the planner, to be
contrary to their welfare. We divide this brief catalogue into two parts,
the first dealing with labor and employment law, and the second
dealing with consumers more generally.""
1. Labor and employment law.</p>
        <p>Under the Age Discrimination in Employment Act (ADEA),
employees are permitted to waive their rights when they are retiring, '
and hence the statutorily conferred right-to be free from age
discrimination-does not reject the libertarian commitment to freedom
of contract. But the employee is presumed to have retained that right
unless there has been a "knowing and voluntary" waiver."" To ensure
that the waiver is knowing and voluntary, the ADEA imposes a range
of procedural hurdles. Thus the waiver must specifically refer "to
rights or claims arising under" the ADEA;"" the employee must be</p>
        <p>I) We are not, therefore, attempting to enter into the debate between paternalists and
antipaternalists, though obviously much of our discussion bears on that debate.</p>
        <p>101For an overlapping catalogue, see Camerer, et al, 151 U Pa L Rev at 1224 (cited in
note 6).</p>
        <p>H)2 29 USC § 626(f)(1) (2000).
103 Id.</p>
        <p>HK4Id § 626(f)(1)(B).
advised in writing to consult with an attorney before executing the
agreement;'Ol the employee must be given "at least 21 days within
which to consider the agreement";"' and the agreement must provide
for a minimum of a seven-day post-execution revocation period.'7 The
ADEA has an unmistakable paternalistic dimension insofar as it
switches the default rule to one favoring the employee and also
creates a set of procedural barriers to insufficiently informed waivers. At
the same time, the ADEA goes beyond the inevitable minimal level of
paternalism by imposing those barriers, which significantly raise the
burdens of waiver. But the ADEA preserves freedom of choice and
thus satisfies the libertarian criterion.</p>
        <p>Labor and employment law offers several other examples. The
Model Employment Termination Act alters the standard American
rule, which holds that employees may be discharged for no reason or
for any reason at all." Under the Model Act, employees are given the
right to be discharged only for cause.'9 But the Model Act complies
with libertarian principles by allowing employers and employees to
waive the right on the basis of an agreement, by the employer, to
provide a severance payment in the event of a discharge not based on
poor job performance.'0 That payment must consist of one month's
salary for every year of employment."' This limitation on waiver is
substantive and in that sense quite different from the procedural
limitation in the ADEA; in this way it is less libertarian than it might be.
But freedom of choice is nonetheless respected.</p>
        <p>An important provision of the Fair Labor Standards Act belongs
in the same category."2 Under that provision, employees may waive
their right not to work for more than forty hours per week, but only at
a governmentally determined premium (time and a half)."' Here, as
under the Model Act, a substantive limitation is imposed on workers'
rights to opt out of a default arrangement.</p>
        <p>2. Consumer protection.</p>
        <p>In the law of consumer protection, the most obvious examples of
libertarian paternalism involve "cooling-off" periods for certain
deci105 Id § 626(f)(1)(E).
]06 Id § 626(f)(1)(F)(i).
107 Id § 626(f)(1)(G).</p>
        <p>108 See Model Employment Termination Act, reprinted in Mark A. Rothstein and Lance
Liebman, Statutory Supplement, Employment Law: Casesand Materials211 (Foundation 2003).
109 Id § 3(a).
110 Id § 4(c).</p>
        <p>III Id.</p>
        <p>I1t2 See 29 USC § 207(f) (2000).
113 Id.
sions.'" The essential rationale is that under the heat of the moment,
consumers might make ill-considered or improvident decisions. Both
bounded rationality and bounded self-control are the underlying
concerns. A mandatory cooling-off period for door-to-door sales, of the
sort imposed by the Federal Trade Commission in 1972,"' provides a
simple illustration. Under the Commission's rule, door-to-door sales
must be accompanied by written statements informing buyers of their
right to rescind purchases within three days of transactions."' Some
states also impose mandatory waiting periods before people may
receive a divorce decree.'"7 We could easily imagine similar restrictions
on the decision to marry, and some states have moved in this direction
as well."" Aware that people might act impulsively or in a way that
they will regret, regulators do not block their choices, but ensure a
period for sober reflection. Note in this regard that mandatory
coolingoff periods make best sense, and tend to be imposed, when two
conditions are met: (1) people are making decisions that they make
infrequently and for which they therefore lack a great deal of experience,
and (2) emotions are likely to be running high. These are the
circumstances-of bounded rationality and bounded self-control
respectively-in which consumers are especially prone to making choices
that they will regret.</p>
        <p>3. Generalizations.</p>
        <p>We are now in a position to categorize a diverse set of
paternalistic interventions: minimal paternalism, required active choices,
procedural constraints, and substantive constraints.</p>
        <p>a) Minimal paternalism. Minimal paternalism is the form of
paternalism that occurs whenever a planner (private or public)
constructs a default rule or starting point with the goal of influencing
behavior. So long as it is costless or nearly costless to depart from the
default plan, minimal paternalism is maximally libertarian. This is the
form of paternalism that we have described as inevitable.</p>
        <p>b) Required active choices. Unsure of what choices will
promote welfare, a planner might reject default plans or starting points
114 See the valuable discussion in Camerer, et al, 151 U Pa L Rev at 1240-42 (cited in
note 6).</p>
        <p>115 16 CFR §429.1 (a) (2003).
116 Id.</p>
        <p>117 See, for example, Cal Fam Code § 2339(a) (requiring a six-month waiting period before
a divorce decree becomes final); Conn Gen Stat Ann § 46b-67(a) (requiring a ninety-day waiting
period before the court may proceed on the divorce complaint). For a general discussion, see
Elizabeth Scott, RationalDecisionmakingabout Marriageand Divorce,76 Va L Rev 9 (1990).</p>
        <p>18 See Camerer, et al, 151 U Pa L Rev at 1243 (cited in note 6) (citing state statutes that
"force potential newlyweds to wait a short period of time after their license has been issued
before they can tie the knot").
entirely and force people to choose explicitly (what we have described
as the strategy of required active choices). This approach finds an
analogue in information-eliciting default rules in contract law, designed to
give contracting parties a strong incentive to say what they want."' To
the extent that planners force people to choose whether or not people
would like to choose, there is a paternalistic dimension to their actions.
("Choosing is good for both freedom and welfare," some appear to
think, whether or not people agree with them!) We think that the
argument for requiring choices stands or falls largely on the welfare
consequences.</p>
        <p>c) Proceduralconstraints. A slightly more aggressive form of
paternalism occurs when the default plan is accompanied by
procedural constraints designed to ensure that any departure is fully
voluntary and entirely rational. When procedural constraints are in place, it
is not costless to depart from the default plan. The extent of the cost,
and the aggressiveness of the paternalism, will of course vary with the
extent of the constraints. The justification for the constraints will
depend on whether there are serious problems of bounded rationality
and bounded self-control; if so, the constraints are justified not on the
ground that the planner disagrees with people's choices, but because
identifiable features of the situation make it likely that choices will be
defective. Such features may include an unfamiliar setting, a lack of
experience, and a risk of impulsiveness. The Age Discrimination in
Employment Act is our principal example here.</p>
        <p>d) Substantive constraints. Alternatively, a planner might
impose substantive constraints, allowing people to reject the default
arrangement, but not on whatever terms they choose. On this
approach, the planner selects the terms along which the parties will be
permitted to move in their preferred directions. The Model
Termination Act and the Fair Labor Standards Act are illustrations.
The extent of the departure from libertarianism will be a function of
the gap between the legally specified terms and the terms that parties
would otherwise reach. Here too the justification for the constraint
depends on bounded rationality and bounded self-control.</p>
        <p>e) A thin line. A planner might reject freedom of choice on the
ground that those who reject the default plan will err all or almost all
of the time. Such a planner will impose significant costs on those who
depart from the plan. As we have said, there is a thin line between
non-libertarian paternalists and libertarian paternalists who impose
high costs, procedural or substantive, on those who reject the plan.
Almost all of the time, even the non-libertarian paternalist will allow
119See Ian Ayres and Robert Gertner, FillingGaps in Incomplete Contracts:An Economic
Theory of Default Rules, 99 Yale L J 87,91 (1989).
choosers, at some cost, to reject the proposed course of action. Those
who are required to wear motorcycle helmets can decide to risk the
relevant penalty, and to pay it if need be. Employers and employees
might agree to sub-minimum wage work and risk the penalties if they
are caught. In this particular sense, penalties are always prices.</p>
        <p>III. How TO CHOOSE: THE TOOLBOX OF THE</p>
        <p>LIBERTARIAN PATERNALIST</p>
        <p>How should sensible planners choose among possible systems,
given that some choice is necessary? We suggest two approaches to
this problem. If feasible, a comparison of possible rules should be
done using a form of cost-benefit analysis, one that pays serious
attention to welfare effects. In many cases, however, such analyses will be
both difficult and expensive. As an alternative, we offer some rules of
thumb that might be adopted to choose among various options. In
general, it makes sense to experiment with possible approaches to
identify their results for both choices and outcomes. We have
emphasized automatic enrollment plans and Save More Tomorrow because
studies have suggested that both of these have a great deal of
potential. In other domains, plans are likely to be proposed in the face of
highly imperfect information; more data will reveal a great deal.
Large-scale programs are most justified if repeated experiments have
shown that they actually work.</p>
        <p>A. Costs and Benefits</p>
        <p>The goal of a cost-benefit study would be to measure the full
ramifications of any design choice. In the context at hand, the
costbenefit study cannot be based on willingness to pay (WTP), because
WTP will be a function of the default rule."" It must be a more
openended (and inevitably somewhat subjective) assessment of the welfare
consequences. To illustrate, take the example of automatic enrollment.
Under automatic enrollment, some employees, who otherwise would
not join the plan, will now do so. Presumably, some are made better
off (especially if there is an employer match), but some may be made
worse off (for example, those who are highly liquidity-constrained and
do not exercise their right to opt out). A cost-benefit analysis would
attempt to evaluate these gains and losses.</p>
        <p>If the issue were only enrollment, we think it highly likely that
the gains would exceed the losses. Because of the right to opt out,
120 See Kahneman, Knetsch, and Thaler, 5 J Econ Persp at 202-03 (cited in note 43). See
also Korobkin, 83 Cornell L Rev at 636-41 (cited in note 18). For a discussion of the variation of
potential employees' VTP for vacation days based on default rules, see text accompanying notes
57-59.
those who need the money immediately are able to have it. In
principle one could also compare the costs of foregone current consumption
and the benefits of increased consumption during retirement, though
this is, admittedly, difficult to do in practice. It is also possible to make
inferences from actual choices about welfare. For example, most
employees do join the plan eventually, and very few drop out if
automatically enrolled.'2' These facts suggest that, at least on average, defaulting
people into the plan will mostly hasten the rate at which people join
the plan, and that the vast majority of those who are so nudged will be
grateful.</p>
        <p>Some readers might think that our reliance on behavior as an
indication of welfare is inconsistent with one of the central claims of this
Article-that choices do not necessarily coincide with welfare. But in
fact, there is no inconsistency. Compare rules calling for mandatory
cooling-off periods. The premise of such rules is that people are more
likely to make good choices when they have had time to think
carefully and without a salesperson present. Similarly, it is reasonable to
think that if, on reflection, workers realized that they had been
"tricked" into saving too much, they might take the effort to opt out.
The fact that very few participants choose to opt out supports (though
it does not prove) the claim that they are helped by a system that
makes joining easy.</p>
        <p>Once the other effects of automatic enrollment are included, the
analysis becomes cloudier. Any plan for automatic enrollment must
include a specified default savings rate. Some of those automatically
enrolled at a 3 percent savings rate-a typical default in automatic
enrollment-would have chosen a higher rate if left to their own
devices. ' If automatic enrollment leads some or many people to save at
a lower rate than they would choose, the plan might be objectionable
for that reason. Hence we are less confident that this more complete
cost-benefit analysis would support the particular opt-out system,
though a higher savings rate might well do so. A more sophisticated
plan, avoiding some of these pitfalls, is discussed below.</p>
        <p>Similar tradeoffs are involved with another important issue: the
appropriate default rule for organ donations. In many
nationsAustria, Belgium, Denmark, Finland, France, Italy, Luxembourg,
Norway, Singapore, Slovenia, and Spain-people are presumed to consent
to allow their organs to be used, after death, for the benefit of others;
but they are permitted to rebut the presumption, usually through an
explicit notation to that effect on their drivers' licenses. ' In the
121 See Choi, et al, Defined Contribution Pensions at 78 (cited in note 1); Madrian and Shea,
116 Q J Econ at 1158-61 (cited in note 1).</p>
        <p>
          122 See Choi, et al, Defined Contribution Pensions at 78-79 (cited in note 1).
123See http://www.presumedconsent.org/solutions.htm (visited Sept
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">6,2003</xref>
          ).
United States, by contrast, those who want their organs to be available
for others must affirmatively say so, also through an explicit notation
on their drivers' licenses. The result is that in "presumed consent"
nations over 90 percent of people consent to make their organs available
for donation, whereas in the United States, where people have to take
some action to make their organs available, only 28 percent elect to do
so. ' We hypothesize that this dramatic difference is not a product of
deep cultural differences, but of the massive effect of the default rule.
Hence we would predict that a European-style opt-out rule in the
United States would produce donation rates similar to those observed
in the European countries that use this rule. Note in this regard that
by one report, over 85 percent of Americans support organ
donation -a statistic that suggests opt-outs would be relatively rare."'
        </p>
        <p>A recent study strongly supports this prediction." Suggesting that
preferences are constructed by social frames, Johnson and Goldstein
urge that with respect to organ donation, people lack stable
preferences and that their decisions are very much influenced by the default
rule. ' A controlled online experiment showed a substantial effect
from the default rule: The opt-in system created a 42 percent consent
rate, about half of the 82 percent rate for an opt-out system. ' The
real-world evidence is even more dramatic. Presumed consent nations
show consent rates ranging from a low of 85.9 percent (Sweden) to a
high of 100 percent (Austria), with a median of 99 percent.2 The
default also produces a significant, though less dramatic, increase in
actual donations, meaning that many people are saved as a result of the
presumed consent system."" There is reason to believe that in the
United States, a switch in the default rule could save thousands of
lives.</p>
        <p>
          The default rules for organ donation do not fit the usual
definition of paternalism. The issue is the welfare of third parties, not of
124 Id (reporting opt-out rates in presumed consent nations); Jean Kadooka Mardfin, Heart
and Soul: Anatomical Gifts for Hawaii'sTransplant Community 5, Hawaii Legislative Reference
Bureau Report No 3 (1998), online at http://www.state.hi.us/lrb/rpts98/soul.pdf (visited Nov 20,
2003)
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">(reporting results of a 1993 Gallup poll that asked Americans whether they had "granted
permission for organ donation on [their] driver's license or on a signed donor card")</xref>
          .
125 See http://www.presumedconsent.org/issues.htm (visited Sept
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">6,2003</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>
          126 See Eric I. Johnson and Daniel Goldstein, Do Defaults Save Lives?
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13 ref6">(unpublished
working paper, Center for Decision Sciences, Columbia University, 2003)</xref>
          .
        </p>
        <p>127 Id at 2.
128 Id at 6-7.
129 Id at 7, Figure 2.</p>
        <p>130 Id at 8-9. Many factors determine how many organs are actually made available and
used for transplants. The transplant infrastructure is certainly important, and fewer organs will
be available if family members and heirs can veto transplants, even under a presumed consent
regime. Johnson and Goldstein estimate that switching to an opt-out system increases organs
actually used by 16 percent, holding everything else constant.
choosers. Here we are speaking not of libertarian paternalism, but of
libertarian benevolence: an approach that attempts to promote
benevolence, and to assist vulnerable people, without mandating
behavior in any way. We suggest that changes in default rules, or a system of
Give More Tomorrow, could produce large increases in public
assistance- and that such approaches could do so in a way that avoids
coercion. With respect to behavior, the analysis of libertarian
benevolence is quite similar to that of libertarian paternalism. One of the
advantages of that analysis is the demonstration that when third-party
interests are at stake, the default rule will matter a great deal. It
follows that planners can often deliver significant benefits to third
parties simply by switching the default rule. In the case of organ donation,
this is what we observe.</p>
        <p>Does one or another default rule promote welfare? At first
glance, the opt-out rule common in Europe seems better, simply
because it should save a large number of lives without compromising any
other important value. The most that can be said against the opt-out
rule is that through inertia, perceived social pressure, or confusion,
some people might end up donating their organs when they would
not, all things considered, prefer to do so ex ante. (Their ex post
preferences are difficult to infer!) If this objection (or some other3'1 ) seems
forceful, an alternative would be to require active choices-for
example, to mandate, at the time of applying for a driver's license, that
applicants indicate whether they want to allow their organs to be used
for the benefit of others. We make only two claims about this example.
First, the evaluative question turns in large part on empirical issues of
the sort that it would be both possible and useful to investigate.
Second, the opt-in approach is unlikely to be best.32</p>
        <p>Rules of Thumb</p>
        <p>In many cases, the planner will be unable to make a direct inquiry
into welfare, either because too little information is available or
because the costs of conducting the analysis are not warranted. The
committed anti-paternalist might say, in such cases, that people should
simply be permitted to choose as they see fit. We hope that we have
said enough to show why this response is unhelpful. What people
choose often depends on the starting point, and hence the starting
point cannot be selected by asking what people choose. In these
cir131 It is conceivable that the care of fatally ill patients might be sacrificed in order to harvest
their organs, but no evidence suggests that this is a serious risk.</p>
        <p>132 It follows from this example that if private or public planners would like to increase
charitable donations, they could easily do that simply by creating automatic deductions for
charity. Even if workers are allowed to opt out, clever planners should easily be able to ensure a
much higher level of donations.
cumstances, the libertarian paternalist would seek indirect proxies for
welfare-methods that test whether one or another approach
promotes welfare without relying on guesswork about that question. We
suggest three possible methods.</p>
        <p>First, the libertarian paternalist might select the approach that the
majority would choose if explicit choices were requiredand revealed.In
the context of contract law, this is the most familiar inquiry in the
selection of default rules'- provisions that govern contractual
arrangements in the absence of express decisions by the parties. Useful
though it is, this market-mimicking approach raises its own problems.
Perhaps the majority's choices would be insufficiently informed, or a
reflection of bounded rationality or bounded self-control. Perhaps
those choices would not, in fact, promote the majority's welfare. At
least as a presumption, however, it makes sense to follow those
choices if the planner knows what they would be. A deeper problem is
that the majority's choices might themselves be a function of the
starting point or the default rule. If so, the problem of circularity dooms
the market-mimicking approach. But in some cases, at least, the
majority might go one way or the other regardless of the starting
point; and to that extent, the market-mimicking strategy is workable.
Note that in the cafeteria example, some options would not fit with
the majority's ex ante choices (healthy but terrible-tasting food, for
example), and that for savings, some allocations would certainly
violate the choices of ordinary workers (say, an allocation of 30
percent or more to savings). In fact a clear understanding of majority
choices might well support a default rule that respects those choices
even if the planner thinks that an inquiry into welfare would support
another rule. At the very least, planners should be required to have
real confidence in their judgment if they seek to do something other
than what a suitably informed majority would find to be in its interest.</p>
        <p>Second, the libertarian paternalist might select the approach that
we have called required active choices, one that would force people to
make their choices explicit.This approach might be chosen if the
market-mimicking strategy fails, either because of the circularity problem
or because the planner does not know which approach would in fact
be chosen by the majority. We have seen the possibility of requiring
active choices in the context of retirement plans and organ donations;
it would be easy to multiply examples. In the law of contract, courts
sometimes choose "penalty defaults" -default rules that penalize the
party in the best position to obtain a clear statement on the question
at hand, and hence create an incentive for clarity for the person who is</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          26
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Gary</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Becker and Kevin M. Murphy</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Theory of RationalAddiction, 96 J Polit Econ</source>
          <volume>675</volume>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          27
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Ole-Jorgen</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Skog</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Rationality,Irrationality,and
          <article-title>Addiction-Notes on Becker's and Murphy's Theory of Addiction, in Jon Elster</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ole-Jorgen Skog</surname>
          </string-name>
          , eds,
          <source>Getting Hooked (Cambridge</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Nondelegation: A Post-mortem</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>................................................. Grading the Government .................................. Richard W</given-names>
            . Parker 1345 i
            <surname>See James J. Choi</surname>
          </string-name>
          , et al,
          <article-title>Defined Contribution Pensions:Plan Rules, Participant Choices, and the Path of Least Resistance</article-title>
          , in James M. Poterba, ed, 16
          <source>Tax Policy and the Economy</source>
          <volume>67</volume>
          ,70 (MIT
          <year>2002</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Brigitte C. Madrian and Dennis F Shea, The Power of Suggestion: Inertia in 401(k) Participation and Savings Behavior, 116</article-title>
          <source>Q J Econ</source>
          <volume>1149</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1149</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          2 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Thaler</surname>
            and
            <given-names>Shlomo</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Benartzi</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Save More Tomorrow:
          <article-title>Using Behavioral Economics to Increase Employee Saving</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J Polit Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          (forthcoming), online at http:// gsbwww.uchicago.edu/fac/richard.thaler/research/SMarTl4.pdf (
          <issue>visited May 10</issue>
          ,
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          3 See, for example, David Boaz,
          <source>Libertarianism:A Primer 16-19 (Free Press</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          4 See, for example, Robert E. Goodin, Permissible Paternalism: In
          <source>Defense of the Nanny State, 1 Responsive Community</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          ,
          <issue>44</issue>
          (Summer
          <year>1991</year>
          )
          <article-title>(justifying traditional paternalism on the grounds that "public officials might better respect your own preferences than you would have done through your own actions"</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>5</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A very brief companion essay, intended for an economic audience and not dealing with law, investigates some of the issues explored here</article-title>
          . See Richard H. Thaler and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Libertarian Paternalism, 93 Am Econ Rev</source>
          <volume>175</volume>
          (May
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>6 Our defense of libertarian paternalism is closely related to the arguments for "asymmetric paternalism," illuminatingly discussed in Colin Camerer</article-title>
          , et al,
          <article-title>Regulation for Conservatives: Behavioral Economics and the Case for "Asymmetric Paternalism," 151 U Pa L Rev 1211 (</article-title>
          <year>2003</year>
          ). Camerer, et al,
          <article-title>urge that governments should consider a weak form of paternalism-a form that attempts to help those who make mistakes, while imposing minimal costs on those who are fully rational</article-title>
          .
          <source>Id at 1212</source>
          .
          <article-title>Our Article, written in parallel, has similar motivations, though libertarian paternalism may or may not be asymmetric in the sense identified by Camerer and his coauthors</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          7 See, for example, Dennis F Thompson,
          <source>Political Ethics and Public Office 154-55 (Harvard</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          ),
          <article-title>which lists three criteria for justified paternalism: impaired judgment, temporary and reversible intervention, and prevention of serious and irreversible harm. We think that this account points in many sensible directions, but it neglects the inevitable effects of default rules, framing effects, and starting points on choices</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          8
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Donald</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            <surname>Redelmeier</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Paul Rozin, and Daniel Kahneman,
          <source>UnderstandingPatients' Decisions:Cognitive and EmotionalPerspectives</source>
          ,
          <volume>270</volume>
          JAMA 72,
          <issue>73</issue>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>9 See id ("The framing effect was just as large with physicians as with lay people.").</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>10 See note 1 and accompanying text.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Milton Friedman and Rose Friedman, Free to Choose:A PersonalStatement (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</article-title>
          <year>1980</year>
          ).
          <article-title>To be sure, it would be possible to imagine a more robust under15 See, for example, Richard A</article-title>
          . Epstein,
          <source>In Defense of the Contract at Will</source>
          , 51
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
            <surname>Chi L Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>947 (</article-title>
          <year>1984</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>16 For a complaint similar to ours, see Ted O'Donoghue</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
            <surname>Rabin</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Studying Optimal Paternalism,
          <source>Illustrated by a Model of Sin Taxes, 93 Am Econ Rev</source>
          <volume>186</volume>
          (May
          <year>2003</year>
          ):
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          19 See generally Gary S. Becker, Accountingfor
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tastes</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>Harvard 1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>20 For a classic illustration, see Bruce A</article-title>
          . Ackerman and William T. Hassler, Clean Coal/Dirty Air:
          <article-title>OrHow the Clean Air Act Became a Multibillion-Dollar Bail-Oat for High-Sulfur Coal Producers and What Should Be Done about It (Yale</article-title>
          <year>1981</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          21
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Korobkin</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 83 Cornell L Rev at
          <volume>611</volume>
          (cited in note 18)
          <article-title>(suggesting that "when lawmakers anoint a contract term the default, the substantive preferences of contracting parties shift-that term becomes more desirable, and other competing terms becom[e] less desirable"</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          5
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Guido</given-names>
            <surname>Calabresi</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            <surname>Douglas</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Melamed</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Property Rules,
          <source>Liability Rules, and Inalienability: One View of the Cathedral, 85 Harv L Rev</source>
          <volume>1089</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1090</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          (
          <year>1972</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>51 On marriage and legal rules, see generally Susan Moller Okin, Justice, Gender,and the Family (Basic</article-title>
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          52 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Human Behavior and the Law of Work, 87 Va L Rev</source>
          <volume>205</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>208</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          53 See the demonstrations in Korobkin, 83 Cornell L Rev at
          <volume>633</volume>
          -64 (cited in note 18), and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kahneman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Knetsch, and Thaler, 5
          <source>J Econ Persp at 194-204 (cited in note 43).</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          54
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Camerer</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Prospect Theory in the Wild at 294-95 (cited in note 30);</source>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
          </string-name>
          , et al, Framing,ProbabilityDistortions,InsuranceDecisionsat
          <volume>238</volume>
          (cited in note 30).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          60 See, for example,
          <source>Ian J. Bateman and Kenneth G</source>
          . Willis, eds,
          <source>Valuing Environmental Preferences (Oxford</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <article-title>But see Peter A. Diamond and Jerry A</article-title>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hausman</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Contingent Valuation:
          <source>Is Some Number Better than No Number?, 8 J Econ Persp</source>
          <volume>45</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that contingent valuation surveys fail to accurately measure willingness to pay preferences with regard to public goods); Note, "Ask a Silly Question</article-title>
          ...
          <source>": Contingent Valuation of Natural Resource Damages</source>
          , 105 Harv
          <string-name>
            <surname>L Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1981</year>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          )
          <article-title>(criticizing contingent valuation in ascertaining natural resource damages, on the grounds that it produces biased results that will lead to unfair liability burdens).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          61 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ian J. Bateman</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Kenneth G.
          <article-title>Willis, Introduction and Overview</article-title>
          , in Bateman and Willis, eds,
          <source>Valuing Environmental Preferences</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          (cited in note 60).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>62 See generally id.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          63
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>John W. Payne</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>James R. Bettman</surname>
            , and
            <given-names>David A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Schkade</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Measuring Constructed Preferences: Towards a Building Code, 19 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>243</volume>
          ,
          <issue>266</issue>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>64 See id at 245-47.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>70 See note 8 and accompanying text.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          71
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Shane</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Frederick</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Measuring IntergenerationalTime Preference: Are Future Lives Valued Less?, 26 J Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          )
          <article-title>(finding that imputed intergenerational time preferences can be dramatically affected by the specific question asked).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          72 See Richard L. Revesz, Environmental Regulation,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cost-Benefit Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>and the Discounting of Human Lives, 99 Colum L Rev</source>
          <volume>941</volume>
          ,
          <issue>947</issue>
          ,
          <fpage>987</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1016</lpage>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>(arguing that the discounting of harms to future generations is "ethically unjustified"</article-title>
          );
          <string-name>
            <surname>Edward R. Morrison</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Comment,
          <source>JudicialReview of Discount Rates Used in Regulatory Cost-Benefit Analysis</source>
          , 65
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
            <surname>Chi L Rev</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>1333 (</article-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing the ethical and economic dimensions of the debate over the appropriate discount rate for regulations and other public projects).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          73
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Revesz</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 99 Colum L Rev at
          <volume>996</volume>
          -1007 (cited in note 72).
          <article-title>We are not suggesting that the preferences of current generations are decisive on the policy question</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          74 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Maureen L. Cropper</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sema K. Aydede</surname>
            , and
            <given-names>Paul R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Portney</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Preferencesfor Life Saving Programs:
          <article-title>How the Public DiscountsTime</article-title>
          and Age, 8
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
            <surname>Risk</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <source>Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>243</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ); Maureen L. Cropper,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sema K. Aydede</surname>
            , and
            <given-names>Paul R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Portney</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Rates of Time Preferencefor Saving Lives, 82 Am Econ Rev</source>
          <volume>469</volume>
          ,
          <issue>472</issue>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          75 Cropper, Aydede, and Portney,8
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
            <surname>Risk</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <source>Uncertainty at 244 (cited in note 74).</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>76 See id at 245-46 (explaining survey methodology).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          77
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Frederick</surname>
          </string-name>
          , 26
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
            <surname>Risk</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>Uncertainty at 50 (cited in note 71) ("Many of the elicitation procedures tested here indicate no substantial discounting of future lives.").</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>