<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Public Law and Legal Theory Working Papers 2004</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Eric A. Posner</string-name>
          <email>eric_posner@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Law and Legal Theory Working Papers by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Recommended Citation Cass R. Sunstein &amp; Eric Posner, "Dollars and Death", University of Chicago Public Law &amp; Legal Theory Working Paper No.</institution>
          <addr-line>71, 2004</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <fpage>25</fpage>
      <lpage>66</lpage>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Follow this and additional works at</kwd>
        <kwd>https</kwd>
        <kwd>//chicagounbound</kwd>
        <kwd>uchicago</kwd>
        <kwd>edu/ public_law_and_legal_theory</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>JOHN M. OLIN LAW &amp; ECONOMICS WORKING PAPER NO. 222 (2D SERIES)</title>
      <p>Dollars and Death
Eric A. Posner and Cass R. Sunstein</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>THE LAW SCHOOL</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</title>
      <p>September 2004
September 5, 2004
Preliminary draft</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>Forthcoming University of Chicago Law Review</title>
        <p>All rights reserved
Abstract. Administrative regulations and tort law both impose controls on activities that
cause mortality risks, but they do so in puzzlingly different ways. Under a relatively new
and still-controversial procedure, administrative regulations rely on a fixed value of a
statistical life representing the hedonic loss from death. Under much older law, tort law in
most states excludes hedonic loss from the calculation of damages, and instead focuses on
loss of income, which regulatory policy ignores. Regulatory policy also disregards losses to
dependents; tort law usually allows dependents to recover for loss of support. Regulatory
policy generally treats the loss of the life of a child as equivalent to the loss of the life of an
adult; tort law usually treats the loss of the life of a child as less valuable. Regulatory policy
implicitly values foreigners as equal to Americans; tort law does not. We argue that both
areas of law make serious mistakes in valuing life and that each should learn from the
other. Regulatory policy properly focuses on hedonic loss from death, and tort law should
adopt this approach. But regulatory policy should imitate tort law’s individualized approach
to valuing the loss from death, including its inclusion of losses to dependents. If these
changes were made, tort awards would be more uniform and predictable, and regulations
would be less uniform and more stringent. In addition, average tort damages for wrongful
death would be at least twice as high as they are today. With respect to dollar judgments for
mortality risks, a pervasive issue is how to combine accuracy with administrability and
predictability; both bodies of law could do far better on this score.</p>
        <p>How should the legal system assign dollar values to human lives? Consider a
highly publicized example.</p>
        <p>On September 22, 2001, Congress enacted legislation to compensate the survivors
of the attacks of eleven days earlier.1 Under the final regulations,2 survivors were
permitted to claim amounts for both economic and non-economic losses. The economic
losses were to be measured by calculating each victim’s expected lost wages from
* Kirkland and Ellis Professor of Law, University of Chicago Law School.
** Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago, Law School
and Department of Political Science. Thanks to Matthew Adler, Ward Farnsworth, Robert Hahn, Saul
Levmore, Richard Posner, Adrian Vermeule, and W. Kip Viscusi for comments, and to Nikkie Eitmann,
Josh Kluewer, Wayne Hsiung, Gavin Martinson, and Andres Sawicki for research assistance. Posner thanks
the Russell Baker Scholars Fund for financial support.
1 Air Transportation Safety and System Stabilization Act, § 405(c)1-2, 49 U.S.C § 40401 (2001).
2 See http://www.usdoj.gov/victimcompensation/. For discussion, see Symposium, 53 DePaul L Rev 205
(2003).</p>
        <p>September 11, 2001 through the anticipated date of retirement, subject to several
adjustments, including a reduction by an estimate of household consumption or
expenditure by the victim. Noneconomic losses were set at $250,000 per victim plus
$100,000 per surviving spouse and for each surviving child.3</p>
        <p>In all, 2,878 families, about 97 percent of those eligible, received compensation
from the fund, with amounts ranging from a low of $250,000 to a high of $7.1 million;
the average award totaled about $2.1 million per family.4 Hence there was significant
variability among awards. But the variability came amidst a serious effort to produce
presumptive floors and caps, with a “baseline” for single decedents of $300,0005 and a
commitment to allow awards exceeding $3,000,000 only in unusual circumstances. These
awards have been attacked on multiple grounds, including excessive and insufficient
variability.6</p>
        <p>The September 11 awards reflect a strong influence from tort law, which they
simultaneously modify. But in American law, tort doctrines provide only one of two sets
of rules for monetizing death. The other comes from administrative regulations, and there
are striking contrasts between the two bodies of law. One of our main goals here is to
bring the two in contact with one another.</p>
        <p>Countless regulations now attempt to reduce statistical risks. Cost-benefit analysis
must generally accompany these regulations, at least if their costs are high,7 and to
undertake that analysis, agencies must turn human lives into monetary equivalents.8 For
example, the Environmental Protection Agency values each life at a uniform number,
most recently $6 million.9 Through tort law, courts provide a set of fact-specific awards
3 28 C.F.R. § 104.44 (2004).
4 See David W. Chen, After Weighing Value of Lives, 9/11 Fund Completes Its Task, The New York
Times, June 16, 2004, at A1.
5 66 Fed Reg 66,274-75.
6 See Alina Tugend, Lives in the Balance, The National Journal Government Executive, September 2003, at
50; David W. Chen, Man Behind Sept. 11 Fund Describes Effort as a Success, With Reservations, The
New York Times, January 1, 2004, at B3.
7 See Stephen Breyer et al., Administrative Law and Regulatory Policy 120-35 (5th ed. 2002).
8 A general overview can be found in Office of Management and Budget, Regulatory Analysis, Circular
A4 (September 17, 2003), available at http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/inforeg/regpol.html#rr
9 See 66 Fed. Reg. at 7012. In its July 2003 regulation governing food labeling of trans fatty acids, the Food
and Drug Administration used a VSL of $6.5 million, see 68 Fed. Reg. 41434, 41488 (July 11, 2003); in its
March 13, 2003 proposed rule on dietary ingredients and dietary supplements, the same agency suggested a
VSL of $5 million, see 68 Fed. Reg. 12158, 12229 (using this value to calculate the “value of a statistical
life day”).
that attempt to compensate for and to deter wrongful death. The resulting awards are
highly variable. For example, courts have recently given successful plaintiffs as little as a
few thousand dollars and as much as tens of millions of dollars.10</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding their overlapping goals, administrative regulations and tort law
diverge from one another in dramatic and puzzling ways. The most obvious difference is
that tort law generally disregards the welfare loss to the person who has died; regulatory
policy treats that loss as its central and indeed exclusive focus. Consider a few other
differences:</p>
        <p>Tort law focuses directly on the loss to dependents;11 regulatory policy pays
no attention to that loss.12
disregards lost income.</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-1-1">
          <title>Tort law makes damages a function of lost income; regulatory policy</title>
          <p>Some individuation has been suggested by the interest in statistical life-years, a measure that
naturally produces a higher degree of particularity. Office of Management &amp; Budget, Circular A-4,
Regulatory Analysis, at 30 (Sept. 17, 2003), available at
http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/circulars/a004/a4.pdf. More specifically, the guidelines say:</p>
          <p>Another way that has been used to express reductions in fatality risks is to use the life expectancy
method, the "value of statistical life-years (VSLY) extended." If a regulation protects individuals whose
average remaining life expectancy is 40 years, a risk reduction of one fatality is expressed as "40 life-years
extended." Those who favor this alternative approach emphasize that the value of a statistical life is not a
single number relevant for all situations. In particular, when there are significant differences between the
effect on life expectancy for the population affected by a particular health risk and the populations studied
in the labor market studies, they prefer to adopt a VSLY approach to reflect those differences. You should
consider providing estimates of both VSL and VSLY, while recognizing the developing state of knowledge
in this area.</p>
          <p>Longevity may be only one of a number of relevant considerations pertaining to the rule. You
should keep in mind that regulations with greater numbers of life-years extended are not necessarily better
than regulations with fewer numbers of life-years extended. In any event, when you present estimates based
on the VSLY method, you should adopt a larger VSLY estimate for senior citizens because senior citizens
face larger overall health risks from all causes and they may have accumulated savings to spend on their
health and safety.</p>
          <p>The valuation of fatality risk reduction is an evolving area in both results and methodology.
Hence, you should utilize valuation methods that you consider appropriate for the regulatory circumstances.
Since the literature-based VSL estimates may not be entirely appropriate for the risk being evaluated (e.g.,
the use of occupational risk premia to value reductions in risks from environmental hazards), you should
explain your selection of estimates and any adjustments of the estimates to reflect the nature of the risk
being evaluated. You should present estimates based on alternative approaches, and if you monetize
mortality risk reduction, you should do so on a consistent basis to the extent feasible. Id.
10 See below.
11 For this and other statements about tort law, see notes below.
12 See, e.g., Regulatory Analysis, supra note, and 66 FR 6976-01 (2001) (arsenic regulation), in support of
all of the statements in this section on regulatory policy.
Tort law uses a case-specific number to assess damages, making individual
differences crucial; regulatory policy embodies a uniform number per life
saved, one that fails to pay attention to individual differences.</p>
          <p>Tort law focuses directly on the suffering and distress felt by the decreased;
regulatory policy does not attend to that issue.</p>
          <p>Tort law generally treats children as worth less than adults, because survivors
lose less, in economic terms, when children die; regulatory policy generally
treats children as equivalent to adults.13
Tort law treats foreign victims of torts differently from American victims,
implicitly valuing them less, because of deference to local law, unless they are
killed in the United States, in which case American values are used. Insofar as
regulations affect people outside of the country, regulatory policy generally
ignores foreigners altogether, implicitly treating their lives as valueless.</p>
          <p>What accounts for these differences? It is tempting to say that the answer lies in
the conflicting goals of the two sets of controls. While tort law seeks to ensure
compensation, especially for family members, regulatory policy is designed to produce
optimal levels of risk. This point contains some truth. Tort law has long focused on the
compensation of those still living—a focus that naturally leads to disregard of the
deceased, an emphasis on what the plaintiffs have lost, and an interest in a set of highly
individuated awards. By contrast, regulatory policy, which has assigned monetary values
to statistical lives for little more than two decades, is concerned above all with producing
the right deterrent signal, a concern that might seem to explain the use of a single,
uniform number for the valuation of what most matters: the loss of life. But as a full
account of the differences, this explanation is much too simple.14 Tort law does and
should provide deterrence as well as compensation, and if wrongful death actions
produce significant underdeterrence, something is seriously amiss. In any case the
catalogue of differences raises many questions about regulatory policy even if it is
focused on deterrence. If the goal of administrative regulation is optimal risk levels,
13 The recent interest in “statistical life-years” would value children more than adults; see below.
14 We return to this question in Part V.
should regulators really use a uniform value per life saved? Should they disregard the
suffering felt by dependents—and by those who die?15</p>
          <p>For both bodies of law, a pervasive question is how to combine accuracy with
administrability. A simple and uniform number, accompanied by blanket exclusions of
values that are hard to calculate, might well be simplest to administer—and regulatory
policy generally takes this approach.16 In addition, an effort at greater accuracy might
invite interest-group maneuvering; a uniform number provides a degree of insulation
against special pleading. But if full compensation and optimal deterrence are the goals,
then a high degree of individuation should be expected, tailoring dollar amounts to the
precise circumstances of mortality risks. Suppose, for example, that both regulators and
courts possessed “hedometers,”17 costlessly able to calculate the anticipated or actual
loss, to all, from every human death. If hedometers were available, courts could ensure
perfectly accurate compensation, and both courts and regulators would bring about
optimal deterrence, attuned to individual circumstances. If administrative costs were zero,
different agencies should offer a wide range of diverse values for statistical lives, subject
15 It would be possible to argue that both of these are picked up by figures for VSL: we explore that
question below.
16 The most explicit discussions of varying VSL have come from the EPA. In its 2003 discussion of
hazardous air pollutants, see 68 Fed. Reg. 1660, 1693 (Jan. 13, 2003), the EPA noted that there “is general
agreement that the value to an individual of a reduction is mortality risk can vary based on several factors,
including the age of the individual, the type of risk, the level of control the individual has over the risk, the
individual’s attitude toward risk, and the health status of the individual.” Nonetheless, the agency
announced, without offering reasons, that it “prefers not to draw distinctions in the monetary value assigned
to the lives saved even if they differ in age, health status, socioeconomic status, gender or other
characteristic of the adult population.” Id.</p>
          <p>An extended discussion of related issues can be found in the EPA’s arsenic proposal, see 65 Fed.
Reg. 38888, 38945 (June 22, 2000). There the EPA noted that the “factors which may influence the
estimate of economic benefits associated with avoided cancer fatalities include (1) a possible ‘cancer
premium’ (i.e., the additional value or sum that people may be willing to pay to avoid the experiences of
dread, pain and suffering, and diminished quality of life associated with cancer-related illness and ultimate
fatality); (2) the willingness of people to pay more over time to avoid mortality risk as their income rises;
(3) a possible premium for accepting involuntary risks as opposed to voluntary [sic] assumed risks; (4) the
greater risk aversion of the general population as opposed to workers in the wage-risk valuation studies;
(5) ‘altruism’ or the willingness of people to pay more to reduce risk in other sectors of the populationl and
(6) a consideration of health status and life years remaining at the time of premature mortality.” The EPA
acknowledged that these factors “may significantly increase the present value estimate,” but said that “there
is currently neither a clear consensus among economists about how to simultaneously analyze each of these
adjustments nor is there adequate empirical data to support quantitative estimates for all potentially
significant adjustment factors.” Id. Hence the EPA solicited comments on these issues and said that it
would ask its Scientific Advisory Board (SAB) to conduct a review. Id.
17 For those who are skeptical of utilitarian approaches, substitute the term “eudaimeters,” based on the
Greek notion of eudaimonia, establishing a more complex notion of well-being. See Martha Nussbaum,
The Fragility of Goodness (1986).
to the limitation that regulatory programs often apply to many people at once; and courts,
focusing on individual cases, would offer an even wider range of dollar awards in the
event of wrongful death.</p>
          <p>Because administrative costs are high (and also because of political constraints on
inequality18), more uniformity is inevitable; but how much? One of the most noteworthy
features of the comparative exercise is that agencies opt for uniformity, whereas courts
call for a high degree of individuation. Undoubtedly this difference is partly a function of
the ex post focus of wrongful death actions and the ex ante focus of regulation. But it
would be most surprising if the radical difference, on this count, could be justified by that
difference in perspective.</p>
          <p>We believe that both bodies of law can learn a great deal from the other.19 In
particular, we suggest five large-scale reforms. First, agencies should move in the
direction of the more individuated approach of tort law. They should not use a uniform
number per life saved. In addition, they should consider pain and suffering, dread,20 and
loss to dependents. These changes would make a dramatic difference for administrative
practice, replacing the crude current effort to use a single value for statistical lives.
Second, courts should move in the direction of administrative regulation by taking
account of the welfare loss to the decedent. This change would significantly alter
wrongful death cases, by producing far higher recoveries in many cases. Third, agencies
should move in the direction of courts by including the emotional distress and other
welfare losses incurred by dependents; courts should not ignore losses of support for
dependents (as agencies do), but they should offer more accurate and fine-grained
understandings of that figure. These changes would increase the stringency of
administrative regulations and promote less arbitrary figures from courts. Fourth, both
courts and agencies should change their valuation of the deaths of children by taking the
child’s welfare loss seriously while also accounting for the possibility of offsetting
18 See below.
19 There is a third body of relevant law: criminal prohibitions. These prohibitions overlap, to some extent,
with both tort law and administrative regulation, carving out a subset of conduct for special sanctions. By
attending to enforcement levels and sanctions, it might even be possible to deduce an implicit value of life,
or of statistical risks, from criminal law. Ideally, of course, legislators would ensure that all three bodies of
law worked well together, producing the right deterrent signal. For present purposes, however, we put
criminal law to one side.
20On some of the complexities here, see Matthew Adler, Fear Assessment (unpublished manuscript 2004)).
behavior by parents. Fifth, agencies and courts should evaluate mortality risks that are
imposed on foreigners—both resident aliens and nonresident aliens whose mortality is
affected by domestic activities—in a manner that is consistent with the diplomatic
objectives of the political branches.</p>
          <p>This Article is organized as follows. Part I provides the background from both tort
law and regulatory policy. Part II discusses the theoretical basis for valuing human lives.
Part III investigates a range of methodological difficulties and implications. Part IV
proposes reforms to tort law and regulatory policy. Part V explores the question why tort
law and regulatory policy currently take such different approaches to valuing loss of life.
I. Background</p>
          <p>A. How Tort Law Values Loss of Life</p>
          <p>At common law, victims (that is, their estates) and dependents could not recover
damages for wrongful death. As a result, courts did not face the problem of calculating
damages for loss of life. In the nineteenth century, however, many states enacted statutes
that provided for recoveries. Wrongful death statutes provided that dependents, including
spouses and children, may recover damages for lost support. Survival statutes provided
that the victim’s estate may recover damages for certain losses that the victim incurred as
a result of the tort, such as medical expenses and earnings lost between injury and
death.21 Today, most states have one or both types of statutes, or statutes that combine
elements of each type. In addition, there has been much judge-created common law that
can be traced to these statutes. As a general proposition, one can say that courts now
award damages on account of death caused by a tort, but the rules vary widely by
jurisdiction. 22</p>
          <p>Despite the variations, there are common themes. Most courts award
“noneconomic” damages, that is, damages for pain and suffering incurred by the victim as a
result of the tort prior to death, and also for the distress and loss of companionship
21 2 Dan B. Dobbs, Law of Remedies 423 (2d ed. 1993).
22 Id., at 421-445.
suffered by dependents or heirs.23 All states award “economic” damages. In states that
use the “loss to dependents” measure, these damages are supposed to make dependents
whole; roughly, they provide the support that dependents would have received if the
victim had lived. This may be measured as lost contributions from victims to dependents
(housing, food, and so forth), or, more crudely, future income minus victim’s expenses.
In states that use the “loss to estate” measure, damages are supposed to approximate the
victim’s estate if she had lived a natural life—total future income minus expenses.24</p>
          <p>Notice that the non-economic and economic measures do not provide an award
for the loss of life per se—that is, the victim’s “loss of life’s pleasure,” also known as
hedonic damages. Plaintiffs suing on behalf of a victim who has no future income, no
dependents, and no spouse, and who dies without feeling pain, should ordinarily receive
zero damages or damages sufficient only to cover funeral expenses.25 This large category
of people includes elderly people who are living off savings and unemployed or homeless
people. It also includes homemakers, unless an implicit value is assigned to household
services. And it includes children—at least in “loss to dependent” states, because children
do not have dependents who lose support as a result of their death.26</p>
          <p>Of course, this is a matter of formal law; in practice, damages are often awarded
on account of the deaths of people who have no income, and often damages are in excess
of lost income. This is partly because non-economic damages will be available in most
cases, partly because juries are given a great deal of discretion to award damages in
wrongful death cases and are provided little guidance by courts, and partly because courts
use fictions in order to ensure a “reasonable” recovery.27 But if all this is true, then
23 Id. There is every reason to believe that the resulting awards have a high degree of arbitrariness. See
David W. Leebron, Final Moments: Damages for Pain and Suffering Prior To Death, 64 N.Y.U. L. Rev.
256 (1989).
24 Id., at 430-38.
25 E.g., McGowan v. Wright, 524 So.2d 308 (Miss. 1988).
26 In “loss to estate” states, the child’s future income will be calculated, and awarded to parents or heirs.
See Dobbs, supra, at 436.
27 For example, the household services of the child – which in most households, and certainly modern
middle class households, are trivial – may be given a high value. See Dobbs, supra, at 440.
damages for wrongful death are highly arbitrary,28 and indeed this is the conventional
wisdom,29 supported by our own evidence as discussed below.30</p>
          <p>Only five states permit damages for hedonic loss: Arkansas,31 Connecticut,32
Hawaii,33 New Hampshire,34 and New Mexico.35 As a matter of theory, plaintiffs in these
states can recover damages on account of the wrongful death of people who have no
income and otherwise would not be entitled to non-economic damages. However, the
statutes and judicial opinions in these states do not explain the methodology, and judges
usually leave the calculation to the jury, with lax oversight.36 In some cases, courts
appear to misunderstand the nature of hedonic loss—for example, confusing it with lost
income.37</p>
          <p>The upshot is that it is exceptionally hard to predict, as a matter of formal law,
what damages for wrongful death will be in any particular case. However, verdict and
settlement data can be used to paint a rough picture. We examined data from two data
sets: (1) an unscientific Jury Verdict and Settlement data set that provides a wealth of
information about the characteristics of the cases (“JVS”)38; and (2) a more scientific
28 Even aside from the legal confusion, jurors do not do a good job of monetizing losses when provided
with no clear guidance to discipline their judgments. David Schkade et al., Deliberating About Dollars: The
Severity Shift, 100 Colum. L. Rev. 1139 (2000).
29 See, e.g., David Baldus, John C. MacQueen, and George Woodworth, Improving Judicial Oversight of
Jury Damages Assessments: A Proposal for the Comparative Additur/Remittitur Review of Awards for
Nonpecuniary Harms and Punitive Damages, 80 Iowa L. Rev. 1109 (1995).
30 See TAN infra.
31 See Durham v. Marberry, 2004 Ark. LEXIS 179 (interpreting ambiguous 2001 amendment to Arkansas
survival statute (Ark. Code Ann. § 16-62-101(b)) as permitting recovery for hedonic loss).
32 See Katsetos v. Nolan, 368 A.2d 172 (Conn.1976); Chase v. Fitzgerald, 45 A.2d 789 (Conn.1946).
33 See Montalvo v. Lapez, 884 P.2d 345, 364 (Haw. 1994).
34 See Marcotte v. Timberlane/Hampstead School District, 733 A.2d 394 (N.H. 1999).
35 See New Mexico St. §41-2-1 (discussed in Smith v. Ingersoll-Rand Co., 214 F.3d 1235, 1245 (N.M.
2000)). Mississippi briefly allowed damages for hedonic losses in wrongful death cases, but the case that
approved such damages – Choctaw Maid Farms v. Hailey, 822 So.2d 911 (2002) – was overturned by
statute. See Brendan I. Koerner, What’s Your Happiness Worth?, Legal Affairs, January/February 2004.
Hedonic losses may also be permitted in federal civil rights cases involving wrongful death. See Sherrod v.
Berry, 629 F. Supp. 195, 205 (N.D.Ill.1985), rev’d on other grounds, 856 F.2d 802 (7th Cir. 1988); Frye v.
Town of Akron, 759 F. Supp. 1320, 1325-26 (N.D. Ind. 1991). However, it is not yet clear whether other
circuits will follow Sherrod. See Wescott v. Crinklaw, 133 F.3d 658, 660-61 (8th Cir. 1998).
36 See Dobbs, supra, at 445.
37 Cohen suggests that they have not, citing Lengel v. New Haven Gas Co., 111 A.2d 547 (1955), where the
court reversed an award of $60,000 because not justified by the decedent’s lost income; the court did not
mention hedonic loss. See Lloyd Cohen, Toward an Economic Theory of the Measurement of Damages in
a Wrongful Death Action, 34 Emory L.J. 295, 307 (1985).
38 The data are from the Jury Verdict and Settlements, Combined database in Lexis. This data set appears to
have been generated from various local verdict and settlement reporting services, whose selection methods
Civil Justice System data set that contains little information about the characteristics of
cases (“CJS”).39
selected to show the range of real world outcomes.
auto accident (81 years old)
railroad-auto accident (77 years old)
$1.75 million
are not disclosed. Thus, it is unsafe to assume that the data are randomly generated, and indeed Lexis
explicitly disclaims that they are.
39 The data were generated by the Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research. Data and
other information are available online at: http://webapp.icpsr.umich.edu/cocoon/NACJD-STUDY/
03957.xml. The website includes information on verdicts and settlements of tort lawsuits between January
and December 2001 from the 75 largest counties in the United States. These data were randomly generated.
40 We do not include punitive damages, pain and suffering damages, medical expenses, past income, and so
forth, so this category is an attempt to determine the implicit valuation of the loss of life itself. Thus, we do
include (after death) losses to dependents, both economic and noneconomic.
41 The driver was high on drugs; we suspect that in this case, as in other high award cases, the damages
included a punitive element, even though not classified as such.
42 Classified as “pecuniary costs”; it is not clear what this means.</p>
          <p>In the JVS data set, the mean award for loss of life—meaning, usually, lost
income to dependents or the estate, or mental distress to dependents (we tried to exclude
punitive damages, damages for pain and suffering of the victim prior to death, medical
expenses, funeral expenses, and so forth)—was $3.1 million, and the median was $1.1
million. This is roughly consistent with the findings of the CJS survey, in which the mean
was about $3,759,000 and the median was $961,000 for a sample of cases from 2001.43
Thus, the CJS survey suggests that the JVS survey may be reasonably reliable.44 In any
event, it seems clear enough that when outliers are excluded, the tort system values lost
lives at well under $3 million, and about half the time under $1 million.45 We suspect that
the real amounts are somewhat lower; the evidence suggests that awards generally
decline during post-verdict proceedings.46 The considerable variance in both data sets
also supports the conventional wisdom that the damage awards have a degree of
arbitrariness, that is, they are not closely tied to the underlying concerns of the tort
system and are also erratic and unpredictable.47
43 Thomas H. Cohen &amp; Steven K Smith, Civil Trial Cases and Verdicts in Large Counties, 2001, Bureau of
Justice Statistics Bulletin, April 2004, NCJ 202803, at p. 10.
44 Another data set was created by Jury Verdict Research, which claims, or appears to claim, that the data
set is reliable. See Current Award Trends in Personal Injury (43rd ed. 2004). Statistics for 2002 jury awards
(not settlements) are: median $1.6 million; mean $4.7 million; low of $5,809 and high of $100 million. Id.,
at 6. Note that these awards would include such (for us) irrelevant elements as punitive damages. And see
Viscusi’s figures, generated from an earlier Jury Verdict Research data set, which show the same pattern.
See W. Kip Viscusi, Reforming Products Liability 108-09 (1991).
45 We should note the problem of selection effects. Parties may be more likely to settle cases that are likely
to produce high awards both because of risk aversion and of the likely higher litigation costs in high stakes
cases. See A. Mitchell Polinsky, Are Punitive Damages Really Insignificant, Predictable, and Rational? A
Comment on Eisenberg et al., 26 J. Legal Stud. 663, 668 (1997). To be sure, verdicts and settlements data
includes settlements, and the settlements are lower than the verdicts; however, this may reflect the
plaintiff’s risk of losing, a risk that is absent for verdicts. Still, all this means, for our purposes, is that there
is a lot of unexplained variance in the cases: if some high amount, X, is the “real” level of damages for loss
of life, then why are so many verdicts so much lower?
46 See, e.g., Ivy E. Broder, Characteristics of Million Dollar Awards: Jury Verdicts and Final
Disbursements, 11 Just. Sys. J. 349 (1986) (finding that plaintiffs ultimately received about 57 percent of
the verdict); Neil Vidmar et al., Jury Awards for Medical Malpractice and Post-Verdict Adjustments of
Those Awards, 48 DePaul L. Rev. 265 (finding reductions of about 7 to 60 percent in different
jurisdictions).
47 The standard deviation for the JVS data set is $6.1 million, with a minimum of $0 and a maximum of $50
million. We do find it difficult to believe that the data were selected because of their variance, however, so
the variance may be reliable (or else it just reflects gaps and inaccuracies in the data, e.g., treating punitive
damages as if they were economic loss damages). In the CJS data set, the standard deviation is $11.7
million, with a minimum of $705 and a maximum of $120 million, according to our own calculations. For
analysis of product liability cases, See W. Kip Viscusi,, International Review of Law and Economics
(1988); W. Kip Viscusi, J. Legal Studies (1988); W. Kip Viscusi, J. Legal Studies (1986).</p>
          <p>Hence two points emerge from the wrongful death cases. The first is that in
principle, the law calls for a highly individuated approach, one that recognizes a wide
range of factors that bear on the degree of loss to dependents. The second is that in
practice, actual awards on account of loss of life are usually well below $3 million and
also characterized by great variance.</p>
          <p>B. How Regulatory Policy Values Loss of Life</p>
          <p>As we have noted, agencies now assign monetary values to human lives. The
practice is recent, having become systematized only as a result of an executive order from
1981.48 For a period, agency figures were highly and inexplicably variable.49 With some
exceptions, however, most regulatory agencies have now converged on a fairly narrow
range for the valuation of life: $5 million to $6.5 million. Consider the following table,
accounting for agency valuations in the recent past:
48 See Exec. Ord. 12291, Fed. Reg. (1981). For discussion of the origins of cost-benefit balancing in federal
regulation, see Richard Pildes and Cass R. Sunstein, Reinventing the Regulatory State, 62 U. Chi. L. Rev. 1
(1995).
49 See Matthew D. Adler and Eric A. Posner, Implementing Cost-Benefit Analysis When Preferences Are
Distorted, 29 J. Legal Stud. 1105 (2000)
Dept. of Health &amp; Human
Services/FDA
Dept. of Health &amp; Human
Services/FDA
Dept. of Agriculture/Food Safety &amp;
Inspection Service</p>
          <p>Control of Emissions from Nonroad Large
Spark-Ignition Engines, and Recreational
Engines (Marine &amp; Land-Based)
November 8, 2002
67 FR 68242-01
National Primary Drinking Water Regulations:
Arsenic and Clarifications to Compliance and
New Source Contaminants Monitoring
January 22, 2001
66 FR 6976-01
Control of Air Pollution from New Motor
Vehicles: Heavy-Duty Engine and Vehicle
Standards and Highway Diesel Fuel Sulfur
Control Requirements
January 18, 2001
66 FR 5002-01
Control of Air Pollution from New Motor
Vehicles: Tier 2 Motor Vehicle Emissions
Standards and Gasoline Sulfur Control
Requirements
February 10, 2000
65 FR 6698-01
Findings of Significant Contribution and
Rulemaking on Section 125 Petitions for
Purposes of Reducing Interstate Ozone
Transport
January 18, 2000
65 FR 2674-01
Final Standards for Hazardous Air Pollutants for
Hazardous Waste Combustors
September 30, 1999
64 FR 52828-01
National Primary Drinking Water Regulations:
Disinfectants and Disinfection Byproducts
December 16, 1998
63 FR 69390-01
Financial Responsibility Requirements for
Licensed Launch Activities
August 26, 1998
63 FR 45592-01
Quality Mammography Standards
October 28, 1997
62 FR 55852-01
Regulations Restricting the Sale and Distribution
of Cigarettes and Smokeless Tobacco to Protect
Children and Adolescents
August 28, 1996
61 FR 44396-01
Pathogen Reduction; Hazard Analysis and
Critical Control Point (HACCP) Systems
July 25, 1996
61 FR 38806-01
$6 million
Consumer Product Safety
Commission
Consumer Product Safety
Commission</p>
          <p>Aircraft Flight Simulator Use in Pilot Training,
Testing and Checking and at Training Centers
July 2, 1996
61 FR 34508-01
Requirements for Labeling of Retail Containers
of Charcoal
May 3, 1996
61 FR 19818-01
Large Multiple-Tube Fireworks Devices
March 26, 1996
61 FR 13084-01</p>
          <p>What is the source of these numbers? The answer involves real-world markets,
producing evidence of compensation levels for actual risks.50 In the workplace and for
consumer goods, additional safety has a price; market evidence is investigated to identify
that price.51 Agency valuations are largely a product of studies of actual workplace risks,
attempting to determine how much workers are paid to assume mortality hazards.52 The
relevant risks usually are in the general range of 1/10,000 to 1/100,000.53 The calculation
of the value of a statistical life is a product of simple arithmetic. Suppose that workers
must be paid $600, on average, to eliminate a risk of 1/10,000. If so, the value of a
statistical life would be said to be $6 million. Additional information comes from
contingent valuation studies, asking people how much they are willing to pay to reduce
statistical risks of death.54 But studies of this kind are not the foundation of agency
policies in the domain of mortality risks, apparently on the theory that real-world
evidence is more reliable.</p>
          <p>Several features of agency practice are noteworthy by way of comparison to
wrongful death actions. The most obvious is that agencies provide a uniform number;
they make no effort to individuate, even though more individuation would not be
50 See W. Kip Viscusi, supra.
51 A valuable and comprehensive overview can be found in W. Kip Viscusi and Joseph E. Aldy, The Value
of a Statistical Life: A Critical Review of Market Estimates Throughout the World, 27 J. Risk and
Uncertainty 5 (2003).
52 See Viscusi, Fatal Tradeoffs, supra note, for discussion.
53 See, e.g., W. Kip Viscusi, The Value of Life: Estimates With Risks by Occupation and Industry, 42
Econ. Inquiry 29, 33 (2004) (showing fatality risks ranging from about 1/100,000 to 45/100,000).
54 See, e.g., James Hammitt and Jin-Tau Liu, Effects of Disease Type and Latency on the Value of
Mortality Risk, 28 J. Risk and Uncertainty 73 (2004); George Tolley et al., Valuing Health For Policy
(1995); Valuing Environmental Preferences (Ian Bateman &amp; K. G. Willis eds., 1999); Peter Diamond &amp;
Jerry Hausman, Contingent Valuation: Is Some Number Better Than No Number, 8 J. Econ. Persp. 45,
4952 (1994); Note, Ask A Silly Question, 105 Harv L Rev 1981 (1992).
difficult. In addition, agencies use a higher (average) value for loss of life to the victim
but place no value on losses to spouses, friends, and others who suffer a welfare loss,
economic and otherwise, in the event of death. The uniform numbers, refusing to make
inquiries that would lead to less uniformity or that would be difficult to administer, are
not surprising in light of the comparative youth of regulatory valuation and in light of the
controversial nature of imaginable distinctions. More accurate, and more complex,
valuations might be expected to follow an initial period in which assignment of some
number of statistical lives becomes entrenched. But these points raise the theoretical
questions that bear on both judicial and administrative practice.</p>
          <p>C. A Comparison: The September 11 Victim Compensation Fund</p>
          <p>As we mentioned at the outset, the September 11 Fund was influenced by tort
principles, and it is instructive to compare the awards to dependents of deceased victims
of the September 11 attacks both with tort wrongful death awards and with agency
valuations of life. Table 3 displays the comparison.
Agency55</p>
          <p>Mean
$3.8 million
$2.0 million
$5. 4 million</p>
          <p>Median</p>
          <p>Minimum</p>
          <p>Maximum
$961,000
$1.7 million
Note: Tort awards from the CJS data set (2001); Sept. 11 awards from Fund Website;56 agency valuations
from Table 2 (post-2000). The Sept. 11 data are based on amounts received after deductions for life
insurance payments, and the like; they therefore understate true valuations, probably by a few hundred
thousand dollars.57</p>
          <p>The Sept. 11 fund has a higher median but lower mean than the tort system does.
The lower mean is due to the lack of extreme awards characteristic of the tort system.
The higher median is probably due to two factors: (1) inflation from 2001 to 2004; and
55 The agency statistics cannot be straightforwardly compared to the statistics for the other systems, because
the former will vary depending on the relative size of the populations that the different regulations affect.
Still, they give a general sense of the differences.
56 Available at: http://www.usdoj.gov/victimcompensation/payments_deceased.html. The website provides
the mean, median, and range; we calculated the standard deviation from the raw data (also provided by the
website).
57 See the examples provided at: http://www.usdoj.gov/victimcompensation/award_summaries.pdf. We
have been unable to find the appropriate statistics.</p>
          <p>Standard</p>
          <p>Deviation
(2) the much higher average income of the September 11 victims compared to that of the
general population. Putting aside the outliers, then, the Sept. 11 Fund and tort awards
seem largely consistent, and both are much lower than agency valuations. What the Sept.
11 Fund shares with agency valuations is the much lower degree of variance than that
found in the tort system.</p>
          <p>II. Theory: Why Should Loss of Life Be Valued?</p>
          <p>Many people believe that a human life is uniquely precious and therefore cannot
be given a monetary valuation.58 Calculating the value of a human life demeans the
victim of the wrong rather than vindicating his memory. The intuition is understandable.
But for purposes of law and policy, what is the alternative? Awarding zero damages for
wrongful death is hardly less demeaning, and an award of an “arbitrary” amount of
money—either the jury or the legislature should pick a number out of thin air—is no
better. Similarly, it is hard to believe that regulatory policy should assume that human life
is worth nothing or, alternatively, that it has some arbitrary value.</p>
          <p>To understand how loss of life should be valued, we need to understand the social
purposes such a practice would advance. There is no acontextual method for assigning
monetary values to mortality and mortality risks. We start with tort law, which is
conventionally said to have two goals: deterrence and compensation.59 Then we turn to
regulatory policy, which shares tort law’s goal of deterrence.</p>
          <p>A. Tort Law and Deterrence</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>1. Principles of Tort Damages</title>
        <p>The tort system has two purposes: compensation and deterrence. Frequently, but
not always, the two purposes lead in similar directions. If the victim of a wrongful death
action cannot be compensated, deterrence is still a possibility. The question we now
investigate is what level of damages produces optimal deterrence of wrongful death. Our
basic conclusion is that two approaches are formally equivalent and will accomplish that
task: a monetary amount, before any harm occurs, that is the multiple of the magnitude of
58 See Frank Ackerman and Lisa Heinzerling, Priceless: On Knowing the Price of Everything and the Value
of Nothing (2004).
59 E.g., Erny v. Estate of Merola, 792 A.2d 1208, 1217 (N.J. 2002).
the harm and its probability, assessed for every person who is made to face the relevant
risk; or a monetary amount, after the harm occurs, that reflects the magnitude of the
harm. The choice between the two approaches largely depends on questions of
administrability.60</p>
        <p>To understand how deterrence works, one must take an ex ante perspective.61
Suppose that at time 1 the legal rules are chosen; at time 2 everyone chooses how to act
and what level of care to take; and at time 3 injuries and deaths occur, and liability and
damages are determined for wrongful death actions. On the deterrence approach, we want
to choose legal rules at time 1 that produce damages at time 3 that give everyone optimal
incentives at time 2.</p>
        <p>As is well known, people can be given optimal incentives to take care if they are
required to pay damages for any financial losses that they cause (or negligently cause).62
Imagine, for example, that a particular behavior, such as driving, will cause $1000 in
losses if an accident occurs. A driver can control the probability that the loss will occur
by taking more or less care. The cost of care increases with the amount of care that is
taken. The efficient level of care is the amount at which the marginal cost of care equals
the expected marginal cost of an accident. By requiring the tortfeasor to pay damages, the
law forces the driver to internalize the losses that she creates, and so she will take
precautions when the costs of those precautions are less than the expected losses.63</p>
        <p>We can think of the victim’s loss in two equivalent ways. We can say that the
victim incurs the cost of the accident, L, at time 3. In our example, L = $1000. This is the
“ex post” loss. Alternatively, we can say that the victim incurs an expected loss of pL at
60 There are also equitable issues here; from the equitable point of view, perhaps it is worse to compensate
everyone ex ante for risks than to compensate those for harm when those harms come to fruition (insurance
practices are obviously relevant to an evaluation). But our focus here is on deterrence, and we do not
engage those issues.
61 As should be apparent, we are not dealing here with intentional killings, as in cases of homicide. It is not
clear that the risk of being murdered should be analyzed in the same way as the risks ordinarily involved in
wrongful death cases, which typically involve negligence in one or another form. Difficult questions are
raised by the evident fact that people would be willing to pay different amounts to avoid statistically
identical risks: A 1/100,000 risk of a cancer death is different from a 1/100,000 risk of a sudden
unanticipated death (as we stress), and a 1/100,000 risk of being strangled, or of being killed in a terrorist
attack, would undoubtedly produce its own distinctive numbers.
62 To keep things simple, we assume throughout that only the tortfeasor can control the probability of an
accident. This allows us to focus on the optimal level of damages for loss of life. We also focus on optimal
incentives to take care, in which case the tort rule can be either strict liability or negligence.
63 William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, The Economic Structure of Tort Law (1987); Steven Shavell,
Economic Analysis of Accident Law (1987).
time 1, where p is the probability of the accident at time 3. This is the “ex ante” loss.
From an economic perspective, these losses are equivalent. If an insurance market exists,
people are assumed to be indifferent between being awarded pL, as potential victims, at
time 1, and L, as actual victims, at time 3.64 Insurers will set the premium equal to pL,
and they will pay out L if the accident occurs. Tort law, in theory, could either require all
drivers to pay all potential tort victims pL at time 1, or (as in fact) only drivers who cause
accidents to pay only actual victims L at time 3. If the insurer is subrogated (as is usually
the case), then the victim is indifferent between these two systems, as is the insurer.
Potential victims who want insurance can use their “damages” of pL under the first
system to pay for the insurance premium, and simply collect from the driver under the
second system without going through the insurance intermediary. Potential victims who
do not want insurance could purchase an investment instrument that pays pL at time 1 in
return for the chance of L at time 3.65</p>
        <p>Why does the tort system award damages of L to actual victims rather than
damages of pL to potential victims, when the two awards are equivalent? A large part of
the answer is one of practicality. Potential victims cannot be easily identified in advance,
and many risks are difficult or even impossible to calculate. In the unusual cases when
the reverse is true—when courts cannot award L to actual victims because the loss will
occur in the distant future—some courts have been willing to force potential tortfeasors
to pay potential victims damages equal to pL.66 Thus, tort law does not, in principle, bar
awards of pL rather than L; its focus on L stems from the fact that L is a far simpler
foundation for judicial decisions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>2. Valuing Loss of Life</title>
        <p>Now let us turn to the problem of measuring L when the loss is death. To fix
intuitions, suppose that the (multiply unfortunate!) victim of the wrongful death tort has
no dependents, no spouse, no friends, and no income; suppose too that the death was
instant, involving no pain, suffering, dread, or medical expenses. Putting aside funeral
64 We put to one side some complexities with this assumption.
65 Cf. Robert Cooter and Ariel Porat, Anti-Insurance, 31 J. Legal Stud. 203 (2002).
66 See Matthew D. Adler, Risk, Death and Harm: The Normative Foundations of Risk Regulation, U. Minn.
L. Rev. 1419-21 (forthcoming 2004) and citations therein (discussing tort cases that recognize torts for
increasing the risk of death).
control) is based on a cost-benefit analysis that values foreign lives and American lives
equally, at the American level. Under the stated assumptions, the second redistributes
resources from Americans to people living in other countries. Which regulation is
superior?</p>
        <p>In the abstract, the answer is hardly clear, and the question cannot be sensibly
approached without consideration of American foreign policy toward the nations that
benefit from the regulation. Let us consider the relation between the U.S. and, say, India.
The two states can gain a lot from each other by cooperating, but there is also a danger of
conflict. To simplify, suppose that the U.S. wants three things from India: security
cooperation (such as flyover rights); an open market for U.S. goods; and an improvement
in the treatment of religious minorities. India seeks from the U.S. similar things:
diplomatic assistance with its ongoing disputes with Pakistan; an open market for Indian
goods; and an improvement of American treatment of Indian residents. Suppose that at a
hypothetical stage 1, India and the U.S. achieve a balance between their aims: each gives
a little of what the other wants.</p>
        <p>Now at stage 2, an American regulatory agency issues an environmental
regulation that happens to benefit India considerably, and at great cost to American
citizens. At this point, the American diplomatic authorities might argue that because the
U.S. is conferring a new benefit on India (say, less flooding of coastal areas), India
should respond by conferring a new benefit on the U.S. (say, more trade). India could
respond by saying thanks for reducing coastal flooding—that is important—but it is not
more important to us than preserving our domestic X industry. In short, the new
regulation disturbs the cooperative equilibrium between the U.S. and India: the U.S.,
perceiving itself as giving more than it is getting, will (in theory) respond by withdrawing
some other benefits, and India will retaliate. The new equilibrium could involve a lower
level of cooperation—one in which the U.S. gives India something of little value to India
and so gets something of little value in return—unless the U.S. government can change
the regulation in a way that benefits India less.141</p>
        <p>Our point is that under certain circumstances, regulations and tort rules that are
based on inflated foreign VSLs will redistribute wealth from Americans to foreign
141 Of course, that may be impossible, in which case cooperation should not decline.
governments. Such transfers would not be wildly popular in the abstract, at least among
Americans. They may nonetheless be desirable for reasons of foreign policy or social
justice, but they should be recognized as such; the use of the inflated VSL conceals the
magnitude of the transfer and even its nature. Further, transfers—whether disguised
through inflated VSLs or undisguised—should cohere with foreign policy; otherwise,
they will lead to perverse results or be ineffective. The simple conclusion is that in many
imaginable circumstances, a high VSL, for people in other countries, will produce
perverse redistribution or redistribution for which there is no strong claim—and that even
when the redistribution through a high VSL seems desirable (because it benefits poor
people on balance), there are many questions about whether regulatory agencies should
adopt it. It follows that as a general rule, both agencies and courts should use a VSL that
attempts to match the figure in the relevant nation.</p>
        <p>IV. Proposals for Reform</p>
        <p>A. Use of VSL in Regulations</p>
        <p>Tort law offers two principal lessons for regulatory policy. The first involves the
need for a greater degree of individuation. The second involves the need to pay attention
to the interests of dependents. A properly designed system of valuation would move
substantially in both directions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>1. Individuation</title>
        <p>We have seen that under the theory that agencies now use, VSL is calculated on
the basis of people’s willingness to pay. That very theory raises serious doubts about the
government’s use of a uniform number. The appropriate value varies across both risks
and persons. If, for example, the risk is accompanied by a high degree of pain and
suffering, it deserves more attention than if it is not—a conclusion that is supported by
studies finding a kind of “premium” for bad deaths.142 Agencies should therefore provide
a higher VSL for cancer risks than for other risks, a possibility that EPA has recognized
142 See Revesz, supra note.
in its “sensitivity analysis” for arsenic.143 A great deal more should be done in this
vein.144 As tort law demonstrates, a uniform number is extremely difficult to defend.</p>
        <p>Variations across persons are important as well. To be sure, it is impractical to
think that regulators should fully individuate risks across persons, in part because
regulations often affect many people at once. But less fine-grained distinctions are
possible. For example, people over sixty tend to show a lower VSL than people between
thirty and forty.145 Regulators might build on these figures to generate different numbers
for programs protecting people at different points along the age spectrum. Putting the
difficult case of children to one side, agency rules should have a lower value when the
benefited class consists largely of elderly people. A movement in this direction would
have significant consequences for valuation; it would drive down the monetized benefits
of a number of programs delivering health gains largely to senior citizens.</p>
        <p>Additional distinctions are possible. If a program would benefit largely wealthy
people, regulators might use an unusually high VSL—a point that would support a higher
VSL for safety decisions involving airlines (the exact opposite, not incidentally, of
current practice, which involves an unusually low number for airline safety146). More
controversially, programs protecting the poor might be given a lower VSL, in a way that
tracks the approach of tort law, at least where those who benefit from regulation are also
paying for it. A possible objection to this approach is that in some circumstances, a high
VSL, for the poor, might be beneficial to the poor, simply because they receive benefits
for which they pay only a fragment. We do not resolve the obvious empirical and ethical
complexities here.147 We note simply that a higher degree of individuation would be
desirable, that in most cases it would raise no serious ethical problems, and that tort law
shows that a movement toward greater individuation is both feasible and consistent with
longstanding practices and intuitions.
143 See note supra.
144 See Sunstein, supra note.
145 Joseph P. Aldy and W. Kip Viscusi, Age Variations in Workers’ Value of a Statistical Life (2003),
forthcoming.
146 See Table 2, supra, showing a lower figure for the FAA than for the EPA.
147 See Sunstein, supra.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-5">
        <title>2. Dependents.</title>
        <p>For regulatory policy, the most obvious gap is that agency numbers do not recognize the
fact that a death causes welfare losses to many people other than the victim. If a worker is
killed as a result of carcinogens in the workplace, others will almost always be affected.
Agency failure to take account of the welfare losses results in numbers that are far too
low.</p>
        <p>We have suggested the importance of distinguishing between two sets of losses:
grief on the one hand and lost income on the other. Following tort law, full individuation
would take account of the fact that the size of those losses very much depends on the
particular situation. Other things being equal, the loss of a parent with six young children
causes more serious harm than the loss of someone without dependents. If our earlier
calculations are correct, several million dollars would be added to the conventional
assessment of the benefits of a regulation that saved that parent’s statistical life. A serious
difficulty here is that agency regulations protect broad classes of people and hence it is
quite impractical to think that agencies should make fully individual judgments about the
welfare losses. But it is not impractical to think that agencies should adjust their numbers
in a way that ensures that serious welfare losses are not ignored. As in the case of
statistical risks, contingent valuation studies and market evidence might be consulted to
generate appropriate numbers for grief. We have offered some suggestions about how
this might be done. For regulations, individual assessments are of course impossible, but
a positive number is better than no number, and population-wide means would be a
sensible place to start.</p>
        <p>In the regulatory context, there is a cautionary note. Any effort at individuation
would have a high degree of political salience and would undoubtedly mobilize affected
interests. Even if the social science were less ambiguous than it now is, well-organized
groups would undoubtedly engage in special pleading, attempting to move agency
practices in their preferred directions. A uniform number helps to insulate agencies from
the relevant pressures. In the context of tort suits, individuation does not face those
pressures, and hence there is little need for insulation. In principle, however,
individuation is clearly desirable, and it seems quite pessimistic to think that the effort to
produce greater accuracy should be rejected because of the possible effects of
interestgroup maneuvering.</p>
        <p>B. Use of VSL in Tort Law
In wrongful death actions, damages should be calculated in the following way.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-6">
        <title>1. The Hedonic Loss of the Victim</title>
        <p>For deterrence purposes, the tortfeasor should pay the amount that the victim
would be willing to pay to avoid the risk that was imposed on him by the tortfeasor’s
class of actions, divided by that risk (R/q). Damages should not be based on lost income;
as in the regulatory context, lost income is at best a proxy for the victim’s loss.
Deterrence can be satisfied through payment to the government, but if it is paid to the
estate or dependents, then indirect compensation is also achieved.</p>
        <p>The amount can be calculated in two ways. First, the VSL (or VSLY) used by
agencies could be used, with any adjustments as necessary to reflect individual factors:
the defendant’s risk preference, life expectancy (if VSLY is used), wealth, quality of life,
and so forth. Indeed, it is possible that the victim’s own wages will reflect his VSL, if he
has a risky job. So long as agencies use a uniform figure, courts might start with the
standard $6 million figure, and then make adjustments as appropriate. If agencies used
more refined figures, as we have argued that they should, then courts might begin with
those figures instead, and make appropriate adjustments from that amount. Second, the
jury could be asked to determine the hedonic loss. However, the proper jury question is
not “what is the value of the life’s pleasures lost by the victim?” This question is too
abstract. A better question would be: “estimate the amount of money that the victim
would have paid to avoid the risk in question.” 148 Of course an abstract answer to that
question would be unreliable; VSL studies should be used to educate juries about
common valuations, so that their own estimates will be informed rather than arbitrary.149
148 Arlen argues that courts are incapable of making such calculations, claiming that “courts’ inaccurate
calculations would come no closer to efficient recovery amounts than would legislation establishing a flat
statutory amount for wrongful death in the hope that the results would be efficient on average.” Arlen,
supra, at 1134. It might be true that legislatures can do better than courts, but that is no argument for
awarding zero damages or an (arbitrary) constant amount instead. Recall too that we are not exploring the
complex issues raised by the possible difference between willingness to pay and willingness to accept.
149 Many courts have refused to admit testimony about VSL studies, arguing that the science does not meet
the Daubert standard. See, e.g., Ayres v. Robinson, 887 F. Supp. 1049 (N.D. IL 1995). This seems to us a
mistake. For a discussion, see Reuben E. Slesinger, The Demise of Hedonic Damages Claims in Tort
Litigation, 6 J. Legal Econ. 17 (1996). Some courts also reject VSL studies on the ground that these studies
To ensure consistent and rational awards, we would strongly prefer the first approach, on
the ground that juries are not well-equipped to answer these questions; but if a strong role
for the jury is deemed important, the second would also work so long as the jury’s
judgments are disciplined by expert witnesses and the court.</p>
        <p>This reform would have a significant impact on tort awards, especially for the
elderly in non-hedonic loss states. We can already see the logic of our argument at work
in some of the hedonic loss states. Consider Thomas v. Hilburn,150 in which the jury
awarded wrongful death damages of $300,000 to the son of the 75 year old victim. On
appeal, the defendant argued that damages should be reduced to $66,311 for lost income,
plus a few thousand dollars more for medical expenses, funeral expenses, and property
damage. The court rejected the argument because Mississippi was (at the time) a hedonic
loss state. Although our approach would have suggested a verdict of a few million or so,
depending on the wealth and other characteristics of the victim, the court clearly
recognized the key point that the hedonic loss of an elderly man is much higher than his
lost income.151</p>
        <p>In the tort context, there is an additional complication. Valuation of statistical
risks has occurred for risks of specified magnitudes, usually ranging from 1/10,000 to
1/100,000.152 Insofar as tort law is dealing with risks in this range, use of agency figures
is fully appropriate. But it should be clear that these numbers need not be taken to support
a VSL that is independent of probability.153 Suppose that people would be willing to pay
$60 to eliminate a risk of 1/100,000. From this it does not follow that people would be
willing to pay $6000 to eliminate a risk of 1/1000, or $60,000 to eliminate a risk of 1/100,
reflect the losses to other people, not to the victim who is the subject of the tort dispute. However, courts
frequently use statistics about other people in order to award damages in tort cases. For example, when
courts calculate lost income in order to determine damages for dependents, they use mortality tables; these
tables are based on the lives of other people, not on the victim’s own life, which would not make any sense.
Just as courts use statistics about other people in order to estimate the victim’s life expectancy, courts
should use statistics about other people in order to estimate how much the victim would have been willing
to pay in order to avoid a risk of death.
150 654 So. 2d 898, 903 (Miss. 1995).
151 See also Motorola Communications and Electronics, Inc. v. Wilkerson, 555 So. 2d 713 (Miss. 1989)
(allowing $150,000 award for the death of an 85 year old man); Marcotte v. Timberlane/Hampstead Sch.
Dist., 733 A.2d 394, 407-08 (N.H. 1999) (allowing $900,000 award for the death of a child whose lost
future income was about $700,000). New Hampshire also recognizes hedonic losses in wrongful death
cases. See supra.
152 See, e.g., W. Kip Viscusi, The Value of Life: Estimates With Risks by Occupation and Industry, 42 Ec.
Inquiry 29, 33 (2004) (showing fatality risks ranging from about 1/100,000 to 45/100,000).
153 See Richard Posner, Catastrophe: Risk and Reason (forthcoming 2004).
or $600,000 to eliminate a risk of 1/10. It is plausible to believe that people’s WTP to
reduce statistical risks is nonlinear.154 As the probability approaches 100%, people
become willing to pay an amount for risk reduction that rises nonlinearly to 100% of their
income, and—at some point—become unwilling to accept any amount in return for
giving up their entitlement to life.155 From this it follows that if a defendant imposes risks
that are far higher than those with which agencies deal, the agency figures are too low,
and hence the tort system should use significantly higher ones.</p>
        <p>The sheer variety of wrongful death actions, in terms of both probability and kind
of death, severely complicates the inquiry into appropriate damage awards. Insofar as the
tort system is dealing with probabilities in the general range with which agencies deal, it
can build on (appropriately reformed) agency practice. Insofar as the tort system is
dealing with the most egregious conduct—homicide, for example—the regulatory
analysis of WTP does not apply directly, but a standard amount of (say) $6 million at
least provides an appropriate floor. Insofar as the conduct imposes high probability risks,
as through gross negligence, a similar floor is appropriate, supplemented perhaps by
punitive damages. These suggestions are in line with our general emphasis on the fact
that all mortality risks are not the same. What cannot be defended is the total exclusion of
hedonic damages in wrongful death actions.
154 See id.
155 There is a great deal of work on disparities between willingness to pay and willingness to accept
(WTA). See, for an overview, Russell Korobkin, The Endowment Effect and Legal Analysis, 97 Nw. U.L
Rev. 1227 (2003). Such disparities are found in the context of risks. See, e.g., see W. Kip Viscusi et al., An
Investigation of the Rationality of Consumer Valuations of Multiple Health Risks, 18 RAND J. Econ. 465
(1987). It follows that people would pay less to eliminate a risk of 1/100,000 than they would demand to be
subject to that same risk. See id. One advantage of the market data on which agencies currently rely is that
the WTP/WTA disparity is essentially irrelevant. If workers and consumers who face a risk of 1/100,000
receive $60 in compensation, the result can be described in terms of either WTA or WTP; any such
description is simply a matter of framing. But we lack reliable market data about how to value much higher
risks -- say, risks of 1/50, 1/20, or 1/10. And for such risks, willingness to accept and willingness to pay
figures surely diverge, not least because the income constraint applies to WTP but not to WTA. People
would undoubtedly pay a great deal to eliminate a mortality risk of 1/20; but they would demand even more
to be subject to that risk, and many people would not incur that risk for any amount. It is not entirely clear,
in principle, whether WTP or WTA is appropriate, though our view is that willingness to accept is correct
and therefore the appropriate compensatory award is either infinite or higher than anyone can pay. Thus, a
billionaire who murders someone ought to forfeit his entire wealth. As a practical matter, however, it
probably does not make much difference that the tort system does not generate such high awards, given that
the entire wealth of most murderers is extremely limited.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-7">
        <title>2. Harm to Survivors</title>
        <p>As we have seen, calculating the loss to survivors is difficult in practice, but
conceptually straightforward. For deterrence purposes, survivors should recover for their
welfare loss—this means grief, mental distress, loss of companionship, and the like. It is
less clear what dependents should recover in terms of lost support (such as lost income
attributable to their care). The conceptually proper recovery is the amount of money that
would make the survivor just as well off (financially) as he would have been if the death
had not occurred, which will usually be tied to the loss of household economies of scale
and the breadwinner’s degree of altruism. This amount may be higher than lost income (if
the victim does a lot of work for the household that is not compensated in the market).
And it may be lower (if the survivor can easily get a job and the victim was never very
generous in the first place).</p>
        <p>If our approach were adopted, tort damages would rise, especially for children and
the elderly. As we have seen, damages for wrongful death are currently under about $3
million, based on lost income, mental distress, and the like. Under our system, they are
likely to be as much as $6 million or higher for the average person. As for children, tort
damages currently should be low in jurisdictions that exclude lost income (though it is
not clear that this is the case); and for the elderly, tort damages currently should be (and
apparently are) low even in jurisdictions that include lost income, given that their earning
years are almost over. By contrast, under our approach their damages are likely to be,
again, in the $6 million or higher range.156 For adults with dependents, we suspect that an
additional several hundred thousands of dollars per dependent would be added to the $6
million baseline. 157
156 Elderly people apparently have VSLs that are either equal to (or even higher than) or not much lower
than those of younger people. See Aldy &amp; Viscusi, supra.
157 If the victim incurs unusual pain and suffering prior to death, including the distress of anticipating one’s
own death in the near future, this cost may not be reflected in standard VSLs. Thus, additional damages
should be awarded for them. Damages for medical and funeral expenses should also be awarded. See Mark
Geistfeld, Placing a Price on Pain and Suffering: A Method for Helping Juries Determine Tort Damages for
Nonmonetary Injuries, who suggests using WTP estimates, 83 Calif. L. Rev. 773 (1995). See also David
W. Leebron, Final Moments: Damages for Pain and Suffering Prior To Death, 64 N.Y.U. L. Rev. 256
(1989).
V. Positive Questions</p>
        <p>Our comparison of tort law and regulatory policy raises an obvious positive
question. Why do these two areas of law take such different approaches to valuing lives?
The beginning of an answer to this question is that even though the two areas of law have
an overlapping purpose—the deterrence of harmful conduct—they also have radically
different historical origins and orientations: tort law is ex post and individualized, while
regulatory law is ex ante and generalized. As a result, tort law is naturally more
particularistic and less rule-bound. The ex ante focus of regulation pushes administrators
away from case-specific standards and in the direction of rule-bound judgments. But this
point raises many complexities.</p>
        <p>A. In General</p>
        <p>Tort law’s ex post and individualistic orientation has several consequences. First,
the implicit (or explicit) valuation of human lives in the tort context is information-rich.
Courts have access to a great deal of evidence about the particular parties and
circumstances. Under the rules of evidence, all relevant evidence may be introduced to
the court, and both plaintiff and defendant have strong incentives to take advantage of
these rules. Given that the victim is a real, identifiable person, it is natural for the court to
determine the actual loss, including losses to dependents, rather than to rely on statistical
averages. In fact there is no need to rely on such averages, which provides less accurate
information than the facts themselves.</p>
        <p>Second, tort remedies direct the decisionmaker to compare the victim’s post-tort
state with her pre-tort state, and to ignore the rest of society. This approach works well
enough when the tort causes a financial loss or a physical injury, but when it kills the
victim, the decisionmaker has no way to compare post-tort and pre-tort well-being in a
way that can be reliably monetized. To determine the hedonic loss from death, one cannot
look at the actual victim’s experience of death; one can rely only on statistical inference
based on generalization from the rest of society. But in view of judicial traditions, this
would be unfamiliar and even odd in the tort setting.</p>
        <p>Third, and following from the first two points, tort damages tend to be highly
variable. Juries lack reference points, so their judgments will depend heavily on the
presentation of evidence by lawyers, and on whatever anchors,158 prejudices, and
expectations citizens bring to the jury box. Juries might also react emotionally to the case,
or misunderstand jury instructions, and allow irrelevant factors (like a desire for revenge)
to influence their determination of the award.</p>
        <p>Fourth, tort law has low public visibility, at least at the system-wide level.
Individual awards may receive considerable public attention, but the system of awards—
the median award, the mean award, the variance—does not.159 Hence public scrutiny is
relatively weak unless and until a salient network of awards (as in the case of the
September 11 fund) is announced. The difficulties of monetization, the variable figures,
and the possible arbitrariness of many outcomes attract little in the way of scrutiny and
review, not least because of the ex post nature of litigation and the fact that awards are
issued one at a time.</p>
        <p>Compare regulatory law. Regulatory decisions are ex ante and highly abstract.
The victims of the regulated conduct are not identified, and so their personal
characteristics do not stand out (although sometimes a disaster or crisis may provoke the
regulation160). Whereas court cases are emotionally rich, regulatory decisions often
(though not always) seem dry and technical, even though usually much more is at stake.</p>
        <p>The ex ante and general orientation of regulatory policy has several consequences.
First, because one cannot identify the actual people benefited by a regulation, one must
rely on averages. The usual notion is that although all individuals are different,
differences will balance each other out, so that averages can be used. Thus, if a regulation
protects people of type X with a VSL of $7 million and people of type Y with a VSL of
$5 million, regulators use the average valuation of $6 million for a regulation that affects
people evenly divided into the two types.
158 On the relevance of anchors, see Gretchen Chapman and Eric Johnson, in Heuristics and Biases: The
Psychology of Intuitive Judgment (Thomas Gilovich et al. eds. 2002).
159 Indeed, the extreme awards that receive media attention are, according to some, too rare to be a matter
of concern. See Deborah Jones Merritt and Kathryn Ann Barry, Is the Tort System in Crisis? New
Empirical Evidence, 60 Ohio St. L.J. 315 (1999). A similar argument has been made about punitive
damages; see Theodore Eisenberg, Neil LaFountain, Brian Ostrom, David Rottman, and Martin T. Wells,
Juries, Judges, and Punitive Damages: An Empirical Study, 87 Cornell L. Rev. 743 (2002) (arguing that
punitive damages are roughly correlated with compensatory damages); but see and Joni Hersch and W. Kip
Viscusi, Punitive Damages, 33 J. Legal Stud. 1 (2004) (disputing this claim).
160 See Timur Kuran and Cass R. Sunstein, Availability Cascades and Risk Regulation, Stan L Rev (1999).</p>
        <p>This reasoning is not implausible, and sometimes averages are appropriate despite
their crudeness; but they can lead regulators astray. Some regulations affect only persons
of type X, and other regulations affect only persons of type Y; then different valuations
should be used. Indeed, we know that some regulations protect people against cancer, a
risk that people are willing to pay a premium to avoid, whereas other regulations protect
people against sudden unanticipated death, a risk that occasions less in the way of public
concern.161 So too, some regulations affect the poor more than the rich, urban people
more than rural people, and so forth. Under the very theory that animates current
regulatory practice, individualized VSLs, taking account of these differences, are
important.</p>
        <p>Second, regulatory decisions affect more people than a tort award does, and thus
are more politically salient. The greater political salience of regulatory decisions may
have good effects simply because public scrutiny can be a corrective against ill-motivated
or foolish decisions; but here we focus on some bad or troubling effects. The most
obvious is that the symbolism of sensible and disaggregated regulatory decisions may
bother people because such decisions seem in conflict with other values—here, we have
in mind the controversy valuing human lives at all, or the likely more intense controversy
over valuing the lives of the rich more than the lives of the poor.162 The risks of public
skepticism may also explain agencies’ failure to value the lives of children properly and
openly.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the isolation of tort awards suppresses these symbolic concerns.
Almost no one complains about the fact that poor people obtain lower damages in tort
awards because they have lost less future income; and the existence of the disparity, and
its longstanding character, at least raises problems for those who believe that ethical
principles require all deaths to be valued the same way. But it appears to be politically
difficult to draw the logical conclusion that VSLs for poor people should be lower than
VSLs for rich people in regulatory decisionmaking.
161 See Revesz, supra note; Hammit and Liu, supra note.
162 Consider the controversy over the idea of “life years,” an idea that strikes many people as ethically
problematic because it treats elderly people as less valuable than younger people. See Ackerman and
Heinzerling, supra note.</p>
        <p>We are unable to explain why agencies have neglected the losses to dependents.
One possible answer is that agencies assume that victims’ WTPs for bearing risks of
death incorporate these costs; but as we have explained, it is unlikely that these WTPs
incorporate these costs fully. Another possible answer is lack of information; it is not
easy to generate a plausible number to capture the costs to dependents on some
population-wide basis. But this problem ought to be remediable. A probable contributor
to the gap is that cost-benefit analysis and the use of VSLs is in its infancy—as a formal
part of regulatory law, it is only about twenty-five years old163—and agencies have
focused on the large problems while neglecting or overlooking more subtle issues. But it
is now time for the VSL methodology to advance to a new stage of sophistication.</p>
        <p>B. September 11 and Compensation</p>
        <p>The different orientations of tort and regulatory law were reflected in an
interesting way by the decisionmaking process of the commission that was set up to
award compensation to victims of the 9/11 terrorist attack. We have briefly outlined the
resulting regulations. Before returning to this topic, let us conduct two thought
experiments.</p>
        <p>First, suppose that Congress had never set up the 9/11 compensation fund, and
instead the victims and survivors had sued under state tort law. Suppose they succeeded
in establishing the liability of defendants such as the airlines. How would damages have
been awarded? It is clear that wealth differences would have been seen in wrongful death
and survivors’ awards. The dependents of investment bankers would have obtained
awards far in excess of those obtained by the dependents of fire fighters. In addition, the
awards would have varied significantly in light of the different characteristics of each
victim. But there also would have been considerable inexplicable variance in the awards,
variance that would not be traceable to relevant factors but to the vagaries of jury
decisionmaking and the law of tort. Hence inequalities would have been pervasive—
some a justified product of existing rules, others a result of simple “noise” in the system.</p>
        <p>Second, suppose that an agency had, prior to the 9/11 attack, issued regulations
designed to force the owners of buildings such as the World Trade Center to install safety
devices that would have saved lives in case of a terrorist attack or similar disaster. Here,
163 See Executive Order 12291, supra.
we can be sure that the agency would have used uniform valuations—such as $6.1
million per life saved—that would have ignored wealth differences and other differences
between victims. The agency would also have ignored dependents.</p>
        <p>How did the 9/11 commission make its decisions? On the one hand, the
commission was directed by Congress to rely on tort principles, and for that reason it
used formulas that took into account wealth differences.164 Estates of investment bankers
did receive more compensation than estates of fire fighters.165 In addition, awards were
an increasing function of the number of dependents. On the other hand, public and
political discomfort with these disparate awards—which seemed to dishonor the fire
fighters, and also to distinguish victims along class lines—led the commission to adopt
awards that were less dispersed than would have occurred under the tort system.166</p>
        <p>There is a lesson here. Because individual tort cases concern just one person or a
few people, awards are unlikely to be politically salient or to be influenced by irrelevant
political considerations. But because they are ex post and individualized, they usually fail
to take advantage of information that is accessible only at the level of the general
population. The 9/11 Commission combined the virtues and flaws of both approaches.
Because of the political salience of the task, and because awarding damages to thousands
of people made comparison easy and obvious, the commission was constrained, like
regulatory agencies, to use relatively uniform numbers; recall that a standard number was
used for noneconomic damages. At the same time, arbitrariness was therefore limited—in
the sense that people in similar circumstances received similar awards. Because the
commission was directed to use tort principles, the numbers were not fully uniform, and a
degree of individual variation was properly allowed. But the use of tort principles also
made it impossible to use figures for hedonic losses, and instead the commission relied
on flawed figures such as lost income, with the result that average awards—in the $2 to
164 See Explanation of Process for Computing Presumed Economic Loss, available at
http://www.usdoj.gov/victimcompensation/loss_calc_deceased.html.
165 For example, the spouse of a 40 year old with an income of $50,000 would receive a little over $1
million, whereas the spouse of a 40 year old with an income of $225,000 would receive about $3.5 million
– not including non-economic loss. See Explanation of Process for Computing Presumed Economic Loss,
supra.
166 See Chen, Man Behind, supra, at B3 (“The statute suffered from two conflicting impulses: to follow the
standards of lost future income typical in tort cases, while at the same time making the fund fair to all
income groups, Mr. Feinberg [the special master] said. He ultimately devised the program to prevent it
from favoring the wealthy over the financially disadvantaged, he said.”)
$3 million range—were less than the hedonic losses that actually occurred, according to
the VSL methodology used by agencies.167</p>
        <p>In normal situations, significant improvements are possible. Courts can, and ought
to, take advantage of information about average persons when the relevant information
about a particular victim is lacking (such as WTP to avoid the risk that produced
death).168 And although politics will always constrain agencies, there are certainly many
steps that agencies can take to improve their use of VSLs without running afoul of
political constraints. At a minimum, we see no reason why agencies cannot estimate the
losses to dependents of people who are killed by regulated conduct, and it seems likely to
us that at least some kinds of individualization will be possible—by, for example, giving
a premium for risks that are especially dreaded.</p>
        <p>Conclusion</p>
        <p>In the United States, two independent bodies of law assign dollar values to deaths.
Regulatory agencies, drawing on willingness to pay studies, use a uniform number that
takes no account of losses to dependents and others. In wrongful death actions, courts
attempt to compensate survivors, failing to incorporate the loss to the decedent and
ensuring a high degree of variability in awards. For both bodies of law, deterrence is an
important goal, and from the standpoint of deterrence, both make serious blunders. And
for both, a key question is how to combine accuracy and administrability.</p>
        <p>There are two central problems with regulatory law. First, the value of a statistical
life is uniform rather than disaggregated. The very theory that underlies current practice
calls for far more in the way of individuation. Second, agency figures do not include the
losses to dependents and others; the result is underdeterrence. We have made suggestions
about how agencies might remedy these two problems. The central problem with tort law
is that it does not include the welfare loss to the decedent; its current reliance on the
decedent’s pre-death losses and the dependents’ losses results in undervaluation of
167 And, bizarrely, death benefits for soldiers and public safety officials as the basis for non-economic, that
is, mental distress, compensation for the dependents of victims. See Explanation of Process for Computing
Presumed Economic Loss, supra.
168 Compare the proposal of Baldus et al., supra.
morality risks, and hence underdeterrence. We have also made suggestions about how
both bodies of law should deal with the deaths of children and foreigners.</p>
        <p>If our recommendations were accepted, we would expect tort awards to become
higher, more uniform, and less arbitrary than they currently are. We would also expect
VSLs used by regulatory agencies to be more variable—in many cases lower and in many
cases higher. The inclusion of losses to dependents should result in more stringent
regulations, as the effective benefit from a life saved would be increased.</p>
        <sec id="sec-3-7-1">
          <title>Readers with comments should address them to: Eric A. Posner University of Chicago Law School 1111 East 60th Street</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sec-3-7-2">
          <title>Cass R. Sunstein</title>
          <p>University of Chicago Law School
1111 East 60th Street
Chicago, IL 60637
csunstei@midway.uchicago.edu
10.
216.
217.
218.
221.
222.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list/>
  </back>
</article>