<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>National Security, Liberty, and the D.C. Circuit Recent Decisions of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Cass R. Sunstein, "National Security, Liberty, and the D.C. Circuit Recent Decisions of the United States</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>73</volume>
      <fpage>2004</fpage>
      <lpage>2005</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit," 73 George Washington Law Review 693 (2004).</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>Circuit</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>When the country faces a genuine threat, how should judges approach
conflicts between national security and freedom? In the aftermath of
September 11, this question has become one of the most pressing in all of
American law.</p>
      <p>It is easy to imagine two extreme positions that federal courts might
adopt: National Security Fundamentalism and Liberty Perfectionism.'
National Security Fundamentalists understand the Constitution to call for a
highly deferential role for the judiciary, above all on the ground that when
national security is threatened, the president must be permitted to do what
needs to be done to protect the country. For National Security
Fundamentalists, courts should adopt a strong presumption in favor of allowing the
president to do as he wishes. If the president cannot safeguard the nation's
security, who will? By contrast, Liberty Perfectionists insist that in times of
war, at least as much as in times of peace, federal judges must protect
constitutional liberty.2 Indeed, Liberty Perfectionists believe that under
circumstances of war it is all the more important that federal judges take a strong
stand on behalf of liberty.3 Liberty Perfectionists emphasize that when
national security is at risk, unjustified public panics are likely, even inevitable.
If federal judges do not protect liberty in the face of panic, who will?</p>
      <p>We can also imagine a third approach: minimalism. 4 Minimalists believe
that, in the most controversial areas, judges should refuse to endorse any
large-scale approach and should be reluctant to adopt wide rulings that will
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor, Law School and Department of
Political Science, University of Chicago. This Essay is a sibling to the discussion in Cass R.
Sunstein, Minimalism at War, 2004 Sup. CT. REV. 47; there is significant overlap between the two
essays. My focus here, however, is on the particular practices of the D.C. Circuit and other
lower federal courts, whereas my focus there is on the general practice of minimalism.</p>
      <p>1 See, e.g., Eric A. Posner &amp; Adrian Vermeule, Accommodating Emergencies, 56 STAN. L.
REV. 605, 606-10 (2003); Samuel Issacharoff &amp; Richard H. Pildes, Between Civil Libertarianism
and Executive Unilateralism:An Institutional Process Approach to Rights During Wartime, 5
THEORETICAL INQUIRIES L. 1, 1-2 (2004), at http://www.bepress.com/til/default/vol5/issl/artl.
National Security Fundamentalism is an extreme version of what Posner and Vermeule call the
accommodationist view; Liberty Perfectionism is akin to what they deem the strict enforcement
view. See Posner &amp; Vermeule, supra, at 605-10. Their target is the civil libertarian concern that
accommodationist rulings will weaken liberty during peacetime and that during emergencies the
government will respond to unjustified public panic. See id.</p>
      <p>2 See generally DAVID COLE, ENEMY ALIENS: DOUBLE STANDARDS AND
CONSTrruTIONAL FREEDOMS IN THE WAR ON TERRORISM (2003).</p>
      <p>3 This is one reading of GEOFFREY R. STONE, PERILOUS TIMES: FREE SPEECH IN
WARTIME FROM THE SEDITION AcT OF 1798 TO THE WAR ON TERRORISM (2004).</p>
      <p>4 On minimalism in general, see CAss R. SUNSTEIN, ONE CASE AT A TIME: JUDICIAL
MINIMALISM ON THE SUPREME COURT (1999).</p>
      <p>June 2005 Vol. 73 No. 4
bind the country in unforeseen circumstances. Instead, minimalists want
judges to rule narrowly and cautiously. In the context of war, minimalists
would like courts to avoid constitutional issues by, for example, holding that
Congress has not authorized the executive to intrude into the domain of
constitutionally protected interests. Minimalists also like to avoid broad judicial
pronouncements about either presidential power or liberty, preferring
instead close consideration of particular measures. In the aftermath of
September 11, minimalists want courts to proceed in small steps, leaving the
largest issues undecided as long as possible.</p>
      <p>This Essay has three goals. The first is to sketch the rise of National
Security Fundamentalism in various places, above all the United States Court
of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. Notably, the Supreme Court
has not yet embraced National Security Fundamentalism; on the contrary,
the Court appears to have repudiated it.5 But National Security
Fundamentalism has played a prominent role in the Department of Justice, in a
remarkable opinion by Justice Clarence Thomas, and in a number of lower-court
decisions. If the risk of terrorism increases, and if the nation is hit with
additional serious terrorist attacks, the temptation to embrace National Security
Fundamentalism might well prove overwhelming.</p>
      <p>My second goal is to provide a brief outline of the tension between
National Security Fundamentalism and the Constitution. I suggest that the
latter provides no room for the former and that a number of loose statements in
the recent past are based on a mistaken understanding of the founding
document. My third and final goal is to understand the appeal of a
constitutionally mischievous approach to liberty amidst war. I suggest that National
Security Fundamentalism is especially tempting for lower courts consisting of
judges appointed by a Republican president and asked to assess actions, by a
Republican president, that are designed to protect national security. When
national security is threatened, Republican appointees are exceedingly likely
to defer to Republican presidents. This is especially so on the lower courts,
which are likely to be most reluctant to invalidate acts of the commander in
chief of the armed forces. Some of the more disturbing rhetoric in recent
decisions by the D.C. Circuit, and by trial courts within that circuit, is best
understood in this light.</p>
      <p>I.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>National Security Fundamentalism</title>
      <p>It should be unsurprising to find that, in the aftermath of the attacks of
September 11, National Security Fundamentalism has obtained a great deal
of support. As I have noted, the Supreme Court has refused to accept it, at
least thus far. 6 But the basic approach can be found in many places, most
prominently in Washington, D.C.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>A. Justice Clarence Thomas in Hamdi</title>
      <p>In recent Supreme Court decisions involving the war on terrorism,
National Security Fundamentalism failed to attract a majority opinion.7 But it
made a conspicuous appearance in a remarkable dissenting opinion by
Justice Clarence Thomas in Hamdi v. Rumsfeld.8 In Justice Thomas's view, the
Constitution accords to the president the "primary responsibility ... to
protect the national security and to conduct the Nation's foreign relations."9
And Justice Thomas emphasized, very broadly, that any constitutional
judgment in this domain should consider "basic principles of the constitutional
structure as it relates to national security and foreign affairs."10 Hence,
judicial judgments should be made against the backdrop set by the president's
inherent and broadly discretionary power to protect national security."</p>
      <p>With respect to the courts, Justice Thomas contended that "it is crucial
to recognize that judicialinterference in these domains destroys the purpose
of vesting primary responsibility in a unitary Executive."'1 2 Judges "lack the
relevant information and expertise to second-guess determinations made by
the President. ' 13 In fact, congressional grants of power should be construed
generously on the president's behalf, rather than narrowly, so as to fit with
institutional limits on the power of the judiciary.1 4 Because the executive
branch of the federal government has an "overriding interest in protecting
the Nation," it can invoke that interest to justify depriving people of liberty.1 5
In fact, Justice Thomas argued in favor of broad constructions of
congressional grants of authority partly to avoid constitutional difficulties:
"Although the President very well may have inherent authority to detain those
arrayed against our troops, I agree with the plurality that we need not decide
that question because Congress has authorized the President to do so."16</p>
      <p>Justice Thomas's opinion is a form of National Security Fundamentalism
because of its breadth and ambition. There is no effort here to offer a
cautious ruling tailored to the facts of the particular case. On the contrary,
Justice Thomas speaks generally about the "primary responsibility" of the
president in the domain of "national security. ' 17 In addition, he adopts a
kind of interpretive principle in favor of presidential authority-suggesting,
at least implicitly, that statutes should be read in a way that does not conflict
with the president's inherent authority.' 8 But from a reading of the
Constitution alone, it would not be entirely clear whether the president or the
Congress has primary responsibility in the domain of national security-an issue
to which I will return. The important point is that Justice Thomas offers a
distinctive vision of the constitutional structure, one that accords principal
authority to the president and a small or even nearly nonexistent role for
courts, and thus exemplifies National Security Fundamentalism.
B.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>The Department of Justice</title>
      <p>In recent years, the most visible moment for National Security
Fundamentalism came from the Office of Legal Counsel of the Department of
Justice, with its 2002 memorandum on the legality of coerced interrogation.1 9
The most remarkable aspect of the memorandum is its suggestion that, as
commander in chief of the armed forces, the president of the United States
has the inherent authority to torture suspected terrorists so as to make it
constitutionally unacceptable for Congress to ban the practice of torture.20
The Office of Legal Counsel emphasized that "the President enjoys complete
discretion in the exercise of his Commander-in-Chief authority and in
conducting operations against hostile forces. '21 In addition, the Office of Legal
Counsel insisted that a core function of the commander in chief includes
interrogation of the enemy. 22 Because of "the President's inherent
constitutional authority to manage a military campaign against al Qaeda and its
allies," congressional enactments "must be construed as not applying to"
interrogations undertaken as part of the president's commander-in-chief
authority.23 "Any effort by Congress to regulate the interrogation of battlefield
combatants would violate the Constitution's sole vesting of the
Commanderin-Chief authority in the President. '24 Hence, coercive interrogation,
including torture, must be permitted if the president wants to engage in it.</p>
      <p>Constitutional interpretation is, of course, very much a function of
institutional role. Those who work for the House of Representatives or the
Senate might well be expected to aggrandize the powers of Congress; those who
19 See Memorandum from the Office of Legal Counsel, United States Department of
Justice, to Alberto R. Gonzales, Counsel to the President (Aug. 1, 2002) [hereinafter OLC
Memorandum] (regarding "Standards of Conduct for Interrogation under 18 U.S.C. §§ 2340-2340A"),
available at http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/nation/documents/dojinterrogationmemo
20020801.pdf. This was the most visible moment for National Security Fundamentalism, but
perhaps not the most extreme one. In Rumsfeld v. Padilla,the president claimed that, as
commander in chief, he had the inherent power to order military authorities to seize an American
citizen in the United States without any judicial approval and to hold him indefinitely,
incommunicado, with no access to a lawyer, a court, family, or friends, and without even informing his
family or friends what they had done with him. See Brief for the Petitioner at 35-38, Rumsfeld
v. Padilla, 124 S. Ct. 2711 (2004) (No. 03-1027). I discuss Padillabelow.</p>
      <p>20 See OLC Memorandum, supra note 19, at 31.
21 Id. at 33.
22 See id. at 38.</p>
      <p>23 Id. at 34. To be sure, the position of the Department of Justice was stated with a degree
of tentativeness. It announced that it "will not read" the congressional ban on torture as
applying in the context of battlefield interrogations. Id. at 34. So phrased, the suggestion is a form of
minimalism, asking for avoidance of the constitutional issue by reading the statute so as not to
intrude on the president's authority as commander in chief. See id. But the general impression
is that the ban probably should be regarded as unconstitutional.</p>
      <p>24 Id. at 39.
work for the Department of State might well be expected to exaggerate the
authority of the president. The Office of Legal Counsel is part of the
executive branch, operating directly under the attorney general, and one of its
major functions is to protect the constitutional prerogatives of the president,
especially those prerogatives that are associated with the commander-in-chief
power. Generous interpretations of the president's prerogatives should be
expected from any office within the Department of Justice, above all when
national security is at risk. But in its endorsement of presidential power, the
memorandum on coerced interrogation went well beyond ordinary practice.
To be sure, the president has inherent authority to oversee battlefield
operations, and Congress has limited power to control such operations. The
president also has the inherent authority to conduct interrogations amidst war.
But, to say the least, it is unusual to say that this authority includes the power
to torture people when Congress has expressly said otherwise. The power to
command the armed forces is not easily taken to include "inherent" power to
torture enemy combatants. Even if it does include that power, it is hard to
contend that Congress cannot provide protection against torture.25</p>
      <p>Whatever one's ultimate judgment on the merits, the memorandum of
the Office of Legal Counsel provides a dramatic example of National
Security Fundamentalism.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>C. National Security Fundamentalismand the D.C. Circuit The President</title>
      <p>and "the War Power"</p>
      <p>In the years since the September 11 attacks, National Security
Fundamentalism has played a large role on the lower federal courts.26 A single
circuit has decided most of the key cases involving a conflict between
national security and individual liberty: the United States Court of Appeals for
the District of Columbia Circuit. That court has shown a remarkable
tendency toward National Security Fundamentalism. In every case in which a
serious challenge was mounted to the power of the president, the president
has prevailed in the D.C. Circuit. Let us investigate a few examples.</p>
      <p>One of the most striking decisions from the D.C. Circuit is Center for
National Security Studies v. Department of Justice.27 In that case, a divided
court of appeals permitted an extraordinary level of secrecy from the
executive branch. Its reasoning is far more important than its (plausible)
conclu25 See Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube Co. v. Sawyer, 343 U.S. 579, 644 (1952) (Jackson, J.,
concurring). Note that in some applications, the commander-in-chief power is more plausibly
read to include the power to torture-when, for example, torture is deemed necessary to prevent
an imminent attack on American troops. But even here, Congress almost certainly has the
authority to forbid the practice of torture.</p>
      <p>26 The principal exception is Padilla v. Rumsfeld, 352 F.3d 695 (2d Cir. 2003), rev'd on
other grounds, 124 S. Ct. 2711 (2004), in which the United States Court of Appeals for the
Second Circuit held that the president could not detain Padilla because he lacked the inherent
authority to do so and because Congress had not authorized the detention of American citizens on
American soil. See id. at 712-18, 722-23. This is an example of minimalism in action, as
discussed in Part IV infra.</p>
      <p>27 Ctr. for Nat'l Sec. Studies v. Dep't of Justice, 331 F.3d 918 (D.C. Cit. 2003), cert. denied,
540 U.S. 1104 (2004).
sion, simply because of its broad pronouncements about presidential
authority.</p>
      <p>A number of public interest groups invoked the Freedom of Information
Act ("FOIA"),2 8 the common law, and the First Amendment to require the
government to release information about those who had been detained in the
aftermath of the September 11 attacks. 29 The requested information
included names, dates of arrest and release, and reasons for detention. 30 The
disclosure request had a strong democratic justification: evaluation of the
executive's behavior could not easily come from a public not provided with this
information. In ruling that disclosure was not required, the court relied on a
broad interpretation of exemption 7(A) of FOIA, which exempts "records or
information compiled for law enforcement purposes.., to the extent that the
production ...31 could reasonably be expected to interfere with enforcement
proceedings."</p>
      <p>As Judge Tatel emphasized in dissent, the court's interpretation of this
exemption was contestable; the court could easily have gone the other way.32
What is most important is that the court was exceptionally deferential to the
government's vague statements about potential harms.33 The court was
entirely aware of this point. In language that is closely linked to Justice
Thomas's dissenting opinion in Hamdi, the court emphasized:
[T]he judiciary owes some measure of deference to the executive in
cases implicating national security, a uniquely executive
purview .... We have consistently reiterated the principle of deference
to the executive in the FOIA context when national security
concerns are implicated.... [W]e have consistently deferred to
executive affidavits predicting harm to the national security, and have
found it unwise to undertake searching judicial review.34</p>
      <p>Indeed, the court went so far as to comment specifically on the
distinctive nature and legal relevance of the current threat to national security:
"America faces an enemy just as real as its former Cold War foes, with
capabilities beyond the capacity of the judiciary to explore. '35 In fact, the court
insisted that deference was "mandated by the separation of powers, '36
suggesting that disclosure under FOIA would raise constitutional problems. The
court left no doubt about the motivation for its action: "[W]e are in accord
with several federal courts that have wisely respected the executive's
judgment in prosecuting the national response to terrorism." 37 What is most
noteworthy about the decision, then, is not the outcome, but the court's
broad pronouncements about the need to defer to the executive and its
interpretation of FOIA with clear and specific reference to separation of powers
principles.</p>
      <p>Another strikingly fundamentalist decision by the D.C. Circuit is Al</p>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>Odah v. United States, which the Supreme Court reversed in Rasul v. Bush.38</title>
        <p>In its ambitious ruling, the D.C. Circuit held that aliens captured outside of
the United States have no rights under the Due Process Clause.39 The court
said that the Guantinamo Bay detainees were, in law, analogous to German
prisoners captured on the battlefield during World War 11.40 The court
acknowledged that Guantdnamo Bay is controlled by the United States
military, but it insisted on the irrelevance of this fact because Cuba has
sovereignty over the area.41 The court's conclusion was hardly unreasonable.
But there can be no doubt that the conclusion in favor of executive discretion
stemmed from a broad and hardly mandatory reading of Supreme Court
precedents. 42</p>
        <p>A concurring opinion by Judge Randolph (who wrote the majority
opinion as well) was, in a sense, even more revealing. Judge Randolph went well
beyond what was necessary to resolve the case. Consider his confessedly
aggressive opening sentence: "I write separately to add two other grounds for
rejecting the detainees' non-habeas claims. '4 3 The fundamental motivation
for his separate opinion seemed to be captured by his final sentence:
The level of threat a detainee poses to United States interests, the
amount of intelligence a detainee might be able to provide, the
conditions under which the detainee may be willing to cooperate, the
disruption visits from family members and lawyers might
causethese types of judgments have traditionally been left to the
exclusive discretion of the Executive Branch, and there they should
remain. 4
Here is an explicit endorsement of National Security Fundamentalism.</p>
        <p>Within the D.C. Circuit, the trial courts have followed the lead of the
court of appeals, showing a similar tendency toward National Security
Fundamentalism. Consider, for example, ACLU v. Department of Justice,45 in
which organizations sought information involving the government's use of
section 215 of the USA PATRIOT Act.46 Section 215 gives the FBI broad
power to "make an application for an order requiring the production of any
tangible things.., for an investigation to obtain foreign intelligence
informa38 Al Odah v. United States, 321 F.3d 1134 (D.C. Cir. 2003), rev'd sub nom. Rasul v. Bush,
124 S. Ct. 2686 (2004).</p>
        <p>39 See id. at 1145.
40 See id. at 1140.
41 See id. at 1143.
42 See id.
43 Id. at 1145 (Randolph, J., concurring).
44 Id. at 1150 (Randolph, J., concurring).
45 ACLU v. Dep't of Justice, 321 F. Supp. 2d 24 (D.D.C. 2004).</p>
        <p>46 See id. at 26; Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools
Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism (USA PATRIOT Act) Act of 2001 § 215, 50 U.S.C.
§ 1861 (Supp. I 2003).
tion ...or to protect against international terrorism. '47 In particular, the
plaintiffs sought to use FOIA to find out (1) the total number of section 215
requests received by the National Security Law Unit of the FBI and (2) any
and all records relating to section 215.48 Notwithstanding the fact that the
Department of Justice had previously made several disclosures of its
behavior under the USA PATRIOT Act, the court ruled broadly that the national
security exemption of FOIA justified the failure to disclose the information. 49</p>
        <p>The court knew that it was dealing with a hard question, candidly
acknowledging that the "issue is hardly free from doubt. ' 50 But it ruled for the
government "because it [was] mindful of the 'long-recognized deference to
the executive on national security issues."' 51 Ultimately the court deferred,
not to specific explanations by the executive, but to the exceedingly vague
claims that release of the number of section 215 field requests "poses the
continuing potential to harm our national security by enabling our
adversaries to conduct their intelligence or international terrorist activities more
securely. ' 52 The court's willingness to embrace National Security
Fundamentalism is best understood in light of a background principle in
favor of executive power in the domain of national security.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-6-2">
        <title>A similar approach can be found in Edmonds v. Departmentof Justice.53</title>
        <p>There the court gave an exceedingly broad reading to the "state secrets
privilege" so as to dismiss a Privacy Act 54 claim brought by a self-styled
whistleblower at the FBI.55 One of the most striking parts of the court's
opinion came in a footnote, in which it addressed the possibility of staying
the case rather than dismissing it: "This is due not only to the nature of the
information, but also because the imminent threat of terrorism will not be
eliminated anytime in the foreseeable future, but is an endeavor that will
consume our nation's attention indefinitely. '56 Under FOIA, then, National
Security Fundamentalism has been explicitly endorsed within the D.C.
Circuit, in holdings that fit well with the general approach in Al Odah.
D.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>FundamentalismAgain: An Echo from the Fourth Circuit</title>
      <p>Next to the D.C. Circuit, the United States Court of Appeals for the
Fourth Circuit has been the most prominent court of appeals in cases
involving the war on terror, and it has taken an approach strikingly similar to that
of the D.C. Circuit.57 The most prominent of its decisions is Hamdi v.
Rumsfeld.5 8 There the court held that enemy combatants, captured on the
battlefield, could be detained indefinitely and without trial, even if they were
American citizens. 59 In so ruling, the court relied largely on a constitutional
source-the president's power as commander in chief of the armed forces. 60
The court contended that this power includes "the authority to detain those
captured in armed struggle" and also "to deport or detain alien enemies
during the duration of hostilities and to confiscate or destroy enemy property. 61</p>
      <p>The central question in the case involved the procedural protection, if
any, that would accompany the exercise of the commander-in-chief power.
The court emphasized the need to defer to the president: "The Constitution's
allocation of the warmaking powers reflects not only the expertise and
experience lodged within the executive, but also the more fundamental truth that
those branches most accountable to the people should be the ones to
undertake the ultimate protection and to ask the ultimate sacrifice from them. 62
Hence, deference to the executive would be the basic rule. 63 The court was
aware that, in denying fair procedure, the president was doing something
unusual, but changed circumstances justified this step: "As the nature of threats
to America evolves, along with the means of carrying those threats out, the
nature of enemy combatants may change also. In the face of such change,
separation of powers doctrine does not deny the executive branch the
essential tool of adaptability."' 64</p>
      <p>Indeed, the court said that the source of the detention was not a statute,
but "Article II, Section 2, of the Constitution, wherein the President is given
the war power. '65 (I will return to this important statement, which seems to
lie behind the D.C. Circuit opinions as well, in due course.) Deference to the
president stems from this explicit grant of authority. So long as a detention
"is one legitimately made pursuant to the war powers," it must be
respected. 66 A general statement on the part of the executive supporting the
claim that a citizen was detained in the course of war and qualified as an
enemy combatant would be sufficient. 67 The court left no doubt that this
conclusion stemmed from National Security Fundamentalism: "The
constitutional allocation of war powers affords the President extraordinarily broad
authority as Commander in Chief and compels courts to assume a deferential
posture."68
59 See id. at 473.
60 See id. at 463.
61 Id. (citation omitted).
62 Id.</p>
      <p>63 See id. at 464. Notably, however, the court was careful to limit the reach of its ruling in
a way that suggests a form of minimalism described below. See id. at 465 ("We shall, in fact, go
no further in this case than the specific context before us-that of the undisputed detention of a
citizen during a combat operation undertaken in a foreign country and a determination by the
executive that the citizen was allied with enemy forces.").</p>
      <p>64 Id. at 466.
65 Id. at 471.
66 Id. at 472.
67 See id. at 472-73.
68 Id. at 474.</p>
      <p>That deference required the conclusion that Hamdi could be held
indefinitely, even after the end of the relevant hostilities. 69 In reaching this
conclusion, the court referred to the judgments of the executive branch without
even pausing to consider what kind of authorization Congress had given it.70
Because the D.C. Circuit and the Fourth Circuit have been the most
important sources of lower-court decisions involving liberty and the war on
terrorism, it is fair to say that National Security Fundamentalism has played the
dominant role on the federal courts in the aftermath of the September 11
attacks.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>National Security Fundamentalism and the Constitution</title>
      <p>Why have lower courts been drawn to National Security
Fundamentalism? In the abstract, National Security Fundamentalism has a great deal of
appeal. Far more than Congress, the president is in a position to act quickly
and decisively to protect the citizenry. He is also likely to be able to acquire
relevant information about what must be done and about when to do it.
Because the president is commander in chief of the armed forces, Congress
cannot override the president's judgments about how to carry out a lawful war.
Justice Thomas correctly emphasizes that Alexander Hamilton defended the
creation of a "unitary executive" as a means of ensuring energy,
coordination, and dispatch in the presidency.71 These qualities are relevant above all
in times of war. By contrast, courts lack good tools for assessing the
president's claims of military necessity.</p>
      <p>At least equally important, judicial errors may turn out to be disastrous
rather than merely harmful. To be sure, American practice suggests that
judges are most unlikely to err by protecting civil liberties; 72 in our history, it
is hard to find even a single case in which judicial protection of freedom
seriously damaged national security. But if Liberty Perfectionism were
accepted, some such errors would become far more probable. In ordinary
contexts, even those that involve criminal justice, the stakes are not nearly so
high. There is every reason for courts to avoid a decision that leads to
freedom for terrorists or to disclosure of information that helps those who want
to kill Americans. Structural concerns, along with simple prudence, argue in
favor of considerable judicial deference to presidential choices when national
security is at risk. These points provide important cautionary notes; they
help to explain why Liberty Perfectionism is senseless. But these
considerations should not be read for more than they are worth. Far from requiring
National Security Fundamentalism, the Constitution is best read to forbid it.</p>
      <p>No one doubts that the president has considerable power in the domain
of national security. I have emphasized that under Article II he is explicitly
authorized to be "Commander in Chief of the Army and Navy of the United
69 See id. at 476.
70 See id.</p>
      <p>71 See Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 124 S. Ct. 2633, 2675-76 (2004) (Thomas, J., dissenting). See
generallyLawrence Lessig &amp; Cass R. Sunstein, The Presidentand the Administration,94 COLUM.
L. REV. 1 (1994).</p>
      <p>72 See generally STONE, supra note 3.
States. '73 He is allowed "to make Treaties," at least when two-thirds of the
senators concur. 74 He is authorized to "appoint Ambassadors" and "other
public Ministers and Consuls. '75 He "shall receive Ambassadors and other
public Ministers.' ' 76 But none of this supports Justice Thomas's suggestion
that the president has "primary responsibility-along with the necessary
power-to protect the national security and to conduct the Nation's foreign
relations. '77 Nor does anything in the document support the Fourth Circuit's
suggestion that under Article II "the President is given the war power. 78
Nor does the Constitution support the view, at least implicit in the rulings of
the D.C. Circuit, that the domain of war is the domain of largely unbounded
presidential discretion. 79 On the contrary, that view is a tendentious reading
of the legal materials. To see why, let us turn to Article I.</p>
      <p>Perhaps most notably, Congress, rather than the president, has the
power "[t]o declare War. ''80 The Constitution also grants Congress, not the
president, the power "[t]o raise and support Armies." ' It authorizes
Congress "[t]o provide and maintain a Navy."'8 2 In a formulation that bears on
the president's supposedly inherent power to torture and that much
complicates any claims about the broad power of the commander in chief, the
founding document permits Congress to "make Rules for the Government
and Regulation of the land and naval Forces. ' 83 It is Congress that is
authorized to raise funds to "provide for the Common Defence and general Welfare
of the United States."84 Congress, rather than the president, is empowered
to "regulate Commerce with foreign Nations."85 Congress is also authorized
to "define and punish Piracies and Felonies committed on the high Seas, and
Offences against the Law of Nations, ' 86 and also to "make Rules concerning
Captures on Land and Water." 87 It is under Article I, not Article II, that the
Constitution allows suspension of habeas corpus "when in Cases of Rebellion
or Invasion the public Safety may require it."88 The fact that the Suspension
Clause can be found in Article I tends to suggest that Congress, not the
president, is entitled to suspend the writ.</p>
      <p>
        73 U.S. CONST. art. II, § 2, cl. 1.
74 Id. art. II, § 2, cl. 2.
75 Id.
76 Id. art. II, § 3.
77 Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 124 S. Ct. 2633, 267
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">5 (2004</xref>
        ) (Thomas, J., dissenting).
78 Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 316 F.3d 450, 471 (4th Cir. 2003), rev'd, 124 S. Ct. 2633 (2004).
79 See, e.g., Ctr. for Nat'l Sec. Studies v. Dep't of Justice, 331 F.3d 918, 926-27 (D.C. Cir.
2003) (noting that "the judiciary owes some measure of deference to the executive in cases
implicating national security, a uniquely executive purview"), cert. denied, 540 U.S. 1104 (2004).
      </p>
      <p>80 U.S. CoNsT. art. I, § 8, cl. 11. For treatment of some of the complexities here, with
reference to the literature, see Curtis Bradley &amp; Jack Goldsmith, CongressionalAuthorization
and the War on Terrorism, 118 HARV. L. REV. (forthcoming 2005).</p>
      <p>81 U.S. CONsT. art. 1, § 8, cl. 12.
82 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 13.
83 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 14.
84 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 1.
85 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 3.
86 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 10.
87 Id. art. I, § 8, cl. 11.
88 Id. art. I, § 9, cl. 2.</p>
      <p>In this light, the Constitution does not repose in the president anything
like the general authority "to protect the national security. '89 On the
contrary, the more natural reading of the document is that protection of national
security is parceled out between Congress and the president-and that if
either has the dominant role, it is the national lawmaker. To be sure, the
Commander in Chief Clause does give the president the authority to direct the
armed forces, an expansive authority;90 but even that authority is subject to
legislative constraints because Congress controls the budget and because
Congress can choose not to declare war. And if Congress refuses either to
authorize the use of force or to declare war, the president is generally
noton the best reading of the document-entitled to commence hostilities. 91
The Commander in Chief Clause allows the president to manage wars; but it
does not give him "the war power." All of this means that National Security
Fundamentalism cannot claim a strong constitutional pedigree.</p>
      <p>Of course, the constitutional text is hardly all there is to our
constitutional tradition.92 In the domain of separation of powers, historical practices
and changes over time are highly relevant. As Justice Frankfurter contended,
"[i]t is an inadmissibly narrow conception of American constitutional law to
confine it to the words of the Constitution and to disregard the gloss which
life has written upon them. '93 In this context, an understanding of that
"gloss" greatly favors the president. There can be no doubt that for
questions of national security the president has assumed authority that the text
alone might not sanction. The power to make war is a leading example; the
president has long engaged in military actions without the kind of legislative
authorization that Article I appears to require. 94</p>
      <p>Historical "glosses" on constitutional text might well be taken to argue
in the direction of National Security Fundamentalism. They make it
plausible to contend that the president has more authority in the domain of
national security than the document alone appears to contemplate.
Undoubtedly, the lower courts have been responding in part to that fact.
Equally undoubtedly, the increasing power of the president is largely a
product of functional considerations having to do with the rise of the United
States as an international power and the growing need for energy and
dispatch. But even when the document is thus glossed, it remains tendentious to
contend that when the nation is at risk, the president must be in charge of the
apparatus of government. To say this is to reject a constitutional
accommodation that, by text and tradition as well, unambiguously retains Congress's
role as the nation's lawmaker.</p>
      <p>If National Security Fundamentalism is to be rejected, what should be
put in its place? What should courts do instead?</p>
      <p>I cannot answer that question in this space.95 It is surely relevant that, in
a number of decisions, the Supreme Court has rejected unlimited presidential
authority and insisted on the relevance of a congressional grant of power.96
For a recent illustration, let us explore the leading alternative to the approach
of the D.C. Circuit and the Fourth Circuit-one that offers a very different
understanding both of the constitutional foundations and the appropriate
judicial role. In the relevant decision, the United States Court of Appeals for
the Second Circuit endorsed a form of minimalism in Padilla v. Rumsfeld. 97</p>
      <p>At issue was the legality of the detention of Jose Padilla, an American
citizen held as an enemy combatant after having been seized on American
soil.98 The court squarely rejected the claim, urged by the executive and
rooted in National Security Fundamentalism, that the "President has the
inherent authority to detain those who take up arms against this country." 99
The court of appeals correctly emphasized that Articles I and II divide the
war powers, rather than confer them on the executive alone. °° The court
added that the grant of numerous war-related powers "to Congress is a
powerful indication that, absent express congressional authorization, the
President's Commander-in-Chief powers do not support" the confinement of an
American citizen captured on American soil.10 1 It stressed that Ex parte
Quirin,102 the government's best precedent, rested on congressional
authorization rather than on inherent presidential authority. 10 3</p>
      <p>The key issue thus was whether such authorization could be found here.
In the court's view, Congress's authorization to use "all necessary and
appropriate force" to respond to the September 11 attacks' 4 should be understood
in light of the Supreme Court's several efforts to ensure that both Congress
and the president, rather than the president alone, authorize interferences
95 See Cass R. Sunstein, Minimalism at War, 2004 Sup. CT. REv. 47, for detailed
discussion.</p>
      <p>96 See, e.g., Duncan v. Kahanamoku, 327 U.S. 304, 322 (1946); Ex parte Endo, 323 U.S.
283, 300-02 (1944); Hirabayashi v. United States, 320 U.S. 81, 90-93 (1943). For further
discussion, see Issacharoff &amp; Pildes, supra note 1, at 7-9.</p>
      <p>97 Padilla v. Rumsfeld, 352 F.3d 695 (2d Cir. 2003), rev'd on othergrounds, 124 S.Ct. 2711
(2004).</p>
      <p>98 See id. at 698.
99 Id. at 712.
100 See id. at 713-14.
101 Id. at 715.
102 Ex parte Quirin, 317 U.S. 1 (1942).
103 See Padilla,352 F.3d at 715-16.</p>
      <p>104 Authorization for Use of Military Force, Pub. L. No. 107-40, § 2(a), 115 Stat. 224, 224
(2001).
with constitutionally sensitive interests. 10 5 The Supreme Court thus had
emphasized that "'[i]n interpreting a war-time measure we must assume that
[the purpose of Congress and the Executive] was to allow for the greatest
possible accommodation between those liberties and the exigencies of
war." 10 6 In Padilla the court of appeals said, correctly, that no clear and
unmistakable statement could be found. 10 7 Such a statement was required,
and hence the indefinite detention of Padilla was beyond the President's
power.'08</p>
      <p>This decision is an unambiguous exercise in minimalism at war. It stands
in sharp contrast with the National Security Fundamentalism that has
dominated the D.C. Circuit. I am not sure that on the particular issue the Second
Circuit was correct; the authorization for the use of force is not implausibly
interpreted to provide a basis for what the executive did in Padilla1.0 9</p>
      <p>I have suggested that much of the appeal of National Security
Fundamentalism lies in functional and structural considerations. Federal judges, no
less than ordinary citizens, want to support the president when the nation is
at risk. Moreover, it is not implausible to suggest that aspects of the
constitutional structure argue in favor of National Security Fundamentalism. But I
have suggested that this approach fits poorly with the founding document, all
things considered. When judges adopt it, why are they doing so? At least in
the recent past, I believe that two factors have, regrettably, been playing a
significant role.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-9">
      <title>Republican Judges, Republican Presidents</title>
      <p>The first factor has to do with the likely posture of Republican judicial
appointees confronted with the efforts of a Republican president to protect
the nation in the aftermath of an attack. No one can doubt that Democratic
appointees and Republican appointees differ with one another on many
crucial questions. 10 With respect to national security, there is reason to
speculate that Republican appointees would be somewhat more likely to rule in
favor of presidential authority than Democratic appointees. (Nothing I have
said demonstrates that they are wrong to be inclined in this direction.) But
their tendency, I suggest, is likely to be heightened when the president in
question is also Republican. In other contexts, this effect has been
powerfully documented; Republican-appointed judges are distinctly willing
to defer to Republican presidents in the general domain of administrative
law-and much less willing to defer to Democratic presidents.111 I have not
done an empirical analysis of lower-court decisions when national security
collides with liberty, but there is every reason to believe that the tendency I
am describing would hold.</p>
      <p>Here is a more concrete way to put the point. It is possible to imagine
the following combinations of interactions: Democratic president,
Democratic-appointed judges; Democratic president, Republican-appointed judges;
Republican president, Democratic-appointed judges; Republican president,
Republican-appointed judges. My speculation is that when presidents are
taking steps to protect security at the possible expense of liberty, the
likelihood of a judicial victory is highest, and probably by far the highest, when
Republican judges are assessing the decisions of a Republican president. For
the other three possible combinations, federal judges are more likely to
invalidate presidential actions that raise serious legal difficulties.</p>
      <p>I am suggesting, then, that in general Democratic-appointed judges
would look more skeptically at liberty-infringing acts by the chief executive,
whether Republican or Democratic, and that Republican-appointed judges
would look more skeptically at intrusions on liberty by (say) President
Clinton than at intrusions on liberty by (say) President George W. Bush. It is
revealing in this regard that the primary illustrations of National Security
Fundamentalism in the recent past have come from Republican appointees
speaking approvingly of exercises of authority of President Bush. Recall that
Judge Ray Randolph wrote both the majority and the concurring opinion in
Al Odah; in addition, Judge Harvey Wilkinson wrote the majority opinion in
Hamdi. These are mere examples, and nothing I am saying here
demonstrates that these judges were wrong in their particular conclusions. I am
making a simple descriptive (and predictive) point: National Security
Fundamentalism will have most appeal to Republican appointees on the lower
courts when the president whose acts are at issue is also Republican.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-10">
      <title>B. Judicial Courage:A Concluding Note</title>
      <p>The final point has to do with the institutional position of lower courts as
compared with the institutional position of the Supreme Court of the United
States. To say the least, it is uncomfortable for federal judges to invalidate a
decision of the president. Invalidation of presidential acts is particularly
uncomfortable when national security is at risk. Our history attests to this
point. 112 If federal judges are going to reject a presidential decision in the
name of liberty, they will have to demonstrate a great deal of courage.
Lower courts, precisely because they are lower, are less likely to show that
courage. Because of its unique place in American government and because
of its national prestige, the Supreme Court is in a far better position to do
so. 113 This is not to say that the Supreme Court will reliably protect liberty,
l1l See, e.g., Linda R. Cohen &amp; Matthew L. Spitzer, Solving the Chevron Puzzle, 57 LAW &amp;
CONTEMP. PROBS. 65 (1994) (Finding that justices are far more likely to defer to an agency's
statutory construction when the agency is controlled by a president of the same political party as
the justice).</p>
      <p>112 See supra text accompanying note 72.
113 See STONE, supra note 3, passim, for a catalogue of cases in which the Supreme Court
even when the legal materials call for it to do so. Judges are merely judges,
and when national security is at risk, an aggressive judicial role is neither
likely nor desirable. It is for this reason that Liberty Perfectionism is a
nonstarter. But to the extent that federal judges need a great deal of courage to
protect constitutional rights when the stakes are high, the Supreme Court is
more reliable than other judicial institutions, at least as a general tendency.</p>
      <p>The best guess, then, is that lower courts, including the D.C. Circuit, will
be inclined to follow the constitutionally mischievous path of National
Security Fundamentalism. I hope that I am proved wrong.
has been reluctant to protect liberty amidst a public panic; see SUNSTEIN, supra note 4, at 61-72,
for a suggestion that the Court has often protected liberty through minimalist rulings.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          5 See Rasul v.
          <source>Bush</source>
          , 124
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>2686</volume>
          ,
          <issue>2699</issue>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          );
          <article-title>Hamdi v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Rumsfeld</source>
          , 124
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>2633</volume>
          ,
          <issue>2647</issue>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>6 See supra note 5 and accompanying text</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          89 Hamdi v.
          <source>Rumsfeld</source>
          , 124
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Ct</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>2633</volume>
          ,
          <issue>2675</issue>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Thomas</article-title>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>J.</surname>
          </string-name>
          , dissenting).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          90 See Loving v.
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>517</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>748</volume>
          ,
          <issue>768</issue>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>91</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>The principal exception is that the president is always permitted to repel sudden attacks-a category that is not self-defining</article-title>
          .
          <source>See John Hart Ely, Suppose Congress Wanted a War PowersAct That Worked</source>
          ,
          <volume>88</volume>
          COLUM. L. REV.
          <volume>1379</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1388</issue>
          (
          <year>1988</year>
          ); Note, Congress, the President, and the Power to Commit Forcesto Combat,
          <volume>81</volume>
          HARV. L. REV.
          <volume>1771</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1782</issue>
          (
          <year>1968</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          92 See generally
          <string-name>
            <given-names>David A.</given-names>
            <surname>Strauss</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Common Law ConstitutionalInterpretation,63
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
            <surname>CHI. L. REV</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>877</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          93
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Youngstown</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Sheet &amp; Tube</given-names>
            <surname>Co</surname>
          </string-name>
          . v. Sawyer, 343 U.S.
          <volume>579</volume>
          ,
          <issue>610</issue>
          (
          <year>1952</year>
          )
          <article-title>(Frankfurter</article-title>
          , J., concurring).
          <source>See generally Bradley &amp; Goldsmith, supra note 80.</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>94 For relevant discussion, see HAROLD HONGJU KOH, THE NATIONAL SECURITY CONSTITUTION: SHARING POWER AFTER THE IRAN-</article-title>
          CONTRA AFFAIR 38-
          <fpage>40</fpage>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          ); John Hart Ely,
          <article-title>The American War in Indochina, Part I: The (Troubled) Constitutionalityof the War They Told Us About</article-title>
          ,
          <volume>42</volume>
          STAN. L. REV.
          <volume>877</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Harold Hongju Koh, The Coase Theorem and the War Power:A Response, 41 DUKE L</article-title>
          .J.
          <volume>122</volume>
          ,
          <issue>127</issue>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ); Gregory Sidak, To Declare War, 41 DUKE L.J.
          <volume>27</volume>
          (
          <year>1991</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Lower Courts, Ideology, and the Irresistible (?) Appeal of National Security Fundamentalism</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          105 See Duncan v.
          <source>Kahanamoku</source>
          , 327 U.S.
          <volume>304</volume>
          ,
          <issue>322</issue>
          (
          <year>1946</year>
          ); Ex parte Endo, 323 U.S.
          <volume>283</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>02</lpage>
          (
          <year>1944</year>
          );
          <article-title>Hirabayashi v</article-title>
          .
          <source>United States</source>
          ,
          <volume>320</volume>
          U.S.
          <volume>81</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>90</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          (
          <year>1943</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          106 Padilla,352
          <string-name>
            <surname>F.</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>3d at 722-23 (alterations in original) (quoting Ex parteEndo</article-title>
          , 323 U.S. at 300).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>107 See id</article-title>
          . at 723.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>108 See id.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          109
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Bradley</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Goldsmith, supra note 80.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          110 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>generally Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>Ideological Voting on FederalCourts of Appeals: A PreliminaryInvestigation</source>
          ,
          <volume>90</volume>
          VA. L. REv.
          <volume>301</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>