<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Fast, Frugal, and (Sometimes) Wrong</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Part of the Law Commons</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics Recommended Citation</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein, "Fast, Frugal, and (Sometimes) Wrong" ( John M. Olin Program in Law and Economics Working Paper No. 265,
2005).
PUBLIC LAW AND LEGAL THEORY WORKING PAPER NO. 110 </p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein </p>
      <p>T H E   L A W   S C H O O L  
T H E   U N I V E R S I T Y  O F   C H I C A G O  </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>November 2005 </title>
      <p> </p>
      <p>This paper can be downloaded without charge at the John M. Olin Program in Law and 
Economics Working Paper Series: http://www.law.uchicago.edu/Lawecon/index.html and at the </p>
      <p>Public Law and Legal Theory Working Paper Series:  
http://www.law.uchicago.edu/academics/publiclaw/index.html </p>
      <p>and 
The Social Science Research Network Electronic Paper Collection: </p>
      <p>http://ssrn.com/abstract_id=844964  </p>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>Preliminary draft 11/3/05</title>
        <p>forthcoming in Walter Sinnott-Armstrong, ed., The Cognitive Science of Morality
All rights reserved</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-2-2">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein University of Chicago Law School and Department of Political Science Abstract</title>
        <p>Do moral heuristics operate in the moral domain? If so, do they lead to moral
errors? This brief essay offers an affirmative answer to both questions. In so doing, it
responds to an essay by Gerd Gigerenzer on the nature of heuristics, moral and
otherwise. While focused on morality, the discussion bears on the general debate between
those who emphasize cognitive errors, sometimes produced by heuristics, and those who
emphasize the frequent success of heuristics in producing sensible judgments in the real
world. General claims are that it is contentious to see moral problems as ones of
arithmetic, and that arguments about moral heuristics will often do well to steer clear of
contentious arguments about what morality requires.</p>
        <p>For many problems, Gerd Gigerenzer celebrates heuristics. He believes that they
are simple, fast, frugal, and remarkably accurate. He emphasizes that heuristics can be
prescriptive, in the sense that they may well lead to good outcomes in the real world. In
the moral domain, Gigerenzer is properly cautious about whether heuristics produce
moral or immoral behavior. What I would like to do here is to emphasize the imperfect
reliability of heuristics in general, and to suggest that their imperfect reliability raises
serious cautionary notes about some of Gigerenzer’s broader claims.</p>
        <p>
          Let us begin with Gigerenzer’s illuminating remarks about the "gaze heuristic,"
which enables baseball players (and others) to make otherwise difficult catches.
Gigerenzer, who has often explored this particular heuristic, is quite right to emphasize
that people who use heuristics are often not aware that they are doing so. But even a
casual understanding of sports requires some qualification of Gigerenzer's claims. Stupid
tennis players tend to use fast and frugal heuristics, which contribute to their stupid
tennis. Often they think, for example, that they should hit the ball hard and deep
whenever the opportunity arises—an intuition, or thought, that can get them into serious
trouble. Stupid athletes adopt simple heuristics that make them dumb. By contrast, smart
tennis players are immensely flexible, and they are able to rethink their rules of thumb as
the occasion demands. The best athletes have an exceedingly complex set of heuristics,
fast but not at all simple, which they deploy as the situation requires. The moral domain
is not so very different
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">(see Nussbaum, 2003)</xref>
          . It is pervaded by fast heuristics, as
Gigerenzer suggests, but they often misfire, and good moral agents are aware of that fact.
        </p>
        <p>
          My own treatment of moral heuristics, criticized by Gigerenzer, emphasizes the
immense importance of moral framing and the possibility that people use “simple
heuristics that make us good”
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">(Sunstein, 2005)</xref>
          . For morality, as for issues of fact and
logic, it is important to see that many heuristics do point us in the right direction– and
hence to stress, as did Tversky and Kahneman
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">(Tversky and Kahneman, 1974)</xref>
          and later
Gigerenzer, that heuristics can lead to excellent judgments in the actual world. If people
believe that they ought not to lie, or harm innocent people, they will often do the right
thing—especially in light of the fact that case-by-case inquiries into the morality of lying,
or harming innocent people, could produce self-serving conclusions that produce
grievous moral wrong. (The case of Nazi massacres, explored by Gigerenzer, can be
understood as an example.) Moral heuristics, understood as simple rules of thumb, might
well have a rule-utilitarian defense, in the sense that they might, on balance, produce
morally preferable behavior even if they lead to unfortunate results in particular cases.
        </p>
        <p>
          But no one should deny that in many contexts, moral and other heuristics, in the
form of simple rules of thumb, lead to moral error on any plausible view of morality.
Consider, for example, the idea, emphasized by Gigerenzer, that one ought to do as the
majority does, a source of massive moral blunders
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7 ref8">(see Sunstein, 2003)</xref>
          . Or consider the
fast and frugal idea that one ought not to distort the truth—a heuristic that generally
works well, but that also leads (in my view) to moral error when, for example, the
distortion is necessary to avoid significant numbers of deaths. Or consider the
actomission distinction, which makes moral sense in many domains, but which can lead to
unsupportable moral judgments as well (Baron, 2004).
        </p>
        <p>Gigerenzer notes, usefully, that it may be possible to modify people’s judgments,
including their moral judgments, by altering the background. The idea is hardly original
(see Sunstein and Thaler, 2004), but it is true that a default rule in favor of organ
donations might well increase what, on one view, is morally desirable behavior (id.).
Indeed there are many applications of this point. If default rules matter, an employer,
including the state qua employer, could dramatically increase charitable contributions by
presuming that (for example) each employer would like to devote 2% of wages to
charitable causes. Of course the use of default rules to steer behavior raises normative
questions of its own (id.). The only point is that default rules greatly matter to choices,
including those with a moral component.</p>
        <p>Thus far, then, Gigerenzer’s general argument seems both plausible and
illuminating, and I am merely underlining the possibility that even good heuristics will go
wrong, for morality as for other questions. But on an important issue, Gigerenzer seems
to me to miss some of the complexity of moral argument. His objections to maximization
theories treat moral judgments as involving a kind of moral arithmetic, and this is a most
contentious understanding.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Gigenenzer is correct to stress the cognitive difficulties of undertaking
a full ex ante calculation of the consequences of social actions. Human beings do not
have unlimited cognitive abilities, and hence they are often unable to specify the effects
of one or another course of action. Gigerenzer believes that satisficers, using moral
heuristics, have important advantages over optimizers. For some questions, this is
undoubtedly correct. But to understand the relationship between heuristics and the moral
domain, much more must be said. Three points are especially important here.</p>
        <p>
          First: Gigerenzer does not mention that many people are rule-consequentialists;
they know exactly what Gigerenzer emphasizes, and they favor clear and simple moral
rules for that very reason
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">(Hooker, 2000)</xref>
          . A complex consequentialist calculus might
lead to error, even if it would be preferable if properly applied. Because people are
selfserving, and because their on-the-spot judgments are unreliable, they might do best to
follow simple moral rules, or one-reason decision making. There are interesting
relationships between Gigerenzer’s understanding of heuristics and rule-utilitarian
approach to morality.
        </p>
        <p>
          Second: Consequentialism can be specified in many different ways. Utilitarianism
is one form of consequentialism, but because it require all goods and bads to be described
along the metric of utility, it is controversial, even among consequentialists. When
Gigerenzer speaks of the limits of maximization theories, and even of consequentialism,
he appears to be operating under a utilitarian framework, without exploring the problem
of plural and incommensurable goods. We might, for example, endorse a form of
consequentialism that sees rights violations (so understood on nonutilitarian grounds) as a
set of (very) bad consequences
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(see Sen, 1982)</xref>
          . Gigerenzer’s exploration of moral
problems does not recognize the complexities in consequentialist accounts of morality.
        </p>
        <p>
          Third: Many people are not consequentialists at all
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">(see Scheffler, 1994)</xref>
          .
Consider the injunction to treat people as ends, not means, an injunction that runs afoul of
many versions of consequentialism
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">(but see Sen, 1982)</xref>
          . Hence—and this is the most
important point—it is not enough for Gigerenzer to show that moral heuristics do a good
(enough) real-world job of achieving what we would achieve if we were optimizers with
unlimited abilities of calculation. Perhaps some heuristics, in some contexts, violate
deontological commands.
        </p>
        <p>Return to Gigerenzer’s first example: Should a Nazi massacre be evaluated in
utilitarian or consequentialist terms? To make the calculation, does it matter if, for
example, there were many more Nazis than Jews, and that many Germans had a great
deal to gain, economically and otherwise, from mass murders? Many people would
respond that this moral atrocity counts as such whatever the outcome of a utilitarian or
consequentialist calculus—and hence that Gigerenzer’s emphasis on the impossibility of
ex ante calculations is often beside the point (or worse). Perhaps many moral heuristics,
followed by most people and even most soldiers (putting Nazi soldiers to one side),
should be seen as fast and frugal ways not of satisficing rather than optimizing, but of
ensuring that people do what is required by nonconsequentialist accounts of morality.</p>
        <p>
          The existence of plural and conflicting accounts of the foundations of morality
makes it all the more difficult to argue that moral heuristics function well. If certain fast
and frugal heuristics are defensible on utilitarian or consequentialist grounds, they might
still be objectionable from the moral point of view. In my view, it is for this reason
productive to explore heuristics that might be defensible, or indefensible, on the basis of
any view of what morality requires, or on the basis of the least contentious views of what
morality requires
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">(Sunstein, 2005)</xref>
          .
        </p>
        <p>Gigerenzer seems to think that moral heuristics might be shown to be prescriptive
if a full consequentialist calculus is not possible; but this thought too quickly treats
morality as a problem of arithmetic. If morality ought not to be so understood, as many
people believe, then it is not clear what is shown by Gigerenzer’s emphasis on the
cognitive problems associated with optimizing. I emphasize that prescriptive treatments
of moral heuristics are likely to be productive; but they should steer clear of the most
contentious arguments about the foundations of morality.
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Readers with comments should address them to:
Professor Cass Sunstein
University of Chicago Law School
1111 East 60th Street
Chicago, IL 60637
csunstei@uchicago.edu </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>Chicago Working Papers in Law and Economics </title>
      <p>(Second Series) 
209. 
210. 
211. 
212. 
213. 
214. 
215. 
216. 
217. 
218. 
219. 
220.  
221. 
222. 
223. 
224. 
225. 
226. 
227. 
228. 
229. 
230. 
231. 
232. 
233. 
234. 
235. 
236. 
237. 
238. 
239. 
240. 
241. 
242. 
243. 
244. 
245. 
252. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Akerlof</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>The Economics of Caste and of the Rate Race and Other Woeful Tales, in An Economic Theorist's Book of Tales (</article-title>
          <year>1984</year>
          ). Cambridge University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Baron</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          )
          <article-title>Nonconsequentialist decisions</article-title>
          .
          <source>Behavioral and Brain Sciences</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          :
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Hooker</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
          <source>Ideal Code, Real World: A Rule-Consequentialist Theory of Morality</source>
          . Oxford University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Nussbaum. M.</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <source>The Fragility of Goodness</source>
          . Cambridge University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Scheffler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <source>The Rejection of Consequentialism</source>
          . Oxford University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sen</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Rights and Agency</article-title>
          .
          <source>Philosophy and Public Affairs</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          :
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>39</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Why Societies Need Dissent</article-title>
          . Harvard University Press.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Thaler</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <source>Libertarian Paternalism Is Not An Oxymoron. University of Chicago Law Review</source>
          <volume>70</volume>
          :
          <fpage>1159</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1202</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2005</year>
          ).
          <source>Moral Heuristics. Behavioral and Brain Sciences</source>
          <volume>28</volume>
          :
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Tversky</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kahneman</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          ).
          <article-title>Judgment under uncertainty: Heuristics and biases</article-title>
          .
          <source>Science</source>
          ,
          <volume>185</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>1124</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>1131</lpage>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>