<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta/>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Irreversible and Catastrophic</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law</string-name>
          <email>unbound@law.uchicago.edu</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Coase-Sandor Institute for Law and Economics</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution>accepted for inclusion in Coase-Sandor Working Paper Series in Law and Economics by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more information</institution>
          ,
          <addr-line>please contact</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <fpage>26</fpage>
      <lpage>67</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Follow this and additional works at: https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/law_and_economics Part of the Law Commons Recommended Citation Cass R. Sunstein, "Irreversible and Catastrophic" ( John M. Olin Program in Law and Economics Working Paper No. 242, 2005).</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>JOHN M. OLIN LAW &amp; ECONOMICS WORKING PAPER NO. 242 
 
 
 
 
This paper can be downloaded without charge at the John M. Olin Program in Law and Economics Working </p>
      <p>Paper Series: http://www.law.uchicago.edu/Lawecon/index.html  
and at the Social Science Research Network Electronic Paper Collection: </p>
      <p> http://ssrn.com/abstract_id=705323  
Irreversible and Catastrophic </p>
      <p>Cass R. Sunstein </p>
      <p>T H E   L A W   S C H O O L  
T H E   U N I V E R S I T Y   O F   C H I C A G O  </p>
      <p>April 2005 
Preliminary draft 3/24/05
All rights reserved</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Irreversible and Catastrophic</title>
      <sec id="sec-2-1">
        <title>Cass R. Sunstein*</title>
        <p>As many treaties and statutes emphasize, some risks are distinctive in the sense
that they are potentially irreversible or catastrophic; for such risks, it is sensible to take
extra precautions. When a harm is irreversible, and when regulators lack information
about its magnitude and likelihood, they should purchase an “option” to prevent the
harm at a later date—the Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle. This principle
brings standard option theory to bear on environmental law and risk regulation. And
when catastrophic outcomes are possible, it makes sense to take special precautions
against the worst-case scenarios—the Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle. This
principle is based on three foundations: an emphasis on people’s occasional failure to
appreciate the expected value of truly catastrophic losses; a recognition that political
actors may engage in unjustifiable delay when the costs of precautions would be incurred
immediately and when the benefits would not be enjoyed until the distant future; and an
understanding of the distinction between risk and uncertainty. The normative arguments
are illustrated throughout with reference to the problem of global warming; other
applications include injunctions in environmental cases, genetic modification of food,
protection of endangered species, and terrorism.</p>
        <p>Many losses are irreversible. Once a species is gone, it is gone forever.
Transgenic crops can impose irreversible costs as a result of increasing pest resistance.1
Because some greenhouse gases stay in the atmosphere for centuries, the problem of
global warming may be irreversible, at least for all practical purposes. Global warming
could be catastrophic as well, potentially endangering many millions of people.2
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, University of Chicago, Law
School and Department of Political Science. I am extremely grateful to Robert Goodin, Robert Hahn, Eric
Posner, Richard Posner, Adrian Vermeule, and David Weisbach, and participants in a workshop at
Columbia Law School for valuable comments; special thanks to Vermeule and Weisbach for many helpful
discussions.</p>
        <p>1 See Justus Wesseler, Resistance Economics of Transgenic Crops under Uncertainty: A Real Options
Approach, in Battling Resistance to Antibiotics and Pesticides 214 (Rmanan Lazminarayan ed. 2003); to
the same general effect, see Benoit Morel et al., Pesticide Resistance to Bt Corn: Real Option and Rational
Option Approaches to Decisionmaking, in id. at 184.</p>
        <p>2 See Richard Posner, Catastrophe: Risk and Response 43-58 (2004).</p>
        <p>Irreversible or catastrophic risks pose distinctive problems for regulators; they require
significant adjustments in the standard forms of cost-benefit analysis.3 In any case
specialists in risk perception have long emphasized the fact that under some
circumstances, people are especially averse to risks that are irreversible, potentially
catastrophic, or both.4</p>
        <p>The Precautionary Principle, used in many international documents,5 is often said
to have a special place in the context of irreversibility and catastrophe.6 Consider a few
examples:


</p>
        <p>The closing Ministerial Declaration from the United Nations Economic Conference
for Europe in 1990 asserts, “In order to achieve sustainable development, policies
must be based on the Precautionary Principle. . . . Where there are threats of serious
or irreversible damage, lack of full scientific certainty should not be used as a reason
for postponing measures to prevent environmental degradation.”7
The 1992 Rio Declaration states, “Where there are threats of serious or irreversible
damage, lack of full scientific certainty shall not be used as a reason for postponing
cost-effective measures to prevent environmental degradation.”8
The United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change states: “Where there
are threats of serious or irreversible damage, lack of full scientific certainty should
not be used as a reason for postponing [regulatory] measures, taking into account that
policies and measures to deal with climate change should be cost-effective so as to
ensure global benefits at the lowest possible cost.”9</p>
        <p>The Final Declaration of the First European “Seas At Risk” conference says that if
“the ‘worst case scenario’ for a certain activity is serious enough then even a small
amount of doubt as to the safety of that activity is sufficient to stop it taking place.”10</p>
        <p>In American law, similar ideas are at work. A special precautionary principle
underlies the analysis of preliminary injunctions in cases involving a risk of irreparable
environmental harm.11 San Francisco has adopted its own precautionary principle, with
an emphasis on seriousness and irreversibility: “Where threats of serious or irreversible
damage to people or nature exist, lack of full scientific certainty about cause and effect
shall not be viewed as sufficient reason for the City to postpone cost effective measures
to prevent the degradation of the environment or protect the health of its citizens.”12 At
the national level, the National Environmental Policy Act requires agencies to discuss
“any irreversible and irretrievable commitments of resources which would be involved in
the proposed action should it be implemented.”13 Courts have been careful to insist that
environmental impact statements should be prepared at a time that permits consideration
of environmental effects before irretrievable commitments have been made.14 A number
of federal statutes, especially in the environmental context, specifically refer to
irreversible losses and make their prevention a high priority.15</p>
        <p>For a long period, both courts and the executive branch also required agencies to
engage in “worst-case analysis,” focusing on potential catastrophes.16 That requirement
has been eliminated by the Council on Environmental Quality,17 but agencies continue to
be directed to explore “impacts which have catastrophic consequences, even if their
probability of occurrence is low.”18 Under the Clean Air Act, the Environmental
Protection Agency is asked to build an “adequate margin of safety” into health-based
national ambient air quality standards.19 This explicitly precautionary requirement is not
limited to irreversible or catastrophic harms, but it might well be understood as an effort
to ensure against them.</p>
        <p>The central notions here—irreversibility and catastrophe—play a critical role in
many domains, and they lie at the heart of countless discussions of how to deal with risks
to safety, health, and the environment. The problem is that both notions are exceedingly
ambiguous, and it is by no means clear how regulators should understand them. The
central purpose of this Article is unpack the ambiguities and to identify the proper role of
both concepts in law and policy. I shall show that standard option theory, emphasizing
the importance of irreversibility, 20 has important implications for environmental law, and
indeed that some statutes and doctrines show an implicit appreciation of this point. I shall
also show that regulators should sometimes attempt to eliminate worst-case scenarios,
even or perhaps especially if they cannot assign a probability to its occurrence. When no
such probability can be assigned, the best approach is to assess what is gained, and what
is lost, by eliminating the most catastrophic outcomes—a point that helps discipline the
inquiry into many risk-related problems, including global warming, terrorism, and
injunctions in environmental cases.</p>
        <p>These general points lead to two refined versions of the Precautionary Principle.
The first involves irreversibility: When regulators lack information about the likelihood
and magnitude of a risk, it makes sense to spend extra resources to buy an “option” to
protect against irreversible harm until future knowledge emerges. The value of the option
is that of delaying the decision until better information is available. An emphasis on
options and irreversibility leads to a distinctive principle, which I shall call the
Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle.</p>
        <p>The second principle involves catastrophe: When risks have extremely bad
worstcase scenarios, it makes sense to pay special attention to those risks, even if they are
unlikely to come to fruition and even if existing information does not enable regulators to
make a reliable judgment about the probability that they will occur. An emphasis on the
19 42 USC 7409 (b)(1). An “ample margin of safety” is mentioned in connection with hazardous air
pollutants lacking a safe thresholds, see 42 USC 7412 (d)(4).</p>
        <p>20 See Arrow and Fisher, supra note, for an early treatment.
need to attend to potentially catastrophic risks also yields a distinctive principle, which I
shall call the Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle.</p>
        <p>At first glance, these two principles seem to justify aggressive action to combat
many environmental risks, including those posed by global warming, threats to
endangered species, and genetic modification of food. Perhaps societies should invest
substantial resources in the reduction of greenhouse gases, first to prevent what might
turn out to be an irreversible loss, and second to stop the worst-case scenarios.21 Outside
of the environmental domain, the two principles bear on appropriate steps to prevent
terrorist attacks, epidemics, asteroid collisions, earthquakes, and more. An emphasis on
the two principles also has the advantage of suggesting the possibility of a rapprochement
between the risk judgments of experts and the risk judgments of ordinary people.22 As
risk analysts have long emphasized, ordinary people sometimes pay a great deal of
attention to whether risks are irreversible or potentially catastrophic.23 If the refined
precautionary principles can be defended, then ordinary intuitions turn out to be
plausible, and experts should accept them. Indeed the two principles might be combined,
in certain cases, into an Irreversible and Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle,24
which provides the strongest basis for aggressive regulation of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>At the same time, I shall show that both principles are subject to important
qualifications. The unifying claim is that the refined precautionary principles should be
implemented with wide rather than narrow viewscreens. They must be attentive to the full
range of consequences, not simply to a subset. A focus on irreversibility, and on
catastrophic harm, threatens to violate this principle through a kind of selective
perception. More particularly, the idea of irreversibility is exceedingly ambiguous;
because time is linear, every step is in a literal sense irreversible. In the technical
21 See R. Posner, supra note, at 162, 184-86, 197, and in particular emphasizing “the practically
irreversible effect of greenhouse-gas emissions on the atmospheric concentration of those gases. . . .
Making shallower cuts now can be thought of as purchasing an option to enable global warming to be
stopped or slowed at some future at a lower cost.” Id. at 162.</p>
        <p>
          22 See Paul Slovic, Perception of Risk 117, 148-
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">51 (2000</xref>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>23 See id. These psychometric studies coexist, however, with evidence that people dismiss many
lowprobability risks of catastrophe, as discussed below. A simple example is that people do not pay much
attention to the risk of asteroid collisions, even though there is a good argument that they should do so. See
Posner, supra note, at 24-29.</p>
        <p>24 An early treatment of relevant points is Talbot Page, A Generic View of Toxic Chemicals and Similar
Risks, 7 Ecology L.Q. 207 (1978).
literature, the problem of ambiguity is solved through a particular definition of
irreversibility.25 But under that definition, irreversibilities are usually on all sides of
environmental problems. If significant steps are taken to reduce greenhouse gases, those
very steps will inflict irreversible losses, environmental or economic—making it
necessary to explore their likelihood and magnitude in order to decide what to do. An
Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle is both coherent and sensible, but it calls for
precautions against the irreversible harms associated with environmental protection, as
well as against the irreversible harms associated with environmental neglect.</p>
        <p>In addition, it can be costly, and even environmentally harmful, to avoid
worstcase scenarios. If those scenarios are exceedingly unlikely, then there are clear limits on
how much regulators should do to eliminate them. If it would cost a great deal to avoid
those scenarios, or if doing so would subject people to high probabilities of very bad-case
scenarios, then avoiding the worst-case may not be sensible. It is both necessary and
possible, in short, to explore what is gained and what is lost by eliminating worst-case
scenarios. As we shall see, an understanding of the uses and limits of the refined versions
of the Precautionary Principle, focusing on irreversibility and catastrophe, casts new light
on the foundations of environmental law, and indeed on all aspects of law that deal with
the reduction of serious risks to safety and health.26</p>
        <p>This Article comes in four parts. Part I briefly explores the conventional
Precautionary Principle, with an emphasis on the fact that precautionary steps often
produce risks of their own. Part II discusses the question of irreversibility. The key point
here is that because environmental harms are often irreversible, it is appropriate to spend
resources to maintain flexibility for the future; the theory of real options has important
implications for the theory and practice of environmental law, and indeed for regulation
in general. An understanding of the problem of irreversibility also helps to explain
continuing debates over the issuance of preliminary injunctions in environmental cases.
Armed with that understanding, we can discipline the analysis of injunctions in such
cases.</p>
        <p>Part III turns to the risk of catastrophic harm. A particular focus is the difference
between risk, where probabilities can be assigned to various outcomes, and uncertainty,
where no such probabilities can be assigned. With respect to catastrophe, risk aversion is
perfectly sensible, but it is hard to defend the idea that regulators should generally seek to
eliminate the worst-case scenario, whatever the environmental and other costs of doing
so. Part III also offers some experimental evidence that people do not focus on the
worstcase scenario under circumstances of either risk or uncertainty. The most important point
here is that a form of cost-benefit balancing, perhaps with distributional weights, can
inform the decision whether to eliminate the most catastrophic outcomes. Part IV offers
some brief remarks on the question whether experts and ordinary people display “rival
rationalities,” and on the relationship of irreversibility and catastrophe to that question.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>I. The Precautionary Principle</title>
      <p>In the face of risks of environmental harm, it has become common to invoke the
Precautionary Principle, an increasingly influential idea for environmental protection.27
My principal concerns here are irreversibility and catastrophe, but in order to understand
those problems, it is necessary to explore the Precautionary Principle more generally.</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, there are twenty or more definitions of that principle, and they are
not compatible with one another.28 The most cautious and weak versions suggest, quite
sensibly, that a lack of decisive evidence of harm should not be a ground for refusing to
regulate. Controls might be justified even if it is impossible to establish a definite
connection between, for example, low-level exposures to certain carcinogens and adverse
effects on human health. Thus the Ministerial Declaration of the Second International
Conference on the Protection of the North Sea, held in London in 1987, sensibly
suggests: “Accepting that in order to protect the North Sea from possibly damaging
effects of the most dangerous substances, a Precautionary Principle is necessary which
may require action to control inputs of such substances even before a causal link has been
established by absolutely clear scientific evidence.”29</p>
      <p>The
widely
publicized</p>
      <p>Wingspread</p>
      <p>Declaration, from
a
meeting
of
environmentalists in 1998, goes much further: “When an activity raises threats of harm to
human health or the environment, precautionary measures should be taken even if some
cause and effect relationships are not established scientifically. In this context the
proponent of the activity, rather than the public, should bear the burden of proof.”30
In Europe, the Precautionary Principle is sometimes understood in a still stronger way,
suggesting that it is important to build “a margin of safety into all decision making.”31
According to one definition, the Precautionary Principle means “that action should be
taken to correct a problem as soon as there is evidence that harm may occur, not after the
harm has already occurred.”32 The word “may” is the crucial one here, because it signals
the need for corrective action even in the face of merely speculative evidence that the risk
is serious.33</p>
      <p>In a comparably strong version, it is said that “the Precautionary Principle
mandates that when there is a risk of significant health or environmental damage to others
or to future generations, and when there is scientific uncertainty as to the nature of that
damage or the likelihood of the risk, then decisions should be made so as to prevent such
activities from being conducted unless and until scientific evidence shows that the
damage will not occur.”34 What is striking about this passage is its requirement that
potentially hazardous activities be prevented until they are shown to be safe. I have noted
that the Final Declaration of the First European “Seas At Risk” conference goes so far as
to say that if “the ‘worst case scenario’ for a certain activity is serious enough then even a
small amount of doubt as to the safety of that activity is sufficient to stop it taking
place.”35
A. Hazardous Precautions</p>
      <p>The weak versions of the Precautionary Principle are unobjectionable and
important. Every day, individuals and nations take steps to avoid hazards that are far from
certain. We do not walk in moderately dangerous areas at night; we exercise; we buy
smoke detectors; we buckle our seatbelts; we might even avoid fatty foods (or
carbohydrates). Sensible governments regulate risks that, in individual cases or even in
the aggregate, have a well under 100% chance of coming to fruition.36 An individual
might ignore a mortality risk of 1/500,000, because that risk is quite small, but if 100
million citizens face that risk, the expected number of deaths is 200, and the nation had
better take the problem seriously.</p>
      <p>For the moment let us understand the Precautionary Principle in a strong way, to
suggest that regulation is required whenever there is a possible risk to health, safety, or
the environment, even if the supporting evidence remains speculative and even if the
economic costs of regulation are high. Recall that under the Final Declaration of the First
European “Seas At Risk” conference, a serious worst-case scenario is said to justify
abandonment of activity even if there is only “a small amount of doubt as to the safety of
that activity”; recall too that under the National Environmental Policy Act, agencies must
pay close attention to risks that have only a small probability of occurrence.37 To avoid
absurdity, any emphasis on the idea of “possible risk” must be understood to require a
certain threshold of scientific plausibility. To support regulation, no one thinks that it is
enough if someone, somewhere, urges that a risk is worth taking seriously. But under the
Precautionary Principle in its stronger forms, the threshold burden is minimal, and once it
is met, there is a presumption in favor of regulatory controls. This version, as we shall
see, helps to clarify a significant problem with the idea of precaution, in a way that bears
on the more refined versions as well.</p>
      <p>The real problem with the Precautionary Principle, thus understood, is that it
offers no guidance—not that it is wrong, but that it forbids all courses of action, including
regulation. Taken seriously, it is paralyzing, banning the very steps that it simultaneously
requires. In some cases, it should be easy to see that in its own way, stringent regulation
would actually run afoul of the Precautionary Principle. Consider the “drug lag,”
produced whenever the government takes a highly precautionary approach to the
introduction of new medicines and drugs onto the market.38 If a government insists on
such an approach, it will protect people against harms from inadequately tested drugs, in
a way that fits well with the goal of precaution; but it will also prevent people from
receiving potential benefits from those very drugs, and hence subjects people to serious
risks that they would not otherwise face. Is it “precautionary” to require extensive
premarketing testing, or to do the opposite? Or consider the case of DDT, often banned or
regulated in the interest of reducing risks to birds and human beings.39 The problem with
such bans is that in poor nations, they eliminate what appears to be the most effective
way
of combating
malaria—and thus significantly
undermine public health.40
Precautionary steps seem both mandated and forbidden by the idea of precaution in its
strong forms.</p>
      <p>Similar issues are raised by the continuing debate over whether certain
antidepressants impose a (small) risk of breast cancer.41 A precautionary approach might
seem to caution against use of such antidepressants because of their carcinogenic
potential. But the failure to use those depressants might well impose risks of its own,
certainly psychological and possibly even physical (because psychological ailments are
sometimes associated with physical ones as well). Or consider the decision, by the Soviet
Union, to evacuate and relocate more than 270,000 people in response to the risk of
adverse effects from the Chernobyl fallout. It is not clear that on balance, this massive
relocation project was justified on health grounds: “A comparison ought to have been
made between the psychological and medical burdens of this measure (anxiety,
psychosomatic diseases, depression and suicides) and the harm that may have been
prevented.”42 More generally, a sensible government might want to ignore the small risks
associated with low levels of radiation, on the ground that precautionary responses are
likely to cause fear that outweighs any health benefits from those responses.43</p>
      <p>The Precautionary Principle is often invoked in connection with genetic
modification of food44—a plausible invocation in light of the multiple risks created by
that practice.45 But many people believe that a failure to allow genetic modification might
well result in numerous deaths, and a small probability of many more.46 The reason is
that genetic modification holds out the promise of producing food that is both cheaper
and healthier—resulting, for example, in “golden rice,” which might have large benefits
in developing countries.47 The point is not that genetic modification will likely have those
benefits, or that the benefits of genetic modification outweigh the risks. The claim is only
that if the Precautionary Principle is taken literally, it is offended by regulation as well as
by nonregulation.</p>
      <p>The example suggests that regulation sometimes violates the Precautionary
Principle because it gives rise to substitute risks, in the form of hazards that materialize,
or are increased, as a result of regulation.48 It is possible to go much further. A great deal
of evidence suggests the possibility that an expensive regulation can have adverse effects
on life and health.49 An early study found that a statistical life can be lost for every
expenditure of $7 million50; one study suggests that an expenditure of $15 million
produces a loss of life.51 Another suggests that poor people are especially vulnerable to
this effect—that a regulation that reduces wealth for the poorest 20% of the population
will have twice as large a mortality effect as a regulation that reduces wealth for the
wealthiest 20%.52 To be sure, both the phenomenon and the underlying mechanisms are
disputed.53 It is unnecessary to accept any particular amount here, or even to suggest that
there has been an unambiguous demonstration of an association between mortality and
regulatory expenditures. The only point is that reasonable people believe in that
association. It follow that a multimillion dollar expenditure for “precaution” has—as a
worst case scenario—significant adverse health effects, with an expenditure of $600
million as leading to perhaps as many as sixty lives lost.</p>
      <p>This point makes the Precautionary Principle hard to implement not merely where
regulation removes “opportunity benefits,” or introduces or increases substitute risks, but
in any case in which the regulation costs a significant amount. If this is so, the
Precautionary Principle, for that very reason, raises doubts about many regulations. If the
principle argues against any action that carries a small risk of imposing significant harm,
then regulators should be reluctant to require large expenditures to reduce risks, simply
because those expenditures themselves carry risks. Here is the sense in which, the
Precautionary Principle is paralyzing: It stands as an obstacle to regulation and
nonregulation, and to everything in between.</p>
      <p>A nation-by-nation study commissioned by the German Federal Environmental
Agency goes so far as to conclude that there are two separate camps in the industrialized
world: “precaution countries” (Germany, Sweden, the Netherlands, and the United
States) and “protection countries” (Japan, France, and the United Kingdom).54 If the
argument thus far is correct, this conclusion is implausible—not empirically but
conceptually. The universe of risks is far too large to permit categorizations of this kind.
The most general point is that no nation is precautionary in general and costly precautions
are inevitably taken against only those hazards that seem especially salient or insistent.55
Taken in its strongest and crudest forms, the Precautionary Principle wrongly suggests
that nations can and should adopt a general form of risk aversion. It is possible to take
precautions against particular risks, but it is not possible to take precautions against all of
them. It is possible to display aversion to particular hazards, but it is not possible to
display aversion to all of them.56
54 See Sand, supra note, at 448.</p>
      <p>55 See David Vogel, The Hare and the Tortoise Revisited: The New Politics of Consumer and
Environmental regulation in Europe, 33 B. J. Pol. S. 557, 570-71 (2003). for a demonstration of this point
for Europe.</p>
      <p>56 It might be tempting to defend the Precautionary Principle—certainly in the context of health, safety,
and the environment—on the ground that early warnings, in the form of merely suggestive evidence of
harm, often turn out to be correct. See The Precautionary Principle in the Twenty-First Century, supra note.
And it is right to insist that indisputable proof of harm should not be required to justify regulation; this is
the sense in which the weak version of the principle is both unobjectionable and important. But the fact that
suggestive evidence must be taken seriously does not render the strong version coherent, simply because
B. A Note on Distributional Issues</p>
      <p>Those who endorse the Precautionary Principle often do so on grounds of
fairness, believing that the principle will assist the most vulnerable members of society.57
Does the principle actually have that effect? In the United States, the Clean Air Act takes
a highly precautionary approach, requiring an “adequate margin of safety” and hence
regulation in the face of scientific uncertainty.58 At the same time, the Clean Air Act
delivers especially large benefits to poor people and members of minority groups—larger
benefits, on balance, than it gives to wealthy people.59 In the international domain,
aggressive action to combat climate change would be more beneficial to poor countries
than to wealthy ones.60 In the context of global warming, at least, the Precautionary
Principle might be invoked to prevent especially severe burdens on those in the worst
position to bear them.</p>
      <p>It makes a great deal of sense to emphasize the distribution of domestic or
international risks, and the distributional effects of global warming are among the
strongest points in favor of aggressive regulation of greenhouse gases.61 But in many
cases, the Precautionary Principle, as applied, would have unfortunate distributional
effects. Consider the case of DDT. A ban on DDT, often supported by reference to the
suggestive evidence of harm is often on all sides. In any case, suggestive evidence of harm has often been
found not to be an early warning worth heeding, but instead a false alarm, producing unjustified fear and
significant social losses of many kinds. See Aaron Wildavsky, But Is It True? (1996). Consider, for
example, fears of contaminated cranberries in 1959, of MSG in Chinese restaurants in 1968, of cyclamates
in 1968, of flouordated water in 1950, and of mercury in tuna in 1970. All of these widely publicized
“hazards” turned out to pose no serious risk. See Allan Mazur, True Warnings and False Alarms 110-141
(2004). For a valuable effort to distinguish between prescient warnings and false ones, see id. at 97-109,
and in particular the suggestion tat the “clearest hallmark of a true public warning during the period
19481971 was a reputable scientific news source. Warnings reaching the press from scientists operating in a
conventional way at an orthodox scientific institution were true more than twice as often as those reaching
the news from government officials or citizen advocates.” Id. at 87.</p>
      <p>57 See, e.g., Frank Ackerman and Lisa Heinzerling, Priceless (2004).
58 42 USC 7409 (b)(1).
59 See Matthew E. Kahn, The Beneficiaries of Clean Air Act Regulation, 24(1) Regulation 34 (2001).
60 See, e.g., Joseph Aldy, Peter Orszag, &amp; Joseph Stiglitz, Climate Change: An Agenda for Gloval
Collective Action (unpublished manuscript 2001); Bjorn Lomborg, The Skeptical Environmentalist
291302 (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2001).</p>
      <p>
        61 Note, however, that if the concern involves poor countries, it is not clear that global warming is an
especially high priority, in light of the many needs of those countries, needs that might be addressed by
wealthier nations. For controversial but illuminating treatments, see Bjorn Lomborg, The Skeptical
Environmentalist 322-23 (2001); Indur Goklany, The Precautionary Principle: A Critical Appraisal of
Environmental Risk Assessment 71-8
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">8 ( 2001</xref>
        ).
Precautionary Principle, is eminently justified in wealthy nations. But such a ban is likely
to have—and is actually having—unfortunate effects in at least some poor countries,
where DDT is the cheapest and most effective way of combating serious diseases, most
notably malaria.62 The case of genetic modification of food might well be a similar
example; according to some projections, the benefits are likely to be enjoyed by poor
people, not the wealthy.63 And recall that expensive regulations have a disproportionately
serious effect on poor people, simply because any price increases are hardest for them to
handle, and because the costs of regulation may well manifest themselves in fewer and
less remunerative jobs.64
      </p>
      <p>Distributional issues should indeed be a central concern of a system of risk
regulation,65 but the Precautionary Principle is a crude, indirect, and sometimes perverse
way of incorporating distributional concerns. As a result, an emphasis on distribution
does not rescue the Precautionary Principle from the charge of incoherence. The real
question is whether more refined understandings of the principle can be developed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-4">
      <title>II. Uncertainty, Options, and Irreversibility</title>
      <p>It is possible to identify an Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle, applicable
to a subset of environmental risks.66 On plausible assumptions, the problem of
irreversibility does justify aggressive measures to combat environmental risks, under a
general attitude of “act, then learn,” as opposed to the tempting alternative of “wait and
learn.” With respect to global warming, for example, some people believe that it is most
sensible to use research as the first line of defense, refusing to commit substantial
resources until evidence of harm is clear.67 But if research alone allows continued
emissions to produce irreversible risks, it might be best to take precautions now as a way
of preserving future flexibility.68 In the environmental context in general, this point
suggest that regulators should proceed with far more aggressive measures than would
otherwise seem justified.69</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-5">
      <title>A. Option Value vs. Use Value</title>
      <p>Begin with the monetary valuation of an environmental amenity, such as a
pristine area. Some people will be willing to pay to use the area; others will be willing to
pay to preserve it, even if they will not use it. Hence “existence value” is sometimes
included in the valuation of environmental amenities,70 and indeed federal courts have
insisted that agencies pay attention to that value in assessing damages to natural
resources.71 But people are also willing to pay for the option to use an environmental
amenity in the future, even if they are unsure whether they will exercise that option.72
Suppose that a pristine area might be developed in a way that ensures irreversible change.
Many people would be willing to pay a significant amount to preserve their option. Under
federal law, option value must also be considered in the assessment of natural resource
damages.73 Many regulations explore the role of option value in the environmental
context.74</p>
      <p>Here, then, is a simple sense in which irreversible environmental harm causes a
loss that is not adequately captured in the standard economic measure of value. Some
skeptics contend that it “is hard to imagine a price for an irreversible loss,”75 but people
do identify prices for such losses.76</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-6">
      <title>B. The Basic Argument</title>
      <p>The idea of option value, as used in the monetary valuation literature just
discussed, is closely related to the use of the notion of “options” in the domain that I shall
be emphasizing here. The simple claim is that when regulators are dealing with an
irreversible loss, and when they are uncertain about the timing and likelihood of that loss,
they should be willing to pay a sum—the option value—in order to maintain flexibility
for the future.77 The option might not be exercised if it turns out that the loss is not a
serious one. But if the option is purchased, regulators will be in a position to forestall the
loss if it turns out to be large.</p>
      <p>In the domain of finance, options take multiple forms.78 An investor might be
willing to purchase land that is known to have deposits of gold; even if the cost of
extraction is too high to justify mining, ownership of the land creates an option to mine if
the cost falls.79 A standard “call option” is a right to purchase an asset prior to a specific
date at a specified price.80 In another variation, people might seek the right to abandon a
project at a fixed price, perhaps on the occurrence of a specified set of events.
Alternatively, they might obtain the right to scale back a project, to expand it, or to
extend its life. Options that recognize multiple sources of uncertainty, of the sort that can
be found for many environmental problems, are termed “rainbow options.”81</p>
      <p>Option theory has countless applications outside of the domain of investments.
Suppose, for example, that because of law or social norms, it is difficult to divorce, so
willing to incur costs to maintain their flexibility before marrying—higher costs than they
would be willing to incur if divorce were easier. Narrow judicial rulings, of the sort
celebrated by judicial minimalists,83 can be understood as a way of “buying” an option, or
at least of “paying” a certain amount in return for flexibility. Judges who leave things
undecided, and who focus their rulings on the facts of particular cases, are in a sense
forcing themselves, and society as a whole, to purchase an option to pay for flexibility in
the resolution of subsequent problems. Whether that option is worthwhile depends on its
price and the benefits that it provides.</p>
      <p>It should be readily apparent how an emphasis on option value might explain the
emphasis, in NEPA and other environmental statutes, on irreversible losses. The central
point of NEPA is to ensure that environmental factors receive serious consideration,84
and if irreversible losses are involved, the delay produced by the duty to generate an
environmental impact statement can be seen as payment for an option. It should also be
clear that the idea of option value might help give content to the Precautionary Principle,
which would, on this view, be understood as requiring societies to pay a kind of premium
in the face of potentially irreversible losses.85 An important implication involves global
warming; the argument for a global carbon tax is significantly strengthened by an
appreciation of the option value of conserving the atmospheric environment.86 Let us
elaborate the argument for the Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle.</p>
      <p>In a classic essay, Arrow and Fisher demonstrate that the ideas of uncertainty and
irreversibility have considerable importance to the theory of environmental protection.87
They imagine a situation in which the question is whether to preserve a virgin redwood
forest for wilderness recreation or instead to open it to clear-cut logging. Assume that if
the development option is chosen, the destruction of the forest is effectively
assess the costs or benefits of a proposed development. If development produces “some
irreversible transformation of the environment, hence a loss in perpetuity of the benefits
from preservation,” then it is worth paying something to wait to acquire the missing
information. Their suggestion is that “the expected benefits of an irreversible decision
should be adjusted to reflect the loss of options it entails.”89</p>
      <p>Much more recently, Fisher has generalized this argument to suggest that
“[w]here a decision problem is characterized by (1) uncertainty about future costs and
benefits of the alternatives, (2) prospects for resolving or reducing the uncertainty with
the passage of time, and (3) irreversibility of one or more of the alternatives, an extra
value, an option value, properly attaches to the reversible alternative(s).”90 To pass a
costbenefit test, it follows that an irreversible decision must clear a higher hurdle. The
intuition here is both straightforward and appealing: More steps should be taken to
prevent harms that are effectively final than to prevent those that can be reversed at some
cost. If an irreversible harm is on side, and a reversible one on the other, an
understanding of option value suggests that it is worthwhile to spend a certain amount to
preserve future flexibility, by paying a premium to avoid the irreversible harm.</p>
      <p>Judge Richard Posner has invoked a point of this sort as a justification for
aggressive steps to combat global warming.91 Posner acknowledges that the nature of the
threat of global warming is disputed, and hence it is tempting to wait to regulate until we
have more information. But there is a serious problem with waiting, which is “the
practically irreversible effect of greenhouse-gas emissions on the atmospheric
concentration of those gases.”92 Thus Posner concludes that making “shallower cuts now
can be thought of as purchasing an option to enable global warming to be stopped or
88 The assumption may be unrealistic, under ordinary understandings of what counts as irreversibility. If
seeds are retained, the forest can be recreated, though perhaps with a significant interim loss. I deal below
with some of the complexities in the notion of irreversibility.</p>
      <p>89 Id. at 319.
90 See Anthony Fisher, Uncertainty, Irreversibility, and the Timing of Climate Policy 9 (2001).
91 See Richard A. Posner, Catastrophe 161-62 (2004). A more technical discussion to the same effect is
Graciela Chichilnisky and Geoffey Heal, Global Environmental Risks, 7 J Econ Perspectives 65 (1993),
emphasizing the need for a distinctive approach to “risks that are poorly understood, endogenous,
collective, and irreversible.” Id. at 67; see especially pp. 76-84 for a treatment of option value and
irreversibility.</p>
      <p>92 Posner, supra note, at 161.
uncertainty. Perhaps regulators are usually able to assign probabilities to outcomes; and if
if not, perhaps they can assign probabilities to probabilities (or, if this proves impossible,
probabilities to probabilities of probabilities). In many cases regulators might be able to
specify a range of probabilities—saying, for example, that the probability of catastrophic
outcomes from global warming is above 2% but below 30%.212 Many scientists and
economists believe that global warming is not likely to create catastrophic harm, and that
the real costs, human and economic, will be high but not intolerable. In their view, the
worst-case scenarios can be responsibly described as improbable.213</p>
      <p>Perhaps we can agree that pure uncertainty is rare. Perhaps we can agree that at
worst, environmental problems involve problems of “bounded uncertainty,” in which we
cannot assign probabilities within specified bands. It is possible to think, for example,
that the risk of a catastrophic outcome is above 1% but below 10%, without being able to
assign probabilities within that band. The pervasiveness of uncertainty depends on what
is actually known. As I have emphasized, Posner believes that “no probabilities can be
attached to the catastrophic global-warming scenarios, and without an estimate of
probabilities an expected cost cannot be calculated.”214 Note in this regard that a 1994
survey of experts showed an extraordinary range of estimated losses from global
warming, varying from no economic loss to a 20% decrease in gross world product.215
This finding, it has been suggested, is enough to support the view that uncertainty is real
and must be taken seriously in environmental policy.216 In my view, uncertainty is both
real and rare in the environmental domain; but this is an empirical judgment, and it may
be wrong.</p>
      <p>5. On maximin, rationality, and genuine uncertainty. Now turn to the most
difficult question: What is the appropriate approach to genuine uncertainty? Is maximin a
rational strategy? I begin with some points about actual behavior and then turn to
normative issues.
show a degree of uncertainty aversion, in the sense that they will avoid gambles to which
probabilities are not assigned. The relevant work was done by Daniel Ellsberg.217 Assume
that people are asked to choose among two lotteries, each involving an urn with 100
balls. All of the balls are either black or red. For the first lottery, the urn contains an equal
division of black and red balls. For the second lottery, the urn contains an unknown
proportion of black balls and red balls. People receive a specified amount of money for
correctly guessing the color of balls randomly chosen from the urn. It turns out that most
people prefer the first lottery to the second, and thus display aversion to uncertainty.218
On the assumption of uncertainty aversion, it might be possible to defend maximin as a
decision rule.219</p>
      <p>Note, however, that uncertainty aversion is bounded. So long as uncertainty
aversion is not infinite, maximin will not always be the preferred decision rule. And
indeed it is reasonable to think that most people will reject maximin if the question is
properly framed. To test this possibility, I asked seventy-one University of Chicago law
students the following problem:</p>
      <p>The government is considering two environmental problems. For the first, the
government is able to estimate the probability that a bad outcome will occur. It believes
that there is a 90% chance that 600 people will die (and the death of 500 people is the
worst-case scenario). It also believes that there is a 10% chance that 400 people will die.
For the second problem, the government cannot assign probabilities to the various
outcomes. The “worst-case scenario” is that 700 people will die.</p>
      <p>Do you think:
(a) the first problem has higher priority?
(b) the second problem has higher priority?
(c) the two problems have equal priority?</p>
      <p>No fewer than 63% chose (a), with the remainder equally divided between (b) and
(c). As noted above, law students at any particular institution may offer idiosyncratic
responses to such questions; but within the general population, it is reasonable to
217 See Daniel Ellsberg, Risk, Ambiguity, and the Savage Axioms, 75 Q J Econ 643 (1961).
218 Id.
219 Chu and Liu, supra note, at 265-66; Woodward and Bishop, supra note, at 496-98.
conjecture that most people will show no consistent preference for maximin, and that
they will reject an approach that eliminates the worst worst-case scenario, under
circumstances of uncertainty, in favor of an approach that eliminates a highly probable
but somewhat less bad worst-case scenario.</p>
      <p>Why is this? The Principle of Insufficient Reason says that when people lack
information about probabilities (say, 1% to 40%), they should act as if each probability is
equally likely.220 Whatever its normative status,221 actual decisions may well use that
principle, which fits well with the results in the experiment just described. Consider
another experiment with a larger group of law students from two institutions (the</p>
      <sec id="sec-6-1">
        <title>University of Alabama and the University of Chicago222):</title>
        <p>One thousand people are at risk from an environmental hazard. (a) If one
approach is taken, a minimum of 400 people will die, and a maximum of 500 people will
die. Regulators are unable to assign probabilities to the various outcomes. (b) If another
approach is taken, a minimum of 10 people will die, and a maximum of 600 people will
die. Regulators are unable to assign probabilities to the various outcomes. Which
approach should be chosen?
(a) The first approach
(b) The second approach</p>
        <p>No less than 85.5% of respondents rejected maximin and chose (b). Why did (b)
seem better to so many respondents? On a reasonable interpretation, people begin by
presuming at least roughly equal probabilities under circumstances of uncertainty, and
conclude that they would much rather go the route that has a much higher expected value,
given that presumption. This interpretation is supported by the results of the following
experiment,223 which asks people to compare a choice under risk with a choice under
uncertainty:</p>
        <p>The government is considering two environmental problems. For the first, the
government is able to estimate the probability that a bad outcome will occur. It believes
that there is a 60% chance that 500-600 people will die (and the death of 600 people is
220 See Duncan Luce and Howard Raiffa, Games and Decisions 284 (1958).
221 Id.; Isaac Levi, On Indeterminate Probabilities, 71 J. Phil 391 (1974).</p>
        <p>222 One hundred and seventy-three law students were surveyed, seventy-one from the University of
Chicago, one hundred and two from the University of Alabama. Interestingly, the answers from the two
groups were essentially identical.</p>
        <p>223 This experiment was limited to seventy-one University of Chicago law students.
the worst-case scenario). It also believes that there is a 40% chance that 200-400 people
will die. For the second problem, the government cannot assign probabilities to the
various outcomes. The worst-case scenario is that 700 people will die.</p>
        <p>Do you think:
(a)
(b)
(c)
the first problem has higher priority?
the second problem has higher priority?
the two problems have equal priority?</p>
        <p>For this problem, maximin was also rejected by a majority of respondents, but
here the margin was much thinner: 52% favored (a), 25% were undecided, and 22%
favored (b). The rejection of maximin is the most striking result here, and it is not entirely
clear why the choice seemed relatively difficult. But the Principle of Insufficient Reason
is consistent with that difficulty. Under the second problem, the expected number of
deaths is 350 is equal probabilities are assigned, a number that is close to the expected
number of deaths for the first problem; with a small degree of risk aversion, the choice
between the two problems becomes extremely difficult.</p>
        <p>To see the role of the Principle of Insufficient Reason, suppose that people are
asked to choose between:
a 99.5% chance of a loss of 200 lives, and a .5% chance of a loss of 2
lives, with
an uncertain chance of losing between 2 lives and 205 lives.</p>
        <p>For most people, it is reasonable to suppose that a) is much worse than b)—and
hence that b) will be the overwhelming choice. Here, then, people will select a choice that
eliminate the worst-case scenario. But compare:
c)
d)
a risk of 60% of a loss of 200 lives, and 40% of 2 lives, with
an uncertain chance of losing between 205 lives and 2 lives.</p>
        <p>For most people, the choice here is much less clear, and it is likely that many
people will choose c) and refuse to follow maximin. It follows that people would have a
great deal of difficulty in choosing between a 51% risk of a loss of 200 lives, and a 49%
chance of a loss of 1 life, as compared with an uncertain risk that threatens to produce
losses of between 200 and 1 lives, with no possibility of assigning probabilities to the
various possibilities.</p>
        <p>The precise role of the Principle of Insufficient Reason, and the nature of people’s
choices under circumstances of uncertainty, remain to be established. The discussion thus
far should be enough to show that people will often reject maximin and that the Principle
of Insufficient Reason is a starting point for their intuitions. The implication for
environmental protection, and for other problems involving safety and health, is clear.
People will not consistently follow maximin under circumstances of uncertainty. If the
worst-case scenario is extremely vivid, and if it is drawn to their attention, they might
neglect the issue of probability and attempt to eliminate it.224 But under ordinary
circumstances, they will select maximin only when the Principle of Insufficient Reason,
accompanied by a degree of risk aversion, suggests that they should.</p>
        <p>(b) A cost-benefit analysis of maximin? A great deal of work explores the question
whether people should follow maximin under circumstances of uncertainty.225 Some of
this work draws on people’s intuitions, in a way that illuminates actual beliefs but may
tell us little about what rationality requires.226 Those intuitions, of the sort described by
the experiments above, may be based on some kind of confusion. Other work is highly
formal, 227 adopting certain axioms and seeing whether maximin violates them. The
results of this work are not conclusive.228 Certainly maximin has not been ruled out as a
candidate for rational choice under uncertainty.</p>
        <p>I cannot resolve these difficult issues here, but will rest content with a general
suggestion. In deciding whether to follow maximin in the environmental context, a great
deal should turn on two questions: (a) How bad is the worst-case scenario, compared to
other bad outcomes? (b) What, exactly, is lost by choosing maximin? Of course it is
possible that choosers, including regulators, will lack the information that would enable
them to answer these questions. But in the regulatory context, answers to both (a) and (b)
may well be possible even if it is not possible to assign probabilities to the various
outcomes with any confidence. By emphasizing the relative badness of the worst-case
scenario, and the extent of the loss from attending to it, I am attempting to build on the
Rawls/Gardiner suggestion that maximin is the preferred decision rule when little is lost
from following it. I have objected that this suggestion threatens to trivialize the case for
maximin; but it is possible to develop the underlying intuition into a far more general,
and useful, method for orienting both private and public choice.</p>
        <p>To see the relevance of the two questions, suppose that you are choosing between
two options. The first has a best-case outcome of 10 and a worst-case outcome of –5. The
second has a best-case outcome of 15 and a worst-case outcome of –6. It is impossible to
assign probabilities to the various outcomes. Maximin would favor the first option, to
avoid the worse worst-case; but to justify that choice, we have to know something about
the meaning of the difference s between 10 and 15 on the one hand and –5 and –6 on the
other. If 15 is much better than 10, and if the difference between –5 and –6 is a matter of
relative indifference, then the choice of the first option is hardly mandated. But if the
difference between –5 and –6 greatly matters—if it is a matter of life and death—then
maximin is much more attractive.</p>
        <p>These points have the important implication of suggesting the possibility of a
(rough) cost-benefit analysis229 of maximin under conditions of uncertainty. Sometimes a
rejection of maximin is compelled by that analysis because the worst-case scenario is not
much worse than the second worst-case scenario (and hence the benefits of maximin are
low),and because maximin imposes extremely high costs.230 But sometimes the
worst229 By suggesting this possibility, I do not mean to assign dollar equivalents to the various outcomes or to
say anything controversial about the ingredients of the analysis. I am referring generally to an
all-thingsconsidered approach to social welfare.</p>
        <p>230 It might be suggested that when people reason in this way, they are implicitly assigning probabilities
to the relevant events. Suppose that the choice is between (a), with uncertain payoffs of 15 or 5, and (b)
with uncertain payoffs of 8 or 6; suppose too that 15 is much better than 8 and that 5 is only a little worse
than 6. On the analysis in text, (a) should be chosen. But perhaps that judgment depends on an implicit
assignment of a significant probability, in case (a), to 15, and of an assignment of some probability of less
than (say) 99%, in case (b), to 5. Without some such implicit assignment of probabilities, why would (a) be
preferable? I cannot prove the point here, but I believe that this question, and this counterargument, are
based on a denial of the possibility of acting under conditions of genuine uncertainty. If such conditions
exist, and if people act under them, then they might indeed be assigning implicit probabilities; but they
might also be acting in terms of the principles described in the text.
case is the worst by far, and sometimes we lose relatively little by choosing maximin. It is
typically thought necessary to assign probabilities in order to engage in cost-benefit
balancing; without an understanding of probabilities, such balancing might not seem able
to get off the ground.231 But a useful form of cost-benefit balancing is possible even
without reliable information about probability. For the balancing exercise to work, of
course, it must be possible to produce cardinal rankings among the outcomes—that is, it
must be possible to rank them not merely in terms of their badness but also in at least
rough terms of how much worse each is than the less-bad others. That approach will not
work if cardinal rankings are not feasible—as might be the case if (for example) it is not
easy to compare the catastrophic loss from global warming with the loss from huge
expenditures on reductions of greenhouse gas emissions. Much of the time, however,
cardinal rankings are possible.</p>
        <p>Irreversibility becomes highly relevant as part of this analysis. Recall that some of
the costs of precautions are irreversible. If governments invest a great deal to control
greenhouse gas emissions, they will be forcing private and public actors to incur
irreversible costs. It follows that if governments follow maximin, they will be limiting
their own flexibility , expending a great deal even though future information might move
the situation from uncertainty to risk, as regulators learn more about the problem.
Suppose that no probability can now be assigned to the catastrophic risk associated with
abrupt global warming, and that for this reason regulators are tempted to spend a great
deal to eliminate that risk. The relevant expenditures will greatly reduce future flexibility,
ensuring sunk costs for a danger that might turn out to be quantifiable or even trivial.
This point is not decisive against large expenditures, but it should be part of the analysis
of whether worst-case scenarios ought to be eliminated. In this sense, there can be some
tension between an Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle and a Catastrophic Harm
Precautionary Principle.</p>
        <p>Imagine, then, two polar situations with respect to global warming. First, suppose
that the catastrophic dangers associated with global warming could be eliminated if every
nation contributed $10 million to a fund to combat that risk. On reasonable assumptions,
that cost would be fully acceptable. Second, suppose that the catastrophic dangers
231 See Ackerman and Heinzerling, supra note.
associated with global warming could be eliminated only if every nation contributed
enough resources to reduce standards of living by 50% world-wide, with a corresponding
increase in global poverty. If global warming really does pose an uncertain danger of
total catastrophe, maximin argues in favor of this extraordinary reduction in world-wide
standards of living. But to incur costs of this magnitude, we might want to insist that the
danger of catastrophe rise about the minimal threshold—that there be demonstrable
probability, and a not-so-low one, that the catastrophic risk will occur.</p>
        <p>To appreciate this point, and the need for an analysis of the effects of following
maximin, imagine an individual or society lacking the information that would permit the
assignment of probabilities to a series of hazards with catastrophic outcomes; suppose
that the number of hazards is ten, or a twenty, or a thousand. Suppose too that such an
individual or society is able to assign probabilities (ranging from 1% to 90%) to an
equivalent number of other hazards, with outcomes that range from bad to extremely bad,
but never catastrophic. Suppose finally that every one of these hazards can be eliminated
at a cost—a cost that is high, but that does not, once incurred in individual cases, inflict
harms that count as extremely bad or catastrophic. The maximin principle suggests that
our individual or society should spend a great deal to eliminate each of the ten, or twenty,
or hundred potentially catastrophic hazards. But once that amount is spent on even one of
those hazards, there might be nothing left to combat the extremely bad hazards, even
those with a 90% chance of occurring. We could even imagine that a poorly informed
individual or society would be condemned to real poverty and distress, or even worse,
merely by virtue of following maximin. In these circumstances, maximin should be
rejected.</p>
        <p>This suggestion derives indirect support from the empirical finding that when
asked to decide on the distribution of goods and services, most people reject the two most
widely discussed principles in the philosophical literature: average utility, favored by
Harsanyi, and Rawls’ difference principle (allowing inequalities only if they work to the
advantage to the least well-off).232 Instead people choose average utility with a floor
constraint—that is, they favor an approach that maximizes overall well-being, but subject
232Norman Frohlich and Joe A. Oppenheimer, Choosing Justice: An Experimental Approach to Ethical
Theory (1992).
to the constraint that no member of society may fall below a decent minimum.233
Insisting on an absolute welfare minimum to all, they maximize over that floor. Their
aversion to especially bad outcomes leads them to a pragmatic threshold in the form of
the floor. So too, very plausibly, in the context of precautions against risks. A sensible
individual, or society, would not always choose maximin under circumstances of risk or
uncertainty. Everything depends on what is lost, and what is gained, by eliminating the
worst-case scenario; and much of that time, available information makes it possible to
answer those questions at least in general terms.</p>
        <p>Nothing here is meant as a proof that maximin is forbidden, or even not required,
by rationality. To decide on the relationship between rationality and maximin strategies,
it is necessary to specify the right account of rationality.234 I am doubtful that any such
specification can establish the status of maximin without making contentious
assumptions. My claim is instead that maximin makes most sense when the worst-case
scenario, under one course of action, is much worse than the worst-case scenario under
the alternative course of action, and when the choice of maximin does not result in
extremely significant losses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-7">
      <title>G. Dealing with Catastrophic Risks</title>
      <p>The most general conclusion is that a degree of risk aversion should be expected
in cases of catastrophic risks; for such risks, margins of safety are entirely sensible. For
this reason, a Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle, of the sort suggested by several
understandings of the Precautionary Principle, is a coherent and defensible part of
environmental policy.235 Indeed, such a principle might well be the best understanding of
the Precautionary Principle itself. It has many uses, not only in environmental policy but
in health and safety regulation as a whole, including the war on terrorism.</p>
      <p>But maximin is not generally a sensible strategy in the environmental context or
elsewhere. First, it is senseless under circumstances of risk, unless we assume an
implausibly high degree of risk aversion. Second, regulators are rarely operating under
circumstances of pure uncertainty; often rough probabilities can be ascribed to serious
233 Id.
234 See Luce and Raiffa, supra note, at 286-97.
235 See notes supra.
outcomes, and if not, at least rough probabilities can be ascribed to probabilities. Third,
adoption of maximin, under circumstances of genuine uncertainty, is most reasonable
when the worst-case scenario is exceptionally bad and when removal of that scenario
does not inflict serious losses of its own.</p>
      <p>It follows that a Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle is best understood to
embody a form of risk aversion for the most dangerous risks. Its central domain involves
. uncertain dangers of catastrophe when the costs of reducing those dangers are not huge
and when incurring those costs does not divert substantial resources from extremely
pressing problems. Four qualifications are important:
1. The Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle must be attentive to the full range of
social risks; it makes no sense to take steps to avert catastrophe if those very steps
would create catastrophic risks of their own. If a preventive war, designed to reduce
the risks of terrorism from one source, would increase those very risks from another
source, then the Catastrophic Harm Precautionary Principle is indeterminate. This
point is a simple extension of that made earlier with respect to the unrefined
Precautionary Principle and the Irreversible Harm Precautionary Principle.
2. Use of the principle should be closely attentive to the idea of cost-effectiveness,
which requires regulators to choose the least costly means of achieving their ends. In
the context of global warming, there are many methods by which to reduce the
relevant risks.236 Both nations and international institutions should choose those
methods that minimize costs. The same is true for efforts to combat terrorism.
3. Here as elsewhere, distributional considerations matter. The principle should be
applied in a way that reduces extreme burdens on those least able to bear them. For
global warming, there is a particular need to ensure that citizens of poor nations are
not required to pay a great deal to contribute to the solution of a problem for which
those in wealthy nations are most responsible.237 If an antiterrorism policy would
impose special burdens on members of racial and religious minority groups—
consider racial profiling—it is worth considering other policies that reduce or
eliminate those burdens.
236 A good discussion is Nordhaus and Boyer, Warming the World, supra note, at 121-44.
237 See the overview in R. Percival et al., supra note.
4. Costs matter as such. The extent of precautions cannot reasonably be divorced from
their expense. In cases of the kind I am discussing, where the worst-case scenario is
truly catastrophic and when probabilities cannot be assigned, a large margin of safety
makes a great deal of sense.238</p>
      <p>There is a final point. It is possible to combine a concern about catastrophe with a
focus on irreversible harm, in a way that generates an Irreversible and Catastrophic Harm
Precautionary Principle. Suppose that by adopting environmental controls at the present
time, regulators can maintain flexibility to prevent a risk that is not only irreversible but
potentially catastrophic as well. Suppose too that the likelihood of catastrophe cannot be
specified with much confidence, or even that it is in the domain of uncertainty rather than
risk. Risk-neutral, risk-averse, or uncertainty-averse regulators might be willing to pay a
great deal to maintain the flexibility that would permit them to avoid the worst-case
scenarios. We have seen that significant expenditures can reduce flexibility too; many
problems involve not irreversibility, but irreversibilities. At the same time, the most
important irreversibilities may well turn out to be environmental in character.</p>
      <p>This argument provides the strongest basis for aggressive measures to combat
global warming.239 The natural objections would either point to the irreversible costs of
maintaining flexibility or question the probability that catastrophe will actually ensue.
The appropriate conclusion rests on an assessment of the empirical questions,240 but in
my view, an appreciation of irreversibility and catastrophe argues for otherwise excessive
steps to reduce greenhouse gases.241</p>
      <p>238 See Woodward and Bishop, supra note, at 505: “If one considers a spectrum of choice problems from
pure uncertainty to pure risk, almost all of the attention of economics has been on one extreme. . . . This has
led to policy advice and analysis that either implicitly or explicitly requires policymakers to divine
probability distributions. We argue, however, that there are important cases where probability distributions
cannot be reasonably formulated and under such conditions dramatically different decision criteria may be
rational.”
239 See Posner, supra note, at 161-65.
240 See Fisher, supra note, for a good discussion.
241 See id.; William Cline, Climate Change, in Global Crises, Global Solutions, supra note, at 13, 15-21.</p>
      <p>When it comes to risk, why do experts disagree with ordinary people? Many
people think that the reason lies in the fact that ordinary people have a “rival
rationality.”242 On this view, experts are concerned with statistics, and, above all, with the
number of lives at stake.243 By contrast, ordinary people are concerned with a range of
qualitative factors that make certain risks a special cause of concern. Irreversibility and
catastrophe are said to loom especially large in ordinary people’s reactions.244 Where
experts simply calculate expected values, ordinary people, and lay rationality, show
special aversion to potentially irreversible and catastrophic harm. If this is so, ordinary
people display “rival rationalities,” and each “side must respect the insights and
intelligence of the other.”245</p>
      <p>According to a competing view, the rival rationality of ordinary people is mostly a
product of cognitive illusions, ignorance, and confusion.246 For the critics, ordinary
people are also concerned with the central question, which is the number of lives at stake.
Unfortunately, they are unable to answer that question well. When ordinary people show
a concern about irreversible and catastrophic harms, it is because they fear that many
lives are at risk, no less and no more.</p>
      <p>The discussion thus far suggests a possible rapprochement between the apparently
rival rationalities. Sensible experts do not and should not believe that there is any
particular magic in irreversibility, and they do and should insist that the line between
catastrophic and non-catastrophic harm is one of degree. But they should also agree that
irreversibility matters, in the sense that it makes sense to spend resources to maintain
246 See Howard Margolis, Dealing With Risk (1995).
242. See SLOVIC, supra note, at 220-31.
243. See id. at 223.</p>
      <p>
        244. See Clayton P. Gillette &amp; James E. Krier, Risk, Courts, and Agencies, 138 U. Pa. L. Rev. 1027,
1061-1085 (1990). Note that the evidence describe above suggests that in certain settings, potentially
catastrophic outcomes will receive less, not more, attention than their expected value, perhaps because
people treat very low-probability risks (eg, 1 in 1 million) as if they were zero. The framing of the question
undoubtedly matters a great deal here. Probably the best generalization is that people sometimes give low
probability risks of catastrophe more attention than its expected value and sometimes give them more less.
See Gary H. McClelland et al., supra note. I suspect that in some of the relevant studies, the evidence of
grave concern for catastrophic harms stems from the affect heuristic, through which a general affective
reaction to a risk—often a negative one—leads people to show concern about all aspects of the relevant
risk. See Paul Slovic et al., The Affect Heuristic, in Heuristics and Biases: The Psychology of Intuitive
Judgment 397
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">(Thomas Gilovich et al. eds 2002)</xref>
        .
      </p>
      <p>245. SLOVIC, supra note, at 231.
flexibility for the future. Insofar as the National Environmental Policy Act247 instructs
agencies to spend time to acquire relevant information before ensuring irreversible losses,
it is on firm ground. Experts agree that any cost-benefit analysis that ignores option value
is missing an important variable—a standard point in finance though not yet in
environmental protection.248 In this sense, ordinary people are correct to see the
importance of irreversibility, and to emphasize the importance, some of the time, of
adopting a strategy of “act, and then learn.”</p>
      <p>What of catastrophic risks? Experts may have little to say on the question whether
it is worse to create a 1/100 risk that 100,000 people will die, or a 1/100,000 risk that 1
million people will die. But they should agree that when regulators are unable to assign
probabilities to catastrophic risks, it is worth doing a great deal to avoid those risks—or at
least to spend resources while more information is acquired. Experts cannot rule out the
choice of maximin under circumstances of uncertainty. At the very least, experts know
that elimination of the worst-case scenario is sometimes justified by a kind of cost-benefit
analysis, one that pays attention to the relative egregiousness of the worst case and the
costs of eliminating it. Sensible experts are interested not only in the expected value of
catastrophic risks, but also in producing strategies for eliminating them when
probabilities cannot be confidently assigned. For these reasons, an understanding of
irreversibility and catastrophe help not only to refine but also to vindicate intuitions that
have been found to play a significant role in ordinary risk perceptions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-8">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The ideas of irreversibility and catastrophe have had a major impact on domestic
and international law, and they play a large role in private and public decisions. My
major goal in this Article is to unpack these ideas and to bring them to bear on law and
policy. I have suggested the possibility of replacing the Precautionary Principle, which is
incoherent, with more refined principles that embody an understanding of the distinctive
problem of irreversible losses and of the need to attend to low-probability risks of
disaster.</p>
      <p>247 42 USC 102 (C)(5).
248 See Dixit and Pindyck, supra note, at 4-7.
and coherent. Drawing on the idea of real options, it suggests that regulators, including
those who make environmental policy, should find it worthwhile to invest resources to
preserve flexibility for the future. In the context of global warming, the Irreversible Harm
Precautionary Principle argues for substantial current investments, above all because
emissions of carbon dioxide stay in the atmosphere for an extremely long time. The
difficulty here is that emissions reductions also impose irreversible costs. An emphasis on
irreversibility does not always favor aggressive environmental regulation, or anything
like an attitude of “act, then learn.” It is even possible to imagine an Irreversible Harm
Precautionary Principle that in many cases argues for a plan of “wait and learn.”249
Everything depends on the magnitude and likelihood of the full range of irreversible
losses. In the context of global warming, the best approach is probably a world-wide
agreement to cap greenhouse emissions, with the size of the cap decreasing over time as
the expense of controls diminish.250</p>
      <p>If expected values matter, then societies should not ignore low probability risks of
catastrophe. A minimal response would be a Catastrophe Harm Precautionary Principle,
one that attempts to counteract the serious risk that both individuals and societies will
treat small risks as if there were zero.251 The argument for this principle is strengthened
by the fact that a catastrophic harm typically has secondary effects that ensure adverse
effects that go far beyond a simple multiple of the number of people who are killed.252 A
less minimal approach would build a degree of risk aversion into the Catastrophe Harm
Precautionary Principle, so as to treat catastrophic harms as worth more than their
expected value. A much more aggressive approach would be to adopt maximin, by which
regulators identify the worst-case scenario and attempt to eliminate it. I have argued that
for most environmental problems, this approach is senseless. Under circumstances of
risk, maximin is far too cautious, and it would inflict serious harms—often including
environmental harms—for no sufficient reason. Usually environmental problems involve
249 See Mendelsohn, supra note, at 45.
250 See Nordhaus and Boyer, supra note, at 121-44.</p>
      <p>251 On some of the cognitive mechanisms here, see Bazerman, Predictable Surprises, supra note; on the
need to attend to low-probability risks, see Posner, supra note, at 245-65.</p>
      <p>
        252 See The Social Amplification of Risk
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">(Nick Pidgeon et al. eds, 2003)</xref>
        .
risk, in the sense that a range of probabilities can be assigned, or at least in the sense that
probabilities can be assigned to probabilities.
      </p>
      <p>As a matter of theory, pure uncertainty cannot be ruled out of bounds. The fact
that people assign probabilities to uncertain outcomes does not negate the possibility of
(objective) uncertainty. Under circumstances of uncertainty, maximin has some appeal if
the worst-case scenario is truly catastrophic. And if it is not terribly costly to eliminate
that scenario, regulators should certainly do so. But maximin can be an unappealing
strategy, certainly under risk, and also when the worst-case scenario is not much worse
than the second-worst case scenario and when the costs of eliminating the worst-case
scenario are extremely high. To operate sensibly, precautionary steps must be attentive to
the full range of consequences, not simply to a subset of them. But a Catastrophic Harm
Precautionary Principle, applied with a wide viewscreen, has an important role in
environmental law as well as ordinary life,253 and it is a strong candidate for replacing
and refining any more general Precautionary Principle.  
253 See William Cline, Climate Change, in Global Crises, Global Solutions, supra note, at 13, 18-19.
2. 
William M. Landes, Copyright Protection of Letters, Diaries and Other Unpublished Works: An 
Economic Approach (July 1991) 
Richard A. Epstein, The Path to The T. J. Hooper: The Theory and History of Custom in the Law of 
Tort (August 1991) 
Cass R. Sunstein, On Property and Constitutionalism (September 1991) 
Richard A. Posner, Blackmail, Privacy, and Freedom of Contract (February 1992) 
Randal C. Picker, Security Interests, Misbehavior, and Common Pools (February 1992) 
Tomas J. Philipson &amp; Richard A. Posner, Optimal Regulation of AIDS (April 1992) 
Douglas G. Baird, Revisiting Auctions in Chapter 11 (April 1992) 
William M. Landes, Sequential versus Unitary Trials: An Economic Analysis (July 1992) 
William M. Landes &amp; Richard A. Posner, The Influence of Economics on Law: A Quantitative Study 
(August 1992) 
Alan O. Sykes, The Welfare Economics of Immigration Law: A Theoretical Survey With An 
Analysis of U.S. Policy (September 1992) 
Douglas G. Baird, 1992 Katz Lecture: Reconstructing Contracts (November 1992) 
Gary S. Becker, The Economic Way of Looking at Life (January 1993) 
J. Mark Ramseyer, Credibly Committing to Efficiency Wages: Cotton Spinning Cartels in Imperial 
Japan (March 1993) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Endogenous Preferences, Environmental Law (April 1993) 
Richard A. Posner, What Do Judges and Justices Maximize? (The Same Thing Everyone Else Does) 
(April 1993) 
Lucian Arye Bebchuk and Randal C. Picker, Bankruptcy Rules, Managerial Entrenchment, and 
Firm‐Specific Human Capital (August 1993) 
J. Mark Ramseyer, Explicit Reasons for Implicit Contracts: The Legal Logic to the Japanese Main 
Bank System (August 1993) 
William M. Landes and Richard A. Posner, The Economics of Anticipatory Adjudication 
(September 1993) 
Kenneth W. Dam, The Economic Underpinnings of Patent Law (September 1993) 
Alan O. Sykes, An Introduction to Regression Analysis (October 1993) 
Richard A. Epstein, The Ubiquity of the Benefit Principle (March 1994) 
Randal C. Picker, An Introduction to Game Theory and the Law (June 1994) 
William M. Landes, Counterclaims: An Economic Analysis (June 1994) 
J. Mark Ramseyer, The Market for Children: Evidence from Early Modern Japan (August 1994) 
Robert H. Gertner and Geoffrey P. Miller, Settlement Escrows (August 1994) 
Kenneth W. Dam, Some Economic Considerations in the Intellectual Property Protection of 
Software (August 1994) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Rules and Rulelessness, (October 1994) 
David Friedman, More Justice for Less Money: A Step Beyond Cimino (December 1994) 
Daniel Shaviro, Budget Deficits and the Intergenerational Distribution of Lifetime Consumption 
(January 1995) 
Douglas G. Baird, The Law and Economics of Contract Damages (February 1995) 
Daniel Kessler, Thomas Meites, and Geoffrey P. Miller, Explaining Deviations from the Fifty 
Percent Rule: A Multimodal Approach to the Selection of Cases for Litigation (March 1995) 
Geoffrey P. Miller, Das Kapital: Solvency Regulation of the American Business Enterprise (April 
1995) 
Richard Craswell, Freedom of Contract (August 1995) 
J. Mark Ramseyer, Public Choice (November 1995) 
Kenneth W. Dam, Intellectual Property in an Age of Software and Biotechnology (November 1995) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Social Norms and Social Roles (January 1996) 
37. </p>
      <p>David A. Weisbach, Measurement and Tax Depreciation Policy: The Case of Short‐Term Assets 
(January 2003) 
Randal C. Picker, Understanding Statutory Bundles: Does the Sherman Act Come with the 1996 
Telecommunications Act? (January 2003) 
Douglas Lichtman and Randal C. Picker, Entry Policy in Local Telecommunications: Iowa Utilities 
and Verizon (January 2003) 
William Landes and Douglas Lichtman, Indirect Liability for Copyright Infringement: An 
Economic Perspective (February 2003) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Moral Heuristics (March 2003) 
Amitai Aviram, Regulation by Networks (March 2003) 
Richard A. Epstein, Class Actions: Aggregation, Amplification and Distortion (April 2003) 
Richard A. Epstein, The “Necessary” History of Property and Liberty (April 2003) 
Eric A. Posner, Transfer Regulations and Cost‐Effectiveness Analysis (April 2003) 
Cass R. Sunstein and Richard H. Thaler, Libertarian Paternalizm Is Not an Oxymoron (May 2003) 
Alan O. Sykes, The Economics of WTO Rules on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures (May 
2003) 
Alan O. Sykes, The Safeguards Mess: A Critique of WTO Jurisprudence (May 2003) 
Alan O. Sykes, International Trade and Human Rights: An Economic Perspective (May 2003) 
Saul Levmore and Kyle Logue, Insuring against Terrorism—and Crime (June 2003) 
Richard A. Epstein, Trade Secrets as Private Property: Their Constitutional Protection (June 2003) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Lives, Life‐Years, and Willingness to Pay (June 2003) 
Amitai Aviram, The Paradox of Spontaneous Formation of Private Legal Systems (July 2003) 
Robert Cooter and Ariel Porat, Decreasing Liability Contracts (July 2003) 
David A. Weisbach and Jacob Nussim, The Integration of Tax and Spending Programs (September 
2003) 
William L. Meadow, Anthony Bell, and Cass R. Sunstein, Statistics, Not Memories: What Was the 
Standard of Care for Administering Antenatal Steroids to Women in Preterm Labor between 1985 
and 2000? (September 2003) 
Cass R. Sunstein, What Did Lawrence Hold? Of Autonomy, Desuetude, Sexuality, and Marriage 
(September 2003) 
Randal C. Picker, The Digital Video Recorder: Unbundling Advertising and Content (September 
2003) 
Cass R. Sunstein, David Schkade, and Lisa Michelle Ellman, Ideological Voting on Federal Courts 
of Appeals: A Preliminary Investigation (September 2003)  
Avraham D. Tabbach, The Effects of Taxation on Income Producing Crimes with Variable Leisure 
Time (October 2003) 
Douglas Lichtman, Rethinking Prosecution History Estoppel (October 2003) 
Douglas G. Baird and Robert K. Rasmussen, Chapter 11 at Twilight (October 2003) 
David A. Weisbach, Corporate Tax Avoidance (January 2004) 
David A. Weisbach, The (Non)Taxation of Risk (January 2004) 
Richard A. Epstein, Liberty versus Property? Cracks in the Foundations of Copyright Law (April 
2004) 
Lior Jacob Strahilevitz, The Right to Destroy (January 2004) 
Eric A. Posner and John C. Yoo, A Theory of International Adjudication (February 2004) 
Cass R. Sunstein, Are Poor People Worth Less Than Rich People? Disaggregating the Value of 
Statistical Lives (February 2004) 
Richard A. Epstein, Disparities and Discrimination in Health Care Coverage; A Critique of the 
Institute of Medicine Study (March 2004) 
Richard A. Epstein and Bruce N. Kuhlik, Navigating the Anticommons for Pharmaceutical Patents: 
Steady the Course on Hatch‐Waxman (March 2004) 
Richard A. Esptein, The Optimal Complexity of Legal Rules (April 2004) 
Eric A. Posner and Alan O. Sykes, Optimal War and Jus Ad Bellum (April 2004) 
Alan O. Sykes, The Persistent Puzzles of Safeguards: Lessons from the Steel Dispute (May 2004) </p>
    </sec>
  </body><script/>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>3 See Kenneth</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Arrow</surname>
            and Anthony C. Fisher, Environmental Preservation, Uncertainty, and Irreversibility, 88
            <given-names>Q J</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>312 (</article-title>
          <year>1974</year>
          ); W. David Montgomery and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Anne E.</given-names>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Global Climate Change and the Precautionary Principle, 6 Human and Ecological Risk Assessment</source>
          <volume>399</volume>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          4
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Paul</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Slovic</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Perception of Risk 117-20</source>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          5
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Arie</given-names>
            <surname>Trouwborst</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Evolution and Status of the Precautionary Principle in International Law (</article-title>
          <year>2002</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>6 For a valuable and somewhat technical discussion, see Christian Gollier and Nicolas Treich, DecisionMaking under Scientific Uncertainty: The Economics of the Precautionary Principle, 27</article-title>
          <source>J Risk and Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          7
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Indur</given-names>
            <surname>Goklany</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Precautionary Principle: A Critical Appraisal of Environmental Risk Assessment</source>
          <volume>5</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          8 Quoted in Bjorn Lomborg,
          <source>The Skeptical Environmentalist</source>
          <volume>347</volume>
          (New York: Cambridge University Press,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          9
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Goklany</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note, at
          <volume>16</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>10 Final Declaration of the First European “Seas At Risk” Conference, Annex 1</source>
          , Copenhagen,
          <year>1994</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          11
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Sierra</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Club v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Marsh</source>
          ,
          <volume>872</volume>
          F2 497 (
          <issue>1st</issue>
          <year>Cir</year>
          .
          <year>1989</year>
          )
          <article-title>; on the complexities here, see below</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>12 See San Francisco Precautionary Principle Ordinance, available at http://temp.sfgov.org/sfenvironment/aboutus/innovative/pp/sfpp.htm</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          13 42
          <string-name>
            <given-names>USC</given-names>
            <surname>102</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>(c)(5).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          14 See Metcalf v.
          <source>Daley</source>
          ,
          <volume>214</volume>
          F3d 1135 (
          <issue>9th</issue>
          <year>Cir 2000</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Scientists Inst. For Public Info v</article-title>
          .
          <source>AEC, 481 F2d 1079 (DC Cir</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Sierra Club v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Marsh</source>
          ,
          <volume>976</volume>
          F2d 763 (
          <issue>1st</issue>
          <year>Cir 1985</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          15 See, eg,
          <volume>33</volume>
          USC 2712(
          <article-title>j) (making special exception to planning requirement for use of federal resources in a situation requiring action to avoid irreversible loss of natural resources”); 42 USC 9611 (i) (same exception for Superfund cleanups); 22 USC 2151p-1 (c)(2)(A) (requiring President to assist developing countries in a way that responds to “the irreversible losses associated with forest destruction”).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          16
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Sierra</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Club v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Sigler</source>
          ,
          <volume>695</volume>
          F2d 957 (
          <issue>5th</issue>
          <year>Cir 1983</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Save Our Ecosystems v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Clark</source>
          ,
          <volume>747</volume>
          F2d 1240 (
          <issue>9th</issue>
          <year>Cir 1984</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          17 See Robertson v.
          <source>Methow Valley Citizens Council</source>
          ,
          <volume>490</volume>
          US 332 (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>18 40 CFR 1502</source>
          .
          <year>22</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          25 See, e.g., Tom Copeland and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Vladimir</given-names>
            <surname>Antikarocov</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Real Options 8-13</source>
          (
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>26 On related issues in tort law, see Ariel Porat and Alex Stein, Tort Liability under Uncertainty (</article-title>
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          27 See, e.g., Precaution, Environmental Science, and Preventive Public Policy (Joel Tckner ed.
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
          <article-title>This section draws extensively from Cass R</article-title>
          . Sunstein, Beyond the Precautionary Principle, 151
          <string-name>
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
            <surname>Pa</surname>
          </string-name>
          . L. Rev.
          <volume>1003</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          28
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Julian</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Morris</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Defining the Precautionary Principle</article-title>
          ,
          <source>in Rethinking Risk and the Precautionary Principle</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          -
          <issue>19</issue>
          (Julian Morris, ed.
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>29 Quoted in id. at 3.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation>
          30 Id.
          <article-title>A strong version is defended in Carolyn Raffensperger</article-title>
          &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Peter L. deFur</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Implementing the Precautionary Principle: Rigorous Science and Solid Ethics</source>
          ,
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>Hum</fpage>
          . &amp;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Ecol</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Risk Assess.
          <volume>933</volume>
          ,
          <issue>934</issue>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation>
          31
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Bjorn</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Lomborg</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Skeptical Environmentalist</source>
          <volume>348</volume>
          (New York: Cambridge University Press,
          <year>2001</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation>32 http://www.logophilia.com/WordSpy/precautionaryprinciple.asp</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>33 See The Precautionary Principle for the Twenty-First Century, supra note, for support of this approach</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation>
          34 Testimony of Dr. Brent Blackwelder,
          <article-title>President, Friends of the Earth, before the Senate Appropriations Committee</article-title>
          , Subcommittee on Labor,
          <source>Health and Human Services</source>
          ,
          <source>(Jan. 24</source>
          ,
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>35 Final Declaration of the First European “Seas At Risk” Conference, Annex 1</source>
          , Copenhagen,
          <year>1994</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>36 See 42 USC 7412(b)</source>
          (
          <article-title>9)(B) (allowing deletion from list of hazardous air pollutants in case of lifetime risk of 1/1</article-title>
          ,000,000 or below).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>3740 CFR 1502</source>
          .
          <year>22</year>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation>
          38
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Henry</given-names>
            <surname>Grabowski</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <article-title>John Vernon, The Regulation of Pharmaceuticals: Balancing the Benefits and Risks (</article-title>
          <year>1983</year>
          )
          <article-title>; K.I. Kaitin</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Jeffrey Brown</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>A Drug Lag Update, 29 Drug Information Journal</source>
          <volume>361</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation>
          39
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Robert</surname>
          </string-name>
          Percival et al.,
          <source>Environmental Regulation 1122-23</source>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation>
          40 See id; Goklany, supra note, at
          <volume>13</volume>
          -27.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation>
          41
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Judith P. Kelly</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <article-title>Risk of Breast Cancer According to Use of Antidepressants, Phenothiazines, and</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Antihistamines</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <volume>150</volume>
          Am.
          <source>J. Epidemiology</source>
          <volume>861</volume>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>; C.R. Sharpe</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>The Effects of Tricyclic Antidepressants on Breast Cancer Risk</source>
          ,
          <volume>86</volume>
          Brit.
          <source>J. of Cancer</source>
          <volume>92</volume>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation>
          42
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Maurice</given-names>
            <surname>Tubiana</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Radiation Risks in Perpective: Radiation-Induced Cancer Among Cancer Risks</source>
          ,
          <volume>39</volume>
          (
          <issue>1</issue>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>Radiat</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <source>Environ. Biophy. 3</source>
          ,
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation>
          43 Id.
          <article-title>For some counterevidence in an important context, see Lennart Hardell et al</article-title>
          .,
          <source>Further Aspects on Cellular and Cordless Telephones and Brain Tumours</source>
          ,
          <volume>22</volume>
          Intl. J.
          <source>Oncology</source>
          <volume>399</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          )
          <article-title>(discussing evidence of an association between cellular telephones and cancer</article-title>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>44 See the discussion in Goklany, supra note</article-title>
          , at
          <volume>29</volume>
          -56.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation>
          45
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Morel</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al., supra note, at
          <volume>184</volume>
          -86.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation>
          46
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Kym</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Anderson and Chantal Nielsen, Golden Rice and the Looming GMO Debate: Implications for the Poor</article-title>
          , available at http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=
          <fpage>508463</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation>
          47 Id.; see also Goklany, supra nte, at 30-41 (
          <article-title>discussing environmental and health benefits of engineered crops).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>48 See the discussion of risk-related tradeoffs in John Graham</article-title>
          &amp; Jonathan
          <string-name>
            <surname>Wiener</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Risk vs</article-title>
          .
          <source>Risk</source>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ); Cass R. Sunstein,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Health-Health</surname>
            <given-names>Tradeoffs</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , in Cass R.
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Risk and Reason,
          <volume>133</volume>
          -
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation>
          49Ralph Keeney,
          <article-title>Mortality Risks Induced by Economic Expenditures, 10 Risk Anal</article-title>
          .
          <volume>147</volume>
          (
          <year>1990</year>
          );
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Randall</given-names>
            <surname>Lutter &amp; John F. Morrall</surname>
          </string-name>
          , III,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Health-Health Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          :
          <article-title>A New Way to Evaluate Health and Safety Regulation, 8(1) J</article-title>
          .
          <source>Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          , 49 table 1 (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation>
          50
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Keeney</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <mixed-citation>
          51
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Robert W. Hahn</surname>
          </string-name>
          et al.,
          <source>Do Federal Regulations Reduce Mortality?</source>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <mixed-citation>
          52
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Kenneth</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
            <surname>Chapman</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp;
          <article-title>Govind Hariharan, Do Poor People Have a Stronger Relationship Between Income and Mortality Than the Rich? Implications of Panel Data for Health-Health Analysis</article-title>
          ,
          <volume>12</volume>
          J.
          <source>Risk &amp; Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>51</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <mixed-citation>
          53See
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Randall</given-names>
            <surname>Lutter &amp; John F. Morrall</surname>
          </string-name>
          , III,
          <string-name>
            <surname>Health-Health Analysis</surname>
          </string-name>
          :
          <article-title>A New Way to Evaluate Health and Safety Regulation, 8</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
            <surname>Risk</surname>
          </string-name>
          &amp; Uncertainty
          <volume>43</volume>
          , 49 table 1 (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <mixed-citation>
          62 Goklany, supra note, at
          <volume>13</volume>
          -28;
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Risk and Reason</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ); Aaron Wildavsky, But Is It True?
          <volume>61</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <mixed-citation>
          63
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Goklany</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note, at
          <volume>55</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <mixed-citation>
          64
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Keeney</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref49">
        <mixed-citation>
          <year>65</year>
          <article-title>On some of the complexities here, see Sunstein, Risk and Reason, supra note</article-title>
          , at
          <volume>124</volume>
          -26.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <mixed-citation>
          66
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Scott</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Farrow</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>Using Risk-Assessment, Benefit-Cost Analysis, and Real Options to Implement a Precautionary Principle, 24</article-title>
          <source>Risk Analysis</source>
          <volume>727</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <mixed-citation>
          67 See, eg, Robert Mendelsohn,
          <source>Perspective Paper 1</source>
          .
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          ., in Global Crises,
          <source>Global Solutions</source>
          <volume>44</volume>
          ,
          <issue>47</issue>
          (Bjorn Lomborg ed.
          <year>2004</year>
          ); Wilfred Beckerman, Small is Stupid (
          <year>1995</year>
          ).
          <article-title>The cautious approach of the Bush Administration can be understood in this light, see, www</article-title>
          .whitehouse.gov/news/releases/2002/02/climatechange.html;
          <article-title>Senators Hagel and Murkowski, High Costs of Kyoto, Wash</article-title>
          . Post, Jan.
          <volume>29</volume>
          ,
          <year>2000</year>
          , at A17.
          <article-title>Nordhaus and Boyer find that extremely little is lost by a ten-year delay in emissions reductions</article-title>
          .
          <source>See William D. Nordhaus &amp; Joseph Boyer, Warming the World: Economic Models of Global Warming</source>
          <volume>127</volume>
          (
          <year>2000</year>
          )
          <article-title>(describing the net loss as “trivially small”). For a technical discussion, see Alistair Ulph</article-title>
          and David Ulph,
          <source>Global Warming, Irreversibility and Learning, 107 Ec J</source>
          <volume>636</volume>
          (
          <year>1997</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <mixed-citation>
          68
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Posner</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note, at
          <volume>161</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <mixed-citation>
          69 See G. Chichilnisky and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
            <surname>Heal</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Global Environmental Risks, 7
          <string-name>
            <given-names>J Econ</given-names>
            <surname>Persp</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>65</volume>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <mixed-citation>
          70
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>David Dana</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Existence Value and Federal Preservation Regulation, 28 Harv Env L Rev</source>
          <volume>343</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          );
          <article-title>Charles J</article-title>
          . Cicchetti and
          <string-name>
            <surname>Louis J. Wilde</surname>
          </string-name>
          , Uniquness, Irreversibility, and
          <source>the Theory of Nonuse Values, Amer J. Agri Econ</source>
          <volume>1111</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <mixed-citation>
          71 See Ohio v.
          <source>Department of Interior, 880 F2d 432 (DC Cir</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <mixed-citation>
          72 Cicchetti and Wilde, supra note.
          <article-title>The independent use of option value is, however, challenged in various places, see</article-title>
          , e.g.,
          <string-name>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
            <surname>Myrick</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Freeman</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>The Measurement of Environmental and Natural Resource Values 249-51</source>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <mixed-citation>73 See Ohio v. Department of Interior, supra.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref58">
        <mixed-citation>
          74 See, e.g.,
          <source>60 Fed Reg</source>
          <volume>29914</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>; 60 Fed</article-title>
          .Reg.
          <volume>28210</volume>
          (
          <year>1995</year>
          )
          <article-title>; 59 Fed</article-title>
          . Reg.
          <volume>1062</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
          <source>But see 69 Fed Reg</source>
          .
          <volume>68444</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          )
          <article-title>(doubting whether option value should be recognized as separate form others values).</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref59">
        <mixed-citation>
          75
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Frank Ackerman and Lisa Heinzerling</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Priceless</source>
          <volume>185</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref60">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>76</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>A helpful overview</article-title>
          is Richard C. Bishop,
          <source>Option Value: An Exposition and Extension, 58 Land Economics</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          (
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
          <article-title>In recognizing the existence of option value, I do not mean to make any controversial suggestions about the role of “willingness to pay” in environmental policy. The only point is that people do place a value on preserving environmental options, and that it would be foolish for regulators to refuse to do so</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref61">
        <mixed-citation>
          77
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Claude</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Henry</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Investment Decisions under Uncertainty: The “Irreversibility Effect,” 64 Am Econ Rev</source>
          <volume>1006</volume>
          ,
          <issue>1006</issue>
          (
          <year>1974</year>
          ),
          <article-title>and in particular this suggestion: “A decision is considered irreversible if it significantly reduces for a long time the variety of choices that would be possible in the future</article-title>
          .”
          <article-title>On precommitment value, see below</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref62">
        <mixed-citation>
          78 See Tom Copeland and Vladimir Antikarocov, supra note, at
          <volume>12</volume>
          -13.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref63">
        <mixed-citation>
          79 See Richard Brealey and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Stewart</given-names>
            <surname>Myers</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Principles of Corporate Finance565</source>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref64">
        <mixed-citation>80 Id. at 582.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref65">
        <mixed-citation>
          81 Copeland and Antikarocov, supra, at
          <volume>13</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref66">
        <mixed-citation>
          82
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Dixit</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Pindyck, supra, at
          <volume>24</volume>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref67">
        <mixed-citation>
          83 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>One Case At A Time</source>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref68">
        <mixed-citation>
          84 See Robertson v.
          <source>Methow Valley Citizens' Council, 490 US 332</source>
          (
          <year>1989</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref69">
        <mixed-citation>
          85
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Benoit</surname>
          </string-name>
          Morel et al.,
          <article-title>Pesticide Resistance, the Precautionary Principle, and the Regulation of Bt Corn: Real Option and Rational Option Approaches to Decisionmaking, in Battling Resistance to Antibiotics and Pesticides, supra note</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref70">
        <mixed-citation>
          86
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Graciela Chichilnisky and Geoffey Heal</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Global Environmental Risks, 7 J Econ Perspectives</source>
          <volume>65</volume>
          ,
          <issue>80</issue>
          (
          <year>1993</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref71">
        <mixed-citation>
          87 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Kenneth J. Arrow</surname>
            and Anthony C. Fisher, Environmental Preservation, Uncertainty, and Irreversibility, 88
            <given-names>Q J</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Econ</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>312 (</article-title>
          <year>1974</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref72">
        <mixed-citation>
          212
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Nordhaus</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Boyer, supra note, at
          <volume>88</volume>
          (
          <article-title>suggesting a 1.2% probability of a catastrophic impact with 2.5 C warming and of 6.8 percent with 6 C warming)</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref73">
        <mixed-citation>213 See id.; Cline, supra note; Mendelsohn, supra note.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref74">
        <mixed-citation>
          214 See Richard Posner, Catastrophe, supra note, at
          <volume>49</volume>
          -50.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref75">
        <mixed-citation>
          215
          <string-name>
            <given-names>William</given-names>
            <surname>Nordhaus</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Expert Opinion on Climatic Change, 82 American Scientist</source>
          <volume>45</volume>
          (
          <year>1994</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref76">
        <mixed-citation>
          216
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Woodward</surname>
          </string-name>
          and Bishop, supra note. To be sure,
          <article-title>divergence among experts is likely to be smaller now than it was in 1994</article-title>
          . See Robert Percival et al., supra note, at
          <volume>1058</volume>
          -1060.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref77">
        <mixed-citation>
          224 See
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
            , Probability Neglect: Emotions,
            <given-names>Worst</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Cases</surname>
          </string-name>
          , and the Law, 112
          <source>Yale LJ</source>
          <volume>61</volume>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>; Cass R. Sunstein</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Terrorism and Probability Neglect, 26 J. Risk and Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>121</volume>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref78">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>225</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>An influential paper, suggesting the rationality of either maximin or maximax (maximize the best-case scenario), is Kenneth Arrow</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
            <surname>Hurwicz</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>An Optimality Criterion for Decision-Making Under Uncertainty, in Uncertainty and</article-title>
          Expectation in
          <string-name>
            <surname>Economics (C.F. Carter</surname>
            and
            <given-names>J.L</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Ford eds.
          <year>1972</year>
          )
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref79">
        <mixed-citation>
          226
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Harsanyi</surname>
          </string-name>
          , supra note.
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref80">
        <mixed-citation>
          227
          <string-name>
            <given-names>See</given-names>
            <surname>Kenneth Arrow</surname>
          </string-name>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
            <surname>Hurwicz</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>An Optimality Criterion for Decision-Making Under Uncertainty, in Uncertainty and</article-title>
          Expectation in
          <string-name>
            <surname>Economics (C.F. Carter</surname>
            and
            <given-names>J.L</given-names>
          </string-name>
          . Ford eds.
          <year>1972</year>
          );
          <article-title>Duncan Luce</article-title>
          and
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Howard</given-names>
            <surname>Raiffa</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>Games and Decisions</source>
          <volume>286</volume>
          -
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          (
          <year>1958</year>
          ).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref81">
        <mixed-citation>228 See id.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>