<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><script/>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Faculty Scholarship at Chicago Unbound. It has been
accepted for inclusion in Journal Articles by an authorized administrator of Chicago Unbound. For more
information</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chicago Unbound</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Cass R. Sunstein</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0">0</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <string-name>Recommended Citation</string-name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0">
          <label>0</label>
          <institution>Faculty Scholarship</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>58</volume>
      <fpage>1898</fpage>
      <lpage>1918</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec-1">
      <title>-</title>
      <p>Much of Justice Sandra Day O'Connor's work on the Supreme Court
embodies a commitment to judicial minimalism, understoodas a preferencefor
narrow rulings, closely attuned to particularfacts. In many contexts, however,
that commitment is hard to justify, simply because it imposes severe
decisionmakingburdens on others and may well createmore, ratherthanfewer,
errors. For this reason, a general preference for minimalism is no more
defensible than a generalpreferencefor rules. The choice between narrow and
wide rulings cannot itselfbe made by rules or even presumptions; it requires a
case-by-case inquiry. The argument is illustratedthroughout this Article with
reference to the problem of affirmative action, where Justice O'Connor's
preferencefor particularityresultedin the impositionofa constitutionalmandate
on admissionsoffices that is not simple to defend in principle.In some contexts,
however, narrow rulings are indeedpreferable,in largepart because they give
flexibility to politically accountable officials. Justice O'Connor'sminimalism is
best understood as reflecting a belief that in dfficult cases at the frontiers of
constitutionallaw,judges woulddo best to avoidfirm rules thatthey might come
to regret.
* Karl N. Llewellyn Distinguished Service Professor of Jurisprudence, the University
of Chicago Law School, Department of Political Science, and the College. I am grateful to
Christine Jolls for helpful discussions and to James Weingarten for research assistance and
excellent comments.</p>
      <p>1899</p>
      <p>INTRODUCTION</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-2">
      <title>Consider two admissions programs:</title>
      <p>" Program A gives a specified number of points to every
AfricanAmerican applicant. More particularly, every such applicant receives
ten points, simply by virtue of being African-American. Ten points are
not trivial, but they are far from enough to ensure admission. Children
of alumni, for example, receive fifteen points; specified academic
achievements produce thirty points; athletic accomplishments result in
the addition of fifteen points. Admission is unlikely unless an applicant
receives at least sixty points.
" Program B dispenses with a point system. Every applicant receives
individualized consideration from one of eight admissions officers. In
hard cases, the admissions officers meet in "teams" of three; in the
hardest cases, all eight admissions officers meet as a group. For
African-American applicants, race counts as a plus, though numbers
are not assigned.</p>
      <p>Under existing law, Program A is unconstitutional because it is too
rulebound.1 Program B is permissible because it calls for "holistic" consideration of
individual applicants. More than anyone else, Justice Sandra Day O'Connor is
responsible for the fact that constitutional law distinguishes so sharply between
the two programs. While Justice O'Connor and Justice Breyer voted to strike
down a variation on Program A and to uphold a variation on Program B,3 the
isnevvaelnidaottihnegr boJuthstipcreosgrawmosu.l4d treat the two the same, either upholding or</p>
      <p>
        Consistent with its general opposition to rigid affirmative action programs,
the Court has long made clear that educational institutions cannot "insulat[e]
each category of applicants with certain desired qualifications from competition
with all other applicants." 5 Extending that principle, the Court has also
invalidated a point system, analogous to Program A, used for undergraduate
1. See Gratz v. Bollinger, 539 U.S. 244, 270, 275 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2003</xref>
        ) (holding that the University
of Michigan's freshman admissions policy, "which automatically distributes 20 points, or
one-fifth of the points needed to guarantee admission, to every single 'underrepresented
minority' applicant solely because of race," violated the Equal Protection Clause because it
was "not narrowly tailored to achieve [the University's] asserted compelling interest in
diversity).
      </p>
      <p>
        2. Grutter v. Bollinger, 539 U.S. 306, 337 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2003</xref>
        ) (emphasizing that the admissions
program in question "engages in a highly individualized, holistic review of each applicant's
file ... ").
      </p>
      <p>3. See Gratz, 539 U.S. at 276-80 (O'Connor, J., concurring); id. at 281-82 (Breyer, J.,
concurring); Grutter,539 U.S. at 311-44 (O'Connor, J.).</p>
      <p>4. See Gratz, 539 U.S. 244; Grutter,539 U.S. 306.</p>
      <p>5. Grutter,539 U.S. at 334 (quoting Regents of Univ. of Cal. v. Bakke, 438 U.S. 265,
315 (1978)).
admissions at the University of Michigan. 6 In that system, students received a
specified set of points for various attributes, including academic performance
(up to 110 points), in-state residence (ten points), having alumni parents (four
points), athletic recruitment (twenty points), and being a member of an
underrepresented minority group (twenty points).7</p>
      <p>The Court did not rule that the twenty points were too high; it ruled instead
that a point system, in the context of racial preference, is invalid as such. The
Court stressed "the importance of considering each particular applicant as an
individual, assessing all of the qualities that the individual possesses, and in
turn, evaluating that individual's ability to contribute to the unique setting of
higher education." 8 The problem with the point system is that its automatic
nature simply does not allow for individualized consideration. And the easy
administrability of this automatic system does not constitute an adequate
excuse, for "the fact that the implementation of a program capable of providing
individualized consideration might present administrative challenges does not
render constitutional an otherwise problematic system." 9</p>
      <p>By contrast, in Grutter v. Bollinger, Justice O'Connor wrote the Court's
opinion permitting educational institutions to create affirmative action
programs if they do not assign points or impose quotas but merely include race
as a "plus" within a system of highly individualized judgment.10 At least such
programs are acceptable if they remain "flexible enough to ensure that each
applicant is evaluated as an individual.""l Hence, the Court permits
raceconscious admissions if, in the words of Justice O'Connor's opinion, there is "a
highly individualized, holistic review of each applicant's file, giving serious
consideration to all the ways an applicant might contribute to a diverse
educational environment." 12 When no policy gives "automatic acceptance or
rejection based on any single 'soft' variable," and when there are "no
mechanical, predetermined diversity 'bonuses' based on race or ethnicity,"
affirmative action is permissible.13</p>
      <p>In drawing a sharp line between rigid and more particularized programs,
Justice O'Connor acted in a way that fits with her jurisprudence far more
generally. She has essentially required educational institutions to proceed in a
way that fits her own "holistic" practice-her preference for case-by-case
judgment, unburdened by clear rules. Because of her general commitment to
particularized consideration, Justice O'Connor has stood as the Court's most
6. Gratz, 539 U.S. at 249-51.
7. Id. at 277-78.
8. Id. at 271 (citing Bakke, 438 U.S. 265).
9. Id.at 275.
10. Grutter,539 U.S. at 334.
11. Id. at 337.
12. Id.
13. Id.
prominent minimalist, asking for narrow rulings rather than broad ones. In
joining the Court's decision to invalidate a Chicago gang-loitering ordinance,
for example, Justice O'Connor went out of her way to suggest that another such
ordinance, more cautiously drawn by the city or more narrowly construed by a
state supreme court, might well pass constitutional muster. 14 In addition,
Justice O'Connor is largely responsible for the "undue burden" standard in the
area of abortion'15_a standard that is rule-free and that calls for close attention
to the details of the particular restriction at issue. In the context of restrictions
on commercial advertising, Justice O'Connor has also written narrow opinions,
carefully tailored to particular facts. 16 The same is true in the context of the
Establishment Clause, where her jurisprudence has a noteworthy minimalist
17
dimension.</p>
      <p>To be sure, no one believes that all details are relevant. No one contends
that judges should attend to the astrological sign of the litigants, or the second
letter of their last names, or the hour of the day on which certiorari was sought.
But in many cases, Justice O'Connor has shown an unquestionable preference
for decisions that are narrowly tailored, that leave a great deal undecided, and
that preserve flexibility for the future. In these respects, Justice O'Connor has
twaiktehnthaeniratpepnrdoeancchy toto wcoanrdstiitnuctiroenmaelnltaawldtehvaetlobpumildenst.o1n8 common law processes,</p>
      <p>My purpose here is to raise questions about that preference. I begin with
the suggestion that in the context of affirmative action, Justice O'Connor's
interest in case-by-case judgment has led her to a puzzling and probably
indefensible conclusion. It is hardly clear that the Constitution should be taken
to require a procedure that sacrifices transparency, predictability, and equal
treatment-and that does so while imposing significant burdens on officials
who must evaluate particular applications for admission. This objection leads to
a much more general point. Any defense of minimalist adjudication is
essentially the same in principle as a defense of standards over rules-and there
is no reason to think that such a defense can be made convincing in all of the
contexts in which Justice O'Connor has ruled narrowly. In short, the choice
between narrow and wide rulings cannot itself be resolved by rule.</p>
      <p>Ironically, Justice O'Connor's own practice suggested a kind of
presumption in favor of minimalism. As a first approximation, the better
approach rejects any such presumption and calls instead for a case-by-case
inquiry into whether case-by-case decisions are desirable. This point serves as a
challenge to minimalism as a general project, but it also helps to produce a
reconstruction and defense of the claim that seems to me to animate much of
Justice O'Connor's work: in the hardest cases, at the frontiers of constitutional
law, the Court usually does best if it proceeds narrowly and if it avoids steps
that might be confounded by unanticipated circumstances. The arguments that
support minimalism in particular cases also support this general use of
minimalism. As we shall see, there is a democratic argument on behalf of the
same position.</p>
      <p>I. AFFIRMATIVE ACTION, RULES, AND TRANSPARENCY</p>
      <p>Begin with affirmative action. We can imagine an admissions program that
operates on the basis of a simple rule, as in the idea that anyone with a certain
score on the LSAT will be admitted, and anyone with a score below that level
will be rejected. If affirmative action is to be introduced, we could imagine an
equally simple rule-saying, for example, that African-American candidates
will be admitted even if their LSAT scores are below the ordinary requirement
so long as the scores are also above a specified level. We could also imagine an
admissions program that operates on the basis of a complex rule. The
University of Michigan undergraduate program is an example; it offered a
range of factors listed in advance, with each being given a specified weight.
Rules can certainly make reference to a large number of factors and, in that
sense, incorporate a high degree of particularity. The identifying feature of a
rule-bound system is not that it makes one or two features central, but that it
involves full or nearly full specification, before the fact, of the factors that are
relevant and also of the weight that will be assigned to them. 19</p>
      <p>Such a system contrasts with rule-free systems, which involve no such
before-the-fact specification, and which require officials to specify, in
individual cases, either the relevant factors or the weight to be given to each (or
both). We could imagine an entirely open-ended admissions process, in which
admissions officers are asked to identify the governing criteria as they see fit.
Under such a process, individual officers could decide whether to consider, and
how much to consider, LSAT scores, extracurricular activities, background,
geography, essays, race, religion, point of view, musical tastes, and so forth;
their exercise of discretion would be unmonitored and unconstrained.</p>
      <p>
        19. See generally Louis Kaplow, Rules Versus Standards: An Economic Analysis, 42
DUKE L.J. 557 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">1992</xref>
        ) (offering an economic analysis of the choice between promulgating
legal commands as rules or standards).
      </p>
      <p>Alternatively, we could imagine a process that rested on factors that were
specified but unweighted-saying, for example, that officers must consider
academic achievement, extracurricular activities, race, geography, athletic
achievement, familial connections to the institutions, and so forth. This process
would be "holistic," not in the sense that admissions officers could consider
such factors as they saw fit, but in the sense that it would not offer anything
like a specification of the weight to be assigned to the different variables. The
weight of each factor would be decided individually in particular cases. If
admissions officers wanted to give great weight to extracurricular activities but
little weight to familial connections, they would be permitted to do exactly that;
the opposite preference would be acceptable as well as far as the institution is
concerned. Indeed, a near-zero weight would seem to be permissible. Perhaps
admissions officers could even give no weight to race, or some other factor, if
that is what they wanted to do.</p>
      <p>The key point is that to the extent that institutions do not specify
admissions criteria in advance, or permit officers to weigh those criteria in
individual cases, they ensure that the content of the governing "law" will be
made on the spot, in the process of assessing applications. This is the essential
difference between a rule-bound and a rule-free system. Of course there is a
continuum here, not a sharp dichotomy. We could imagine admissions systems
that specify a great deal but still leave some discretion for on-the-spot
decisions. We could imagine systems that specify little but do not leave
admissions officers utterly unconstrained.</p>
      <p>A court could coherently say that the constitutional issue turns on the
degree of the racial preference. Perhaps a constitutional distinction should be
drawn between different sorts of rules: those that give excessive weight to race
and those that do not. On this view, an admissions office may not accord
"undue significance" to race, in a kind of analogue to the "undue burden"
standard in the law of abortion. Undue significance would be found, for
example, in a rule allowing all African-American applicants to be admitted
simply by virtue of their skin color. At the same time, an admissions office
might be allowed to grant one point, or a few more, to African-American
applicants. In other words, there would be no logical difficulty with saying that
some weight, but not too much, may be given to race. An "undue significance"
standard would itself require a form of individuation at the level of judicial
administration, but perhaps it could be specified either in advance or through
application.</p>
      <p>But-and this is the key point-undue significance, in the form of
excessive weight, is not Justice O'Connor's concern. Rigidity, not weight, is
her objection. She does not contend that the University of Michigan accorded
too many points to race-an objection that would also apply to rule-free
systems if, in actual operation, they gave an extremely strong preference to
African-American applicants. Justice O'Connor's complaint is about ruleness
as such, in the form of an ex ante specification of the weight to be given to
race. Hence the distinction between Program A and Program B is not that
Program A gives more attention to race; it is that Program A is more rigid and
imposes firm limits on individual discretion.</p>
      <p>But is this objection convincing? Consider the behavior of an admissions
officer engaged in review of applications under Program B. So long as
affirmative action is in place, Program B will operate, in a sense, as the
functional equivalent of a point system; the only difference is that its essential
characteristics, above all the weight given to race, are not disclosed or
systematized. As Program B is administered, each admissions officer will
inevitably be operating with her own informal point system, in the form of a
rough sense of how much weight to give to the relevant factors. (If an officer's
decisions were recorded, and if there were enough of them, it should be
possible to discern, retrospectively at least, the number of "points" given to
race in the average case.) Whether the implicit point system will be constant
across officers, or across applicants, is anyone's guess. We can go further.
Program B can be drawn up so as to require each officer to give some
(unspecified) weight to race, or so as to permit officers to give some
(unspecified) weight to race if they choose. In this sense, race may or may not
matter at all, depending on the judgment of each officer.</p>
      <p>The key point is that under Program B, it is unlikely that any particular
officer will be able to give constant, rather than fluctuating, weight to race. It is
even less likely that different officers will use the same system, in the sense
that they will allocate the same informal points, or weight, to race. The
resulting criteria will likely be highly variable across applicants, and they will
not be transparent to anyone. It follows that as compared to Program A,
Program B sacrifices three important values: predictability, transparency, and
equal treatment. It does so while also imposing significant decisionmaking
burdens on individual officers, who have to decide how much weight to give to
race in individual cases.</p>
      <p>
        It is tempting to think that the real difference between Program A and
Program B is that the latter is fairer, less mechanical, and more accurate,
precisely because it is so highly individualized. In fact Justice O'Connor's
opinion in Grutterseems to be based on a judgment to precisely this effect. 20
But the appearance is a kind of optical illusion. Program B also involves
something akin to a point system, in the sense that affirmative value is placed
on race; the difference is that points are not formally assigned, and hence
variability will likely arise from applicant to applicant, with a corresponding
lack of transparency and equal treatment. Different African-Americans will be
treated differently, as some obtain larger racial bonuses than others. At first
glance, it is not at all clear why that procedure should be constitutionally
20. See Grutter v. Bollinger, 539 U.S. 306, 337 (
        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2003</xref>
        ) ("The importance of this
individualized consideration in the context of a race-conscious admissions program is
paramount.").
preferred.
      </p>
      <p>Is anything at all gained with Program B? The most obvious point is that
under Program B, there will be a greater lack of knowledge, in individual cases,
about what role, if any, race played in an admissions decision. For this reason,
the lack of transparency may itself be a benefit; perhaps there are expressive
reasons for it. With Program B, a successful applicant does not know that he
was affected by being the beneficiary of affirmative action. Such an applicant
can think, plausibly, that affirmative action played no role in his case. Perhaps
Program A imposes a kind of general stigma that Program B does not, simply
because under Program A every African-American knows that a certain number
of points were awarded (and every white applicant knows that the same points
were not awarded). Under Program B, perhaps applicants can think that their
own individual characteristics may have been all that mattered, with race
playing little or no role.</p>
      <p>But it is reasonable to wonder whether this possibility, a matter of
appearance and psychology rather than reality, really distinguishes the two
programs, and it is reasonable to doubt that it should make a constitutional
difference. Under Program A, it remains possible that African-American
applicants, like athletes and children of alumni, did not really "need" the
points-that race played no role in their admission. Along this dimension, there
is no evident difference between the two programs. 2 1 At least it is not clear that
beneficiaries of Program A feel more stigmatized, or are more stigmatized, than
beneficiaries of Program B. And even if this is so, it is not clear that Program A
is constitutionallyinferior for that reason. Stigmas of various kinds are imposed
by many public decisions, such as the decision to admit a child of an alumnus
or an especially good football player, and stigmas are not unconstitutional
because of their status as such. In any case, Program A, far more than Program
B, is likely to yield equal treatment. Why is the latter superior to the former,
under a constitutional provision designed to ensure the equal protection of the
laws?</p>
      <p>Any judgment on that point requires an interpretation of the Equal
Protection Clause, which is not my topic here. Perhaps Justice O'Connor
believes that expressive values lie at the heart of the Clause, that Program A is
far inferior to Program B on expressive grounds, and that the constitutional
issue must turn on that distinction. But at the very least, we should be able to
see that it is not simple to explain why Justice O'Connor concluded that
Program B is constitutionally acceptable, whereas Program A is not. To be sure,
a holistic, particularistic program is less transparent and less predictable than
21. Perhaps a program akin to Program B would be different, in expressive terms, if
officers could decide, in individual cases, to give no weight to race-if applicants could
believe in the possibility that race played no role at all. But it is unclear that this possibility
should make a constitutional difference, and in most "holistic" admissions programs, it is
generally agreed that race plays a positive role for African-American applicants.
one that uses points, but is that a constitutional advantage?</p>
      <p>My discussion of the example is meant not only to indicate a difficulty
with an important area of constitutional law, but also to help to identify a series
of problems with particularistic judgments. They might well lead to inequality.
They impose burdens on subsequent decisionmakers, in a way that might lead
to errors and arbitrariness. They increase unpredictability. They reduce
transparency. They might increase the number and size of mistakes at the same
time that they increase the costs of decisions. These problems beset not only
case-by-case admissions decisions, but also what Justice O'Connor frequently
prefers: case-by-case rulings from the Supreme Court.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec-3">
      <title>II. RULES, STANDARDS, AND MINIMALISM</title>
      <p>For the last generation, Justice O'Connor has been the Court's leading
minimalist, in a way that has left a large impact on American law. Her
minimalism embodies an interest in small steps along two distinct
dimensions. 22 First, she favors rulings that are narrow rather than wide.
Narrow rulings do not venture far beyond the problem at hand; they attempt to
focus on the particulars of the dispute before the Court. When presented with a
choice between narrow and wide rulings, Justice O'Connor often opts for the
former.23 To be sure, the difference between narrowness and width is one of
degree rather than kind; no one favors rulings that are limited to people with the
same birthdays as those of the litigants before the Court. But among the
reasonable alternatives, Justice O'Connor shows a frequent preference for the
narrower options.</p>
      <p>Justice O'Connor also seeks rulings that are shallow rather than deep.
Shallow rulings attempt to produce outcomes and rationales on which diverse
people can agree, notwithstanding their disagreement on fundamental issues.
For example, there are many disputes about the underlying purpose of the free
speech guarantee: does the guarantee aim to protect democratic
selfgovernment, the marketplace of ideas, or individual autonomy? 24 Minimalists
hope not to resolve these disputes.25 They seek judgments and rulings that can
attract support from people who are committed to one or another of these
foundational understan26diTnghse, inotrerweshtoinareshualnlsouwreneassboruatistehse dfiostuinndctaitvioenisssuoefst,h2e7
free principle.
and Isspheaelclhbe exploring narrowness rather than shallowness here.</p>
      <sec id="sec-3-1">
        <title>A. Minimalism andIts Discontents</title>
        <p>The discussion of affirmative action does not demonstrate that minimalism
is a mistake or that Justice O'Connor has generally been wrong in seeking
narrow rulings and in expressing caution about judgments that extend far
beyond the facts of particular cases. To understand the uses and limits of
minimalism, it is necessary to broaden the viewscreen, venturing well beyond
any particular context. Consider, for example, the following propositions:
" The constitutional status of sex segregation in education cannot be
settled by rule. Often segregated institutions will be invalid, but it
remains possible that they can be adequately justified.28
" The President is required to provide some kind of procedure before
detaining suspected terrorists, but the extent of the required procedure
should be elaborated in particular cases, not through firm rules laid
29
down in advance.
" Commercial advertising is often entitled to protection under the First
Amendment, but the protection is far from absolute; the extent of
protection, in individual cases, depends on a balancing test.30
" Under the Equal Protection Clause, most classifications face mere
rationality review. But for some classifications, rationality review is
bmuotrneosteaalrlcfhoirnmg,s ionfadwiscaryimthiantatwioilnl odnootmhe (bamasoisngofostehxeuramloeariseunrteast)iosno. m31e
" In the context of statewide recounts held under a single judge, states
must develop adequate standards to constrain the exercise of discretion
26. See Cass R. Sunstein, Incompletely Theorized Agreements, 108 HARV. L. REv.
1733 (1993) (discussing possibility of reaching agreements on practices or decisions amidst
disagreements on large theoretical issues).</p>
        <p>27. See id. (discussing the issues involved in "shallow" rulings).</p>
        <p>28. See Miss. Univ. for Women v. Hogan, 458 U.S. 718 (1982) (holding that
statesupported university's policy of denying otherwise qualified males the right to enroll for
credit in its nursing school violated the Equal Protection Clause); see also United States v.
Virginia, 518 U.S. 515 (1996) (holding that the Commonwealth of Virginia's exclusion of
women from a citizen-soldier program at a state military college violated the Equal
Protection Clause because Virginia did not show an exceedingly persuasive justification, and
the remedial program offered by the Commonwealth was not sufficiently comparable in
substance to survive equal protection evaluation).</p>
        <p>29. Hamdi, 542 U.S. 507.
30. Thompson v. W. States Med. Ctr., 535 U.S. 357, 367 (2002).
by those who are counting votes. 32 But this requirement may not be
applicable in other settings. 33
" Restrictions on the right to choose abortion should be evaluated not
through the rigid trimester system of Roe v. Wade, but through a more
flexible standard, one that forbids any "undue burden" on the right to
34
choose.
" Public acknowledgements of the existence of God do not always
offend the Establishment Clause; history and context matter a great
35
deal.</p>
        <p>In all of these cases, it would be possible to argue that case-by-case
judgments are desirable, not for the obscure reasons that underlie Grutter, but
on the ground that the Court lacks the information that would permit it to
produce sensible rules. For example, a judge might not want to set out any rule
to govern the constitutional status of commercial advertising, on the ground
that the relevant situations are hard to foresee in advance, and any simple rule
would be confounded by circumstances. Or a judge might believe that the
procedural protection to be accorded to enemy combatants cannot easily be
specified in an initial encounter with that problem; perhaps it is best to avoid
rules and to rely instead on an incompletely specified decision, one that will be
given content as particular cases arise. Perhaps public acknowledgements of
God are acceptable if they do not amount to an effort to inculcate any particular
set of religious convictions, but perhaps that test is itself only a crude gesture
toward an appropriate set of governing principles, which must emerge from
careful investigation of particular cases.
can Ibfealjlutshtiisfieisdsoo,nthethne Jusastmicee gOr'oCuonndnsorth'satgesnuepraplorptresftearnednacredsforomveirnimrualeliss;m36
indeed, her own preference for minimalism is very close, analytically, to a
preference for standards over rules. Importantly, the two preferences are not
identical. A holding that is governed by a standard is, in a relevant respect,
narrow, because the standard needs to be specified in particular cases; but a
narrow decision need not be a standard at all. Such a decision may even be a
rule, restricted to an unusual set of facts; it may endorse a rule and reject a
standard of any kind. (Indeed, a holding is always a rule, at least insofar as it
32. Bush v. Gore, 531 U.S. 98, 109 (2000) ("The recount process ... is inconsistent
with the minimum procedures necessary to protect the fundamental right of each voter in the
special instance of a statewide recount under the authority of a single state judicial officer.").</p>
        <p>33. Id. at 107 (emphasizing a lack of uniform standards guiding the discretion of vote
counters).</p>
        <p>
          34. Planned Parenthood of Se. Pa. v. Casey, 505 U.S. 833, 869-79 (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">1992</xref>
          ); see also
Webster v. Reprod. Health Servs., 492 U.S. 490, 522-31 (1989) (O'Connor, J., concurring).
        </p>
        <p>35. See Elk Grove Unified Sch. Dist. v. Newdow, 542 U.S. 1, 33-45 (2004)
(O'Connor, J., concurring).</p>
        <p>36. See Kaplow, supranote 19, at 557.
binds the parties, and a rationale for a holding is often a standard.) What I am
emphasizing is that by its very nature, a minimalist ruling leaves a great deal
undecided, in a way that frees up future decisionmakers but also leaves them to
some extent at sea. This is exactly the characteristic that distinguishes standards
from rules. Insofar as Justice O'Connor prefers narrow rulings to wide ones, it
is for the same kinds of reasons that lead some people to prefer standards to
rules.</p>
        <p>That preference makes the most sense when it serves to reduce the number
and magnitude of errors and when it serves as well to reduce the aggregate
burdens of decision. 37 Suppose that the Supreme Court is attempting to resolve
a difficult question involving, say, the constitutional status of segregation on
the basis of sex. The Court might think that it lacks the information that would
enable it to set out a sensible rule. It may believe that sex segregation is not
acceptable when such a practice excludes women from a valuable educational
opportunity, but that it is permissible to have sex-segregated sports teams and
that the legitimacy of sex-segregated high school education presents a difficult
question. The Court might believe that a simple rule-sex segregation yes or
sex segregation no-would be outrun by reality. It might also believe that a
complex rule, specifying the validity of segregation across diverse contexts, is
too difficult to set out during an early encounter with the question.</p>
        <p>Points of this kind might well justify a preference for narrow rulings in
many contexts. The problem-a general one for those who favor
narrownessis that there is no reason to think that judges should systematically favor
standards over rules. Whether standards are desirable, and whether narrowness
makes sense, depends on whether the arguments that justify them apply in the
particular case. There is no justification for a general presumption in favor of
standards or minimalism. To the extent that Justice O'Connor has adopted such
a general presumption, 38 she seems to have erred.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-2">
        <title>B. The Casefor Rules?</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-3">
        <title>1. In defense of rules</title>
        <p>It is possible to go further. In an influential essay, Justice Scalia made a
general argument on behalf of rules over case-by-case judgments. 39 Justice
Scalia marshals a range of considerations on behalf of rules-considerations
that track those that argue against a "holistic" admissions process. Justice
37. See id.</p>
        <p>38. I do not claim that she has adopted any such presumption; a judgment to that effect
would require a sustained analysis of her votes and opinions. I contend only that in many
prominent cases she has struck a minimalist chord and embraced narrowness.</p>
        <p>39. Antonin Scalia, The Rule of Law Is a Law of Rules, 56 U. CHI. L. REv. 1175
(1989).
Scalia emphasizes that case-by-case judgments introduce unpredictability. 40
They threaten to deny both the reality and the appearance of equal treatment.4 1
They export decision costs to others-above all, to lower courts and litigants,
who must give effective content to the law.4 2 At the same time, they leave
judges free to exercise their discretion so as to favor their preferred causes, in a
way that43also leaves liberty at risk when the Court faces intense political
pressure.</p>
        <p>Rule-bound decisions have the dual virtues of binding judges, thus
reducing the exercise of discretion, and also of stiffening the judicial spine
when the stakes are highest.44 "The chances that frail men and women will
stand up to their unpleasant duty are greatly increased if they can stand behind
the solid shield of a firm, clear principle enunciated in earlier cases.' ' 5 This
point, made in 1989, has evident power in the face of contemporary conflicts
between individual rights and efforts to protect the nation against terror. Justice
Scalia is linking a point about method with a point about substance. If judges
embrace his method, they are more likely to respect the Constitution's
substance when the going gets tough.</p>
        <p>Justice Scalia's argument is strengthened by the fact that the Supreme
Court is not an ordinary tribunal, entrusted with deciding particular cases. It is
not a trial court or even a court of appeals. One of its principal functions is to
provide guidance for numerous other judges, public officials, and private actors
potentially involved with the legal system.4 6 When focusing on a particular
case, the Court may not readily "see" the large assortment of burdens that it
imposes on others by virtue of its reticence. It may be much better for the Court
to risk error by venturing more broadly than to leave others at sea about the
law's requirements. If the Court does not say much about the obligation to
provide procedures to enemy combatants, it may create terrible guessing games
for the executive branch and for lower courts, in a way that imposes high costs
and burdens. Alert to the Court's role in a hierarchical legal system, Justice
Scalia contends that the preference for common law methods, focused on
narrow rulings, should be reversed.</p>
        <p>In attacking case-by-case judgments, Justice Scalia is best taken as
marshaling a set of considerations that support rules over standards. If we are
interested in minimizing the costs of errors and the costs of decisions, we might
well conclude that the Court should frequently choose width over narrowness.
40. Id.at 1179.
41. Id. at 1178.
42. See id. at 1180-81.
43. Id. at 1180.
44. Id.
45. Id.</p>
        <p>46. See Peter L. Strauss, One HundredFifty Cases Per Year: Some Implications of the
Supreme Court's Limited Resources for Judicial Review of Agency Action, 87 COLUM. L.
REv. 1093 (1987).
Wide rulings will impose decisional burdens on the Court, to be sure, but those
burdens might well be lower than those associated with narrow rulings. Perhaps
rules will be overinclusive, but they might well produce lower error costs, on
balance, than those emerging from a regime of case-by-case decisions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-4">
        <title>2. Meta-questions</title>
        <p>But Justice Scalia does not make the implausible suggestion that the Court
should always avoid case-by-case particularism. He acknowledges that a degree
of particularism is sometimes not "avoidable. ' '4 7 His claim is only that when
rules are "possible," the Court should rely on them. But why does Justice Scalia
contend that rules should be chosen unless the rule of law "must... leave
off'? 48 It would be more plausible to say that the choice between rules and
particularity, or width and narrowness, should depend on which is best, all
things considered. Rules and width should not be selected merely because they
are possible if they are not optimal. The question whether they are optimal
cannot itself be settled by rule. And if this point is right, then at the
metalevel-in the choice between rules or width and particularity-we should
follow Justice O'Connor's approach and be particularistic. No rule can possibly
resolve the meta-question. It follows that a case-by-case inquiry, into the choice
between rules and particularity or of the optimal degree of ruleness, is the
correct way to make that choice.</p>
        <p>But this conclusion does not mean that Justice O'Connor has been right to
opt, so much of the time, for particularity. On the contrary, it immediately
raises the possibility that she has been wrong, simply because it is unlikely that
a case-by-case inquiry would generally suggest that a case-by-case inquiry is
best. But Justice Scalia has not adequately supported his apparent suggestion
that there should be a kind of presumption in favor of wide rules, rather than a
case-by-case inquiry into whether wide rules make sense in the particular
49
context.</p>
        <p>Is there anything that Justice Scalia might say at this point? Perhaps Justice
Scalia believes that there is a real risk that a case-by-case inquiry at the
metalevel will misfire-that if we are concerned with decision costs and error costs,
we will do best with a presumption in favor of rules, or at least with constant
alertness to their virtues. On this view, the problems that beset case-by-case
decisions in individual cases also beset such decisions about whether to
proceed via rules or instead through particularized decisions. The idea that
courts should reject case-by-case judgments unless that course is not
47. Scalia, supranote 39, at 1187.
48. Id.(emphasis added).</p>
        <p>49. Indeed, Judge Richard Posner has stated, "No sensible person supposes that rules
are always superior to standards, or vice-versa ...." MindGames, Inc. v. W. Pub. Co., 218
F.3d 652, 657 (7th Cir. 2000).
"avoidable" might not produce the optimal results that would follow if courts
could costlessly engage in accurate case-by-case inquiries. But because they
cannot, they might do best with a presumption on behalf of rules. The
presumption makes case-by-case decisions less burdensome (at the meta-level,
as elsewhere), simply because it is a presumption. And perhaps the
presumption pushes judges, and especially Justices, in the right direction, in a
way that replicates what would emerge from a system in which case-by-case
judgments could be made costlessly and accurately.</p>
        <p>But Justice Scalia does not attempt to defend his position in this way, and
for excellent reason. He is best taken to have marshaled a series of
considerations against case-by-case judgments, without having demonstrated
that those considerations justify a rule or a presumption in favor of wide rulings
from the Supreme Court. The weight, or force, of those considerations depends
on the same factors that underlie the general choice between rules and
standards. To summarize a complex story: 50 When the Court's decision must
be applied by numerous actors, dealing with frequent or common situations, the
argument for rule-bound decisions has great force. When there is reason to
distrust those who would operate free from rules, there is a good argument for
rules. When predictability is exceedingly important, case-by-case decisions
impose high costs. When the potential rulemaker has the information to
produce good rules, there is every reason to produce rules.</p>
        <p>But no general argument in favor of rules would make much sense, even at
the meta-level. When the Court lacks relevant information, so that any rule will
predictably misfire, rules are hazardous. When there are few decisions in the
pertinent domain, the argument for rules is less insistent. When the potential
rulemaker cannot be confident about any rule, rules may not be worthwhile.
When subsequent decisionmakers can be trusted, because of their competence
and lack of bias, the argument for avoiding rules is certainly strengthened.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Justice O'Connor's view is the converse of Justice Scalia's-and
similarly vulnerable. Perhaps she believes that for the Supreme Court, it is
frequently or typically the case that the case-by-case inquiry, at the meta-level,
will produce a judgment in favor of case-by-case decisions. Her implicit
judgment to that effect might reflect the application of a case-by-case
metarule. But it is difficult to see how such a meta-rule might be defended,
especially if we notice that minimalist decisions from the Court do not promote
predictability and impose high decisional burdens on fallible actors at later
stages. Too much of the time, narrow rulings are properly subject to Justice
Scalia's critique.</p>
        <p>It is possible to identify specific domains in which the argument for rules is
difficult to resist. Consider the question whether speed limits should involve
standards or rules-a question easily resolved in favor of the latter in part
50. The best discussion of the choice between rules and standards remains Kaplow,
supra note 19.
because of the need for predictability and the sheer number of decisions that
must be made. So too, there are domains in which the argument for standards is
strong. For decisions involving parole, for example, a rigidly rule-bound
system, forbidding a degree of individualized attention, would risk a high level
of error. But for adjudication as a whole, even at the Supreme Court, no general
conclusion makes much sense.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec-3-5">
        <title>3. Minimalism 's domain</title>
        <p>It might be possible, however, to defend Justice O'Connor's approach in
narrower terms, and the discussion thus far should enable us to see the form the
defense might take.</p>
        <p>In my view, the most promising claim on her behalf involves a particularly
important subset of cases on the Supreme Court's docket: the "frontiers"
questions in constitutional law. By their very nature, these questions are
unlikely to come up often and require answers about which the Court cannot
always be confident. In these domains, the argument for wide rulings, offering
large and hard-to-reverse steps, is substantially weakened. Two considerations
are relevant here. First, predictability is likely to be less important, simply
because the relevant questions arise infrequently. Second, the likelihood that a
wide ruling will misfire is often high, simply because the Court lacks much
familiarity with the context.</p>
        <p>Indeed, this latter point has been emphasized by Justice Breyer in the
context of the use of new technologies to compromise privacy, where he insists
that courts do not have the experience that would justify width. 5 ' Much of
Justice O'Connor's jurisprudence might be taken to have generalized the point.
Her largely minimalist opinion in Hamdi can be understood in exactly these
terms; 52 in its first decisions involving conflicts between constitutional rights
and the war on terror, the Supreme Court had good reason to proceed
cautiously. The same point helps to justify the Court's minimalism in Bush v.
Gore, where a most unusual controversy with enormous stakes might be taken
as a good occasion for particularly small steps. 53 The same can be said in
defense of Justice O'Connor's reluctance to embrace a broad ruling during the
Court's first encounter with gang-loitering legislation. 54</p>
        <p>None of this means that minimalism is always appropriate in constitutional
cases. When the area requires a high degree of predictability, and when the
Court has had a great deal of experience with the area, width might well be
51. See STEPHEN BREYER, ACTIVE LIBERTY: INTERPRETING OUR DEMOCRATIC
CONSTITrrION 70-73 (2005).</p>
        <p>52. Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 542 U.S. 507 (2004).
53. 531 U.S. 98 (2000).</p>
        <p>54. See City of Chicago v. Morales, 527 U.S. 41, 64-69 (1999) (O'Connor, J.,
concurring).
justified. The same conclusion follows if the Court, notwithstanding its lack of
experience, has good reason for confidence in a wide ruling. The only point is
that in many frontiers cases, the very arguments that justify standards will
justify minimalism as well. In short, Justice O'Connor's practice of minimalism
is best defended on the ground that it can be found in exactly the areas in which
an assessment of the contest between rules and standards argues most
powerfully in favor of the latter.</p>
        <p>III. DEMOCRACY</p>
        <p>Thus far my emphasis has been on error costs and decision costs-the
conventional foundation for analysis of the choice between rules and standards.
But there is another issue, and it has to do with the relationship between Justice
O'Connor's preference for minimalism and democratic self-government. There
are two different points here.</p>
        <p>First, the Court might choose a narrow ruling precisely because it seeks to
retain room for democratic debate and experimentation. Justice Frankfurter's
concurring opinion in the Steel Seizure Case offers the most elaborate
discussion of the basic claim. 55 He emphasized that "[r]igorous adherence to
the narrow scope of the judicial function" is especially important in
constitutional cases when national security is at risk, notwithstanding the
national "eagerness to settle-preferably forever-a specific problem on the
basis of the broadest possible constitutional pronouncements .... "56 In his
view, the Court's duty "lies in the opposite direction," through judgments that
make it unnecessary to consider "delicate problems of power under the
Constitution." 57 Thus, the Court has an obligation "to avoid putting fetters
upon the future by needless pronouncements today." 5 8 Justice Frankfurter is
naturally read to be emphasizing the costs of error, but his emphasis is also on
"putting fetters" on those involved in democratic self-government.</p>
        <p>If the Court were able to invalidate a legally unacceptable decision in a
way that nonetheless would maintain flexibility for other institutions, it might
do so for that very reason, at least if it cannot be confident that a broader ruling
is correct. 59 And indeed, Justice O'Connor's separate opinion in Morales, the
gang-loitering case, emphasized the continued authority of state and local
governments. 60 Narrow rulings permit a kind of continuing dialogue within the
55. Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube Co. v. Sawyer, 343 U.S. 579, 594-97 (1952)
(Frankfurter, J., concurring).</p>
        <p>56. Id. at 594.
57. Id. at 595.
58. Id. at 596.</p>
        <p>59. See Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 542 U.S. 507, 577-78 (2004) (Scalia, J., dissenting)
(contrasting the Court's institutional deficiencies with Congress's flexibility in setting terms
for suspension of writ ofhabeas corpus).</p>
        <p>60. See City of Chicago v. Morales, 527 U.S. 41, 64-69 (1999) (O'Connor, J.,
polity, and between the Court and other institutions, in a way that promotes
learning.6 1 As between wide and narrow invalidations, the latter have
significant advantages for just that reason.</p>
        <p>This, in fact, is a large part of Justice Breyer's claim in the context of
privacy, 62 where narrowness ensures that the legislature will not be foreclosed
by an inadequately informed decision from the Court. The same point
emphatically holds amidst the war on terror. In Hamdi, the Court pointedly
declined to say anything about the President's power as Commander in Chief,
relying instead on statutory authorization. 63 At least where the issue has a great
deal of novelty, and where the Court is unsure how to handle it, a great deal is
to be gained by allowing the democratic process continuing room for
experimentation.</p>
        <p>Second, some minimalist rulings are democracy-forcing, in the particular
sense that they work to ensure that decisions are made by the democratically
preferred institution of government. The most prominent example is the
Avoidance Canon-the idea that intrusions on constitutionally sensitive
interests must be authorized by Congress and may not be made by the
executive alone. 64 Justice O'Connor has attempted to vindicate this idea in
prominent cases.6 5 The simple idea is that when a reasonable constitutional
objection is raised, the Court does best, if it possibly can, to construe the
relevant statute so as to make it unnecessary to address that objection, and so as
to force the national legislature to confront it directly and first. The Avoidance
Canon is minimalist in the simple sense that it ensures narrower rulings than
constitutional invalidations. But it also has the distinctive property of forcing
national legislators to deal with the question squarely and unambiguously.</p>
        <p>The same general idea helps to explain Justice O'Connor's controversial
opinion in the Brown &amp; Williamson case. 66 There the Court struck down the
FDA's assertion of regulatory jurisdiction over tobacco and tobacco products,
notwithstanding the ambiguity of the statutory language and the ordinary rule
that agencies are permitted to interpret ambiguous statutes as they see fit.67
Early on, Justice O'Connor's opinion suggests that "we must be guided to a
degree by common sense as to the manner in which Congress is likely to
delegate a policy decision of such economic and political magnitude to an
concurring)
61. See BREYER, supranote 51, at 73-74.
62. See id.</p>
        <p>63. Hamdi, 542 U.S. at 517 ("We do not reach the question whether Article IIprovides
such authority, however, because . . . Congress has in fact authorized Hamdi's
detention ....).</p>
        <p>64. See, e.g., Kent v. Dulles, 357 U.S. 116, 127-31 (1958).
65. See Rust v. Sullivan, 500 U.S. 173, 223-25 (1991) (O'Connor, J.d,issenting).
66. FDA v. Brown &amp; Williamson Tobacco Corp., 529 U.S. 120 (2000).
67. See Chevron, USA, Inc. v. Natural Res. Def. Council, Inc., 467 U.S. 837 (1984).
administrative agency. ' 68 This is a clear suggestion that for certain questions of
great "economic and political magnitude," a legislative resolution, rather than a
delegation to an agency, will be anticipated. And in closing, her opinion insists
"that Congress could not have intended to delegate a decision of such economic
and political significance to an agency in so cryptic a fashion." 69 We might
well take this passage to suggest a kind of democracy-forcing minimalism, in
the form of a suggestion that if the United States government is going to assert
jurisdiction over the tobacco industry, it must be because of a clear judgment to
that effect from Congress and not because of the construction of ambiguous
terms by an administrative agency.</p>
        <p>A general effort to defend Justice O'Connor's approach, focusing on
frontiers cases, might invoke these points as well. When minimalism is
defensible in democratic terms, it is in precisely these areas, simply because it
is there that the Supreme Court should be reluctant to foreclose democratic
experimentation, and there too that the Court might evince a preference for
judgments by the nation's lawmakers. At the very least, I suggest that ideas of
this kind play a significant role in Justice O'Connor's work on the Court.</p>
        <p>CONCLUSION</p>
        <p>One of my central goals in this Article has been to raise some questions
about minimalism-to suggest that any general preference for narrow,
case-bycase rulings would be too crude and reflexive, and insufficiently attuned to the
frequent advantages of width. In Justice O'Connor's opinions, the most vivid
example of this problem can be found in the context of affirmative action,
where she approves "holistic" admissions decisions but disapproves of point
systems. The difficulty is that in key respects, holistic decisions involve the
functional equivalent of a point system-but in a way that is not transparent,
that eliminates predictability, and that almost certainly ensures unequal
treatment of the similarly situated. The idea that the Constitution requires
"holistic" judgment neglects the many benefits of clarity and width, not least
from the standpoint of equality itself.</p>
        <p>None of this means that width is always preferable, or even that courts
should adopt a presumption in its favor. The choice between narrow and wide
rulings must itself be made on a case-by-case basis; no rule is adequate to the
task. Where the Court's decision must be applied in many contexts, and when
the issue frequently recurs, the argument for width may well be irresistible. But
where the issue arises infrequently, and when the Court lacks the information
that would enable it to produce a wide rule in which it has much confidence,
the argument for narrowness is quite strong.</p>
        <p>68. Brown &amp; Williamson, 529 U.S. at 133.
69. Id at 160.</p>
        <p>In the context of the war on terror, there is good reason to avoid wide rules,
simply because they are so likely to misfire. But in the context of sex
discrimination, the Court has earned the right to create strong presumptions that
are also wide. Ideas of this kind follow from a conventional inquiry into the
costs of decisions and the costs of errors. They are also supported by reference
to democratic considerations. I have emphasized that narrow rulings often leave
democracy room to maneuver; an additional point is that some forms of
minimalism turn out to be democracy-forcing.</p>
        <p>With respect to method, a sympathetic understanding of Justice
O'Connor's legacy might therefore take the following form. In the most
difficult and sensitive cases, at the frontiers of constitutional law, the Court
usually does best if it proceeds narrowly. It does so not because there is any
general reason to prefer narrowness to width, but because there are identifiable
settings in which width is likely to misfire, and in which it is best to preserve a
large space for public dialogue and debate. Understood in these (narrow) terms,
Justice O'Connor's preference for narrowness is likely to leave an enduring
mark on constitutional law.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>IN TRODUCTION .............................................................................................. 1900</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>I. AFFIRMATIVE ACTION</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>RULES</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>AND TRANSPARENCY ............................... 1903</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>II. RULES</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>STANDARDS</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <string-name>
            <surname>AND MINIMALISM ................................................... 1907</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>A. M inimalism andIts</surname>
            <given-names>Discontents........................................................ 1908</given-names>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>B .</given-names>
            <surname>The Casefor</surname>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Rules? ..........................................................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1910</year>
          1.
          <article-title>In defense of rules</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>.......................................................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1910</year>
          2.
          <article-title>M eta-questions</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>............................................................................</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>1912</year>
          3.
          <article-title>M inimalism 's domain</article-title>
          <string-name>
            <surname>.................................................................. 1914</surname>
          </string-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>III. DEMOCRA CY ........................................................................................... 19</surname>
          </string-name>
          <year>15</year>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>CON CLUSION ................................................................................................. 19</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>17 14</article-title>
          . See City of Chicago v.
          <source>Morales</source>
          , 527 U.S.
          <volume>41</volume>
          ,
          <issue>68</issue>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>(O'Connor</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>concurring)</source>
          .
          <volume>15</volume>
          . See Planned Parenthood of Se. Pa. v. Casey, 505 U.S.
          <volume>833</volume>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          . See Thompson v.
          <source>W. States Med</source>
          . Ctr., 535 U.S.
          <volume>357</volume>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          )
          <article-title>(striking down as</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <given-names>Administration</given-names>
            <surname>Modernization</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>Act of 1997 that exempted compounded drugs from standard</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>compounded drugs")</source>
          .
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Elk Grove Unified Sch</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Dist. v. Newdow, 542 U.S.
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <issue>33</issue>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>(O'Connor</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation>
          <source>for different approaches.")</source>
          .
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>For</surname>
          </string-name>
          <article-title>a classic treatment, see EDWARD H. LEVI, AN INTRODUCTION TO LEGAL</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>REASONING</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>1949</year>
          ).
          <article-title>For an effort to link constitutional law and common law, see David A</article-title>
          .
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>Strauss</surname>
            , Common Law ConstitutionalInterpretation,63
            <given-names>U.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          <string-name>
            <surname>CHI. L. REV</surname>
          </string-name>
          .
          <volume>877</volume>
          (
          <year>1996</year>
          ).
          <article-title>22. I explore minimalism in CASS R. SUNSTEIN, RADICALS IN ROBES: WHY EXTREME</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation>
          <string-name>
            <surname>RIGHT-WING COURTS ARE WRONG FOR AMERICA</surname>
          </string-name>
          (
          <year>2005</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>; CASS R. SuNsTErN</surname>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <source>ONE CASE AT A</source>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>TIME: JUDICIAL MINIMALISM ON THE SUPREME COURT (</article-title>
          <year>1999</year>
          ).
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See Elk Grove Unified Sch</surname>
          </string-name>
          . Dist. v. Newdow, 542 U.S.
          <volume>1</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>45</lpage>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          ); Grutter,
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation>
          539 U.S. at 311-44; Thompson v.
          <source>W. States Med</source>
          . Ctr., 535 U.S.
          <volume>357</volume>
          (
          <year>2002</year>
          ); City of Chicago
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation>
          v. Morales, 527 U.S.
          <volume>41</volume>
          ,
          <issue>68</issue>
          (
          <year>1999</year>
          )
          <article-title>; Planned Parenthood of Se</article-title>
          . Pa. v. Casey, 505 U.S.
          <volume>833</volume>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>1992</year>
          ).
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
            <given-names>FREDERICK SCHAUER</given-names>
          </string-name>
          ,
          <article-title>FREE SPEECH: A PHILOSOPHICAL ENQUIRY (</article-title>
          <year>1982</year>
          ).
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          .
          <string-name>
            <surname>See</surname>
          </string-name>
          , e.g.,
          <article-title>Hamdi v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Rumsfeld</source>
          , 542 U.S.
          <volume>507</volume>
          (
          <year>2004</year>
          )
          <article-title>(refusing to offer ambitious</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation>
          <article-title>account of President's authority as Commander in Chief); Virginia v</article-title>
          .
          <source>Black</source>
          , 538 U.S.
          <volume>343</volume>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          )
          <article-title>(upholding ban on cross-burning with intent to intimidate without ambitious account</article-title>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation>
          31. See Lawrence v.
          <source>Texas</source>
          , 539 U.S.
          <volume>558</volume>
          ,
          <fpage>579</fpage>
          -
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          (
          <year>2003</year>
          )
          <string-name>
            <surname>(O'Connor</surname>
            ,
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </string-name>
          , concurring).
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>